<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Dec. 17, 2003</date>
<text>
An unlikely bond -- with the emphasis on unlikely -- forms between a man determined to commit suicide and the man who saves him in "After You." Elegantly written, well-thesped comedy is too hermetic and bittersweet to be laugh-out-loud funny, but sustains a fairly successful ratio of uncomfortable situations to amusing solutions. Enthusiastic reviews, and general affection for talented central trio of Daniel Auteuil, Jose Garcia and Sandrine Kiberlain, suggest decent local returns for the pic, which went out Dec. 17 opposite "The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King."
Antoine (Auteuil) works as a tuxedoed maitre d' at Chez Jean, a charming old Paris brasserie. Antoine is so profoundly hooked on being of service to others that he can't say "No": If there's a problem, big or small, he endeavors to solve it on the spot.
Well over an hour late for dinner with his long-suffering g.f., Christine (Marilyne Canto), Antoine takes a detour to rescue a man in the process of hanging himself from a tree. The well-meaning Antoine had no way of knowing that Louis (Garcia), distraught over the departure of his girlfriend, Blanche (Kiberlain), really did want to end it all. Feeling guilty over his unwanted intervention, Antoine invites Louis to stay with him, and then starts to go way above and way beyond the call of duty.
When Louis remembers he mailed a sinister farewell letter to his elderly grandparents, Antoine drives all night to their village enclave in hopes of intercepting the missive. The postman gets to granny's door first, but Antoine cleverly averts disaster.
Antoine then arranges for Louis -- who hasn't held a job for five years -- to try out at Chez Jean. After a delectably awkward interview for the position of wine steward, Louis -- who knows wine like Britney Spears knows opera -- is given a one-week trial. Louis' performance is disastrous, but Antoine comes up with an ingenious ruse to keep him employed.
Antoine also decides to track down Blanche and see if a reconciliation is possible. But from the moment he locates the lanky florist, his problems intensify.
Pic's template is Hollywood-style screwball comedy but, filtered through French storytelling rhythms and an underlying layer of cruelty, result is less diverting than it should be. To its credit, action is anchored in a realm where characters have jobs and actually spend time at work. However, as Antoine's meddling and adjusting become a full-time occupation and no good turn goes unpunished, the romance that should be at pic's center is buffeted so often that the outcome seems more like a toss of the coin than a structural imperative.
Helmer Pierre Salvadori ("Wild Target," "The Apprentices") opts for a stately rather than frantic pace, and gets lovely perfs from his seasoned cast. Recurring mid-'70s tune "Papa Tango Charly" is both infectious and annoying -- just like Louis. Animated opening credits are adorable.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
