<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep. 29, 2004</date>
<text>
Be Here to Love Me: A Film About Townes Van Zandt
 (Docu)
  By 
EDDIE COCKRELL

    
 
 
 
The poignant profile of a troubled troubadour, "Be Here to Love Me" is a dignified and wistful look at the unusual life, difficult career and lasting influence of singer-songwriter Townes Van Zandt. Continuing their focus on music-driven acquisitions with a post-Toronto fest buy, Palm Pictures promises a mid-2005 theatrical release. In the meantime, pic will be a popular fest and specialized theatrical attraction worldwide, with Palm's eventual DVD sure to be in demand from fans and new converts.
Pic's title comes from a song off Van Zandt's second, most aurally lush and distinctive, record, 1969's "Our Mother the Mountain." Covered by Norah Jones on her soph outing, "Feels Like Home," tune sets the tone for first-time helmer Margaret Brown's exploration of Van Zandt's legacy: "Your eyes seek conclusion in all this confusion of mine," he wrote, "I want you to stay and hold me and tell me you'll be here to love me today."
Among those influenced at various stages of their careers by Van Zandt's songwriting are interviewees Willie Nelson, Kris Kristofferson, Emmylou Harris and Steve Earle. Sonic Youth's Steve Shelley, who was producing sessions for Van Zandt in 1997 when he died at 52 of a heart attack following hip surgery, best sums up the legacy, noting that what makes Van Zandt great is that is music couldn't be categorized as either Country, Blues, Folk or Pop.
Tall and skinny, with a quiet demeanor and aw-shucks grin, Van Zandt was born into affluence in Ft. Worth, Texas, in 1944. A troubled childhood resulted in shock therapy treatments that essentially erased his memory, and he drifted away from the first of his three marriages in the mid-1960s to "blow everything off ... get a guitar and go."
Though his prolific output earned him the immediate respect of his peers, Van Zandt's records kept going out of print and he was dogged by substance abuse. In a career that spanned 30 years, he never had anything approaching a hit record himself -- though Nelson and Merle Haggard went to No. 1 on the country charts in 1983 with his "Pancho &amp; Lefty," and the subsequent roster of those who've covered his songs is impressively long.
Helmer Margaret Brown arranges the interview, performance and poignant homemovie material chronologically, rendering the essential elusiveness of what made Van Zandt tick more of a mystery than a narrative impediment. "I don't envision a very long life for myself," he says matter-of-factly near the beginning, underscoring his eccentricity by later announcing, "I'd like to write songs that are so good nobody understands 'em -- including me."
Tech package is pro, with regular Richard Linklater d.p. Lee Daniel smoothly integrating the range of film and vid sources into a pleasing whole. Toronto fest screenings were on crisp digital vid, with 35mm prints promised after Palm Pictures' pick-up.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
