<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep. 19, 2004</date>
<text>
When the master of French thrillers Claude Chabrol meets the mistress of English suspense fiction Ruth Rendell, the result is a potent if very classic blend. "The Bridesmaid" is pleasing precisely for the way it expertly follows genre rules in its story of a young femme fatale who demands ultimate proof of love. At 74, Chabrol is in full possession of his talent for elegant, understated filmmaking, though he's far from his disturbing films of the '50s and '60s. Current pic, as satisfying as a latenight read in bed, should have little trouble finding an audience with suitable handling.
In a quiet French town only slightly rocked by the news of a missing girl, Philippe (Benoit Magimel) lives with his attractive hairdresser mother Christine (Aurore Clement) and his two younger sisters. One night, Christine introduces her offspring to Gerard (Bernard le Coq), a businessman who has been courting her, and asks their permission to give him the sculpted head of a woman in their garden as a present. They reluctantly agree.
Gerard, however, disappears from Christine's life and Philippe retrieves the sculpture in secret. He hides it in his closet and develops a strange attachment to it; not long after, at his sister's wedding, he meets her bridesmaid Senta (Laura Smet) who bears an eerie resemblance to the statue. She seduces him during a thunderstorm and the die is cast for an unpredictable, dangerous relationship.
Senta, a model and wannabe actress, lives in the basement of a huge house her father left her. Rather humorously, Philippe tries to juggle his sultry girlfriend and exciting new sex life with a steady job and family propriety. But the girl's true nature remains shrouded in mystery, creating a low-level tension that hovers unnervingly in the background of the film.
When she asks Philippe to murder a stranger to prove his love for her, he doesn't take her seriously. Things precipitate in the following scenes, and the conclusion, while far from a surprise or great psychological revelation, offers a satisfying last twist.
The pseudo-anonymous Magimel astutely uses his clean good looks to fill the shoes of the hard-working young career man whose secret inner urges derail his normal life. Smet doesn't go far beyond casting smoldering looks for a character who could have used more depth. As the jilted mother of the bride, Clement catches a nicely modern equilibrium between maternal and feminine.
Excellent tech work also follows the classic beat to create a rich atmosphere around commonplace events. Eduardo Serra's cinematography bathes the town in night shadows, while editor Monique Fardoulis gradually raises the tension until film's final revelation. Matthieu Chabrol's mystery music is discreet and well-dosed.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
