<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 9, 2006</date>
<text>
Lover Other: The Story of Claude Cahun and Marcel Moore

"This Is Spinal Tap" meets "Stuck on You," with a heavy dose of '70s Brit-rock grunge, in loopy mockumentary "Brothers of the Head." Feature debut by Yank duo Keith Fulton and Louis Pepe isn't so far from their engrossing docus on Terry Gilliam's filmic adventures, "The Hamster Factor" (1996) and "Lost in La Mancha" (2001), except here the madness and exploitation is part of the music scene. Not for the PC crowd, pic, about a pair of conjoined Siamese twins who enjoy 15 minutes of fame prior to total madness, has modest legs as a cult item beyond festival gigs.
Screenplay by occasional Gilliam collaborator Tony Grisoni, based on the 1977 illustrated novel by Brian Aldiss, plunges straight into its invented world. A lawyer (Jonathan Pryce) treks across a desolate patch of the eastern England coastline to the home of twins Tom and Barry Howe, where father Albert (Roger Watkins) signs a contract.
This turns out to be a scene from an unfinished movie, appealingly titled "Two-Way Romeo," by helmer Ken Russell (playing himself). Russell straightfacedly notes he saw the pic as about "the loss and exploitation of innocence." Author Brian Aldiss (James Greene) adds simply that "it's all incredibly Gothic."
Per usual biodocu style, pic backgrounds the quieter Tom (Harry Treadaway) and more manic Barry (Luke Treadaway). Born joined in the lower chest, and raised in the bleak fens of Norfolk, they were spotted by Zak Bedderwick (Howard Attfield), a down-on-his-luck band manager. Notes one observer: "Zak wanted singing Siamese twins -- and he wanted them pop."
Fulton and Pepe move freely between interviews in the present and docu footage from the past -- latter shot by American documaker Eddie Pasqua (Tom Bower) -- as well as stirring in clips from the increasingly outre "Two-Way Romeo," in which the twins develop a malicious third head. Initial effect is dizzyingly dense, but dialogue is so right-on for its era and period detail so real that the mockumentary sucks the viewer into its created world.
Dubbing the act the Bang Bang, the massively untalented twins stumble to success in a haze of drugs and booze before a woman, sexy Laura Ashworth (Diana Kent, Tania Emery, both excellent), tears them apart. Black humor pushes the envelope in scenes of the twins' conjoined sex lives, and like most mockus, "Brothers" starts treading water in its final reels. Still, Grissoni's dialogue catches the genre's emotional cliches so accurately -- even down to a pathos-filled ending -- that pic's downtime is relatively small.
Lensing by Anthony Dod Mantle ("28 Days Later," "Manderlay") is quietly skilful, from the burnished sheen of clips from Russell's movie to Pasqua's fly-on-the-wall B&amp;W docu. Performances by the largely no-name cast are spot-on.
 Camera (color/B&amp;W), Anthony Dod Mantle; editor, Nicolas Gaster; music/original songs, Clive Langer; production designer, Jon Henson; art director, Patrick Rolfe; costume designer, Marianne Agertoft; sound (Dolby Digital), Tim Barker; assistant director, Mike Elliott; casting, Nina Gold. Reviewed on DVD, Berlin, Jan. 30, 2006. (In Berlin Film Festival -- Panorama; also in Toronto Film Festival -- Visions.) Running time: 88 MIN.

 


 
 


 
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
