<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Jun. 28, 2004</date>
<text>
Very much the typically crass teen sex comedy, "Eating Out" is distinguished by its determination to aim genre's conventions toward horndoggery both hetero- and homosexual. That novelty aside, it's par for the course: Rude, heavily contrived, pretty funny, just remotely connected to real-world youth life. Somewhat guilty minor pleasure will work best viewed in the company of rowdy fellow viewers (the younger the better) and many alcoholic beverages. Vidshot production's very modest dimensions suggest small screen as the most natural destination, though limited theatrical exposure isn't out of the question.
Pic begins on a rather gamy note with the attempted "rape" of bossy blonde Tiffani (Rebekah Kochan) by alleged phone repairman Caleb (Scott Lunsford). Turns out it's her sexual fantasy being enacted, and she's fussy enough to fire him as too nice for the role mid-act. Bad-taste humor thus established, pic plunges into a nondescript college atmosphere in which it seems all social boundaries between straights and gays have ceased to exist. Caleb shares an off-campus apartment with gay best friend Kyle (Jim Verranos).
Similarly crossing lines in platonic cohabitation are gorgeous-and-he-knows- it Marc (Ryan Carnes) and pretty, trash-talking Gwen (Emily Stiles). They're in each others' business to such a degree that Gwen not only manages Marc's revolving-door sex life, but seems attracted to men only if they're gay.
Attending a party at latter duo's flat, Caleb catches the hots for Gwen, while Kyle gets cold-shouldered yet again by impossible-dream Marc. Kyle decides the solution to both their problems would be for Caleb to pose as a gay man -- thus Gwen will view him as a potential conquest and Kyle will have more of an excuse to hang around Marc. Trouble is, Marc becomes smitten with this supposedly just-out-of-the-closet new guy, and Gwen encourages that liaison rather than picking up on Caleb herself.
Credibility need not apply as the finale rigs an all's-well pairing-off between the sex-preference-appropriate parties. However, given Gwen's shallow, insensitive behavior right up to the end, one might question just how this constitutes a "happy ending" for Caleb, even in silly wish-fulfillment terms.
Graduating to features after some well-received shorts, Brocka (nephew of late leading Philippines helmer Lino) has perhaps over-hedged his bets by making nearly every line a quip, to variable results. Sitcom-ish tenor is furthered by frantic pacing, few (mostly interior) locations and over-reliance on close-ups. Characters are scarcely lent any depth, though lead thesps manage well enough. Support roles tend to be shrilly conceived and played.
Nonetheless, within the terms of broad, even crude comedy the pic sets for itself, "Eating Out" is funny more often than not, hilarious on occasion, particularly during one set-piece in which Gwen via cell phone talks Caleb through his first gay sexual experience -- the effect being psychologically hetero and physically homo.
Tech aspects are smooth given the evidently minimal budget.
Camera (color, HD DV), Keith J. Duggan; editor, Phillip J. Bartell; music, Dominik Hauser; production designer, Melissa Fischer; costume designer, David Devincenzo; sound, Michael Cottrell; assistant director, Scott Findley; casting, Don Carroll, Cathy Reinking. Reviewed at San Francisco Lesbian &amp; Gay Film Festival, June 20, 2004. Running time: 90 MIN.

 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
