<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Oct. 10, 2006</date>
<text>
Vancouver plays itself for once in "Generation X" author Douglas Coupland's first original screenwriting venture, "Everything's Gone Green." Starring an excellent Paulo Costanzo (late of "Joey") as a twentysomething uberslacker who is nonetheless willing to fall into accidental success, pic is seasoned with fine perfs by JR Bourne as a charismatic, creepy hustler and Steph Song as Constanzo's sexy potential love interest. Playful combo of geo-particulars and amusing universals could help "Green" go far. 
 Costanzo's Ryan loses his job and is dumped the same day by his g.f. (Katharine Isabelle), who delivers a classic college-age kiss-off: "I'm sick of you and your Billy bookshelves." Being a man more of Ikeas than ideas, he lucks into a new job, writing blurbs about lottery winners in a tacky government mag. 
Device is a brilliant way to parachute Ryan into lifestyles of the suddenly rich and not-otherwise-likely-to-be-famous. It also brings him into contact with Bryce (Bourne), a scammer who comes up with a money-laundering scheme involving the new winners. Soon, and without a lot of thought, Ryan has got the sports car and leather jacket of moneyed youth -- something that puts him at odds with Ming (the versatile Song), a beautiful set-dresser who just so happens to be in the process of getting rid of b.f. Bryce; the last thing she needs is Bryce Lite. 
Helmer Paul Fox, a non-Northwesterner, has handily captured the Pacific Rim ambiguities of a town still immature about its own best attributes. "Everything" starts coming into sharper focus as it seemingly shambles along, making smart points about the limits of greed (and green) in a world of diminishing resources and expanding competition. Costanzo and Song have a nice, easygoing chemistry, oddly helped along by Chiu-Lin Tam as the girl's spunky, non-English speaking granny.
Soundtrack is appropriately heavy on jangly B.C. bands like the Fembots and Sloan.
Camera (color) David Frazee; editor, Gareth C. Scales; music, Sloan, Fembots, others; music supervisor, David Hayman; production designer, Peter Andringa; art director, Carolyn Neuert; set designer, Matthew Versteeg; costume designer, Sheila White; sound (Dolby SRD), Eric Batut; line producer, Ken Lawson; assistant director, Patricia Ann Dyer; casting, Corinne Clark, Robin Cook, Jennifer Page. Reviewed at Vancouver Film Festival (Canadian Images -- competing), Sept. 15, 2006. Running time: 95 MIN. 

 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
