<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Nov. 15, 2005</date>
<text>
From Scots national poet Robert Burns, to American comedian Lenny Bruce; from Country Joe McDonald's give-me-an-F cheer at Woodstock to "South Park: Bigger, Longer and Uncut," the offensive word that provides the title for Steven Anderson's penetrating documentary/social critique has either enriched or infected Western culture to the point that we're either drowning in a "floodtide of filth" or blessed with the best verbal relief valve ever devised by man. The only thing clear is that this movie will have a cult following, the size of which may depend on whether it can be advertised anywhere. 
Director Anderson is out to discover where the word comes from, why it offends so many so deeply and what possible benefit can be gained from its use. Old wives' tales about the word being an acronym are explored ("Fornication Under the Consent of the King" is one theory, which is pretty much put to bed by the movie's linguistic experts). The conclusion reached is that the word's origin is unknown, but that its very mention drives certain people into spasms of righteous indignation.
"Every civilization has had to battle to preserve itself," says radio talkshow host Dennis Prager, who sees the increased use of the word as proof we're losing the battle. "Cathartic" is what TV talk show host Bill Maher calls it. While it's hard to defend the use of the word as an artistic device -- especially since Lenny Bruce long ago got most of the mileage he could out of it -- it's also hard to get as worked up about it as do Robert Peters, of Morality in Media, or right-wing watch dog Michael Medved. Although Anderson gives each side equal time, the determining factor in which side the movie leans toward is which side is the funniest. And the censorship advocates are too grindingly indignant to be funny.
Anderson plays fast and loose with his editing -- people who may never have been in the same room (all the interviewees are filmed solo) seem to be having arguments, which seems like dirty pool given some of the "exchanges." Anderson also flops his subjects on occasion, reversing the negative so that someone who was looking right is suddenly looking left (in Prager's case, the part in his hair moves from right to left). 
In terms of entertainment, the movie is consistently amusing, often hilarious, and energetic in its editing. Animator Bill Plympton's interspersed contributions sparkle with wit, as usual, and comedians like Drew Carey and wild man Billy Connolly revel in being encouraged to use the word. 
Where Anderson starts to go wrong is when he moves away from the linguistic aspects and into its visual representation. Outtakes from porn movies and interviews with porn stars Tera Patrick and husband Evan Seinfeld send the movie off track. 
Docu recovers its wits when Anderson starts following the word into the U.S. executive branch to include Dick Cheney's celebrating muttering at Sen. Patrick Leahy and the notorious vulgarity of the Nixon and Johnson presidential tapes. So despite the protestations of Pat Boone, who decries the rise of gangsta rap's vulgarity, the "no-class, low-life" behavior he bemoans has been embraced by the supposed top shelf of society. And there's no end in sight.
Camera (color, DV), Andre Fontanelle; editor, Jayne Rodericks; music, Carvin Knowles; music supervisor, Dondi Bastone; animation, Bill Plympton. Reviewed at AFI Los Angeles Film Festival, Nov. 9, 2005. Running time: 91 MIN. 

 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
