<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Apr. 3, 2007</date>
<text>
Boy meets dog, bonds with dad and foils a dangerous arsonist in "Firehouse Dog," a likable but ungainly mutt of a movie in which a very smart canine unexpectedly becomes fireman's best friend. Leaving no heartstrings untugged and no doggie-fart jokes uncracked, scruffy pic reps a very mixed breed of obvious humor, gently moving father-son drama and sub-"Backdraft" trial by fire. Lack of big names and blah title should place the Fox release near the lower end of the family-friendly B.O. spectrum, though this "Dog" will probably have its day on homevid.
The star of such hit films as "The Fast and the Furriest" and "Jurassic Bark," Rexxx is Hollywood's pre-eminent four-legged celebrity, so ridiculously pampered he would've fit right in on Christopher Guest's "Best in Show." But after a dangerous airborne stunt separates Rexxx from his owner, Trey (Dash Mihok), and causes the dog to lose his (hideous) trademark hairpiece, the now ordinary-looking mutt wanders into Dogpatch, an inner-city fire station that's fallen on hard times.
Connor Fahey (Bruce Greenwood, excellent) has reluctantly assumed leadership of the small squad after his brother, Dogpatch's former captain, perished in the line of duty. Stress and grief have strained Connor's relationship with his 12-year-old son Shane (Josh Hutcherson), who gets the unenviable task of taking care of the dog (identified as Dewey by his collar) and finding his owner.
Familiar boy-and-his-dog scenario is enlivened by the fact that Shane initially loathes Dewey, who, far from acting like a normal stray, expects to be treated like the celebrity canine he is. (In a nice comic touch, Shane puts up fliers that read "Found: Ugly stinkin' mutt.") But it's only a matter of time before Dewey -- with his unusual intelligence, acrobatic skills and bravery in the face of danger -- becomes both an excellent rescue dog and a handy PR tool, single-pawedly saving the embattled fire station from closure.
Scenes of gradual father-son reconciliation are very affectingly played by the film's two-legged leads. Between this and the recent "Bridge to Terabithia," Hutcherson is fast becoming the studios' go-to guy for sensitive, neglected tykes, while Greenwood, supplying his usual gravelly understatement, once again proves temperamentally incapable of overacting.
The same can't be said of the other actors, most of whom are saddled with either obvious roles (Bill Nunn as a fireman who's a lousy cook, Mayte Garcia as the squad's attractive lone female) or strained bits of slapstick, and mug their way through accordingly. Additional comedy is supplied by silly flashbacks to Dewey's celebrity life (he once had a tabloid-worthy romance with a dreadlocked Dalmatian), as well as some movie-biz satire as Trey looks for his prized pooch. Overlong at nearly two hours, "Dog" frequently bites off more than it needs to chew.
Veteran TV helmer Todd Holland (whose previous feature was 1998's lamentable "Krippendorf's Tribe") struggles to balance the film's broad, occasionally crass humor against its more serious elements -- namely, the mysterious arsonist who's been setting fires strategically throughout the city. Resolution is predictable but rousing as Connor, Shane and Rexxx/Dewey cement their bond through individual acts of love and courage.
Building-on-fire set pieces are workmanlike but capably handled, and not too scary for tots. Title role is well played by four red-coated Irish terriers (with the Tolkien-inspired names of Arwen, Frodo, Rohan and Stryder), though some of the dog's more athletic feats suggest possible f/x enhancements. 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
