<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Oct. 2, 2002</date>
<text>
Small is beautiful indeed in the case of "Minimal Stories," a beguiling tale of three parallel journeys across the dusty steppes of Patagonia that culminate in subtle but satisfying moments of self-fulfillment. Endowed with captivating simplicity, gentle humor, rich humanity and infectious generosity of spirit, Argentinean director Carlos Sorin's road movie won the Special Jury Prize at San Sebastian. A sure-fire festival favorite, the modest production could also find a receptive arthouse niche with the right handling.
A veteran commercials director, Sorin won a Silver Lion at the Venice fest with his 1986 debut "La Pelicula del Rey" but dropped out of sight after 1989's poorly received "Eversmile, New Jersey" with Daniel Day-Lewis. Only his third feature, "Minimal Stories" was completed thanks to the Cinema in Progress joint funding program between San Sebastian and the Toulouse fest. Pic was shown at the latter in an incomplete version in March, at which point Spanish co-producer Wanda Vision came aboard.
The principal characters all travel from their native village far from the modern world in remote southern Argentina to the nearest, only marginally more sophisticated town of San Julian. Their stories are loosely but seamlessly interwoven as they each pursue their humble dreams.
Unable to drive after losing his license due to failing eyesight, retired general store owner Don Justo (Antonio Benedictis) defies his son's travel veto and sets off on foot after hearing his missing dog has been seen in town. Traveling salesman Roberto (Javier Lombardo) plans to court the widow of a client by showing up on her child's birthday with a cake. A timid young mother with an unemployed husband, Maria (Javiera Bravo) gets a reprieve from her hand-to-mouth existence when she's selected to compete on a TV gameshow for the top prize of a food processor.
By far the most touching of the three stories, Don Justo's journey is punctuated by encounters with characters that all show a profound respect for the aged, from a doting biologist (Julia Solomonoff) to a goodhearted night-watchman (Anibal Maldonado). The old man's urge to be reunited with his mangy mutt is driven by a deeper need to atone before death for what he perceives as his abandonment of the animal years earlier.
By turns poignant and funny, Roberto's mission may be to find love, but he approaches his goal with guidance from a marketing self-help manual. His efforts to redecorate the soccer-ball cake with more generic frosting when he realizes he's unsure of the child's gender provide some of the film's most amusing scenes.
Bowing to pressure from a habitual gameshow contestant (Silvia Fontelles), Maria swaps the food processor for an inferior prize, plus the cash to cover a restaurant meal and hotel stay with her daughter before heading home. The experience fosters a quiet sense of joy and discovery that dwarfs her triumph on the TV show.
While all three stories share a soul-stirring view of the everyday kindnesses between characters and are all resolved with sweetly disarming outcomes, there's nothing manipulative or artificial in Pablo Solarz's economical screenplay or Sorin's warmly observational direction. This extends also to the unaffected work of the largely non-professional cast, with 80-year-old novice Benedictis a natural scene-stealer.
The action hums along at a pleasurably unhurried pace to the lovely sonorous strains of a Latino guitar-flavored score by the director's son, Nicolas Sorin. Shooting with two Super 16 cameras, lenser Hugo Colace nicely offsets the intimacy and seemingly inconsequential nature of the stories, lending dignity and scope to the characters with the windswept plains and endless skies.
Camera (Cinecolor), Hugo Colace; editor, Mohamed Rajid; music, Nicolas Sorin; art director, Margarita Jusid; sound (Dolby Digital), Abbate &amp; Diaz; assistant directors, Veronica Souto, Federico Badia. Reviewed at San Sebastian Film Festival (competing), Sept. 26, 2002. Running time: 92 MIN.
 

With:
 Carlos Montero, Anibal Maldonado, Maria Rosa Cianferoni, Maria del Carmen Jimenez, Mario Splanguno, Julia Solomonoff, Armando Grimaldi, Cesar Garcia, Laura Vagnoni, Rosa Valsecchi, Silvia Fontelles, Rosario Vera, Enrique Otranto, Francis Sandoval.
 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
