<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Mar. 29, 2007</date>
<text>
The story's bywords may be "Keep Moving Forward," but the time-jumping narrative does some wild loop-the-loops in "Meet the Robinsons," a sharp-minded, plenty entertaining toon that will keep children of all ages wide-eyed and on their toes. Latest computer-generated animated feature from Disney is leagues ahead of the first, the successful but thick-headed "Chicken Little," in wit and art-istry, and shows the unmistakable influence of newly arrived Pixar wizard John Lasseter and friends. Snazzy entry should do strong if not smash biz through the spring, especially in the 600-plus theaters equipped to project it in the superb Disney Digital 3-D process.
The three-dimensional technique requires glasses, large, lightweight specs with dark lenses rather than the colored ones so dismally employed for the likes of "The Adventures of Sharkboy and Lavagirl in 3-D." Seen previously in limited engagements of Disney's "Chicken Little" and "The Nightmare Before Christmas," the state-of-the-art technology combines dramatic, in-your-face perspectives with a more than acceptable comfort level.
Happily, as has not often been the case in the past, 3-D has here been put to use in the service of what is, on its own merits, a good film. More than has any previous Disney effort, "Robinsons" resembles Pixar's smash "The Incredibles," both in the way the visuals combine futuristic and retro elements, and in the smart talk and can-do energy of the characters.
Left as a tot on the doorstep of a big city orphanage, straw-haired Lewis is a passionate science geek who, at 12, despairs of ever being adopted and gaining a family of his own. His fellow wastrel and only pal is sad-sack "Goob," a baseball fanatic forever depressed over a muffed catch that lost his team a big game.
Lewis is convinced he's made his big scientific breakthrough with a cleverly designed brain-scanner. But his presentation of the device at his school science fair is dashed by the interference of a mysterious crab-legged bowler hat doing the bidding of a dastardly villain, a curiously 19th-century figure with a cape, thin moustache, spindly legs and sinister laugh.
Just when Lewis and the audience might become concerned about what lies ahead, the boy is literally whisked off his feet by Wilbur, a cocky teen with a time machine. While Lewis would prefer to go back in time to look for the mother who abandoned him, Wilbur insists upon zooming ahead to the future, where his large family, the endlessly eccen-tric and imaginative Robinsons, await.
Pic comes into its own at this point, about a third of the way through -- first with the lovely design elements, then with the narrative time-jumping that makes all sorts of wild inventions possible in the adaptation of William Joyce's illustrated book engineered by seven screenwriters, among them first-time director Stephen Anderson (whose most prominent previous credits were as story supervisor on Disney's "The Emperor's New Groove" and "Brother Bear").
Wilbur's genius dad is the brain behind Robinson Industries, where the brightest new inventions are hatched for futuristic environs of the sort portrayed at world's fairs anytime from the '30s through the '50s. People glide around in transparent bubbles amidst elegant examples of the Streamline Moderne architectural style, exemplified by clean lines and graceful curves.
But due to an unfortunate time ma-chine wreck, a theft and the unwanted visit of the archfiend with the thin moustache and malevolent hats, this brainiacs' paradise is turned upside down; worse for Lewis, he's denied longed-for adoption just when he's found the family of his dreams. Wickedly clever manipulations of time travel make for some wacky character identity flip-flops, as well as the retrieval of a ferocious T-Rex brought forward to wreak havoc on the impeccably manicured landscapes of the future.
Especially in 3-D, pic has an im-mensely sharp, vivid look (sans glasses, the projected image is fuzzy in spots, focused in others), and the filmmakers have taken to heart the "Keep Moving Forward" attitude, attributed in an onscreen postscript to Walt Disney himself, in the way they keep the momentum revved up. Unlike some frantic animated efforts, "Robinsons" is never exhausting, but neither is there anything resembling a dull moment.
Voicings are spirited -- helmer Anderson himself performs the chief villain, among other roles -- and Danny Elfman's score, aided by other musical elements, further augments the energy level.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
