<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 2, 2003</date>
<text>
Writer-director Joe Maggio, who made a mark with his 2001 debut "Virgil Bliss," again coaxes edgy performances from an ensemble cast in "Milk &amp; Honey," a dexterously scripted, darkly humorous account of a New York couple's all-night odyssey of spiraling anxiety as they struggle to keep a grip on reality and their severely damaged relationship. While the agitated shooting style suits the material, the poor-quality, drab DV visuals represent a commercial stumbling block, probably limiting exposure to fest and cable dates.
Writer-director Joe Maggio, who made a mark with his 2001 debut "Virgil Bliss," again coaxes edgy performances from an ensemble cast in "Milk &amp; Honey," a dexterously scripted, darkly humorous account of a New York couple's all-night odyssey of spiraling anxiety as they struggle to keep a grip on reality and their severely damaged relationship. While the agitated shooting style suits the material, the poor-quality, drab DV visuals represent a commercial stumbling block, probably limiting exposure to fest and cable dates.

Core of the drama is the imploding marriage of Rick (Clint Jordan) and Joyce (Kirsten Russell), following a disastrous party intended to reintroduce him to professional colleagues after what appears to have been a breakdown. Rick hits the streets, bouncing from his girlfriend to his shrink to a stranger, to whom he offers payment to end his life, while Joyce also ventures out for her own confrontations. Benefiting from another strong collaboration between the director and "Virgil Bliss" lead Jordan, Maggio's intricately interwoven tale has a certain eccentric affectation that recalls the films of Hal Hartley, who composed the austere score.
Camera (color, digital video), Gordon Chou; editor, Seth E. Anderson; music, Hal Hartley, Yo La Tengo, Fischerspooner; production designer, Bryce Paul Mama; art director, Nick Stavrides. Reviewed at Sundance Film Festival (American Spectrum), Jan. 18, 2003. Running time: 91 MIN.
 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
