<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 10, 2003</date>
<text>
An intricate, fetchingly lensed tale of historical speculation framed as a plausible thriller, "Monsieur N." takes the rhetorical gag "Who's buried in Grant's tomb?" and applies it to Napoleon Bonaparte. If those aren't the remains of General-cum-Emperor Napoleon the first -- who died on Saint Helena in 1821--then whose are they? And what really became of the short guy with the distinctive forelock about whom some 300,000 books have been written and whose legacy can work up a room of Frenchmen to this day?
Beautifully appointed Franco-British co-production is dramatically dense, neatly thesped and visually involving. Versatile funnyman Antoine de Caunes, whose career is shaping up as a Gallic reply to Steve Martin's, delivers an impressive sophomore feature (after "Les Morsures de l'aube"/Love Bites) that should do nicely at home and has a solid shot at the offshore market. Pic opens Feb. 12 in Gaul, and Berlin Panorama slot shouldn't hurt.
In a credits sequence set in 1840, a coffin is exhumed and opened in a downpour. Witnesses pronounce the occupant to be a well-preserved Napoleon. Story, told in voice-over by Basil Heathcote (Jay Rodan) -- the film's only composite character -- then backtracks to June 1815 when 20-year-old Lt. Heathcoate arrived on Saint Helena under the command of no-nonsense Sir Hudson Lowe (a delectably imperious Richard E. Grant).
As governor of the remote British outpost, Lowe's chief responsibility (one that 3,000 men help enforce) is to make certain the island's notorious prisoner Gen. Napoleon Bonaparte (Philippe Torreton) does not escape. Heathcoate lives at Longwood -- the musty house assigned to Napoleon and his handful of retainers -- and is under orders to make sure he spots the prisoner twice a day.
A small group of loyal followers accompanied Napoleon into exile: Marshal Bertrand (Roschdy Zem), Gen. Montholon (Stephen Freiss) and his wife Albine (Elsa Zylberstein), and Gen. Gourgaud (Frederic Pierrot). Also in residence is Cipriani (Bruno Putzulu), Napoleon's fellow Corsican and lifelong friend, who runs the household.
Having turned himself in to the British in the wake of Waterloo, Napoleon is very much a prisoner.  Nevertheless, he's managed to maintain a protocol-laden lifestyle worthy of Versailles.
Lowe is much troubled by the fact that Napoleon's captivity is costing England 8 million pounds a year and galled by the projected expense should he "live another 20!" His upkeep is costly, his impatient retainers would like to collect their presumed inheritance -- and arsenic is a popular item on the island to ward off rats. The disgraced emperor still has many admirers and sympathizers in the outside world as well, but closest and most problematic is Betsy Balcombe (Siobhan Hewlett), the fresh-faced teen daughter of a local civilian couple.
Heathcoate is smitten with Betsy, who only has eyes for Napoleon. But it's not until 1840, at the ceremony in Paris during which Napoleon's remains are interred at Les Invalides, that Heathcoate -- catching a glimpse of adult Betsy in the solemn crowd-- is compelled to track down the members of the emperor's erstwhile inner circle.
While tale bounces around in time and demands concentration, narrative is never confusing. Dialogue in appropriate mix of French and English is consistently sharp.
Torreton ("Captain Conan"), who gained 20 pounds for the role, is terrific. Grant hits the bull's-eye as the officious task master. Rodan carves a handsome presence as the junior officer assigned to accompany Napoleon on his walks and rides. Zylberstein scores as the conniving spouse who shares Napoleon's bed -- with her husband's tacit approval -- as the small French contingent jockeys for generous mention in the emperor's will.
Craggy vistas lensed in South Africa are gorgeous and the faintly glum, ever-dramatic light, expertly molded by Pierre Aim is deftly expressive. Hands-on producers Marie-Castille Mention-Schaar and Pierre Kubel have spared no expense in production design, props or costumes, all of which contribute to an aura of authenticity.
Stephan Eicher's score is a bit overblown in spots, but not to the point of distraction. It's just that with a premise as strong as this, "movie" music isn't really needed.
Camera (color, widescreen), Pierre Aim; editor, Joelle Van Effenterre; music, Stephan Eicher; production designer, Patrick Durand; costume designer, Carine Sarfati; sound (Dolby), Dominique Levert, Didier Lozahic; assistant director, Valerie Othnin-Girard; second unit director, Shaun O'Dell; casting, Frederique Moidon (France), Sarah Beardsall (U.K.). Reviewed at Elysees-Biarritz screening room, Paris, Jan. 13, 2003. (In Berlin Film Festival -- Panorama.) Running time: 128 MIN. 
(French and English dialogue.)
 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
