<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Aug. 23, 2004</date>
<text>
Direction, performances and lensing blend into an immensely satisfying, if almost uncategorizable, whole in Pawel Pawlikowski's "My Summer of Love," a tale of transient teenage love marbled with modern-Gothic weirdness. Terrific playing by rising young thesps Nathalie Press and Emily Blunt, against an irreal northern English landscape, make this the most accomplished work so far from Polish-born Pawlikowski, whose sophomore feature, grungy immigrant-center drama "The Last Resort," marked him as a helmer to watch four years ago. Beyond the festival circuit, specialized distribution looks rosy.
Pic is more inspired by than based on Helen Cross' 2001 novel, which was set during the '80s miners' strike and featured a series of murders as background. Script by Pawlikowski and Michael Wynne focuses almost entirely on the girls' idyllic, almost fairytale love story, with the addition of a wacko, born-again Christian brother.
In look and tone, film is completely different from Pawlikowski's first two TV features (including his first, journo saga "The Stringer"), both rooted in Brit-realist tube drama. "Summer" has a looser, almost Central European feel in its approach to character and landscape.
Sixteen-year-old Mona (Press) is a sparky, working-class Yorkshire girl in an unnamed town in a picturesque valley. Her elder brother Phil (Paddy Considine), a former con with a violent past, runs the local pub but, having suddenly found God, now wants to turn the hostelry into a spiritual center.
Out on the moors one balmy summer's day -- pic was shot during the 2003 heat wave, and has a tangible sultriness -- lonely Mona meets Tamsin (Blunt), a rich, well-educated girl who's her own age but seems considerably older with her snooty self-confidence. Both are looking for companionship -- Tamsin effectively lives alone in a large manse with her actress mom away and her father shagging his secretary -- and, after some teenage pranks together and dancing to an old Edith Piaf song, the two end up kissing in a mountain pool.
With its tight exposition and free-flowing style, film's first half-hour sweeps the viewer up into a world that seems to exist somewhere on the periphery of normality, entirely constructed by the two girls. The sense of dislocation, also evident in the witty, non-sequitur dialogue between the offhand Tamsin and down-to-earth Mona, continues as the weirdness multiplies.
Tamsin talks of a dead sister, whose bedroom is now a shrine. Meanwhile, Phil is building a massive cross that he and his followers carry up the hill overlooking the town, on a mission to expunge "the evil in the valley." As Tamsin and Mona pursue their clandestine affair, pledging love until death, Phil gets the idea that Tamsin is the devil incarnate.
Pic's whiffs of modern English Gothic recall movies like "The Wicker Man," as well as child-centered pics like "Our Mother's House." But finally it's just one more element of offbeat flavoring in a story of two neglected teens who pine for each other's qualities -- Mona's instinctiveness vs. Tamsin's cautiousness. The girls, one feels, aren't even career lesbians, more lonely souls at the mercy of their hormones.
Press, putting on a flawless Yorkshire accent, almost steals the movie as the ditzy Mona (real name: Lisa), a plain-but-pretty lass swept away by Tamsin's erudition and poise. But Blunt's perf as the mysterious, mixed-up Tamsin grows, adding a sense of menace which coincides with Considine's loony Phil.
Cinematography by Polish d.p. Ryszard Lenczewski creates a rural, summertime England that's recognizable but with a rough, northern, magical-realist flavor. Music by Alison Goldfrapp and Will Gregory isn't afraid to play up the big moments, adding to the film's evident desire not to fall into any neat, predetermined genre. Tight running-time is spot-on.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
