<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 12, 2004</date>
<text>
"The Nomi Song" is an absorbing homage to obscure but fascinating late '70s-early '80s German stage artiste Klaus Nomi. As with helmer Andrew Horn's previous pic, "East Side Story," a tribute to Warsaw-pact musicals, the new docu sports a trove of archival footage and frank contempo interviews with friends and collaborators. Nomi died of AIDS-related illness in 1983. Like Charles Atlas' doc, "The Legend of Leigh Bowery," about a similar character, pic could do niche theatrical biz in metrosexual-friendly cities before screening on upmarket TV slots and transfer to DVD. 
Born Klaus Sperber in Bavaria, 1944, Nomi trained as an opera singer and made his way to New York just in time for the burgeoning downtown underground scene centered around Max's Kansas City. Performance artist Ann Magnuson recalls how Nomi debuted his act -- singing countertenor opera tunes, dressed in extraordinary costumes with a white face and thick makeup -- at the first gig of the "New Wave Vaudeville Show," a cabaret where Nomi met several of his future collaborators, including producer Kristian Hoffman and art director Page Wood.
Nomi maintained his monochrome look onstage and off, so much so that photographer Anthony Scibelli, whose striking snaps of Nomi are included here, notes Nomi was "the first person I'd ever met who'd been chemically treated to become black and white." Performing an eclectic repertoire of both original material and idiosyncratic covers, from arias to pop, Nomi quickly became a fixture on the NYC club scene.
When David Bowie asked him to help design costumes and sing backup for him on "Saturday Night Live," (excerpts from which are shown), Nomi looked set for a national breakthrough. But a disastrous attempt at a tour sent him back to New York practically almost as soon as the tour began.
Interviewees candidly recall Nomi's prima donna moments, how he dropped old friends and collaborators when success seemed within grasp, and his persistent loneliness. His much-hoped-for crossover from avant-garde character to recording star only really happened in Europe. A sound-only interview with Nomi's beloved elderly aunt, Trude Sperber, is accompanied by inventive visuals showing a dolls' house and cutaways to his home town, which bring to life the tristesse of his last visit, by which time he knew he was seriously ill.
Pic's moving last act deals sensitively with his lonely death from AIDS, one of the first celebrity victims of what was then called "the gay plague."
Although bookended with clips from vintage '50s sci-fi "It Came From Outer Space" to underline Nomi's fascination with retro futurism and alien personae, "The Nomi Song" sports a less camp sensibility than one would expect given subject's outre lifestyle.
Pic's crunchy visual texture is made up of an assortment of footage, including 35mm, 16mm and Super8 Sound stocks, plus Betacam, U-Matic and Portapack footage. Editing by Angela Christlieb (co-helmer of docu "Cinemania") and Guido Krajewski moves story niftily along, making for a dense but diverting 99-minute running time. Sound by Alexandra Baltarzuk brings out the best from the problematic archival footage, seemlessly marrying what at times appear to be separate music and visual tracks.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
