<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 8, 2006</date>
<text>
Lover Other: The Story of Claude Cahun and Marcel Moore

From the first frames, when lollypops are offered to the camera, there's no escaping the saccharine miasma of whimsy enveloping Peter Cattaneo's "Opal Dream." Based on an acclaimed novella first published in Grantamagazine, the pic jettisons the story's adult flavor for a strictly cotton candy diet, investing its nine-year-old protag with a cutesy fantasy life that in the real world would be grounds for therapy. Moderate moppet biz can be expected for Focus Features, who bought Stateside rights, though parents may get a tummy ache.
Story is set in the South Australian opal mining community of Coober Pedy, where the Williamson family struggles to make ends meet while dad Rex (Vince Colosimo) pursues his dream of striking it rich underground. Mom Annie (Jacqueline McKenzie) works the supermarket counter, only rarely allowing her doubts about outback life to cloud her day.
While son Ashmol (Christian Byers) seems like a well-adjusted kid, little Kellyanne (Sapphire Boyce) is a social misfit who's constructed an inner life inhabited by two imaginary friends, Pobby and Dingan. She's first seen playing patty-cake, clapping the air with one or the other (thankfully, Cattaneo chose to keep them invisible).
The family is getting tired of Kellyanne's obsession, but weaning her off Pobby and Dingan proves impossible. Dad has the bright idea of claiming to take the two off with him one day into the mines, but when he returns without them Kellyanne throws a tantrum and insists he return at night to search for them.
Quicker than you can say "enabler," off he goes, but when Rex ventures too close to a rival miner's property, he's accused of trying to steal someone else's opals. Kellyanne doesn't give a fig for her Dad's problems, she just wants her friends back, and while Dad is made a target of the vicious miners' wrath, she slowly wastes away in bed.
Any shrink would label the family dysfunctional and Kellyanne psychotic, but Cattaneo instead presents her behavior as a charming byproduct of an over-productive imagination. Time and again, the little girl manipulates those around her into buying into her fantasy, sending a message to child viewers that parents will certainly not want reinforced in their own homes.
While Colosimo ("Lantana") and McKenzie do their best to make the characters three-dimensional, Boyce is a major drawback. Both child actors are newcomers to the screen. Byers is surprisingly strong and gives his role real weight, but Boyce remains limp throughout, her sickbed scenes recalling a kiddie production of "Camille."
The infectious smiles and foot-tapping soundtrack of Cattaneo's runaway hit "The Full Monty" are nowhere to be found. Where the "Pobby and Dingan" novella was much praised for its richly evoked landscape, Cattaneo and d.p. Robert Humphreys fail to make the eerie, semi-lunar terrain an ever-present character. Sound is occasionally positioned too far forward, and music, while generally avoiding violin swells, manages to make plucked guitars equally schmaltzy.
 Camera (color), Robert Humphreys; editor, Jim Clark; music, Christian Henson, Dario Marianelli; production designer, Elizabeth Mary Moore; art director, Nell Hanson; costume designer, Ruth de la Lande; sound (Dolby Digital), Toivo Lember, Robert Farr, Nick Foley; line producer, Elisa Argenzio; associate producers, Kate Myers, Michael Solinger; assistant director, Brendan Campbell; casting, Nikki Barrett. Reviewed at Rotterdam Film Festival (Time &amp; Tide), Jan. 29, 2006 (Also in Berlin Film Festival -- Kinderfilmfest.) Running time: 85 MIN.
 


 With:
 Peter Callan, Robert Menzies, Adam Morgan, Rusty Potter, Denise Roberts.
 


 
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
