<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Jan. 12, 2007</date>
<text>
Horror movies are routinely slammed for recycling the same old formulas, so you have to give "Primeval" some credit for imagination, or at least perversity: It's 55% giant-crocodile "Jaws" and 45% fact-inspired, "Blood Diamond"-esque civil-war-violence thriller. There won't be any Oscar campaigning for this
 Africa-set action movie, but despite some inevitable silly moments, handsome widescreen production is decently handled genre fare. Its dumping by the Mouse House into the market sans sneaks or press screenings makes pic look worse than it is -- it's not exactly good, but it's not bad, and far from boring.
Breaking a political scandal that turns out to be baseless leaves ace TV reporter Tim (Dominic Purcell) no option but to accept the unappealing assignment his boss sticks him with: finding and capturing the world's largest croc, a 25-foot monster in war-torn Burundi that's been eating villagers for decades. Assisting him on the tabloid-like stunt "story" are Aviva (Brooke Langton), a fluff-news reporter who hopes this will be her big break; cameraman Steven (Orlando Jones), pic's designated wisecracking comic relief; and world-famed croc expert Matthew (Gideon Emery, instructed to evoke the late Steve Irwin, albeit as a snippy jerk-- something that ceased to be a good idea several months ago).
Since action is set in pre-2005 Burundi, violence is still rife between warlords and anyone who gets in their way. Natch, the croc (which locals dub Gustave) is located in an area also terrorized by followers of one elusive warlord who's dubbed himself Little Gustave. Crusty local guide Jacob (Jurgen Prochnow, playing the Robert Shaw "Jaws" role, complete with near-identical exit) informs the travelers that it's a tossup which Gustave "is the colder-blooded."
Despite armed guards, the party is machine-gunned upon en route. Still, they make it intact to the site of the latest villager-munchings. Matthew has brought along a large reinforced-steel cage he's designed to capture the critter alive, though for personal reasons Jacob would much rather see it dead. All concerned (now including a small dog and Gabriel Malema as orphaned teen Jojo, both of whom the visitors "adopt") settle in with their live-goat bait, weapons and high-tech surveillance equipment.
Needless to say, when the scaly behemoth does show up, things do not go as planned. They go even worse when Little Gustave (whose real identity is revealed late) finds out Steven accidentally witnessed an execution in the bush and videotaped it. Henchmen are dispatched to retrieve the tape and kill everyone.
While the combination of creature thrills and historically inspired paramilitary thuggery may strike some as rather tasteless, John Brancato and Michael Ferris' script does a solid enough job juggling both perils so they have equal narrative importance. Director Michael Katleman, making his bigscreen debut after a couple decades' TV work, keeps the pacing tight, the acting straight-faced and the laughs mostly intentional (though Jones' one-liners occasionally fall flat).
Editing is sometimes a little too frenetic to maximize the heavily physical, fairly gory action. Though Gustave is clearly a CGI reptile when seen in full-body motion, production package is high-grade for this sort of enterprise, with excellent lensing by Edward J. Pei of the spectacular wildlife and landscapes (South Africa standing in for Burundi). Soundtrack features a nice mix of African and orchestral sounds.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
