<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep. 22, 2005</date>
<text>
A true account of how a woman's intelligence and stoicism saves her huge family, "The Prize Winner of Defiance, Ohio" sensitively presents an unvarnished view of the 1950s and early '60s through the subtle filter of the present. Tailor-made for writer-director Jane Anderson -- making her first feature film after several small-screen triumphs ("The Baby Dance," "Normal," etc.) -- pic allows Julianne Moore to again inhabit the conformist '50s, but in an entirely different key than "Far From Heaven" or "The Hours." Depending on how well DreamWorks' sub-division Go Fish gets the word out, women should respond, and appeal of this all-American tale will be felt in smaller cities as well as large.
As far back as her brilliant solo theater work, "How to Raise a Gifted Child," Anderson has been concerned with the relationship between mothers and children --as well as true sagas. Though her original work can be quite dark, as in "The Baby Dance," "Prize Winner," which Anderson also scripted, is told in a memoir form that both lightens and deepens the story about a woman with exceptional talent for writing jingles, yet is born in the wrong era to fully realize it. Even more than in "Far From Heaven," Moore's housebound wife is a study in pent-up brilliance, with extraordinary devotion to her family.
Having delivered her 10th (and final) child in 1956, Evelyn Ryan is already a frequent winner of the jingle contests companies used to hawk their consumer products after WWII. Inserting contest forms into her Underwood as easily as she slips off a diaper, Evelyn and her Defiance, Ohio, home appear to be the picture of Midwestern bliss.
But cracks soon appear below the domestic sheen, and the family's lower-middle-class condition is only part of it. Husband Kelly (Woody Harrelson), a factory machinist, drinks himself into a lather every evening. It's Evelyn's steady winnings that provide the margin to barely pay for essentials like milk.
Evelyn's occasional winnings -- one of them big enough to place a down payment on a house feel like the well-earned victories of a talented writer who happens to be a full-time mom, rather than scripted fantasies. Yet they also feel somewhat hollow, since the family can never get ahead; consumer goods being produced by America's exploding economy are frequent prizes, and a large freezer, plunked down in the middle of the kitchen, strikes Kelly as a symbol for what's wrong with his life.
As years roll into the '60s, the film develops a fine novelistic view of the sacrifices made by ordinary people growing older. Few of the kids are foregrounded, but one who is -- Tuff (Ellary Porterfield) -- learns valuable lessons at 16 when she's able to meet some fellow ace contestants with her mom across the Indiana border.
The trek to get there, and meet Dortha Schaefer (Laura Dern) and her gal friends, marks the first time Evelyn has gone anywhere. Tuff (nickname of author Terry Ryan) asks her mom why she's put up living such a "miserable life," and the mother's stoic response is the film's anthem for grit.
A deception by the pathetic Kelly and a last-minute contest win by Evelyn that rescues the clan from dissolution feel too dramatic, yet there's hardly a moment onscreen that doesn't ring of truth. Huge credit is due Moore, in a fascinating performance that again show's she's among the best American actresses onscreen. Ever mindful she must keep up a good face for the kids, Moore's Evelyn, rather than being a re-creation of '50s-style feminine selflessness, is a character who knows her resourcefulness is the best way for her to fulfill her expected role in life. This makes the her rare emotional breakdowns all the more shattering.
Harrelson, with a limited range of options as little more than a drunken slob who's jealous of his wife's abilities, soon grows tiresome. Dern makes a brief but charming impression, and Porterfield, in a striking debut, crafts a beautiful role built on teen smarts.
Anderson's dalliances with tiny flights of fancy serve as visual contrasts to her deliberately plain direction, which are confidently supported by Jonathan Freeman's desaturated color lensing and a superb design team (production designer Edward T. McAvoy, art director Andrew Stearn and costume designer Hala Bahmet) capturing the period in a way that feels fully lived in.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
