<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep. 27, 2004</date>
<text>
Based on a novel by notorious pre-Revolutionary Russian terrorist Boris Savinkov, Karen Shakhnazarov's costumer "Rider Named Death" instead of using its hot-button issues as a present-day hook, sticks with a 19th century mindset which it accompanies with elegant turn-of-the-century decors. This exquisite, self-contained curio will doubtless travel far on fest circuit and but the sinister hero, sadly lacking in villainous panache, is unlikely to target any but small-screen distribs Stateside.
Gorgeous set design by Ludmila Kusakova stacks the deck even before the plot kicks in: It would be criminal to destroy such stunning works of art as the raspberry-colored palace of the Grand Duke or blow up a masterful layout where even beggars figure as essential parts of the decor.
Director Shakhnazorov's sumptuous set pieces include one staged in a palatial antechamber where a splendidly garbed, ravishing young woman prettily begs for an audience with a minister and, once admitted to the attentive official's presence, calmly pumps him full of lead.
A more explosive assassination attempt fills the cobblestone streets with screaming horses and swirling black smoke that clears to reveal the casualties. Lastly, in the stately marbled halls of the Bolshoi theater, coincidentally empty of guards, an assassin enters the Grand Duke's box and shoots him at point-blank range, while onstage a lively opera continues without pause.
The conspirators meet in a cavernous cabaret where dancers perform a suggestively choreographed can-can, their hairdos, costumes and clownish poses straight out of Toulouse-Lautrec. Except for George (Andrey Panin), the revolutionists' cold fish of a leader, the rank and file's intensity markedly contrasts with the promiscuous decadence of the overall milieu.
Fydor (Rostislav Bershauer), the peasant of the group, is angered at the inequity of the class system that values a woman's dress at 200 times a worker's daily wage. Heinrich (Aleksey Kazakov) was a university intellectual. Idealist Vanya (Artem Semakin), on the other hand, is positively Dostoyevskian in his mystical, romantic belief in good, evil and salvation. Erna (Ksenia Rappoport), bombmaker extraordinaire, is hopelessly in love with George.
The social-revolutionist cell is first introduced at the cabaret wearing masks, and when George removes his, it uncovers a face so willfully devoid of expression that only the sweat on his brow indicates that there is not yet another mask underneath the first. His face recalls the masked figure in the final segment of Ophuls' "Le Plaisir."
A chilly assassin, voluptuously obsessed with his victim's demise, Panin's George seems more dedicated to death than to justice.Tech credits are top drawer.
Camera (color, widescreen), Vladimir Klimov; editor, Lidia Milioti; music, Anatoly Kroll; production designer, Ludmila Kusakova. Reviewed at Montreal World Film Festival (competing), Sept. 3, 2004. Running time: 106 MIN.
 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
