<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Apr. 4, 2005</date>
<text>
Coming across like the love child of Lenny Bruce and Sandra Bernhard, Sarah Silverman has something to offend everyone in the film rendition of her live performance at North Hollywood's El Portal Theater. "Sarah Silverman: Jesus Is Magic" showcases the comic-actress in her familiar on-stage persona as a blithely self-involved Jewish American Princess whose penchant for perky vulgarity can be explosively funny or unnervingly shocking (and sometimes both, simultaneously). Pic should please longtime fans, and may impress viewers who know Silverman only as a quirky character actress ("The School of Rock," TV's "Greg the Bunny").
Despite occasional cutaways to off-stage skits (featuring, among others, fellow comics Brian Posehn and Bob Odenkirk) and a few deliberately cheesy production numbers, pic remains mostly stagebound as Silverman sounds off on various topics in a freewheeling monologue punctuated with songs. As she comments on the absurdities of a world in which she, and she alone, always should be the center of attention, no subject -- not even 9/11 or the Holocaust -- is off limits.
From the start, Silverman indicates everything and everyone, including herself, is fair game during her unflinching pursuit of big laughs. ("I was raped by a doctor -- which is so bittersweet for a Jewish girl.") In fact, she's rarely more hilarious than when she makes herself the punchline of her nastiest cracks. Rail-thin yet full-bosomed, she's sufficiently attractive to infuse her talk of sexual misadventures with none-too-subtle erotic charge.
For some viewers, Silverman's iconoclastic envelope-pushing will be genuinely discomforting, if not completely off-putting. She skates on perilously thin ice as she unapologetically rationalizes her use of language that is, at best, racially insensitive -- and at worst, just plain racist. On the other hand, she diminishes the sting of her tasteless slanguage by reminding the audience that, what the hell, her on-stage persona isn't exactly the sharpest knife in the drawer: "I don't care if you think I'm racist. I just want you to think I'm thin."
Helmer Liam Lynch does a respectable job of using off-stage elements as bridges and counterpoints. To her credit, though, Silverman doesn't cheat during these in-between bits: She remains "in character" even when she's being a backstage prima donna. Her refusal to be easily likable is perversely adorable.
Camera (color, DV), Rhet Baer; music, Lynch, Sarah Silverman; production designer, Henry Arce; costume designer, Dayna Pink; sound (Dolby), Alex Lamm, John Hogan; assistant director, Scott Dorel. Reviewed at South by Southwest Film Festival (Spotlight), March 12, 2005. Running time: 72 MIN.
 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
