<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Feb. 12, 2004</date>
<text>
A triple threat for gay, Jewish and German film festivals, Berlinale Panorama-opener "Walk on Water" attempts the miraculous but achieves the adequate. With its story of a Mossad assassin humanized through his relationship with the German grandchildren of a Nazi war criminal -- one of them a gay man -- helmer Eytan Fox probes themes that bubbled up nicely in his sophomore effort, the Israeli Army closet story "Yossi and Jagger." However, an overly schematic, deeply flawed script and wan perfs keep this from being a crossover crowd-pleaser. "Walk" is likely to struggle in the shallows outside its best-bet Israeli and German markets.
After a tight, Istanbul-set prologue showing main character Eyal (Lior Ashkenazi, "Late Marriage") in action killing a Hamas leader, film sets up an interesting narrative by throwing hawkish, macho Eyal into instant conflict with liberal, cosmopolitan German siblings Axel and Pia Himmelman (Knut Berger and Carolina Peters, respectively). Eyal's assignment is to pose as tour guide while Axel visits his kibbutz-dwelling sister, and to learn the whereabouts of their war-criminal grandpapa Alfred, with whom Eyal's dead mother and avuncular Mossad controller Menachem (Gidon Shemer) had tragic dealings during WWII.
Fox and Uchovsky manage to work some nuance into first two acts. Eyal's rattled sense of self after the suicide of his wife Iris (Nataly Szylman) mirrors German characters' shame about their country's -- and family's --past.
However, all along the way, the plot seems to be chugging toward coupling Eyal and Axel, classic opposites who might attract, starting with scenes where they shower together and discuss their foreskins or lack thereof (before the at-first homophobic Eyal realizes Axel's gay), to the moment Eyal shows up in Berlin looking like a lovelorn puppy. There's manifestly more chemistry between the two men than between Eyal and the woefully underwritten Pia, who seems crowbarred into the happy ending.
Worse, in the climactic Berlin section, the main players are asked to perform seemingly totally out of character. And still other characters pop up out of nowhere for no good reason. Further, a poorly staged fight with some neo-Nazis is jerry-rigged into the mix. Suspension of belief is completely shattered when, after Eyal pulls a gun on the thugs, Axel's first question is, "Why did you bring that?" not "How the hell did you ever get that on a plane from Israel?" as any normal person would ask.
The three comely leads tend to deliver lines in a monotone, especially when speaking in English.
Tech credits are glossy enough to disguise pic's peskier flaws at first, with Tobias Hochstein's colorful, sun-seared lensing a standout. Music is mostly source, and makes great narrative play with one-hit wonder, Europop tune "Cinderella Rockafella," originally recorded by Esther and Abi Ofarim in the late 1960s.
Camera (color), Tobias Hochstein; editor, Yosef Grunfeld; music, Ivri Lider; art directors, Avi Fahima, Christoph Merg; costumes designers, Rona Doron, Peter Pohl; sound (Dolby Digital 5.1), Gil Toren; assistant directors, Tamar Ichilov, Michael Johnson; casting, Yael Aviv, Chun Mei Tan. Reviewed at Berlin Film Festival (Panorama), Feb. 6, 2004. Running time: 102 MIN.

 

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
