<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Apr 19 2005</date>
      <text>Isild Le Besco , the young star of Benoît Jacquot 's Tout de Suite , has the face of someone woken from a thousand-year slumber. Her lids are heavy; her brow is impossibly smooth. With her serene ovoid face and tragic curving mouth, Le Besco would have made a sensational cubist model.
In Tout de Suite , adapted from Elisabeth Fanger 's memoir When I Was 19 , Le Besco plays a character at once passive and daring. The title can be translated as "Right Now," but shot in luminous black-and-white, the movie is set in the mid '70s. Le Besco's Lili is a bored, mildly wanton rich girl&#151;a 19-year-old art student living in her father's labyrinthine Paris apartment. She goes out dancing in a Belleville  dive and falls madly in love with a cherubic-looking Moroccan boy. Innocent as he appears, Bada (Ouassini Embarek) turns out to be a petty criminal; a few nights later, he calls Lili from a botched bank job, replete with hostages and casualties. She shelters him and his surviving confederate, taking it happily on the lam, first in Spain, then Morocco , and finally Greece , where her trip takes a more hazardous, discombobulated, and existential turn.
Lili is more expressive than articulate; not surprisingly for Jacquot, who made his reputation largely as a director of stylish young women in the act of self-actualization, the movie revolves around Le Besco's Picasso -mask visage. Less a tale of desperado lovers than a cruel story of youth, Tout de Suite  is framed largely in close-up, with few transitional shots and a narrative that grows increasingly fragmented. (The filmmaker occasionally interpolates newsreel clips or interjects his protagonist's voice-over to temper the tale's immediacy.)
Jacquot's most recent movies&#151;including Sade , which featured the then teenage Le Besco as a Marquis-smitten ingenue&#151;have been flossy period pieces. Tout de Suite  harks back to the suave and somewhat creepy psychologically fraught trio&#151;The Disenchanted , A Single Girl, Seventh Heaven &#151;that he made during the '90s. Like those, it has its fairy-tale aspect; in this case, it's the story of a sleeping beauty roused.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>