<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Mar 22 2005</date>
      <text>Guess Who   Directed by Kevin Rodney Sullivan   Columbia, in release
Professionally caustic and often brilliant, comedian Bernie Mac  still ain't got nothing on my pops and his friends. After I brought home a decidedly Nordic-featured lass (being a lighter shade of brown myself), my father&#151;who, to his credit, won't spare his only son from a well-aimed jab&#151;shared with me what his friend had said after seeing my Nordiquette and me together: "Your boy done went Tiger Woods  on you." I had to smile because, well, that shit was funny, but funny because it hurt a little bit&#151;funny because the hurt bled truth.
In Guess Who , Mac plays Spencer Tracy  to Ashton Kutcher 's Sidney Poitier  (yeah, I said it), racially inverting Stanley Kramer 's pointed, "pigmentation problem" classic, 1967's Guess Who's Coming to Dinner . Kutcher is&#151;shock&#151;no Poitier, and his performance as Mac's prospective son-in-law is largely textureless. But the screenwriters deserve a cowardly lion's share of the blame. At times no more than a collection of comedic set pieces&#151;Mac and Kutch sharing a bed, listening to "Ebony and Ivory," or racing go-karts&#151;the film is predictable and its humor is tension free, ultimately hurting only Mac, whose lifeblood is his threateningly melodic cadence and irresistible I-say-what-you-scared-to-say vibe. Mac's acidic humor is often predicated on a challenge, revealing the truth at the heart of every quip&#151;his goading of Kutcher to tell black jokes over dinner is Guess Who 's sole piece of genius&#151;and the script's lack of nerve fails to challenge him or its audience with enough dangerous humor. PETER L'OFFICIAL

BEAUTY SHOP    Directed by Bille Woodruff    MGM, opens March 30
A morality play paradoxically pimping self-reliance and community, 2002's Barbershop  stresses the importance of its titular location as a haven for free speech. After being chastised for his boneheaded dismissal of Rosa Parks 's achievements, Cedric the Entertainer 's character asks: "If we can't talk straight in a barbershop, then where can we talk straight?" An extended riff on its progenitor, Beauty Shop also offers opportunities for trenchant observation, though the clientele prefers kinky sex advice to sociopolitical chitchat. Girls just wanna have fun, and so does the film, which recycles the requisite moralizing into a breezy, sporadically funny package. Queen Latifah  takes the Ice Cube  role, playing a cosmetologist who ditches a ritzy Atlanta salon in order to beautify the ladies DIY-style. Highlights include a drive-by bitching from her former boss and a deus ex machina in the form of a pint-sized booty hound.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>