<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jun 12 2007</date>
      <text>Evan Almighty  is the work of an angry God. A sanctimonious sitcom dolled up as the most expensive comedy ever made&#151; $175 mil, so they say, no doubt choking&#151;it marks an unfortunate low point in the history of recent American comedy. There goes Steve Carell 's perfect game.
In short, God (Morgan Freeman , who you know is God because his white linen shirts never wrinkle) tells Evan, an anchor-turned-politician, that if he builds it, they will come&#151;"it" being an ark, "they" being animals lined up two by two. The movie suggests, quite frankly, that God's nothing more than a son of a bitch who's willing to drown thousands of people just to prove that one character&#151;and you'll know who, like, 12 minutes in&#151;is up to no good. Rather than use Evan as a vessel to warn innocent people about impending disaster, God turns the poor guy into a Rogaine  freak show with a messianic complex toward whom elephants and monkeys migrate.
And why does God choose Evan? Because he was played in the original, Bruce Almighty , by Steve Carell, on a roll till now with The Office  and The 40-Year-Old Virgin , in which the former Daily Show   correspondent proved he was willing to debase himself for a well-deserved laugh. Who better to build a sequel around than an actor for whom self-humiliation is considered an act of heroism?
Evan Almighty  actually stoops, repeatedly, to remind you how much you like Carell. There's a movie marquee advertising The 40-Year-Old Virgin Mary  , and the camera actually lingers on it for several seconds. Jon Stewart  appears twice from the Daily Show  set, poking fun at Evan's transformation from suit-and-tie politician into robed messiah. (In the film's holier-than-thou context, Stewart comes off like a godless heathen, which, blessedly, he is.) And several of Carell's Office  and Virgin  cast mates make small cameos. Sweet Lord, how they all try&#151;to no avail. This is PG-rated proselytizing tinged with Al Gore  self-righteousness, all with the narrative thrust of a film about the apocalypse starring Kirk Cameron .
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>