<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Sep 6 2005</date>
      <text>Utterly unfilmable novels don't scare some people&#151;a would-be Cronenberg after a fashion, actor-turned- Yiddishe -auteur Liev Schreiber  has fashioned a serviceable, small-boned adaptation of Jonathan Safran Foer 's inherently defiant, voice-mottled debut book, lean and silly and modest. Not only is Foer's language necessarily dropped from the loop&#151;apart from the inevitable narration, giving us a molecular taste of the Ukrainian protagonist's chaotic consumer English&#151;but so is the mysterious no-man's-land between page and reader, where absurdist ideas are not visualized but can be seen  nonetheless. Schreiber jettisons the novel's juicy mock-folk shtetl legends and focuses on the "very rigid search" of young American neurotic Foer (Elijah Wood ) for the Slavic woman who saved his grandfather from the Nazis. Wood's Foer is an anemic straight-man caricature (hardly the precocious nebbish Foer suggested himself to be), and so texture is provided by Eugene Hutz  (of Gogol Bordello ) as Alex, Foer's Odessa  hipster guide, and grizzled Russian vet Boris Leskin , as Alex's irascible, anti-Semitic, guilt-riddled grandfather.
What tale there is left to tell is reduced to driving (through the Czech Republic ) and mildly comic culture clash conversation&#151;until the three-man convoy reaches the extinct village where Foer's ancestral treasure lies half buried, waiting for rediscovery. Schreiber relies on relentless soundtrack oompah-pah to make the jokes seem like jokes&#151;until the sniffly climax. (Schreiber, like many actor-directors, is indulgent of"heavy" moments of staring and gesture that actually have no weight at all.) Still, Foer's ironic ideas have a lovely roundness to them, and somehow the film achieves Holocaust-fiction balance without much ado or melodrama. It may be substantially less ambitious than its source material, but that may be what saves it from implosion.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>