<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Wednesday, Apr 1 2009</date>
      <text>With the molded-rubber face of Savalas, the basso profundo of Stallone, and the name of an underdog gas alternative, Vin Diesel &#146;s already-dubious ripped-tough-guy star has dimmed enough to warrant a return to the car-chase series that made him&#151;and money. In the latest, notably slack Fast &amp; Furious  (number four), incidental beatdowns are often more exciting than the flaunting of reinforced-steel nerves during cruddily shot speed-racing.
Diesel reprises the role of larcenist/muscle-car- enthusiast Dom Toretto  and stars opposite Paul Walker &#151;whose Timberlakean build could fit inside Diesel&#146;s bulk twice over&#151;as the import-fancying undercover agent Brian O&#146;Conner, our stand-in for Guy with Most Awesome Job Assignment in the World (with his pick of cars from the impound lot). The untimely death of Dom&#146;s partner-in-crime, Letty (Michelle Rodriguez ), sends the rivals converging on thoroughly unremarkable drug-runner Campos  (John Ortiz ); they infiltrate his surefire business model of smuggling heroin across the border via inconspicuous hot rods.
The highlight remains the advertisement: The movie opens with the broad-daylight fuel-tanker hijacking from the no-introduction-needed trailer, but never recovers the hand-rubbing glee of that modular stunt. For a better sense of the movie&#146;s other road sequences, note that the press-kit blurb for Diesel, a WoW and D&amp;D maven, climaxes with his video-game production shingle. Pointing out Xbox  aesthetics has become as familiar a move as bemoaning the continuing disappearance of the frame in mainstream cinema, but sequences in Fast &amp; Furious   are as up-front about imminent adaptation to video game as some directors used to be about accounting for future TV broadcast.
The blindered, vectored-wall look of a tunnel dash to Mexico is straight-up first-person console&#151;an unreal nowhere-space in a genre reliant on door-rattling thrills&#151;while the Campos-sponsored recruitment race in Koreatown features constant GPS street mapping and a disembodied female voice giving updates with tranquilized urgency. Beer-ad nightclub ambience around a couple of race scenes, replete with ladies makin&#146; out, might as well be cut-and-pasted from Grand Theft Auto . And the homogenized complexion, hair, and features of Jordana Brewster , as Dom&#146;s sister and hideout confidante, might as well be computer-generated. (Not that the stunts necessarily need the Tarantino Death Proof   treatment: The feverish rainstorm pursuit in We Own the Night   was famously software-augmented.)
All of which subverts the early praise for the series as journeyman genre work. Director Justin Lin , who also chaperoned the last installment, here probes the significant thrills of outrunning or outwitting a flying burning chassis (though a preview audience seemed just as excited by the reappearance of reggaeton stars Tego Calderón  and Don Omar  in subtitled bit parts). Unlike in Tokyo Drift , Lin doesn&#146;t dig into his locations enough (though, hurray, Bendix  sign!), and seems to be at that awkward stage where he believes that what a Vin Diesel actioner needs is more lugubrious dialogue. Dom&#146;s regretful flirtation with Campos&#146;s assistant (he likes a lady who&#146;s &#147;20 percent angel, 80 percent devil, down-to-earth . . .&#148;) and other interludes are DOA, and once O&#146;Conner has actually broken the nose of his jerkwad FBI  co-worker, scenes at the Union Station &#150;size department are likewise deadweight.
A movie whose second spoken line of dialogue is, candidly, &#147;Let&#146;s make some money&#148; at least ends with a satisfyingly ludicrous desert pile-on, with (wholly unnecessary) provisions for a sequel. But whether you blame the Part Four blues, the Dom-O&#146;Conner stalemate, or Diesel&#146;s distraction by the prospect of starring in and making a video game of Carthaginian general Hannibal, Fast &amp; Furious   reconfirms that car-chase movies&#151;good, bad, or mediocre&#151;all assume the future employment of the quaint old fast-forward button.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>