<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Dec 13 2005</date>
      <text>Have enough news cycles now passed for the Enron  debacle to be funny? Probably not to anyone whose "retirement" will be spent greeting shoppers at the local low-price emporium, and certainly not to that company's dazed, pocket-picked employees and shareholders. But with his toothless remake of 1977's Fun With Dick and Jane , moneybags producer Brian Grazer &#151;whose shit-into-gold touch makes him as immune to financial insecurity as he is to cinematic relevance&#151;is gambling that the rest of us will find the last half-decade of corporate malfeasance a real scream. Who says Hollywood  is out of touch with mainstream America?
Dick &amp; Jane  stars Jim Carrey  as Dick Harper, a self-satisfied, upwardly mobile marcom shill for a '90s-style media conglomerate who's promoted to VP shortly before the firm collapses. The stereotypical trappings of Dick's success&#151;generic McMansion, spanking-new BMW , Latina domestic&#151;are thus put in jeopardy, and he and his wife, Jane (Teá Leoni ), subsequently embark on a series of unfunny vignettes in which frugality, menial labor, illegal immigration, petty crime, and yes, Wal-Mart  serve as the butt of jokes. To no one's surprise the couple gets everything back, with some newfound humility to boot.
Director Dean Parisot , who exhibits little in the way of visual imagination but at least showed a flair for broad humor in 1999's Galaxy Quest  , seems undermotivated by Judd Apatow  and Nicholas Stoller 's rushed, flaccid screenplay. It's one thing to milk humor and pathos from a Star Trek   send-up, though, and quite another to make sudden destitution hilarious without seeming like a jerk. Ted Kotcheff  couldn't pull it off in the original Dick and Jane , either, but he had two charismatic leads (George Segal  and Jane Fonda ) with chemistry. Parisot has Carrey, whose obsessive mugging subverts any attempt at anything but the most manic tone, a checked-out Leoni, and Alec Baldwin  unconvincingly channeling Ken Lay  and Dubya as a corrupt CEO. Plus, he's stuck with this story in the age of Bush, whose sympathies lie with the Ken Lays of the world; slapstick might have been the perfect vehicle to expose middle-class myopia 30 years ago, but these days only the blackest of farces will do. This Dick &amp; Jane  is precisely the kind of social-problem comedy you'd expect from well-intentioned millionaires unaccustomed to putting their money where their mouths are.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>