<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Nov 8 2005</date>
      <text>It begins in nightmare and ends in a labyrinth, a shape right out of Borges. Along the way, Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire , the fourth filmed installment of J.K. Rowling 's still-unfolding boy-wizard saga, pulls out all the stops, relentlessly spinning adolescent terrors into metaphor: whiplash teleportation, dragons and disguises, octopoid nasties, screaming golden eggs, and a clammy-palmed interlude of ballroom dancing. Like a dream, it's everywhere and nowhere, by turns scarily intense and scattered. It yearns for forbidden space, delivering an underwater dumb show, a roof-clinging melee, a graveside revelation. If the entire Potter enterprise is a cash cow, at least it's one with two heads and three or four tails. To this viewer and reader, the decade-old juggernaut is as deeply felt as it is flawed, dense and illogical and laudably weird .
By this point, surely, you're either in or you're out: Those who haven't kept up with the Potteriad shouldn't take their first sip at the Goblet . Given the sheer cumulative density of plot points and players, Number Four sometimes only has time (even at nearly two and a half hours) to allude to past actions and characterizations. Even Harry's hotly anticipated nascent love interest, Cho Chang  (Katie Leung , sporting a killer Scottish accent), gets shunted to the wings. Things frequently move too fast&#151;who are the Death Eaters , again?&#151;even for the initiated. But as far as backstory goes, the only one that matters is Harry's, repeatedly (if not always clearly) referenced here: the death of his parents at the hands of Lord Voldemort , an attack that the infant Harry mystifyingly survived. The series' obsession with this primal wound, which started out as a mainline to everyone's deep-seated dread of orphanhood, here reaches its delirious, histrionic peak.
Goblet 's setup isn't particularly inspired. Contingents from two wizardry schools&#151;an Eastern European manly-man academy and a French girls' seminary&#151;visit Hogwarts  for the Triwizard Tournament, revived after a century of neglect. The eponymous vessel (a cover version of the sorting hat in Sorcerer's Stone ) spits forth the name of one upperclassperson from each school&#151;and for some reason taps the underage Harry (Daniel Radcliffe ) as well. The contest is borderline sadistic, less a test of imagination than grit, at one point recalling the hold-your-breath torture sessions of Fear Factor , if not the Saw  franchise.
It's hard to believe that any educational program outside the Navy SEALs  would condone (let alone enshrine) such a brutal tradition. Still, as we settle into the framework, it becomes clear how the tourney's structured violence mirrors the ferocious energies coursing through Goble t 's subterranean storyline, which focuses on the advent of Voldemort, a/k/a He Who Must Not Be Named, a/a/k/a You Know Who. (At the very least, this triathlon beats having to watch another inning of Quidditch.)
Unlike the lapidary events of Middle-earth (or Narnia ), Rowling's imaginings as yet have no end. The relatively quick book-to-film transfer, and the growing length and looser structures of her tomes, mean that despite all the filters of publishing and producing, what we're getting has a strange, ineradicable rawness. As Harry, Radcliffe is a touch less petulant than previously, but he's still not quite likable, a half-contained id itching for a fight, with I suppose the superego and ego roles filled by his more accessible buds, Hermione (Emma Watson ) and Ron (Rupert Grint , sporting Jagger-esque 'do). And though Ralph Fiennes 's suitably creepy Voldemort has no nose, the whole savage mess still smells like teen spirit.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>