<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Aug 18 2009</date>
      <text>Energetic, inventive, swaggering fun, Quentin Tarantino 's Inglourious Basterds  is a consummate Hollywood  entertainment—rich in fantasy and blithely amoral.
It's also quintessential Tarantino—even more drenched in film references than gore, with a proudly misspelled title (lifted from Italian genre-meister Enzo Castellari 's 1978 Dirty Dozen  knockoff) to underscore the movie's cinematic hyperliteracy. Tepidly received in Cannes , and thereafter tweaked, Inglourious Basterds  may still be a tad long at two and a half hours and a little too pleased with itself, but it's tough to resist the enthusiastic performances and terrific dialogue—if you're not put off by the juvenile premise or cartoonish savagery. (See Ella Taylor 's interview with Quentin Tarantino here .)
Not the year's preeminent genre exercise (The Hurt Locker  is a superior war film, as well as a serious reworking of the Hawksian group drama), Inglourious Basterds  is something sui generis—a two-fisted Hollywood occupation romance, in which a Jewish special unit wreaks vengeance on the Nazis. It also has the best Western opener in decades: The first of five chapters nods to Sergio Leone  with the title "Once Upon a Time in Nazi-Occupied France," and to the genre in general with a shot of a French farm family hanging their laundry as a Nazi convoy approaches in the distance like a Comanche band. Violence is not immediately forthcoming—Inglourious Basterds  is as much talk-talk as bang-bang. Or rather, as Andrew Sarris  described the characteristic Budd Boetticher  Western, it's a "floating poker game," in which characters, many of whom have assumed false identities, take turns bluffing for their lives.
The first of a half-dozen one-on-one verbal jousts pits a taciturn salt-of-the-earth peasant against a loquacious Nazi colonel, Hans Landa  (Christoph Waltz ), who, humorously officious, hypnotizes his prey with a twinkling eye, giant grin, and steady stream of civilized chatter. Landa, the S.S. functionary assigned to rid France of Jews, is not only the movie's villain, but also its master of revels. Waltz's turn isn't the lone showy performance—Mike Myers  has a ripe cameo as the British general who conceives the film's convoluted Operation Kino, and Diane Kruger  is convincingly unconvincing as a German movie diva channeling Mata Hari. (Her exasperated "Can you Americans speak any other language except English?" brought down the house at Cannes.)
But there's a reason why the hitherto unknown Waltz was named Best Actor at Cannes, appears on the current Film Comment  cover, and is the subject of an "Arts &amp; Leisure" profile. Waltz's elegant and clever S.S. man is the movie's most crowd-pleasing creation—another in the long line of glamorous Hollywood Nazis. (See: Tom Cruise  in Valkyrie  for a recent example.) Indeed, this smooth operator is Eichmann as fun guy! He's also a European sissy whose "barbaric" antagonists are a squad of Jewish-American commandos led by wily hillbilly Aldo Raine  (Brad Pitt ). The Jews are out for blood, and Raine promises his eponymous Basterds that, under his leadership, they will terrorize the Germans with "Apache tactics," demanding only that each contribute 100 Nazi scalps.
Given its subject and the director's track record, Inglourious Basterds  has less mayhem than one might expect. There's nothing comparable here—either as choreographed violence or virtuoso filmmaking—to the D-Day landing that opens Saving Private Ryan . (But neither is there anything as false, sanctimonious, and emotionally manipulative as the rest of Spielberg's movie.) Inglourious Basterds  is essentially conceptual and, as with any Western, all about determining the nature of permissible aggression. Operating like a cross between the Dirty Dozen and a Nazi death squad, the Basterds take no prisoners—designated "survivors" are shipped back to Germany, swastikas carved in their foreheads to spook the brass. The rest are sent to Valhalla, most spectacularly by Sgt. Donny Donowitz  (exploitation director Eli Roth ), who uses a Louisville  slugger to bash German brains. "Watching Donny beat Nazis to death is as close as we get to the movies," one of the Basterds exults, tipping Tarantino's hand.
The heroine of, and most artificial construct in, Inglourious Basterds  is Shosanna Dreyfus  (Mélanie Laurent ), Jewish survivor of a Nazi massacre, hiding in plain sight as the proprietress of a Paris movie theater. "We have respect for directors in this country," she curtly tells the flirtatious German soldier who wonders why she includes G.W. Pabst 's name on her marquee. Shosanna articulates Tarantino's own cinephile credo: His characters live and die in (and sometimes at) the movies, and only there. Tarantino can't resist dispatching two characters in a John Woo –style slow-mo double shoot-out staged in a projection booth, or taunting Hitler  (Martin Wuttke ) and Goebbels (Sylvester Groth , re-creating his role in Dani Levy 's recently released My Führer ) by forcing them to witness an allusion from their supposed favorite movie—Metropolis  —in what could be their final moments on earth.
In a sense, Inglourious Basterds  is a form of science fiction. Everything unfolds in and maps an alternate universe: The Movies. Even Shosanna's Parisian neighborhood bears a marked resemblance to a Cannes back alley, complete with a club named for a notorious local dive. Inflammable nitrate film is a secret weapon. Goebbels is an evil producer; the German war hero who pursues Shosanna has (like America's real-life Audie Murphy ) become a movie star. Set to David Bowie 's Cat People  title-song, the scene in which Shosanna—who is, of course, also an actor—applies her war paint to become the glamorous "face of Jewish vengeance," is an interpolated music video. Actresses give autographs at their peril. The spectacular climax has the newly dead address those about to die from the silver screen. Operation Kino depends not only on Shosanna's movie house and the German movie diva's complicity, but a heroic film critic (!), played by Michael Fassbender .
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>