<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Mar 21 2006</date>
      <text>Iron Island  opens (like many Iranian features) by invoking "the name of God," then provides an image that could be said to say: Let there be light. The second feature by 33-year-old Mohammad Rasoulof , showing this week in New Directors/New Films, is an obvious allegory. But it's an unusually vivid, even visceral one for being set almost entirely on an abandoned oil tanker&#151;a corroded planet adrift in the azure cosmos of the Persian Gulf .
The ark is a floating neighborhood populated by an assortment of cute kids, busybody octogenarians, and women masked in stylized burkas. (According to press notes written by critic Godfrey Cheshire , the boat's inhabitants are largely Bandaris&#151;members of Iran 's small Sunni Arab minority&#151;and thus exotic even in a Persian context.) Giving advice, delivering orders, making matches, working his cell phone, setting cultural policy, and dispensing God's justice, Captain Nemat (the well-known actor Ali Nasirian ) is the father of his "tenants"; as his name echoes Jules Verne 's Captain Nemo, he variously assumes the more primally patriarchal roles of Abraham, Noah, and Moses.
There's a timeless, elemental quality to the situation, but Captain Nemat's reign is not without incident. The densely packed boat is thrown into a tumult by a bit of unsanctioned boy-girl infatuation. A woman dies in childbirth. Some young people smuggle a TV on board. Nemat confiscates it and tosses it over the side. Then the threat of forced evacuation prompts the captain to pull up anchor. His boat is on the ocean . . . and, as he is loath to admit, taking on water.
Rife as it seems with political points, Rasoulof's fable might almost be a kid's film were it not for a disturbing sequence in which the kindly old captain turns abruptly cruel and tortures a teenage runaway by repeatedly dunking him in the drink. It's an object lesson for his people: "If I let him go there'll be chaos on this ship." Soon after, the ark makes for land, where Nemat secures everyone's power of attorney and, promising a beautiful new town, sends them wandering through the desert.
Part Pentateuch, part Animal Farm , Iron Island  is closer to Makhmalbaf faux naïveté than Kiarostami modernism. Depending on one's mood, the movie might seem boldly simplified and poetic&#151;or boringly simpleminded and prosaic. Either way, Iron Island  poses the question that was always asked of movies produced behind the Iron Curtain and later in China: How was it shown at home and what does it mean there?
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>