<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jul 12 2005</date>
      <text>Anyone who has ever endured the brute skull crunch of a Michael Bay  movie will find that The Island , the director's stab at icy, dystopian sci-fi, is virtually an art film by comparison. For almost a full hour, the narrative endeavors to withhold information and even smuggles in high-toned references to Stanley Kubrick  and Shirley Jackson . There are no undermotivated explosions; shots last for seconds at a time. By the frat-metal standards of Bad Boys, The Rock , and Armageddon , the pace is downright Tarkovskian. The perhaps deliberate effect of this unusual temperance is that you can't wait for Bay to start blowing shit up.
In the post-apocalyptic year 2019, Ewan McGregor  and Scarlett Johansson  are the hottest inhabitants of a regimented colony that, with its retro-future hyperdesign and newfangled smart drinks, has the oppressive vibe not of a supermax facility but of a boutique hotel in the meatpacking district. Residents wear fetching white bodysuits reminiscent of '60s&#150;'70s sci-fi and the house rules are derived from early-21st-century reality TV: The winner of a weekly lottery is transported to the Island, "Earth's last remaining pathogen-free zone."
But as even the trailer reveals, and as should be instantly apparent from the presence of Sean Bean  as a doctor with a God complex (poor Steve Buscemi  is left to diagnose the condition: "It's called a God complex"), there is no Island and there was no viral disaster. The sealed-off outpost houses clones who are being harvested for organ donations and have been implanted with fake memories&#151;in this near future, millionaires have the option of purchasing their very own genetic replicants as spare-parts insurance policies. As a cautionary scenario, it's hardly original but it has bottomless resonance: Adopting a sidelong approach to a similar premise, Kazuo Ishiguro 's recent novel Never Let Me Go  is a marvel of sneaky understatement, occluded details and ominous euphemisms adding up to a wrenching investigation of what it means to be human, to be conscious of mortality. But for Bay, restraint means not dropping a fireball on a large urban center within the first act. In a blockbuster season freighted with grim allegory, The Island  seems especially dim and literal minded. It recognizes a certain hot-button relevance in its subject, but can't get beyond thumbs-up/thumbs-down assessments: clones good, science bad. (If someone were to gently point out that the science was responsible for the clones, you suspect the movie would self-destruct.)
When the stars escape into the outside world, Bay himself seems liberated. (From start to finish, though, he fulfills his product placement duties like a pro: The Island , like Minority Report , envisions the future as an ad-saturated consumer paradise; the brazen prominence of the brand names seeks to put the act of selling in quotes, except it doesn't.) As for the chases and shoot-outs, suffice to say the virtuosic clumsiness of Bay's action style, simultaneously lumbering and kinetic, reaches a new apotheosis in The Island 's best sequence. I can't remember why exactly, but at one point McGregor and Johansson are zipping down a freeway on a big rig, tossing giant metal spools into traffic, percussive dents serving as rhythm section on the concussive soundtrack. This is pure essence of Bay&#151;it's big, it's loud, it has no context, and if you show up tanked, I'm sure it's really quite poetic.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>