<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Feb 22 2005</date>
      <text>Broadly speaking, there are two kinds of time-travel movies&#151;one in which the protagonist's attempts to meddle with chronological cause and effect result in a traumatic collapse of the space-time continuum, the other in which a malleable universe grants infinite license to the laissez-faire time traveler, who doesn't stop tampering until everything is exactly as he or she pleases. While last year's Primer  is a sterling example of the cautionary mode, The Jacket  subscribes to the latter ideology with dubious vigor: Casting aside metaphysical dilemmas and political subtexts, the film devotes itself solely to securing an acceptable outcome for its war-traumatized hero.
The Jacket  steals its notion of a man haunted by his own death from any number of La Jetée  variants, but mostly, given the suggestion of post-combat syndrome, from Jacob's Ladder . After suffering a near-fatal gunshot to the head from an Iraqi child during the first Gulf war, Jack Starks  (Adrien Brody ) is shipped home to snowy Vermont . One disorienting day, he stops to help a drunk woman (Kelly Lynch) and her daughter, winds up in a shoot-out, and is arrested for killing a cop. Sentenced to a mental institution, Starks, suffering from partial amnesia, is subjected to a highly experimental treatment by the baleful Dr. Becker (Kris Kristofferson )&#151;electroshocked, straitjacketed, and shoved into a mortuary drawer that has the properties of a time machine.
Commuting between 1992 and 2007, where Starks soon begins romancing the now grown little girl (Keira Knightley ), The Jacket  is a disappointing nosedive into the mainstream for John Maybury , the Derek Jarman  acolyte who transitioned successfully from experimental work to features with 1998's hallucinatory Francis Bacon  biopic Love Is the Devil . Maybury gives the movie's night-sweat visions a strobing, vaguely avant-garde flourish, but proves only that he's a cut above the average David Fincher  wannabe. The hero's condition, which goes unconnected to the amnesia of war, instead becomes an allegory for a filmmaker forgetting his roots.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>