<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Sep 18 2007</date>
      <text>Concluding a month that brought the sixth commemoration of 9/11, a video missive from Osama bin Laden , and a surge endorsement by General David Petraeus , The Kingdom  is a timely&#151;if tepid&#151;fantasy of American vengeance on the Qutbian extremists of Saudi Arabia .
Directed by Peter Berg  from Matthew Michael Carnahan 's screenplay, The Kingdom  opens by analogizing the attack on the World Trade Center . A gang of Saudi terrorists orchestrate a Sunday-afternoon assault on an American compound in Riyadh &#151; complete with stormed checkpoint, suicide bombers, and a massive, strategically delayed explosion. The grounds are littered with civilians, but the key casualty is a visiting FBI agent .
Cut to D.C., where the incensed FBI would gladly invade Saudi Arabia were it not for the timidity of craven bureaucrats&#151;mainly the U.S. attorney general. (In this alternate universe, the attorney general panders to the Senate, not the president.) The most gung-ho of FBI agents is Jamie Foxx , a volatile woof-machine who intimidates a stray Saudi prince into signing off on an FBI mission to solve the crime. Actually, Foxx is the movie's surrogate president; in his softer moments, he comforts fatherless boys and effects twangy New Age reconciliation.
Leading the mission to Mars (the locations mix Arizona and Abu Dhabi ), Foxx is accompanied by a demographically provocative trio. There's a hard-bodied, no-nonsense chick (Jennifer Garner ), a wise-guy Jew (Jason Bateman ), and a good- natured good ol' boy (Chris Cooper ). Can you guess which of the three will be abducted and made the subject of a throat-slit video? And here's another puzzler: Are there any good Saudis&#151;and, if so, who are they? By their appealing looks and appreciation of Foxx's street cred shall we know them: "America is not perfect, but we are good at this. Let us help you," Foxx pleads with the local chief of police (the Arab-Israeli actor Ashraf Barhom , who played a suicide bomber in Paradise Now ).
Should terrorism, as John Kerry  suggested, be handled as a crime? Halfway through the movie, the FBI agents go Marine. United in vengeance, the combined American and Saudi forces eventually eschew dull procedure for thrilling car-chase action, ending with a firefight in a very bad neighborhood. (Call it "Black Hawk downtown.") A hand-to-hand slamming-gouging-stabbing denouement got a mild rise out of the preview audience at the Loews 83rd Street, but the movie's main satisfaction is the utopian spectacle of wounded Americans heading home, mission accomplished.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>