<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Oct 30 2007</date>
      <text>Less a war drama than a set of dueling position papers, Robert Redford 's Lions for Lambs  may be the gabbiest movie ever made about American foreign policy&#151;and it wasn't even written by Aaron Sorkin . Hot young screenwriter Matthew Michael Carnahan  is fresh off his alpha-male script forThe Kingdom , which would explain the presence early on of that movie's director, Peter Berg , striding around Afghanistan  in a buzz cut and stiff upper lip, barking bytes from Von Clausewitz  and imploring his noticeably minority foot soldiers to show the enemy "the full measure of American mean." Compared to facing the meanie back home in Washington&#151;a Republican hardbody played by Tom Cruise  in crisp white shirt, sparkly molars, and oodles of blind ambition&#151;the war zone Over There is peanuts.
We find the senator in his office, hectoring a tough old broad of a journalist in comfy '60s-liberal tweeds (Meryl Streep ) about the need for a surge to end all surges in the Middle East. She lectures him right back on the folly of United States warmongering, and to drive the point home, we head west to "a California university," where a world-weary professor and Vietnam  vet (Redford) cuts a deal that only a celluloid academic could make without losing his job: He promises straight B's to a disaffected failing student (Andrew Garfield ) on the condition that he cast sloth aside to become all that he can be against the war.
For a movie so relentlessly bent on realism, Lions for Lambs  is riddled with implausibilities. Would a rising young Republican with an acquisitive eye on the presidency choose a liberal reporter with the stubborn intractability of a Christiane Amanpour  to push his latest war on terror? Are today's college youth really as politically lethargic as this privileged white boy? Would his star classmates, an African-American (Derek Luke ) and a Latino (Michael Peña ), having boot-strapped themselves out of East L.A., chuck it all away and blithely join the Army in order to become the movie's conscience?
Known for making stately, linear films with lovely sunsets, Redford has none of the piss and vinegar, the technical bravura, or the hip irony of younger directors making political films, like Stephen Gaghan  or Paul Greengrass . His editing is artless, the action scenes listless, the characters almost entirely representational of the political attitudes they strike. Researched, data-crunched and op-eded to the hilt, Lions for Lambs  talks and talks and TALKS your head off as it lumbers toward complete coverage of the state of our nation.
What can I tell you? The movie is awful&#151;and also oddly touching, even adorable in its dogged sense of responsibility, its stubborn refusal of style. There's something refreshing about a movie as earnest and well-briefed as this one. Redford is no intellectual, but I found myself unaccountably charmed by his lack of cynicism, his old-fangled desire to plead the case of ordinary people caught up in the reckless aggression of the powerful.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>