<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Wednesday, Jul 16 2008</date>
      <text>I've always enjoyed ABBA &#151;not in that post-hoc, so-bad-it&#146;s good hip way, but innocently, the way I like Phil Spector . To this day, howling along in my car to that echoing, cascading, multiply overdubbed wall of sound makes me feel like a member of some dippy but joyous cathedral choir. So I was crushed to learn that the score for Mamma Mia!  isn&#146;t canned ABBA&#151;the only way to enjoy those dumb-blonde lyrics&#151;but ABBA covers, sort of.
Sure, it&#146;s nice that the actors sing their own numbers and all that &#151;we already know from Postcards From the Edge  and A Prairie Home Companion  that Meryl Streep  has a fab set of pipes, and the fact that Pierce Brosnan  sings like a bullfrog in heat is used in the movie to adorable effect. But without all the in-studio bells and whistles, the tunes go flat and the words beyond silly, and the only time the music gets its due is when it&#146;s paired with big production numbers, in those rare moments when Mamma Mia!  decides to be itself: a flashy, appealingly vulgar, tirelessly nostalgic pub crawl through a narrow street in 1970s pop history, when flower power turned to glitter rock.
Mostly, though, Mamma Mia!  is a collection of droopy ditties draped around a threadbare plot about the daughter of a single-mother hippie who secretly invites three men&#151;each of whom might be her long-lost father&#151;to her Greek island wedding. Threes are the name of the relentlessly symmetrical game here: Sophie, the daughter (wide-eyed, pearly-toothed, vacantly smiling Amanda Seyfried ), is joined by two similarly dewy OMG-ing BFFs who serve as bridesmaids and help her rummage through her mother&#146;s 20-year-old diary for clues to her paternity. From various glamorous global locales come the candidates, three middle-aged men in a boat: Brosnan as Sam the businessman; Colin Firth , doing his usual endearing stiff as a pent-up banker; and Stellan Skarsgard , looking as though he&#146;d rather be anywhere but here, as a writer with &#147;unavailable&#148; written all over him. All three are conveniently unattached, which means nothing, nudge-nudge, to the self-sufficient female trio (Streep, with Julie Walters  and Christine Baranski  for backup) who play out the movie&#146;s themes of regret, courage, and generation gap.
For all its half-hearted stabs at catering to the transatlantic youth market (with a little gift tucked in for the stage show&#146;s voluminous gay following), Mamma Mia!  is a (Shirley) valentine to fiftysomething, we&#146;re-not-done-yet broads. The three fiftysomething British broads&#151;director Phyllida Lloyd , screenwriter Catherine Johnson , and co-producer Judy Craymer&#151;who so successfully courted that wildly under-served demographic in the smash-hit stage version of Mamma Mia!  came on board the movie with no prior film experience. They haven&#146;t a clue, and though their screw-it-all ineptitude lends the movie a sporadically infectious gaiety, basically it&#146;s a mess.
Like many theater types on their first outing in movies, Lloyd gets anxiously busy with a hyperactive camera, shooting from above, below, and upside-down, and scooting endlessly over the sparkling blue Aegean like a travelogue parody gone wild. Worst of all, she keeps homing in on Streep, who over-emotes with growing desperation as she tries to pull off serious character acting and a vaudeville turn at the same time. For all her girlish simpers and acrobatic splits, the actress in Streep inevitably triumphs. Though she has some touchingly wistful moments as a hippie mom trying to grasp her daughter&#146;s reactive desire for stability and a fancy wedding, as a performer Streep is completely eclipsed by Baranski. With the legs of Cyd Charisse  and the arch wit of a sitcom sidekick, Baranski steals the show in a coyly filthy dance number with a corps de ballet  of pectorally gifted young blades, who show up elsewhere doing a hilarious routine with frogman flippers.
It&#146;s with moments like these&#151;and the show-stoppingly sublime glam-rock performances by oldsters who know better but refuse to give in to their stiffening knees&#151;that Mamma Mia!  comes into its own and frankly takes ownership of what it is: a stage musical that made a big ol&#146; heap of money, shamelessly shoved onto the big screen to make a whole lot more. Given that the movie has no tale worth the telling, we&#146;ll see.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>