<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Wednesday, Mar 25 2009</date>
      <text>
At the end of 2008, DreamWorks Animation  bossman Jeffrey Katzenberg  embarked on a cross-country tour, toting 20 minutes&#146; worth of Monsters vs. Aliens . The reason for his trek? To convince critics that 3-D movies are no longer the snake-oil salesman&#146;s hustle, but the future of filmmaking&#151;if not the very savior of big-screen cinema. &#147;Emotionally immersive,&#148; the prophet called it. The Last Word in &#147;the shared communal experience.&#148;
The five-year-old sitting beside me at a preview screening of Monsters vs. Aliens  last weekend offered his own endorsement not 10 seconds into the movie&#151;around the time chunks of blown-up planet appeared to land in his lap. &#147;Whoa , Dad,&#148; he said. &#147;Awesome .&#148; The chorus of children around us agreed, as the theater echoed with giggles, squeals, and the random bleats of adolescent amazement.
Directed by Rob Letterman  and Conrad Vernon  from a screenplay written by more than half a dozen, Monsters vs. Aliens  will heretofore be known as the first 3-D movie to genuinely and effectively and astoundingly merge screen and theater, actors (well . . .) and audience&#151;it&#146;s The Purple Rose of Cairo   come to life, starring a gelatinous blue blob named Bicarbonate Ostylezene Benzoate . . . or B.O.B. It renders all previous comers headache-inducing charlatans, rinky-dink pretenders. For the first time in the medium&#146;s history, you are there&#151;from the president&#146;s war room (shades of Dr. Strangelove) to a prison facility where the government&#146;s been storing assorted mutants and monsters collected since the 1950s.
Of course, such places, plot points, and predicaments&#151;and the attempt to shove them and a red paddle ball in your face&#151;have been around just as long; Monsters vs. Aliens  is a tomorrow very much indebted to movie&#146;s yesterdays. B.O.B. (voiced by Seth Rogen , nearly as genius a move as the 3-D) has slithered out of Irvin Yeaworth Jr. &#146;s 1958 Z-grade classic The Blob , but this time, the blob&#146;s a former ripe red tomato injected with ranch-flavored dessert topping, thus rendering him a shape-shifting stoner, a blissfully self-aware naïf with a crush on lime-green Jell-O . Will Arnett  voices the Missing Link, a defrosted ape-fish known for terrorizing spring breakers on Cocoa Beach  back in 1961; only the Link can communicate with Insectosaurus, a 350-foot-tall silk-snotting grub who&#146;s been exposed to nuclear radiation. The film even comes with its very own version of Vincent Price : Hugh Laurie  as Dr. Cockroach, the mad scientist who sports the noggin of a cockroach and the bwah-haw-haw  of his fiendish ancestors.
Reese Witherspoon  is more or less the film&#146;s star: Susan Murphy  of Modesto , turned a lovely shade of glowing green by a stray meteorite on the day she was to wed an ambitious weatherman named Derek (Paul Rudd ), who&#146;s not terribly well-equipped to deal with a suddenly 50-foot-tall fiancée. The egomaniacal Derek, looking to make the move to bigger-market Fresno , can&#146;t live in a shadow that size. Which is just as well: Susan is woman, hear her roar as Ginormica, rounded up by the government and recruited to save the planet from the invading five-eyed blowhard Gallaxhar (voiced by Rainn Wilson , who has turned being a self-aggrandizing blowhard into an art form).
That&#146;s the story: alien-invasion camp commingled with yet another Dr. Strangelove  paranoia parody, strictly playbook material. DreamWorks&#146; kidult-friendly pop-culture mash-ups&#151;Shrek   (as disposable as an episode of Best Week Ever  rebroadcast two years later), Bee Movie  (nothing more than a way-too-long episode of Seinfeld ), and Over the Hedge  (admit it, you forgot all about that one)&#151;banked the funds that paid for Monsters &#146; R&amp;D. They were stepping stones to the mountaintop: the ultimate interactive mash-up, the cinematic equivalent of what Nintendo  offered gamers with the Wii , the you-are-there experience.
Monsters vs. Aliens  was conceived from jump as a 3-D work, so every single plot point is tethered to the attendant visual bang&#151;the waves of heat emanating from the military&#146;s attack on a mountainous alien probe; the slabs of concrete falling off the Golden Gate Bridge  as it disintegrates into the bay; the armies of clones marching through Gallaxhar&#146;s cavernous spaceship; the vast spaces of the Area 51 prison, which looks as though it reaches back a good half-mile.
But children who see the movie on DVD in a few months will wonder what happened to their roller coaster as it morphs into little more than a bumper-car ride. Take away the 3-D, and this is significantly more slight than, say, Madagascar 2  or Kung Fu Panda , DreamWorks movies that had to rely more on the clever factor than the wow factor. The chasm between Monsters vs. Aliens &#146; technical accomplishment and artistic achievement is vast: The story&#146;s familiar, and as good as the performers are, they&#146;re still doing their trademark shtick (though Stephen Colbert  as the President is a stroke of casting brilliance). But the grandeur of the effects&#151;the honest-to-God spectacle of the thing&#151;elevates Monsters vs. Aliens  to something approaching art. It&#146;s not a masterpiece, but it&#146;s most certainly a milestone.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>