<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jun 20 2006</date>
      <text>Hardly a native flowering of extra-mainstream vision these days, American indies are trapped in a ghetto of second-class homogenization, less pandering than Hollywood  but just as conservative. The little-people semi-stories, colorless dialogue, stiff-legged acting, sniffly amused middle-class soundtracks, deficit of visual intelligence: It's a cinema its own lower-middle-class characters would find dull and patronizing, not due to narrative asceticism but for the lack of ambition or imagination. The Motel , Michael Kang 's modest Sundance applause reaper, doesn't deserve to be shotgunned for the sins of 30 other movies. But the underwhelming syncopation of make-nice clichés is too familiar. Based on a novel by Ed Lin , Kang's film is a pubertal dramedy centered on Ernest (Jeffrey Chyau ), a Chinese American 13-year-old junk-foodie who works as a maid at his mother's backwater motel. There he impassively finds discarded porn, hangs with a 16-year-old waitress (Samantha Futerman ), puts up with bullies, argues with his regally ferocious mother (Jade Wu ) about a writing contest he entered, and learns about irresponsible loitering from a lonely Korean American whoremonger (Sung Kang ) who leaves only to pick up booty and booze.
Kang shot his film in Poughkeepsie , but the locale has been anonymized, and the blind tumble into banality is easy and inevitable. ("I hate you!" Ernest eventually hollers at his hard-case mom; "You need me!" Ernest is told by his new hooker-loving pal; "I don't need anyone!" is the reply.) If The Motel  circles around to a single effective moment of generational confrontation amid the sulking, credit should perhaps go to Wu, expertly limning out the script's most interesting character by far, a fearless immigrant woman we first see busting down a goldbricker's door with a baseball bat. She radiates experience, which is more than can be said about the filmmakers. Michael Atkinson
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>