<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, May 24 2005</date>
      <text>Rock of underages: Kids get Zap-tized by tyrannical tutor
The short-fused motormouth who runs the Paul Green School of Rock Music , an after-school program for nine-to-17-year-olds in Philadelphia , has claimed, not unreasonably, to be the inspiration for Jack Black 's character in School of Rock. But where Richard Linklater 's movie approached its central incongruity&#151;the idea that anti-establishment rock can and should be schooled &#151;with a breezy mix of ironic farce and fuck-the-Man feelgoodism, Paul Green , the frustrated musician and self-proclaimed "really good teacher" at the center of this documentary, embraces the same philosophy with grim, cranky resolve. Students like Madi, a Quaker folkie, and Will, the resident depressive, attest that rock school is a misfit sanctuary and that Green's manic tantrums serve a motivational purpose. In any case, as Will deadpans, "It's a lovable quirk that he's mentally disturbed."
But with his Hannibal Lecter  impersonations, Vietnam  P.O.W. re-enactments, and borderline abusive teasing, Green tends to be more actively unpleasant than amusing. He almost gets misty-eyed envisioning a 2007 issue of Rolling Stone : "Where did all these bands come from? All of a sudden they start tracing stuff back to me." Given that Green's curriculum is even more ossified than his fictional counterpart's, this immodest forecast assumes the resurgent popularity of Frank Zappa -style art-prog. There's plenty of talent on display&#151;12-year-old guitar prodigy CJ kills every time he's on&#151;but as the kids dutifully make the pilgrimage to Germany 's tribute-band Zappanale, it's depressingly clear whose dreams they're acting out. (Is it really fair to be force-feeding drug music to listeners who aren't, um, properly equipped to enjoy it?) Don Argott's lively documentary, ostensibly a paean to alternative pedagogy, extends its subject a long leash, and he in turn does his damnedest to sabotage the project. Rock School ends up being a movie about just how little fun rock 'n' roll can be.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>