<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, May 13 2008</date>
      <text>&#147;Things never happen the same way twice.&#148; Thus boometh Aslan the lion (Liam Neeson ), alias the Son of God, popping his computer-generated shaggy head briefly into The Chronicles of Narnia: Prince Caspian  to pep-talk a bunch of discouraged Brits into fighting the good fight again.
As in life, so in sequels. Aslan and other once-key figures&#151;and by extension the Christian ethics of author C.S. Lewis , who would likely have been more disgusted than amused to know that his wildly popular 1950s children&#146;s novels have inspired a blooming 21st-century movie franchise&#151;are no more than bit players in the new movie by Andrew Adamson . Not that the first Narnia   did shabby business in 2005: $65 million its first weekend, over $700 million worldwide. But part deux  comes with a visible mandate to bring home yet more bacon&#151;on the order of, say, the Harry Potter   movies&#151;and to attract a slightly older and far more male demographic.
If Prince Caspian  falls to Indy 4  at the box office, it won&#146;t be for want of trying to out-he-man the competition. Adamson has retooled the old-fashioned, handmade charms of his first Narnia into a schoolboy epic strung together by CGI-laden action sequences featuring men and boys wearing metal while showing mettle. Gone, aside from a fleeting resurrection of flash-frozen evil late in the day, is Tilda Swinton &#146;s White Witch, while sweet Pevensie sibling Susan (Anna Popplewell )&#151;she of the bee-stung lips and distaff habit of pouring oil on troubled waters&#151;comes to us improbably refurbished as a girl warrior. A dab hand with the bow and arrows in a tight squeeze, Susan briskly repels the longing glances cast at her by Caspian (Ben Barnes ), a deposed heir to the throne who has literally blown the suggestively phallic horn that Susan left behind at the end of part one, to recall her to Narnia. &#147;It would never work,&#148; she admonishes the deflated swain. &#147;After all, I am 1300 years older than you.&#148;
Inevitably, character and story suffer. Though Prince Caspian  continues the first Narnia &#146;s terrified fantasy of foreign occupation that lingered in England just after World War II, when Lewis wrote his novels, there&#146;s something both less magical and less human about the new incarnation. This time, the Pevensie children re-enter the world where they once earned the right to be kings and queens not via a musty old cupboard, but via the no-less-smelly London Underground  at Trafalgar Square . The Narnia they find, abandoned by Aslan and by them, has fallen into disrepair. Nature itself has shut down, the trees don&#146;t walk, the animals don&#146;t talk, and all that remains of the brave new kingdom they left behind are some dignified centaurs and a potential resistance force composed of gnarly-looking, mildly depressed, and fatalistic short people with funny accents&#151;in other words, Englishmen&#151;headed by a grumpy dwarf (Peter Dinklage ) and a knightly mouse (Eddie Izzard ). The marauders, by contrast, are a virile and vaguely Mediterranean bunch of thugs and politicians with no great respect for the rule of law. The rest of the movie, with perfunctory pit-stops for speeches about whether God owes man or vice versa, is armed combat between swarthy humans, buffed centaurs, and two boy-Brits quarreling over who has the bigger, er, sword. This all culminates in an entertaining final conflict featuring the biggest, hairiest water sprite you&#146;ve ever seen helping to restore peace, prosperity, and the divine right of kings to Narnia.
Prince Caspian  is fairly good fun, and I&#146;m trying to decide whether it was the capable swordplay or Ben Barnes&#146;s bedroom eyes that prompted a significant shift in brand loyalty on the part of my 10-year-old, who announced that she&#146;s had it with the cute penguins and henceforth will attend only actioners, no matter how bloodthirsty. That may bode well for Prince Caspian &#146;s juvie box office. But a wimpy mother who grew up on the Narnia  books misses kindly Mr. Tumnus with his skinny pectorals and red scarf, and the cuddly cockney beavers (half-heartedly replaced in the sequel by an overly benign badger and Izzard&#146;s intrepid mouse), and the growing-up struggles that played out on both sides of the land of War Drobe in the country of Spare Oom.
Hell, I&#146;d even settle for a little more overt Christianity&#151;though, give or take the washing of self-sacrificing Aslan&#146;s wounds by two adoring females, even the first Narnia  was about as Christian as The Golden Compass  was atheist. As befits a movie whose target global audience is more likely to funnel its worldview through Buddha, Muhammad, or Mao than through Jesus, Prince Caspian  settles for more tactfully generic hints at a higher authority. A pity that, other than the fights, everything else in the movie is equally bloodless.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>