<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Aug 30 2005</date>
      <text>The more things change, the more they stay the same&#151;A Sound of Thunder  begins 50 years from now, when having finally conquered the fourth dimension, humanity is ready to get down to the truly serious business: exploiting the epochal discovery for a quick buck. Enter Time Safari Inc. , a travel agency specializing in carefully controlled dinosaur-hunting expeditions for high rollers. Lured by the promise of research funding, Dr. Travis Ryer  (Edward Burns ) puts up with rich-fool clients and a craven boss (a delightfully hammy Ben Kingsley ); it's the type of work-place where colleagues justify their fuck-ups by appealing to the Heisenberg uncertainty principle. Before long, the inevitable happens: One would-be dino slayer inadvertently squashes a butterfly instead, setting off a chain reaction of cosmic proportions.
Using Ray Bradbury 's 1952 story as a jumping-off point, A Sound of Thunder deals with the narrative troubles endemic to time travel movies by positing a scenario in which the altered past ripples through the future in waves, allowing Ryer and fellow scientist Sonia Rand  (Catherine McCormack ) a brief window to set things right before their own species is wiped out. Harder to explain away are the shaky CGI effects&#151;the actors appear to have been clumsily blue-screened into the unconvincing visualization of mid-21st-century Chicago  (a glance at the walls of Ryer's apartment confirms the movie's sci-fi status by revealing that the Cubs have won not one, but two World Series in the interim). Still, the movie recovers from a sluggish opening act to pack some real suspense in its second half, set in a literal urban jungle populated by giant bats, piranha-faced eels, and&#151;in a harrowing scene&#151;a pack of carnivorous primate-reptile mutants. Consistent with the spirit (if not the craftsmanship) of Bradbury's cautionary fable, A Sound of Thunder can be read as a timely warning about climate change, but here in Mesozoic America, the movie's most political aspect may be its quaint respect for the basic principles of evolution.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>