<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jun 7 2005</date>
      <text>Many a struggling indie filmmaker has turned to his family for help. But writer-director Andrew Wagner , embarking on his first feature after a shelf-ful of unproduced screenplays, asked for something considerably more complicated than a financial infusion&#151;for his pseudo-confessional road movie The Talent Given Us , he wanted his mother Judy, father Allen, and sisters Emily  and Maggie to play themselves. The results are mortifying&#151;which is exactly as Wagner intended.
Seamlessly solipsistic and basically a glorified home movie, The Talent Given Us  is this year's Tarnation . It's also a Sundance film through and through, a less bleak Capturing the Friedmans  with the familiar arc of countless dysfunctional domestic comedies. But Wagner's anti-vanity project, despite the self-congratulatory vigor with which it makes a show of picking at family scabs, also possesses a curious integrity&#151;this raw, fascinating, often unpleasant film is not in the least coy about its queasy mix of exploitation and therapeutic exhibitionism.
A stunt premised on the unembarrassed supply of too much information, The Talent Given Us  is blessed, if that's the right word, with almost shockingly unselfconscious performances: Wagner's sisters are both professional actors, but his parents are not. Judy, eager and volatile, seems like a natural; more surprisingly, so is lumbering, slightly speech-impaired Allen&#151;at least to the extent that he has a real skill for ignoring the camera. They tackle the specter of late-life regret with gusto, excavating the desires and resentments underlying a marriage that, while comfortable in its rituals, has ossified from years of neglect. Sis Emily has seemingly been appointed the movie's safeguard against sappiness&#151;playing herself as a morbidly narcissistic sub-Hollywood  creature with a litany of bodily and New Age fixations and a habit of expressing them in almost Tourette-ish gushes. Emily's self-help shtick becomes less funny when it's clear that Wagner wants in on it too. The Talent Given Us  climaxes with a gentle reminder that "the fulfillment that you are looking for is right here." That this line is spoken by the real-life Bruce Joel Rubin  in his real-life meditation class is perhaps the film's best joke.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>