<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Dec 11 2007</date>
      <text>As an actor, John C. Reilly  is the opposite of Mr. Cellophane. He doesn't disappear into a role; roles disappear onto him&#151;the unlikely porn sidekick of Boogie Nights , the inadequately adequate family man of The Hours , the cutup cowboy of A Prairie Home Companion , all stamped and imprinted with the actor's doughy kisser. The only catch is, the role has to exist first. He's a character actor in the true sense: He'll provide the perfect coatrack, but someone's got to hand him a coat.
As Dewey Cox, a hard-livin', hard-lovin', hard-everythingin' singer with a Zelig-like proximity to every major music figure of the past 50 years, Reilly cuts a hilarious and electrifying figure&#151;live. On a recent promo tour, playing Nashville's Mercy Lounge in a concert that was part Spinal Tap  , part Hedwig and the Angry Inch , and completely riotous, Reilly slipped hungrily into the guise of a surly, self-obsessed spotlight hog. Surprisingly lithe and snake-hipped, he played selections from his protest-singer phase ("not that I believed in that shit"), bestowed female patrons with hankies steeped in ball sweat, and congratulated the crowd for its taste: "I've never heard so many men say, 'I love Cox!' " His Dewey was an arrogant bastard&#151;and more important, he was funny as hell.
Sadly, Walk Hard: The Dewey Cox Story  isn't. And seeing Reilly perform the material live only points out how fundamentally misconceived this barrage of dry-docked yacht-rock gags is at every level&#151;starting with its flaccid Cox. (Live by the dick joke, die by the dick joke.) It's not that the pop biopic isn't ossified enough to get its own Epic / Date /Scary Movie : There were moments, watching La Vie en Rose  and Ray , when you could swear it already had. You better walk the line, Johnny Cash ! Hit the road, Ray Charles ! Vous ne regrettez rien , Edith Piaf ! But this burlesque of biopic clichés flounders from one setup to the next without the engine that drives the genre: a strong central character.
Scripted by the high-powered team of Judd Apatow  and Jake Kasdan  and directed by Kasdan, Walk Hard  often plays like scene-for-scene nose-thumbing at Walk the Line . Only Dewey is less a Man in Black than a twerp in twill: a humble country boy who steps forward at his high-school talent show to croon a mushy ballad. This being a pop biopic, it takes all of a stanza to induce a riot, prompt cries of "It's the Devil's music!" and unleash an epidemic of teenage lust. It also bum-rushes Dewey down the path to stardom, leading to an affair with dewy duet partner Darlene (Jenna Fischer , in a Reese Witherspoon  parody that's one joke shy of a one-joke part) as well as busted marriages, drug addiction, patricide&#151;and, at rock bottom, his own '70s variety show.
Reilly's Roy Orbison &#150;ish tenor is game for anything from funk to punk, and he's been given a ready-made hit parade of clever knockoffs. Had Dewey been the mean, obscene sex machine of Reilly's live shows, Walk Hard  might've been a hoot&#151;at least as funny as the recent Will Ferrell  comedies it resembles, down to the unnecessary attempt to make the self-infatuated hero ultimately lovable.
But Dewey doesn't hang together as a character. He's a blank festooned with ill-fitting traits swiped from a season's worth of Behind the Music s, and when the movie isn't sending up something specific&#151;Cash's drug habit, Dylan's protest singing, Brian Wilson 's obsessive mania&#151;Reilly has nothing to play. (Maybe this  is the movie that should've been called I'm Not There .) Gag-a-minute Airplane! -style comedy isn't Apatow's or Kasdan's strong suit, either. Even when the skewering of bio tropes is spot-on&#151;as in the obligatory conquering-the-charts montage for a single "recorded just 35 minutes ago!"&#151;the timing is off, stifled by Kasdan's needlessly glossy direction or Apatow's ability to flog a running joke into whimpering exhaustion.
The biggest laughs come from players who know how to hit their sketch-comedy marks quickly and move on: from Tim Meadows  as Dewey's drummer, whose antidrug warnings inevitably turn into a can't-resist come-hither, to Harold Ramis  as Mad  magazine's idea of a Jewish record mogul, more likely to cut foreskins than 45s. The rest of the movie blows through opportunities like Mötley Crüe  through coke money. It takes almost a perverse determination to put Jack Black , Paul Rudd , Jason Schwartzman , and Justin Long  in a room together as the Beatles , then give them so little to do that even Eddie Vedder 's cameo as an awards-show presenter smokes them. (The DVD extras will almost certainly be better.) Walk Hard  limps soft&#151;but if John C. Reilly turns up anywhere onstage in your town, go. If there's anything America needs now, it's more Cox.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>