<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jun 13 2006</date>
      <text>Larry Clark 's latest finds the grizzled shock-meister in a thoughtful mode and a mellow mood. Unusually benign, Wassup Rockers  details a foray into deepest Beverly Hills , made by a septet of 14-year-old South Central skateboarders-cum&#150;punk rock aficionados.
The movie opens with the prettiest member of this possibly invented, anti-hip-hop subculture (Jonathan Velasquez ) sitting shirtless on his bed, in double screen, rapping about his sexual experiences and as-yet-unseen friends. The credit sequence includes a totally desultory drive-by shooting, but despite this Wassup Rockers  is hardly a screed against inner-city violence. Rather, it's a kind of fairy-tale adventure.
There aren't any drugs to be seen but the movie has a mildly antic, buzzy energy. There's a musical aspect to the scenes in which the rockers skateboard en masse. Indeed, bod-caressing camerawork aside, it seems as though Uncle Larry's underlying fantasy might be a neorealist remake of A Hard Day's Night  or a goofball West Side Story. Jonathan and his posse&#151;Kico, Spermball, Porky, Eddie, Louie, and Carlos&#151;are good kids, amiable, high-spirited, and exceedingly photogenic. I missed the macguffin that sent them on their way to Beverly Hills, but once a friendly cop confiscates their corroded jalopy, they wind up taking a bus.
At this point, Wassup does threaten to turn tedious&#151;too much skateboard practice and an endless, increasingly inane interaction with a racist Beverly Hills cop. But things bid to get lively in the Larry Clark way once the rockers are picked up by an appraising pair of age-appropriate local girls. There's a definite frisson as they skate past the Beverly Hills Hotel  to wind up at the white-chick palace. "You're not circumcised," one tells Jonathan. "Ooh, that looks dangerous." More culture is exchanged than bodily fluids&#151;but try telling that to the irate white boys who show up and launch an attack on the rockers, sending them on a homeward odyssey through the backyards of Beverly Hills.
Events move from the absurd to the ridiculous. Landing in the midst of a pool party infested with pseudos, the strangers in paradise are told that they're "like the Mexican Ramones." The next house, occupied by a Beverly Hills Actor (David Livingston , squinting and grimacing like Clint Eastwood ), is altogether less welcoming, but a frighteningly avid Beverly Hills Actress (Janice Dickinson ) literally knocks herself out trying to make the boys feel at home.
The rockers take a detour up to Hollywood Boulevard to skate on the stars before returning at dawn to what one portentously calls the Ghetto. Not everybody makes it back but no matter: Spermball gets the gang to recognize his name is Milton.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>