<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Wednesday, Jun 17 2009</date>
      <text>Character is destiny—at least for Woody Allen 's Whatever Works . Allen's exercise in Woody Allen nostalgia opens with a snatch of Groucho Marx  singing his trademark paradoxical assertion ("Hello, I must be going") and is powered almost entirely by the presence of a single, larger-than-life, and less-than-likeable, figure.
Whatever Works  is Allen's first New York movie after five years abroad. It's his first in even longer to center on the Woody Allen character—an urban neurotic wise guy, here named Boris Yellnikoff  and brashly played (or rather, brayed) by HBO  star Larry David . Toughened and (relatively) rejuvenated by David's aggressive performance, the Allen surrogate is introduced treating his café friends to a lecture on the "God racket," which segues into a rant against the stupidity of feel-good movies. Hah!
Nothing especially new—Allen wrote this script 30 years ago and intended it for no less a force of nature than Zero Mostel . What gives the material weight is the loquacious curmudgeon's derisive half-smile. Nastier than David's character on Curb Your Enthusiasm  , Boris is a cousin to insult comedian Don Rickles  or former New York mayor Ed Koch —a smug, self-absorbed, argumentative nudnik with unshakeable faith in his listeners' stupidity and his own "huge worldview." Resplendent in T-shirt and plaid Bermuda shorts as he limp-lurches toward the camera to buttonhole the viewer, this boorish yelling-kopf writes the check for a comic masterpiece that Whatever Works  is unable to cash.
A former physics professor who gimped his leg in a ridiculous suicide attempt, Boris supports himself teaching chess to kids whom he derisively browbeats as "patzers," pint-size versions of the "mindless zombie morons" who populate the Earth. In an earlier era, he might have been the rudest of waiters in a dairy restaurant. Is there anything at all that could rock this schmuck's world? Whatever Works  shifts into gear when Boris finds a teenage runaway named Melodie (Evan Rachel Wood ) camped out in front of his anachronistically shabby downtown digs, and grudgingly takes her in.
Of course, Melodie is also a type. Woody Allen looks at her and hears America singing. She's a cheerful, optimistic, winsome Mississippi belle—Margaret Dumont  meets Daisy Mae or, as her benefactor ungraciously puts it, "a character out of Faulkner not unlike Benjy"—so apparently stupid that she doesn't get Boris's sarcasm and even develops a crush on him. They "date" (he takes her to Grant's Tomb  and Yonah Shimmel 's knishery), and, living out the Woodman's fondest fantasy, they marry.
The wonder of Melodie's character is that she manages to internalize Boris's crabby, karping worldview while maintaining her sweet and tolerant disposition. Sex aside, Yellnikoff's cronies wonder what he sees in her. "She keeps me company at the Emergency Room when I'm convinced my mosquito bite is a melanoma," he explains. It's less apparent what Melodie sees in him, until her estranged parents, Marietta  (Patricia Clarkson ) and John (Ed Begley Jr.) , arrive. Still, the introduction of these well-off, white-bread, Jesus-praising "aborigines," as their son-in-law characterizes them, serves to upstage and hence diminish Allen's antihero even as Allen's own narcissism is globalized—there's no one so primitive they won't be grateful for an introduction to Manhattan sophistication. The yokels come to New York and, casting off the shackles of their benighted upbringings, go native. It is at this point that the movie dons its jammies and goes to sleep.
Like previous Woody Allen characters, Boris is allowed to directly address the audience: "I'm the only one who sees the big picture," he explains. But what sort of perspective is there when a movie that goes out of its way to mock It's a Wonderful Life  winds up even more lazily pandering? To drown Boris's bitterness in a sickly vat of Manischewitz  is the aesthetic equivalent of depraved indifference. Whatever Works  illustrates, even as it names, Allen's artistic limitations.
To suggest, as Mark Harris  did in a recent New York  cover story, that Whatever Works  marks the end of Jewish humor as we know it is to give this blown opportunity more significance than it warrants. Allen did invent and inhabit the persona of an anxious misfit, but, as ambitious as he is, he never came close to producing a truly corrosive, antisocial comic work—an equivalent to Portnoy's Complaint , the original version of The Producers , Borat , or any number of Lenny Bruce  monologues. His problem, as Boris would surely have deduced, is a pathetic desire to be loved. He wants to make nice—it's just his nature.
Etgar Keret  is sometimes described as Israel 's Woody Allen , but this hugely popular humorist is more fanciful and morbid in his evocation of cultural schlemielery. Co-written with Keret, Tatia Rosenthal 's stop-motion animation $9.99  adds a measure of creepiness to Keret's dark whimsy. Like Jellyfish— the live-action film Keret directed with his wife, Shira Geffen , in 2007—$9.99  is an episodic affair detailing the absurd or fantastic encounters between all the lonely people.
An Israeli-Australian co-production, $9.99  is set in a city that vaguely resembles Tel Aviv , but is populated by Aussie-accented clay puppets: An aggressive beggar (voiced by Geoffrey Rush ) shoots himself and returns as a no less irascible angel; a stoner is dumped by his girlfriend and consoled by a trio of heavy-partying pixie dudes; a repo man takes up with a supermodel whose apartment includes some peculiar anthropomorphic furniture; and a little boy bonds with his ceramic piggy bank—a particularly uncanny relationship in this claymated world, not unlike the Disney -normalized notion of a mouse owning a pet dog. The movie's nominal protagonist, a terminally unemployed 28-year-old still living at home with his depressed father, discovers, first, the meaning of life in a paperback purchased for $9.99 and, second, that nobody cares.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>