<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Nov 29 2005</date>
      <text>Part road movie, part extreme-sports biopic, and all shaggy-dog story, Roger Donaldson 's The World's Fastest Indian  evades easy classification&#151;to say nothing of a target audience, unless aficionados of over-the-hill-biker flicks have become a sought-after demographic. Regardless, it's hard to resist the film's pleasantly rambling narrative and market-defying eccentricity. Indian  tells the true-ish story of Burt Munro  (Anthony Hopkins ), a sexagenarian New Zealand  loner who, in 1967, hauls his 40-plus-year-old Indian brand motorcycle to a Utah  raceway to see how fast it'll go, and subsequently breaks a speed record. On his trip, the amiable Munro encounters and invariably charms various rural Yank oddballs (including, briefly, a randy isolato  played by Diane Ladd ) in a succession of tender, go-nowhere vignettes that owe something to The Straight Story .
Donaldson, a decent light-action director whose spotty Hollywood  career reveals selectiveness if little else, chronicled the real-life Munro in his 1972 doc Offerings to the God of Speed , and his fondness for the subject is evident; Indian  largely eschews excessive speed-junkie thrills in favor of sharp, affectionate characterization, and its stabs at an overarching message&#151;something about holding on to your dreams no matter how old you get&#151;are mercifully minimized. Which isn't to say that Indian  is a masterwork of realism or even Lynchian homespun weirdness: Munro's stopover in a cartoonishly freakified L.A. is banal and tedious, and the dubious distinction of making one's loud, stinking machine go faster than anyone else's loud, stinking machine hardly amounts to a universal preoccupation. Moreover, Hopkins&#151;whose interiority, unlike his feigned Kiwi accent, fits the role nicely&#151;phones in a good deal of his performance. But Donaldson and his cast still manage to capture something of the strange randomness of existence here, and the result is a film as tenacious, peculiar, and likable as Burt Munro himself.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>