<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Tuesday, Jun 14 2005</date>
      <text>With the recent spike in Iraq  carnage, it may seem genteel to propose working through Muslim-West cultural tensions in the form of forbidden romance&#151;in iambic pentameter no less. But we're dealing with Sally Potter , whose films (Orlando , The Man Who Cried ) demand leaps of faith and often reward them. In Yes , which unfurls entirely in verse, Joan Allen  plays an Irish American biologist whose antiseptic work in blue-lit labs mirrors the icy vibe of her opulent London home. Her husband (Sam Neill ) is a fatigued Blair-like politico who unwinds by getting Scotched up and playing air guitar to B.B. King .
Allen's character feels alive only when her flirtation with a Lebanese restaurant worker (Simon Abkarian ) becomes an affair. Potter is, as usual, attentive to the female viewpoint. She lingers on the burst of cultural sharing that begins the tryst&#151;sensual talk of native fruits and heritage, the tentative move to subjects of language and numeracy, the delighted discovery of new mating rituals. But sheet-lolling scenes are soon spliced with more kinetic ones of the male lover's fraught work life, a Shakespearean kitchen dumb show that turns on the alternately funny and vicious barbs of his co-workers&#151;a Scot, an East Ender, a Jamaican immigrant&#151;all suspicious of one another but resentfully bound by class. The Allen character, known only as "She," has no access to her lover's post-9-11 pressures, and when the precarious situation of this man who forfeited his job as a surgeon for manual labor in the West falls apart, she can only take his fury personally.
Potter indicts both characters' prejudices while advancing a version of a rarely depicted middle-aged female fantasy. Her tactics might seem at once too dogmatic and too flowery. Both attributes combine in a Hallmark-ish Cuban beach sequence that unites the two lovers with a global radical tradition. But in jettisoning the patterns and pacing of Hollywood -ized male fantasy, she's aiming her critique at nothing less than the main conundrum of both characters' cultures&#151;the problem of a woman's freedom. Even the freedom to be flowery or dogmatic. And when Yes  bristles with rhapsodic sex talk ("I'll fuck you as a mistress/As a queen!") and searing recriminations ("Terrorist!" "Bigot!" "Bitch!"), or veers off into the delightful soliloquies of a housekeeper (Shirley Henderson ) who uses unflushed condoms and dust bunnies to construct a philosophy of entropy and endurance, Potter's anachronistic rhyme schemes tumble forth with an out-damned-spot verve that rages against irrelevance.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>