<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date> June 16, 2006
</date>
      <text>         Based on the popular syndicated comic strip by Eric Orner, "The Mostly Unfabulous Social Life of Ethan Green" is a fairly straightforward romantic comedy that just happens to take the gay social scene as its setting. Ethan (Daniel Letterle) is a nice regular guy, predictably unlucky in love, who is torn between his old boyfriend, his more recent boyfriend and a raucous fling.
 
 As directed by George Bamber from a script by David Vernon, no one involved seems to be under the impression they're doing anything more than having a little fun, and the performances have a spirited playfulness that gives the film a surprisingly bouncy personality.
 


         






   At times the eager-to-please attitude does push too far toward cartoon slapstick, mostly in the inordinate amount of screen time given the flamboyantly cross-dressing "Hat Sisters," played by veteran character actors Joel Brooks and Richard Riehle.
 
 Inoffensive even as it makes some fairly explicit sex jokes, "Ethan Green" may not exactly be fabulous, but it is pleasantly diverting.
 
 "The Mostly Unfabulous Life of Ethan Green," 
unrated. Running time 1 hour, 28 minutes. Exclusively at Regent Showcase, 614 N. La Brea Ave. (323) 934-2944.

 
 
A discordant 'Dog Lover's'

 
 The ins and outs of Southern California dog culture have tantalized filmmakers before, as potential lovers can meet in the park, take meaningful walks and, of course, play with their puppies.
 
 "Dog Lover's Symphony" further exploits the conceit by having the story narrated by the dog that brings the lucky couple together, as a young man on parole (Jesse Berns) is taken in by a lawyer (Maxwell Caulfield) and his daughter (Alaina Kalanj), who both encourage him to become a dog trainer.
 
 Written and directed by Ted Fukuda, the film is so off on all fronts it becomes a chicken-egg conundrum trying to pinpoint specific problems — as the stiff acting isn't aided by the overly expository dialogue, which in turn is driven by the functional plotting. It's sort of as if the component ideas for a movie were put into a computer and this is what came out.
 
 By the time the film's left-field conclusion drops, involving temporary resurrection and a check for $10 million, the only suitable ending for such a stinker involves a twist-tie and a baggie.
 
 "Dog Lover's Symphony," 
unrated. Running time: 1 hour, 43 minutes. Exclusively at Laemmle's Fairfax Cinemas, 7907 Beverly Blvd. at Fairfax Ave. (323) 655-4010; Cinema City Theatres, 5635 E. La Palma Ave., Anaheim (714) 970-6700.
   
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
