<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date> July 22, 2005
</date>
      <text>         "November" is not the sleek lady-in-distress thriller that its trailers suggest. More of a psychological mystery, it gets underway with a well-staged opening sequence as a young man (James Le Gros) stops at a corner market in Los Angeles one evening to buy chocolate ice cream for his girlfriend, Sophie (Courteney Cox), only to walk straight into a holdup and wind up shot dead. Writer Benjamin Brand and director-editor Greg Harrison divide their highly stylized and atmospheric 78-minute film into three sections, each dated Nov. 7, the date of that fateful evening, and titled, respectively, "Denial, "Despair" and "Acceptance," which may or may not offer a clue as to what's really going on in this increasingly perplexing film, which is more concerned with being clever than satisfying.
 
  When "Despair" appears, the holdup plays out in a distinctly different manner, and "Acceptance" carries those events further, leading to a climactic moment that leaves a key element dangling. "November" can be seen as a tragedy that is a jumbled flashback, as a tormented fantasy on the part of Sophie in the throes of a mental breakdown — or both. Or perhaps there's still another layer of meaning, seemingly involving Sophie's spurned lover, Jesse (Michael Ealy), and therefore a stunning coincidence, but it's hard to say.
 


         






    Cox capably manages her character's constantly changing emotions, as does Le Gros as Hugh. Although too young for the part, Anne Archer, as Sophie's sophisticated mother, offers a warm, relaxed contrast to the harried Sophie. There's also good support from Nora Dunn, Nick Offerman and others. Locations are almost entirely in recycled buildings in downtown L.A., and cinematographer Nancy Schreiber, costume designer Danny Glicker and production designer Tracey Gallacher have conspired assiduously to create a look of drab, brownish retro chic. Lew Baldwin's score is suitably unsettling. There's enough talent and imagination on display in Harrison's second feature — the first was "Groove" — to suggest he and his team could come up with a more accessible film next time around.
 
 'November'

 
 MPAA rating:
 R for violence and some language
 
 Times guidelines:
 Complex adult themes in addition to violence and language
 
 A Sony Pictures Classics release  Director-editor Greg Harrison. Producers Danielle Renfrew, Gary Winick, Jake Abraham.  Cinematographer Nancy Schreiber. Music Lew Baldwin. Costumes Danny Glicker. Production designer Tracey Gallacher. Running time: 1 hour, 18 minutes.  At selected theaters.   
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
