<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>08/04/2006</date>
      <text>
Speaking as both a parent and a critic, I do believe I'd rather drive rusty railroad spikes through my eyes than have to sit through one more computer generated family film about talking animals. The bad news for Hollywood is that after seeing ``Barnyard" my kids feel the same way.
Written and directed by Steve Oedekerk, the comic mind behind ``Bruce Almighty" and ``Jimmy Neutron: Boy Genius," ``Barnyard" is nothing so much as ``The Lion King" chewed in a cud and digitally regurgitated. It's manic and maudlin, borderline creepy, occasionally inspired. More often, it's just plain strange
: with the brief appearance of a character named Wild Mike, a sort of break-dancing Tasmanian Devil the other farm animals keep imprisoned in a box, my daughters and I looked at each other in the dark with alarm. What fresh CGI hell is
 this?
The story concerns the coming of age of Simba -- excuse me, Otis (voice of Kevin James), an irresponsible young cow whose father, Ben (Sam Elliott), is the august leader of the barnyard. Ben holds the barnyard morning meetings, keeps watch at night against coyotes, and dispenses homilies like ``A strong man stands up for himself. A stronger man stands up for others."
Otis is having too much fun being a party animal to pay attention until the unthinkable happens and he has to step up to the plate. Can crippling guilt and the love of a pregnant heifer named Nala -- sorry, Daisy
 (Courteney Cox) -- overcome his urge to go human-tipping with a crew of ``Sopranos"-accented Jersey cows?
I'm not making this up; I don't think I could without drinking a punch-bowl of Ritalin mixed with cough syrup. ``Barnyard" gives us a shiny, rather ugly world of humanoid beasties; it's as if a bunch of Little Tykes toys had been given life and stroppy attitudes. There are humans here, but they're grotesque and few, and the gag is that the animals have to hide from them their ability to use cellphones and drive cars. You may be willing to suspend your disbelief to buy that, but you'll probably stop short at the movie's extremely odd notion that male cows have udders.
That's right: udders. Did no one involved with this movie bother to Google the word ``bull"? Have we in fact wandered onto a top-secret genetic research station? (That would explain the rapping rat and the giant mutant chick.) Sure, it's a family film and no one wants to spoil the party with details, but I say give the kiddies the straight anatomical dope, more or less, so they won't be in for a terrible surprise when they wander into a field with a milk pail some day.
``Barnyard" is not without its laughs. The cast is enthusiastic, the musical numbers bizarrely catchy, and Oedekerk keeps throwing animals at us: the farm dog (Dom Irrera) addicted to fetching balls, a wimpy rooster (Rob Paulsen), a drooling coyote (David Koechner), a neurotic ferret or fox or something (Cam Clarke). Danny Glover voices the wise old mule who might as well be named Rafiki; he's fine, and Jeffrey Garcia as a smart-aleck Hispanic field mouse is the funniest thing in the movie.
By contrast, Wanda Sykes's sassy-black-chick schtick -- she plays Daisy's friend, Bessy -- is way past its freshness date, and so, really, is the whole racial profiling of CGI family flicks. Every vibrant cultural movement eventually descends into rococo excess, and with ``Barnyard," computer-generated cartoons have at last arrived at their moment. The film ends with a bovine nativity scene that would delight the camp artist Jeff Koons, but this is a studio film so it's played insanely straight. A strong man might weep. A stronger man might rent ``Babe" instead.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
