<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>07/15/2005</date>
      <text>
There is good weird and there is bad weird, and despite whatever glow of unearned nostalgia has gathered about it over the years, the 1971 ''Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory" is mostly bad weird. Directed by journeyman director Mel Stuart, it has the feel of a pilot episode for a child's first acid trip, up to and including the shock-cuts of worms and rotting food. Only Gene Wilder's fey Willy Wonka and Peter Ostrum as a choirboy Charlie Bucket save it; the rest is ''H.R. Pufnstuf" gone tediously wrong.
Roald Dahl, by contrast, wrote books that are very nearly the working definition of good weird -- fanciful, rebellious, tinged with the un-
happiness kids know is always out there, no matter how much the grown-ups simper. What director Tim Burton, screenwriter John August, and star Johnny Depp have fashioned out of ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory," Dahl's most celebrated novel, is pretty good weird, too -- five minutes into the film, my 8-year-old grinned and said ''This is odd
" -- but weird it is, and not just because Depp does his level best to convince us he's Michael Jackson.
Seriously. His Willy Wonka has ashen pancake make-up and an unsettling lack of wrinkles (except for one nervous little crease that goes tick-tick-tick under his right eye); under a top hat encircled by a lavender ribbon, he wears his hair in a pageboy of the sort Bette Davis favored in her later years. His voice is a sing-song pitched somewhere between Mr. Rogers and Carol Channing. In many ways, he's a bigger baby than anyone else in the movie.
In the trailers, this looked like a recipe for disaster. In the film itself, Depp's performance works surprisingly well, because there's an idea behind it and a good one. Willy is the sort of celebrity our culture coins all too easily these days; the youthful superstar whose drive sends him to the top and whose early fame isolates him into increasing eccentricity. (He has father issues to boot: In flashbacks, we learn that Wonka Sr., played by Christopher Lee, was a domineering dentist with no patience for sweets or the cavities they produce.) Depp creates something close to Howard Hughes as a self-made chocolatier, Brian Wilson with a factory instead of a sandbox -- and, yes, the King of Pop in a spun-sugar Neverland.
All of which sounds like Burton and company have ventured far beyond the confines of the book. I'm happy to report, then, that ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory" is much more faithful to its source than the 1971 film, and for the better. August's script often transposes Dahl's dialogue word for word from page to screen, where it shimmers wryly. And while Wonka's new psychological demons would drag the proceedings down in the hands of other filmmakers, Burton keeps things inventively and garishly delightful for the most part. The movie's overlong and there are lumps in the batter, but this is a ''Charlie" that the author would recognize as upholding his playfully dyspeptic tradition.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
