<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>02/15/2008</date>
      <text>
Horror movie Rule #1: The only way to kill a zombie is to shoot it in the brain. George Romero himself laid this maxim down with his first film, the endlessly influential 1968 gutter classic "Night of the Living Dead." Forty years later, with "George A. Romero's Diary of the Dead," the venerable filmmaker has done something almost as startling: He has put brains back into the zombie genre.
This was not how it was supposed to go. Romero is 68, and his last film was 2005's "Land of the Dead," a love-it-or-hate-it studio film that felt oddly gutless despite the churning gore. Against expectations, the director has returned to the drawing board, producing "Diary" independently and rebooting the narrative back to the present day, when the undead are once more freshly with us. This time, though, the film's shot entirely through the lens of the characters' own video cameras.
Oh, yawn, more first-person horror? Another "Clo verfield Witch Project"? Not quite. "Diary of the Dead" explicitly wonders what's worse for your soul: becoming a flesh-eating corpse or hiding from the world behind a viewfinder. The movie plays like "Cloverfield" for grad students or anyone else up for a ruthless exegesis of our omnipresent media culture. In a world where reality exists only if someone's filming it, Romero has one character dare to ask, "What happens when no one's left to watch?"
All this, plus cheesy exploding heads. Refreshingly, "Diary" has a lean, mean low-budget thrust that delivers both the shocks and subversive implications of Romero's earliest work. The movie begins with a televised crime-scene news report that turns apocalyptic when the victims come back to life. We abruptly cut to a reality documentary, pompously titled "The Death of Death," that's being posted to the Web after supposedly having been shot by a Pittsburgh-area film student named Jason (Josh Close).
At first Jason is shooting his own fictional zombie movie in the woods, complete with panicked babe actress (Amy Lalonde), boozy film professor (Scott Wentworth) on the sidelines, and strict adherence to the Romero Rules. Then reports filter in about the real-life undead attacks in the cities, and the crew hits the road in their production van, aiming for the Scranton home of Jason's girlfriend, Debra (Michelle Morgan).
Now, the reason a point-of-view shot is so baseline efficient at generating suspense is that you never know what's going to go "Boo!" (or in this case "Urggghhhh") when the character holding the camera swivels around. "Diary" thus wrings the maximum screams from a visit to an eerily empty hospital, while a stopover with a deaf-mute Amish farmer named Samuel generates unexpected hilarity along with the expected zombie-scything.
As the body count increases and the film crew gets winnowed down, Romero illustrates society's response to Armageddon with his usual cold-eyed dyspepsia. We meet looters and jackals, some of them in Army uniforms. There's a band of African-American survivalists happy to be the Man for a change.
And there's the emergence of a resourceful, no-nonsense hero in Debra. Because she's not stuck behind a camera like her wimp boyfriend, she's free to deal with reality as it's happening. This mostly involves fleeing, shooting, cursing, and chopping. A lot of chopping. Jason, for his part, constantly has to stop and recharge - unlike Hud in "Cloverfield," he doesn't have a MagicCam - while uploading to the Internet on the fly. But, hey, he just got 72,000 hits in eight minutes, so he must be doing something right.
Debra's scorn for such Internarcissism is only outmatched by the filmmaker's, and if "Diary of the Dead" has a fault it's that Romero's outrage keeps turning didactic. He's a '60s radical at heart - check those survivalists - and his zombie films have always reflected our worst tendencies as a culture: consumerism, groupthink, a reliance on fascism when all else fails. You suspect his sympathies are really with the zombies, who after all have pretty basic needs (human flesh and an open field to stagger through). Hardcore horror junkies may nonetheless object to the fingerwagging here, or point out the irony of an anti-blogging screed itself having a healthy MySpace promotional page.
The meta-narrative of "Diary," meanwhile, patches into various video feeds as it goes - security cams, cellphones, yada yada - and we sense that Jason's editing it for maximum dramatic impact (and to make him look good: An argument with Debra neatly excises her half of the discussion). He expresses shock at the doctored news feeds broadcast by the mainstream media, but how's he any better? Romero says our urge to shape what we see deludes us into thinking we can control reality.
Heady stuff, especially when intercut with the guts spilling out of a mangled zombie. "Diary" acknowledges its own B-ness - it's schlock Brecht, with thin characters and italicized dialogue - but Romero has still delivered a merry, blood-soaked kick in the Facebook. His bleakest joke comes toward the end, when one of the characters begs the others to shoot him. For a second, nobody's sure whether he means with a camera or a gun.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
