<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>03/18/2005</date>
      <text>
Casey Carlyle (Michelle Trachtenberg) is a physics whiz. She's earned straight A-pluses and is on the fast track for a scholarship and a spot in Harvard's freshman class, where I'm sure she'd happily give President Larry Summers a piece of her very scientific mind. But, in ''Ice Princess," a feel-good but inane Disney production, what Casey really wants to do is figure skate.
So in the process of devising exact aerodynamic formulas for how to land perfect lutzes and salchows, Casey transforms from one kind of prodigy to another. She joins the same skating program as the popular girls at her school, one of whom is Gen (Hayden Panettiere), an unnaturally tan, unnaturally blond skater. Her single mother, Tina (Kim Cattrall), is her coach and a former champion; Gen's brother (Trevor Blumas) drives the rink's Zamboni and develops a crush on you-know-who.
Tina is taking these potential champs as far as she can, but she has reservations about Casey. Does she have the fire and competitive drive to make it? Nothing about Trachtenberg's chirpy and flustered demeanor says so. But, man, when she and her stunt double start landing triple axels, we're convinced. So is Tina, but only up to a point. Casey is ultimately her daughter's rival, and at Eastern sectionals, mom has a momentary psychotic lapse. One punky skater informs Casey that Tina's behavior is eerily reminiscent of what Tina pulled back in her championship days. ''It's just like Sarajevo," she says.
Because Casey is being raised by a stark-raving feminist, she has to disguise most of this from her academic single mom, Joan (Joan Cusack), who mysteriously holds the sport as an affront to women. Casey's mom righteously hates the outfits, the smiling, and what she perceives as an undue emphasis on physical appearance. Besides, going to Harvard has been the plan for Casey since she was a toddler. But was it Joan's dream or Casey's?
As long as Casey is fighting with her mother or sneaking off to practice, ''Ice Princess," written by Hadley Davis, is looking for drama in places it shouldn't. Cusack and Cattrall have juicy negative tension (I never thought I'd see these two go at each other), but some mothers would love to have the dilemma Joan faces. Her contempt for skating simmers at a level most parents save to rail against stripping, drugs, or a personal invitation for milkshakes with R. Kelly.
Joan might have a more compelling case if Casey were a boy (that would be a more interesting movie), or if the Carlyles were destitute and Harvard were their ticket out of the ghetto. But the stakes aren't high enough to justify Joan's irrationality. Indeed, her confession about what truly bothers her is poignant in its pettiness.
I'm not sure that 
'tween girls will know what to do with the astounding amount of unsteady handheld photography and the gracelessness with which the movie cuts between Trachtenberg and her double. Still, while he's not a strong technician, director Tim Fywell (''I Capture the Castle") ensures maximum cuteness and gives ''Ice Princess" a heart.
I especially appreciate how Gen becomes determined to befriend Casey when a zillion other stories would keep them at odds. The movie paints such a gentle picture of the figure skating world that neither we nor Joan can stay resentful for long.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
