<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>11/30/1999</date>
      <text>
So your husband's boss is coming over for dinner. The meal you've prepared is splendid. But the boss's wife is in a foul mood. She refuses to remove her sunglasses. She accuses her husband of sleeping with whores. She chucks a glass of wine in his face, then curses you for being snotty and pathetic. With that, she's gone. Only she's not. Days later, you've allowed her to move in to your nice home in southern France. Are you crazy?
Not nearly enough to wring any naughty pleasure out of ``Lemming," Dominik Moll's aggravating follow - up to 2000's unnerving thriller ``With a Friend Like Harry." The new movie is just as clammy as the previous one, but it's more psychologically impenetrable than it really ought to be. When we meet Bénédicte (Charlotte Gainsbourg) and her robotics specialist husband, Alain (Laurent Lucas, who played the stalked pal in ``Harry"), they're a blissful couple. The mirth disappears not long after the boss, Richard (André Dussollier), drags his vicious wife, Alice (Charlotte Rampling), to dinner.
Alice, of course, is a piece of work, having set out to destroy happiness wherever it exists. Naturally, moving in with Bénédicte and Alain and then planting seeds of doubt about the strength of their marital bond are obvious means of sabotage. But before long, Moll moves on to even more opaque developments, such as what to do about the rodent Alain finds clogging the kitchen sink. It's a lemming, and it's not entirely dead. Despite the title, though, it seems beside the point.
Moll goes out of his way to ensure that ``Lemming" inspires maximum head scratching. Even by the strictest standards of odd French psychological drama, the behavior here is particularly opaque. There's a suicide, an affair, and a murder, and I wish I could say I knew why any of them occurred. Moll even provides inconsequential shots of the road as Bénédicte and Alain head for the country, seemingly to give us time to figure it all out. The actors, however, appear to have been instructed to give nothing away, especially Gainsbourg, who has never seemed more like a mannequin than she does here. This is such a wasted opportunity for her and Rampling to go Charlotte à Charlotte.
Moll is even determined, with his sulky and stultifying grip on the action, to snuff out even the littlest bits of intrigue. Like ``Harry," the movie might be an exercise in covetousness. But is Moll kidding with that extramarital affair? Or the silly ending that explains everything yet explains nothing?
Because ``Harry" was such a darkly efficient piece of work, you stick with ``Lemming" to see where Moll and his co-writer Gilles Marchand might take us. (More horrifying scenes with lemmings gone wild, please.) The truth is, we go nowhere in particular. The score is the most effective thing about the film. Sometimes it's a suspicious, mischie-vous distraction from the reality that not enough of this makes sense.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
