<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>06/09/2006</date>
      <text>
Some early moments in Robert Altman's ``A Prairie Home Companion" suggest that the director is on one of the minor adventures that produces a dotty picture like 2000's ``Dr. T and the Women." But he and Garrison Keillor have turned Keillor's beloved radio show into the sort of backstage entertainment allegory that brings out the best in the director.
His 38th theatrical feature isn't as politically incisive as ``Nashville" nor as satirically vicious as ``The Player." What ``Prairie Home Companion" does, however, is bring us the 81-year-old Altman in a reflective state of mind.
Distilling the radio show to its live performances and homemade commercials, Altman and Keillor emphasize the melancholic undercurrents that flow through the airwaves during broadcasts of the show.
In doing so, these two Midwesterners make a surprisingly cozy pair. Altman's hostility would seem to short-circuit Keillor's earnestness. But neither man has much need for sentimentality or nostalgia. They've turned their collaboration into a pungent wake for a bygone era.
The film imagines the evening of the final live broadcast of ``Prairie Home." According to Keillor's script, the owners of the St. Paul, Minn., theater that puts on the show have sold it to a Texas corporation whose icy CEO (Tommy Lee Jones) watches from a skybox.
Backstage, entertainers and crew carry on unaware that the plug is soon to be pulled. They include the Johnson Sisters, Yolanda and Rhonda (Meryl Streep and Lily Tomlin), who blow into their dressing room, dragging Yolanda's morbid daughter, Lola (Lindsay Lohan) behind them; and Dusty and Lefty, the sparring, folksy, and vulgar singing trail hands, played by Woody Harrelson and John C. Reilly.
Altman integrates the performers and backstage personnel with his usual deceptive effortlessness. The small-scale mayhem feels firmly under control. The concerned makeup lady (Sue Scott), the neurotic stage manager (Tim Russell), the prankish, pregnant stagehand (Maya Rudolph), and the seasoned woman (Marylouise Burke) running the food stand and carrying on a lusty affair with one of the show's even more seasoned performers (L.Q. Jones): They all move seamlessly in and out of the story's focus. (Jacob Craycroft is the ace editor, and the great Edward Lachman shot the picture.)
Keillor plays the broadcast's narrator, G.K., whom Yolanda chides for being unfeeling. Indeed, Keillor's expressionless carriage really is made for radio. But his voice is something else. No one will hear a lovelier sound in a movie this year than his intoning the words ``rhubarb pie." His diction is so impeccable you can hear the ``h" and almost smell the pie.
The actors harmonize on stage and off with the energetic off-key idiosyncrasy that Altman prefers. Tomlin and Streep, who's busty and blowsy, have an amusing honey-and-vinegar rapport that even requires them to sing over each other. Lohan, meanwhile, can frequently be seen scribbling in a composition book. I can only hope she plans to use her notes to get herself into more movies this good.
The seemingly inessential character here is played by Kevin Kline. He wanders incongruously through the film, playing a hapless gumshoe who works as the backstage doorkeeper. He knows about the sale and spends the movie trying in his own inept fashion to save the station.
Kline's combination of pratfalls and urbanity is funny, but it rubs against the rest of the movie's effortless rustic charm. He's like Errol Flynn on a hayride.
But he does lust after the movie's best invention: Virginia Madsen, who wanders from scene to scene, luminously, in a white trench coat, playing an angel of death. Some characters can see her and some can't. Either way, her appearance here goes from silly to ethereal to utterly holy, transforming a trifle into a genuinely affecting movie.
Like ``Nashville," ``Prairie Home Companion" culminates in a jamboree. This one moves Tommy Lee Jones's character to observe that it makes him feel like an anthropologist who's discovered a lost tribe. He's not wrong. Before our eyes, it seems like a form of entertainment is dying right along with the people who make it.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
