<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>06/02/2006</date>
      <text>
The sly ultra-low-budget film ``The Puffy Chair" fits right in with recent news reports about college graduates refusing to grow up already. If 30 is the new 20, as the headlines say, this movie insists that 25 is the new 12.
Directed by Jay Duplass from a script by his brother Mark, ``The Puffy Chair" stars the latter as a young slacker named Josh, who's already in denial about the way his life isn't going. His rock band a failure, Josh has disinterestedly turned to music promotion, and his relationship with winsome longtime love Emily (Kathryn Aselton) is feeling the strain. She wants to talk marital commitment, which may simply be asking too much of a guy who calls his girlfriend ``dude."
The film puts us right at the chipped kitchen table with these two, avoiding context or larger framework, and it assumes (rightly) that self-absorbed 20-somethings will recognize the psychic terrain as their own. A delicate vibe of romantic dinner-a-deux is quickly spoiled when Josh takes a cellphone call from one of his buds and Emily storms out. Dude!
Whatever inarticulate demons are gnawing at Josh, he'll do anything to steer clear of them. Instead he talks bravado and plows his insecurities into a weekend car trip to pick up a secondhand purple La-Z-Boy
 -- the puffy chair of the title -- which he plans to deliver to his dad in time for Father's Day. First mistake: Never trust the photos you see on eBay
.
Emily comes along for the ride -- she rather touchingly takes his invitation as a sign of love when it's really just a way to shut her up -- and the two make an overnight stop with Josh's kid brother Rhett (Rhett Wilkins). Here's where the film starts showing its teeth. Rhett's one of those earnestly crunchy young men who loves to lecture people on their insensitivity while remaining blind to his new-age caddishness. Why bother with a puffy chair, he wonders, when the brothers can be
 their own surprise gift to dad? He has a point, but he's still insufferable.
Ostensibly a road-trip farce, ``Chair" really depicts the highway to man-child hell: The laughs come from the gulf between how mature the characters think they're being and what emotional toddlers they are. A scene where Rhett woos a small-town free spirit (Julie Fischer) and cements their instant eternal love with impromptu wedding vows supplied by Josh is funny, telling, and ruthless. ``I promise to always support you in what you want, even when you don't know what you want" -- a divorce lawyer couldn't come up with a better escape clause.
``The Puffy Chair" is part of the wave of no-budget human comedies made by up-and-coming filmmakers such as Andrew Bujalski (``Funny Ha Ha") and Joe Swanberg (``LOL"): rough-hewn narratives of the hip and clueless. The found sound, wobbly camerawork, and throat-clearing performances all aim to replicate ``real life" as it's experienced in underdecorated first apartments three blocks from campus.
In many ways, of course, these movies are just as navel-gazing as their antiheroes. There's no reference to a larger world of other people's problems and pleasures, no sense that life exists outside the postcollegiate playpen. When we finally meet Josh and Rhett's parents, they're stick figures who offer few insights into why their sons are such big babies. ``The Puffy Chair" is an act of self-critical solipsism.
At least the Duplasses don't soft-soap us. The final scene is sad, abrupt, and more caustically on target than anything in the big-budget Jennifer Aniston relationship comedy that opens today. Breaking up is hard to do, says this movie, but growing up may be impossible.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
