<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>07/20/2007</date>
      <text>The early sign that a good time will be had at Danny Boyle's new space marvel, "Sunshine ," comes when we discover the name of the ship meant to launch a bomb at the sun. It's called the Icarus II , meaning Icarus I totally failed, and now, 50 years into the future, a new eight-person crew will attempt to succeed where its predecessor failed. It may cost everyone their lives, but the achievement will be historic: the rare sequel that trumps the original.

Boyle made "Sunshine" in collaboration with the novelist Alex Garland , who wrote the script (they also made the zombie allegory "28 Days Later "). If their movie doesn't float your boat as a work of science-fiction, action, philosophy, heliocentrism, or staggering visual spectacle (although, it really should), then it certainly succeeds as a parable for cinematic ambition.

The movies as a medium began more or less with a trip to the moon. And now we have the crew of the Icarus II hurling itself at the sun -- for the future of mankind, sure, but for mankind's entertainment, too. One crew member, the shrink (Cliff Curtis ), likes to sit on the ship's deck and stare in awe at the sun at the risk of his complexion and his sight -- this solar movie, whose light the ship filters for him, is so brilliant it leaves him blinded, burned, and strung out. The darkness of space becomes the ultimate single-screen theater, and the idea of dying to save a planet is equal to the idea of dying to make art. But Boyle and Garland don't push that metaphorical parallel. The surface of this movie is plenty enthralling on its own.

Ever since a portion of the sun went on the fritz, a solar winter has gripped the Earth . The Icarus II's mission is to jump-start the sun. The ship itself is like an enormous, ornate antenna situated behind a giant absorptive red disc that serves as the ultimate sun block. (It's simply the most beautiful Frisbee ever filmed.) Inside, the ship speaks in ominously soothing cadences, like the HAL 9000 from "2001: A Space Odyssey." Icarus II, though, has a woman's voice (Chipo Chung ). She takes commands, intones unwelcome alerts ("Fire in the oxygen garden "), and offers increasingly dire statistical probabilities to her international-looking crew, which includes the captain (Hiroyuki Sanada), the pilot (Rose Byrne), the engineer (Chris Evans), the communications expert (Troy Garity), the navigator (Benedict Wong), the botanist (Michelle Yeoh) running that doomed oxygen garden, and the physicist (Cillian Murphy).

It takes about 15 minutes to get over the fact that none of these people resemble the average-looking middle-aged white people you see on the typical US space expedition. They kind of look like they're on their way to Sonic Youth's solar-system show. But they're dedicated to their jobs: One crewman's dire miscalculations leave him suicidal with shame. The cast is similarly dedicated.

As the mission starts to go awry, the crew is forced to debate how to proceed in terse, well-written arguments. Soon, even those debates seem like a luxury in the face of lethal repair missions, a diminishing oxygen supply, and the unexpected if disorienting detour the movie makes into a sort of spiritual horror.

The tale of unlikely people (Evans, coming off a little Tom Cruisey, and Michelle Yeoh?) co-existing in the close quarters of a vast spacefaring vessel is a familiar one -- "Alien" being the most reputable example. But Boyle and Garland free their science fiction from impenetrable mumbo-jumbo and nebulous artiness. They're not going for the gargantuan cosmic profundities of Stanley Kubrick's "2001." (Talk about flying into the sun.) Whether you're taking "Sunshine" as action or metaphor, it has an unmitigated intensity.

But there are gorgeous physical touches, too. The golden space suits for the repair missions are very astro-disco: Elton John goes to Pluto. And the production design itself is astounding. Unlike the way that the effects and art direction suffocated everything in George Lucas's last three "Star Wars" movies, the sets and effects in Boyle's movie are breathtakingly persuasive. You're not watching a toy drift through space. You're watching the future -- even though the movie beats with an old hippie's heart.

"We are stardust," someone says climactically at one point. Here we are 50 years into the future, and people are still quoting lyrics from Joni Mitchell's "Woodstock." But, in a nice blockbustering twist, if we're going to get ourselves back to the garden, we'll first have to blow up the sun.

Because Boyle is a protean filmmaker who doesn't care to get traction in any particular film style or genre -- "Shallow Grave," "Trainspotting," "The Beach," "A Life Less Ordinary," "Millions," and "28 Days Later" are different cinematic planets -- each of his pictures has a jarring freshness. Boyle seems to disdain repetition, so his movies seem wonderfully egoless, which is not to say they lack wit, kick, or personality; he's actually the rare director who can make entertainments that run deep. Each movie sends him straight into the sun. But he returns anew, eager to fling himself out there again.


</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
