<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>02/04/2005</date>
      <text>
There are exactly two good moments in ''The Wedding Date." One lasts two seconds and is unprintable. The other happens when the male escort hired by the movie's addled heroine informs her that she owes him an additional fee for services that may have been rendered the night before.
Since she was drunk, she doesn't remember. And because he's falling in love with her, he's hurt. So he demands payment, which she finds outrageous. ''Seventeen hundred dollars
? That's a down payment on a Ford Focus!"
The woman delivering the line is Debra Messing, a comedian who does this sort of thing (fevered zingers, stark-raving neurosis) weekly on ''Will &amp; Grace." When her show is in shape, Messing's the funniest woman on television: a lunatic cross-breeding of Lucille Ball and Rosalind Russell. Her character is inconsistent: Is Grace a pathetic dingbat or the modern woman misunderstood? But Messing is a virtuoso at banter and slapstick.
Her most embarrassing moments on that show are the earnest, teary ones. And ''The Wedding Date" is composed almost exclusively of those. Messing plays Kat Ellis, one of those super-successful New York women with slumping love lives whom movies love to torture. For her sister's wedding, Kat hires Nick, whom Dermot Mulroney inhabits with an understandable lack of interest: He's playing cardboard. They meet on the plane, head over to London, where her family lives, and plunge into the inevitable.
Kat's sister, Amy (Amy Adams), has allowed Kat's ex-fiance, Jeffrey (Jeremy Sheffield), to be her groom's best man. Kat is the maid of honor, and she spends most of her time using her new man to make her old one jealous. Eventually, we're dragged through a soap-opera plot twist that confirms what many will already suspect: These people are stupid.
Well, Nick is not. He was a comparative literature major at Brown, which may account for why he sounds so stoned. It might also explain why he just hangs out here, stranded, like someone dropped him out of a Jane Austen book: Kat will come around and realize he's the one. He and her stepfather (Peter Egan) give Kat loads of advice about how she's her own worst enemy: ''Every woman has the exact love life she wants," she's told in one of the film's many maudlin moments. Mom, for the record, is played by the redoubtable Holland Taylor, who seems boozy even when all she's swilling is ginger ale.
Not much else about ''The Wedding Date" is fun. It's decidedly sub-Aniston, as in so blah not even the star of ''Picture Perfect" or ''The Object of My Affection" would have bothered. Director Clare Kilner seems to prefer clumsily assembled montages pasted to bad pop songs over actual storytelling: The first 10 minutes are devoted to Kat's packing for the UK and various dull helicopter shots of Manhattan, while on the soundtrack The Corrs' ''Breathless" mewls unforgivably around her. It's the same lazy strategy Kilner used to bloat the length of her last inept movie, the Mandy Moore vehicle ''How to Deal."
''The Wedding Date" is adapted from a steaming pile of chick lit called ''Asking for Trouble" and plays it all with a straight face. The cast seems discouraged from doing anything witty or madcap -- especially the movie's star, who looks lost, ordinary, and more than a little sorry. Messing should know this is precisely the kind of movie Grace would ridicule Will for dragging her to see.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>
