<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A gangster movie that tries harder, “10th and Wolf” is the directorial debut of Bobby Moresco, a writer and producer of “Crash.” It desperately wants to matter in the same way that its Academy Award-winning forerunner tried to matter: by trafficking in a blunt, populist morality that insists we’re all in this mess together. The mess, in this case, isn’t the stew of simmering ethnic and class antagonisms addressed in “Crash,” but a pervasive feeling that there’s not much difference nowadays between the good guys and the bad; everyone is tainted.  If that message is moldy, “10th and Wolf” gives it a meretricious new twist. Without thinking very hard, it compares America’s exit from the first Persian Gulf war to gangster morality in a shabby neighborhood of an Eastern industrial city. That comparison doesn’t add up, except in the mind of the movie’s putative hero, Tommy Santoro (James Marsden). In a solemn voice-over narration, he analogizes his reaction to the United States withdrawal from the gulf in 1991 to his traumatic disillusionment at age 12, when his father was shot dead on the front lawn. It was then that he realized that his beloved dad was a mobster who probably deserved what he got.  Because the movie, filmed in Pittsburgh, is loosely based on real events that occurred in Philadelphia in the 1980’s and early 90’s, its particular circle of urban hell is an unidentified hybrid of the two cities. Filmed in shades of brown and gray and slathered in blood, its world is as drab and menacing as that of “Donnie Brasco.” In a diabolical touch, mob colloquies take place in a giant meatpacking cellar amid the hanging carcasses.  The movie is narrated by Tommy, its only male character with a glimmer of nobility. (The women are the usual long-suffering, silent partners who know too much and occasionally erupt in hysterical fits.) A handsome, tarnished angel, Tommy, the one member of his family not caught up in a life of crime, returns to his hometown in 1991 after serving as a Marine in the gulf. Initially gung-ho to fight the good fight, he decided that the war made no sense when Saddam Hussein was left in power. Running amok, he stole a jeep, beat up an officer and served time in the brig.  With no clear future in view, he stays with his aunt Tina (Lesley Ann Warren) and exerts a good influence on his dimwitted younger brother, Vincent (a dissipated-looking Brad Renfro). Almost immediately he is accosted by Horvath (Brian Dennehy), a hulking, corrupt F.B.I. agent who threatens to put him in prison for years unless he infiltrates the family business and wears a wire to record negotiations between his cousin Joey (Giovanni Ribisi) and a Mafia drug lord (Francesco Salvi) moving in on family territory.    Because “10th and Wolf” is set in gangland, it falls back on mob family values to provide whatever sympathy it can scrounge up for its lowlifes. The movie is full of the usual scenes of hugging, grieving and vowing of loyalty that signal that these people have feelings too: operatic ones.  But the characters never transcend the clichés embedded in the culture since “The Godfather.” Except for Tommy, who doesn’t seem to belong to the family, the men are raging, foul-mouthed beasts who exact revenge with the sadistic relish that Brian De Palma’s “Scarface” made into a mob movie imperative. Early on, a one-legged sociopath (Dash Mihok) bludgeons another man to a pulp with his prosthesis. If you can’t technically fault the hot-wired performance of Mr. Ribisi as a rising mob boss, his character amounts to little more than a reheated Joe Pesci-Harvey Keitel stereotype.  For efficiency’s sake, the screenplay crams all the information about its characters’ backgrounds and the neighborhood history into its first 20 minutes. As the consequences of this rushed introduction play out, you are at a loss to recall the details shoehorned into that gory lump of exposition.  Amid all the violence, a half-baked love story wobbles into view,  as Tommy connects with Brandy (Piper Perabo), a beautiful, embittered bartender in the seedy stripper club run by her husband’s killer, Willie (Ken Garito). She and Willy coexist warily until a showdown on top of the bar that begins as an attempted rape and explodes into ultraviolence.  Forget the movie’s spurious moral agenda; scenes like this quasi-pornographic set piece show what trying harder really means in the gangster movie business.  “10th and Wolf” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It is packed with profanity, violence and gore.</text>
      <date>August 18, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>