<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Like its predecessors “49 Up” begins with black-and-white images of British children frolicking on a playground, as a portentous voice-over recites a Jesuit maxim: “Give me the child until he is 7, and I will show you the man.” Ever since they were heard in “7 Up!,” a “World in Action” television documentary first broadcast in 1964, those words have served as the motto for one of the most remarkable experiments in the history of cinema.  Every seven years the director Michael Apted has checked in with as many of those children as were willing to sit for his camera. The resulting films — 14, 21, 28, 35, 42 and now “49 Up” — have confirmed, complicated and in some cases subverted the assumptions of that first inquiry, which promised a glimpse of Britain’s future.  The subjects ranged from children of London’s rough-and-tumble East End to the son of a Yorkshire farmer to three upper-class schoolboys, quite certain at 7 that they were bound for Oxford or Cambridge. But now that they have settled into middle age  — discovering that the thinning of hair and the thickening of midsections respect no rank or station — their lives reveal less about the British class system than about marriage, family relations and the slow turns of the life cycle.  In many ways they are more alike than different. Most married younger than their American counterparts and are now sending their children out into the world, or in some cases welcoming grandchildren. No longer sociological case studies — the boys from the group home, the girls from the council houses, the suburban lads on their bicycles — they are now stubborn and unforgettable individuals. Tony, Suzy, John, Jackie, Andrew, Bruce, Sue, Simon, Paul, Lynn, Nick and Neil: each is a universe of perceptions and experiences, some of which they explain to Mr. Apted, who remains discreetly unseen.  “Forty-Nine Up,” screening tonight at the New York Film Festival and opening nationwide tomorrow, feels less dramatic than the earlier films, which sometimes revealed shocking changes and reversals. The surprises that pop up here — a divorce, a remarriage, a bout of depression, the threat of a lost job — are less dramatic, and the overall mood hovers somewhere between resignation and contentment. Forty-nine, it seems, is not an age for hatching  big plans or foreseeing major changes, but rather a time for taking stock, getting comfortable and keeping an eye on the next generation.  By now, if you have been following the series (and you can catch up with it thanks to a must-have DVD boxed set released two years ago by First Run Features), you recognize, for example, Tony’s playful good humor and entrepreneurial drive. Disappointed in his early hope of becoming a champion jockey, he did rather well as a London cab driver and occasional actor, and now he and his patient wife, Debbie, have built a vacation home on the sunny southern coast of Spain. You are also aware of Neil’s difficulties adjusting to adult life, and of the professional and marital ups and downs experienced by Sue, Jackie,  Suzy and the others.    Rarely has ordinary existence seemed so multifaceted and enigmatic, even in its banal everyday details. Mr. Apted’s method is straightforward. There are interviews, and what television producers call b-roll — slightly stiff sequences of the subjects pretending to go about their daily business at home or at work — and illustrative flashbacks to earlier episodes. Because Mr. Apted avoids intrusive cinéma vérité or tabloid television techniques, the feeling of intimacy, which has grown over time, is rarely uncomfortable.  Except, as it turns out, for the subjects themselves, several of whom reflect, with a degree of bitterness that may startle fans of the series, on how it has affected their lives. John, one of the public school boys whose conservatism announced itself early and has moderated only a little, compares the “Up” project to reality shows like “Big Brother” and “I’m a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here!”  Suzy, who could not meet the filmmaker’s eye at 14 and could barely control her anger at 21, has grown into a mild, apparently contented adult. Of her participation in the films, she says, “I haven’t enjoyed it in any way,” which feels like a rebuke not only to the filmmaker but to the audience as well.  It is impossible to dismiss her indictment, echoed by a handful of her peers. There is something ethically troubling about this project, however serious and high-minded it has been. But one of the remarkable things about these films, which have lavished so much attention, however unwelcome, on their subjects, is that the subjects turn out to be the most trenchant critics.  This only makes me like the films more, even as I feel a bit ashamed of myself for liking them so much. I agree: Suzy’s marriage, Nick’s divorce, Paul’s work history: none of it is my or anyone else’s business. But these things — these people — have become, through Mr. Apted’s films, a vital part of modern life, which seems to grow richer every seven years, when the new “Up” movie comes out.  49 UP  Plays tonight at the New York Film Festival; opens nationwide tomorrow.  Directed by Michael Apted; director of photography, George Jesse Turner; edited by Kim Horton; produced by Claire Lewis and Mr. Apted; released by First Run Features. Running time: 134 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown tonight at 6 at Alice Tully Hall, at Lincoln Center, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, as part of the 44th New York Film Festival; opens nationwide tomorrow; in Manhattan at the IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at Third Street, Greenwich Village. </text>
      <date>October 5, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>