<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Who said mainstream Hollywood has a monopoly on dumb, gross-out farces? The gay, independent comedy "Adam &amp; Steve" is as crude and nonsensical as any number of B-list studio equivalents, with the added disadvantages of a low budget and shaky direction by Craig Chester, who wrote and also stars.  When the title characters meet in a downtown New York club in 1987, Adam (Mr. Chester) is a timid gay goth clinging to his obese best friend, Rhonda (Parker Posey in a fat suit). Steve (Malcolm Gets), a buff, glitter-clad dancer flying on cocaine, makes a beeline for him.  The movie then spins its preposterous story of love interruptus around a scatological money shot:  Steve's explosive reaction when the baby laxative used to cut the coke aborts his precoital striptease, leaving him traumatized for the next 18 years.  Skip to 2005. Adam, now a recovering cocaine addict, leads bird-watching expeditions in Central Park. Steve, a psychiatrist, takes pity on Adam when he brings his injured dog to a hospital. The two fail to recognize each other, but the old spark reignites, and soon they are dating seriously. Will they make it through the minefields of Adam's insecurity and Steve's addiction to quickies with strangers in gym shower stalls to the land of happily ever after?  The movie's funnier jokes revolve around Rhonda, now a svelte standup comic whose act consists of self-loathing fat jokes delivered in a tone of weary hostility to bored audiences of five. An additional laugh or two is squeezed out of Steve's introduction to Adam's accident-prone family, who are propped around the dinner table in casts and braces.  None of it holds together. "Adam &amp; Steve" purports to believe in true love. But the lovers' clinches are so clumsy and heat-free that the actors appear to be wincing through their osculatory chores: not a promising indicator of bliss unto eternity.</text>
      <date>March 31, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>