<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Adoration,” a profound and provocative exploration of cultural inheritance, communications technology and the roots and morality of terrorism, the Canadian filmmaker Atom Egoyan nimbly wades into an ideological minefield without detonating an explosion.  Its story of a high school class assignment that becomes a minor cause célèbre is a rigorously structured variant of the everything-is-connected-to-everything school of filmmaking that has produced movies like “Babel” and “Crash.”  But unlike those movies “Adoration,” Mr. Egoyan’s finest film since “The Sweet Hereafter” (1997), doesn’t strain to maintain a pretense of naturalism. In every scene you feel the controlling hand of Mr. Egoyan who wrote, produced and directed it. Its characters’ burning passions are attached to symbols — a violin scroll, Christmas ornaments, old photographs, a lawn display of the Nativity, a beaded Islamic veil — that have the mystique of sacred relics to the people who possess them.  This meticulously assembled montage weaves flashbacks and fantasies into an enthralling story of a boy’s search for the truth surrounding his parents’ deaths in a car crash years earlier. Repeated scenes show the boy, Simon (Devon Bostick), interviewing his dying grandfather Morris (Kenneth Welsh) in a hospital via video cellphone about the circumstances of their deaths.  Simon’s imagination is also enflamed by a true story read in a high school class in Toronto by Sabine (Arsinée Khanjian), his French and drama teacher, who is Lebanese, about a terrorist who secreted explosives in the luggage of his pregnant girlfriend, who was traveling to Israel. The bomb was confiscated by Israeli security before it went off.  The story is based on a real incident in 1986, in which a Jordanian terrorist secreted a bomb in the hand luggage of his pregnant Irish girlfriend without her knowledge on an El Al flight from London to Israel. Had it exploded, 380 passengers would have died.  Morris, who despised his Lebanese son-in-law, Sami (Noam Jenkins), a luthier, leads his grandson to believe Sami deliberately crashed the car that killed his daughter (Simon’s mother) Rachel (Rachel Blanchard), a gifted violinist. Morris’s account has so tainted his grandson’s memory of his father that it easy for the boy to imagine that he is the son of the couple in the news story.  Sabine encourages him write it as a piece of fiction and present it to the class as a true story. He agrees, then takes it a step further and relates it via Webcam in Internet chat rooms where it kicks up a storm of debate among his peers and their parents.  Simon lives with his uncle, Tom (Scott Speedman), a tow-truck driver, who has inherited Morris’s hatred of Middle Eastern people. Tom is confronted with his prejudice when a mysterious woman in a beaded veil visits the house and asks pointed personal questions about his beliefs.  The words Christian, Jew and Muslim are never attached to the characters. Mr. Egoyan’s refusal to push those verbal buttons forces you to view the characters as human beings without labels and to draw your own conclusions about their cultural backgrounds.  If the plot outline of “Adoration” suggests a clanking mechanism that defies credibility and logic (especially a subplot involving Tom’s tow truck), to watch the movie is to be caught up in a detective story that operates on several levels. Mr. Egoyan conveys a voluptuous, slightly sinister apprehension of the material world in which people harbor secrets, and blind rage can suddenly erupt in the most placid setting for no apparent reason. Here the possibility of violence rears up in a shabby restaurant when three people argue over a sandwich that has just been consumed.  The lurking violence in “Adoration” coincides with scenes of ravishing beauty: Rachel playing the violin at the end of a pier overlooking a river while Sami observes her adoringly from afar; the wooden pieces of a Nativity  being tossed into a fire along with a cellphone in which the image of a person fades from a likeness into digital rectangles, until the device itself begins to crumple.  As always in Mr. Egoyan’s films, technology has a life of it own. Wondrous but also scary, it has the potential to warp reality and to release demonic forces.  During Simon’s science-fiction-like chat sessions his computer screen divides into as many as nine squares; in each you see a different talking head; an old woman who survived a concentration camp bares her tattoo; a Holocaust-denying skinhead shows his pen-and-ink scrawled statement of disbelief. Does the technology unite us? Or are we blindly trapped inside our own squares?  The binding ingredient of “Adoration” is its rich, violin-soaked musical soundtrack by Mychael Danna. Its mood of sorrowful sensuality evokes the troubled histories of flesh-and-blood people whose complicated personal stories, if we knew them, might  or might  not provide reasons for heinous crimes against humanity.  The movie is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language and mild violence.</text>
      <date>May 8, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>