<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There's a reason children aren't allowed to vote, drive or make movies with multimillion-dollar budgets. Lively and imaginative as their inner worlds may be, the very young still lack the discipline and maturity to shape them into coherent and compelling stories - a task the director Robert Rodriguez ("El Mariachi," "Sin City") also fails to accomplish in this film based on characters and themes created by his son, Racer Max, when he was 7.  The movie's hero, also named Max (Cayden Boyd), is a 10-year-old boy growing up in an unnamed Texas town, where his parents (Kristin Davis and David Arquette) argue about money, while his fellow classmates look for excuses to beat him up. Max is the kind of lonely underdog kid audiences are supposed to root for, but his whiny voice and prissy attachment to his leatherbound "dream journal" sort of made me want to beat him up, too.  Max's stern teacher, Mr. Electricidad (George Lopez) discourages the boy from writing in his journal about the imaginary superheroes who visit Max in his daydreams. But when two of Max's creations, Sharkboy and Lavagirl (Taylor Lautner and Taylor Dooley), show up to beg for Max's help in saving their home planet, our hero realizes the importance of dreaming (a lesson reinforced by plenty of wooden, redundant dialogue and several grating songs.)  Halfway through, the film turns into a muddled quest narrative, in which Max and his companions must locate a magical jewel called the Crystal Heart to save Planet Drool from extinction at the hands of the evil Mr. Electric (also played by George Lopez). The plot is full of logical holes (early on, Sharkboy and Lavagirl demonstrate an ability to fly; later, they cling to a crumbling bridge, terrified of falling). But more important, Mr. Rodriguez seems unsure what his film is really about, making the moral of the story - "dream an unselfish dream" - feel more like a vaguely judgmental homily than a satisfying conclusion.  "Sharkboy and Lavagirl" is Mr. Rodriguez's second experiment in three-dimensional filmmaking, after the third installment of his "Spy Kids" series, "Spy Kids 3D: Game Over." Upon entering the theater, each viewer receives a pair of cardboard 3-D glasses, to be worn and removed at intervals throughout the movie as various objects (bubbles, wads of paper, fists) are hurled our way. This system worked well enough at the adults-only preview screening I attended, but fumbling with multiple pairs of glasses could get cumbersome in a dark theater filled with squirming children.  "The Adventures of Sharkboy and Lavagirl in 3-D" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some very mild bodily-fluid humor, but no swearing or sexual situations.</text>
      <date>June 10, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>