<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “After the Wedding,” a Danish drama about ideals and money, sanctimony and obligation, bodies ricochet off one another like pinballs. Shot in digital video with a skittish, at times urgent freehand, the movie opens in India, where slender adults and scrambling children often fill every inch of the frame amid whorls of color and noise. Later, when the story moves to Denmark, where the bodies are paler and more spatially separated, the chaos of the street will have been replaced by the din of selfish human desire.  The plot involves an aid worker, Jacob, played by the eloquently unhappy-looking Mads Mikkelsen, who reluctantly returns to his native Denmark from Mumbai, where he helps run an orphanage. Home to throwaways with dusty feet and solemn smiles, the orphanage is in danger of closing for lack of funds when Jacob receives news of a possible patron. The catch, he glumly learns, is that he has to visit the homeland he left 20 years earlier and to which he has never returned. And so,  to Copenhagen he goes, reeled back by a rich man, Jorgen (the jowly, growling Rolf Lassgard, by turns seductive and horrifying), with a beautiful family, a difficult story and a sense of entitlement as absolute as that of a king.  Dressed in a cheap suit that hangs off him like a tablecloth, Jacob meets his Danish billionaire, who floats a promise worth millions in funds and tenders an invitation to attend  his daughter’s wedding. Jacob reluctantly and somewhat uncomfortably agrees. At the wedding, an expensive affair with a big white tent and a crowd of ruddy celebrants, he is surprised to meet an old acquaintance, Helene (Sidse Babett Knudsen), who happens to be Jorgen’s wife. There is the beloved daughter too, Anna (Stine Fischer Christensen), who is marrying one of her father’s employees and eager admirers, Christian (Christian Tafdrup), not quite realizing that this smiling young man would as soon marry the old man as her. Every court has its courtiers and every family its complications.  Directed by Susanne Bier, whose previous features include “Open Hearts” and “Brothers,” “After the Wedding” is a modern creation  with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The whiff of the modern comes from the harmonious synchronization of the kinetic camerawork with the abrupt editing patterns, which will be familiar to anyone who has ever watched a Dogme film. Ms. Bier doesn’t adhere to all of Dogme’s tenets — found in its so-called vow of chastity — which exclude, among other things, any music or props not originating at the filmmaking site. Instead she opts for a style that might be called Dogme-lite, which mimics the movement’s visual tropes but eschews its ethos and formal rigor to create what is, at core, canned realism.  Despite the whooshing camera work, the crashing edits and the hairpin turns in Anders Thomas Jensen’s screenplay, “After the Wedding” relies on whipped-up familiar ingredients — a birth, a death, a wedding, a funeral, a man, a woman, another man, another woman — to pique the audience’s interest rather than rock its world. That makes it a fine and, on a scene-by-scene basis, often better than fine, if effectively unadventurous work, in which a man’s anguished cry is met by a finale designed to ease the pain. As in many Danish films the performers are top-flight, in particular Mr. Lassgard and Mr. Mikkelsen, an otherworldly screen presence perhaps best known outside Denmark as the villain who weeps blood while giving the lash to James Bond in “Casino Royale.” The tears only look more real here.  “After the Wedding” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). There is some adult language and coitus interruptus. </text>
      <date>March 30, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>