<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Celebrity trumps ideology,” Al Franken says in the new documentary that bears both his name and God’s. The occasion for this observation is a party, given by Newsweek around the time of the 2004 Republican National Convention, at which Mr. Franken hobnobs, rather awkwardly, with other well-known people who dwell mainly to his right on the political spectrum. (Henry A. Kissinger is there, and so is Alan K. Simpson, former Republican senator from Wyoming.)  And it is true that people touched by the dominant forms of modern fame — tabloid notoriety, box-office appeal, media exposure and so on — are in many ways more alike than different, whatever their views on the issues of the day. But it is also the case that Mr. Franken, like his principal adversaries (some appear in the film), represents a relatively new and rapidly proliferating species: the ideological celebrity, hero to partisans and anathema to foes, who reaps money and renown throwing red (or, as the case may be, blue) meat to true believers.  “Al Franken: God Spoke,” directed by Chris Hegedus and Nick Doob, is perhaps best viewed as an investigation of the phenomenon of ideological celebrity, with Mr. Franken as a willing case study. But to the extent that the ferocious polarization of which his fame is a symptom extends into the moviegoing public, the film is more likely to attract or repel viewers according to the sides they’ve already chosen.  In other words, anyone who shares Bill O’Reilly’s  view (cited in the film) that Mr. Franken is “a vile human being” is unlikely to want to spend 90 cinéma vérité minutes in his company, while those who think (to quote the title of Mr. Franken’s first polemical best seller) that “Rush Limbaugh is a big fat idiot” will be more inclined to buy a ticket.  But even his fans may find themselves frustrated, since the film observes Mr. Franken closely without generating much insight into him. Like many other comedians, he seems to be performing constantly. And like many other comedians, he is evidently angry, though he is driven not by psychic torment but by moral fury at the Republican Party and the conservative news media.  “Al Franken: God Spoke” gives him plenty of time to express this anger, and also to crack a few jokes, but not really enough to present his arguments. Those can be found in his books or on his radio show.  The movie is more interested in process and personality, and in the things a public figure does on his way onstage and off. In this it is true to its pedigree. Ms. Hegedus was a co-director on both “The War Room” (with D. A. Pennebaker, her husband and an executive producer of this film) and “Startup.com” (with Jehane Noujaim, who went on to make “Control Room”). These documentaries are part of a tradition of fly-on-the-wall, behind-the-scenes films about well-known figures or public events,  going back at least to Mr. Pennebaker’s 1967 Bob Dylan documentary,  “Don’t Look Back.”  The point is less to explain those people and happenings than to alter your perspective by bringing you in close. “Al Franken: God Spoke” is not quite biographical, though it does include some old “Saturday Night Live” clips and a visit by Mr. Franken to the house in Minnesota where he spent his childhood.  Unfortunately, it does not answer the most interesting question about him, which is how he went from being a writer, stand-up performer and sketch comedy fixture to being a liberal scourge, best-selling fact checker, radio host and possible contender for his old friend Paul Wellstone’s seat in the United States Senate.  Instead, the movie follows him through an eventful passage in this second career, taking in a period that includes the rocky beginnings of the Air America Radio network, the 2004 conventions and that year’s presidential election. Mr. Franken hustles from one event to the next, pausing to rest his aching back, to wink at the camera, and to banter with his wife, Franni.  As Election Day approaches, he ponders the etiquette of gloating, and then keeps going when the occasion for gloating evaporates. He encounters Ann Coulter, Sean Hannity and Michael Medved. Like him, they never seem to get tired or to waver in their convictions. Which is probably what separates them, as ideological celebrities, from the rest of us.</text>
      <date>September 13, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>