<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>hen the director James Cameron proclaimed himself "king of the world" on winning the Oscar for "Titanic," who knew that he also had designs on the rest of the solar system? His newest film, "Aliens of the Deep," is a grandiose hybrid of undersea documentary and outer-space fantasy that begins on our planet's ocean floor and ends many miles under the ice crust that covers Europa, the second moon of Jupiter. The movie's sneaky transition from undersea documentary to speculative fantasy of a journey yet to be undertaken is so seamless that you could easily mistake the last part for the record of an actual space voyage. Filmed in IMAX-3D, this 48-minute film is a visual adventure worthy of that much degraded adjective, awesome. And when the movie is observing the ocean floor where lava from the Earth's inner core is leaking into the water, the strangeness and beauty of an autonomous, teeming ecosystem that has probably existed for two billion years matches any science fiction you could conjure. Mr. Cameron's theory, supported by astrobiologists, is that the life forms found at the deepest levels of the ocean, where no light from the sun penetrates, may hold clues to the nature of possible life in outer space. Even on the Earth, it turns out, the sun isn't the essential be-all and end-all for the existence of life, as was once supposed. Working with scientists at NASA and the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Mr. Cameron, who sporadically narrates the film, accompanied by a team of researchers, journeys several miles under the ocean's surface in submersible vehicles. There they observed and photographed the tumultuous undersea world clustered around cracks where emerging lava creates giant chimneys of superheated water. The submersibles resemble spacecraft, complete with smaller modules that venture out from the mother ship. One of the dangers faced by the explorers is venturing too close to a chimney whose heat could melt the windows. For all the caution expressed, the researchers voice no real fear, only wonder at the sights they behold. They include six-foot-long sea worms with crimson plumes; blind white crabs; and thousands, perhaps millions, of tiny white shrimp swarming in and out of the chimneys. Because the imagination of "Aliens of the Deep" is pure Hollywood, the movie can't resist giving us a "Close Encounters" moment when a human hand pressed against the window of a submersible is met by a welcoming, nonhuman tentacle. Could similar environments exist in outer space? Some astrobiologists speculate that a hidden ocean, twice the size of those on Earth, exists many miles under Europa's ice-covered shell. The movie imagines a robotic vehicle that drills through the ice and surveys that ocean, which teems with similar but even more exotic life forms. And so the primal human impulse to explore goes on.</text>
      <date>January 28, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>