<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It seems incredible, but the grimly unfunny comedy “All About Steve” might just be the worst movie on Sandra Bullock’s résumé. What makes this insult (to her, to us) even worse is that her production company backed the project. This means that unlike movie stars of the classical studio system, who were contractually obliged by their bosses to sometimes play insulting, trivializing roles, Ms. Bullock, or more likely her representatives, actually tapped people to make her look this bad. She’s the mistress of her own misfortune.  As it often does, an unfortunate hairdo serves as an early indicator of the ensuing trouble. (See also Elizabeth Taylor in “Cleopatra” and Colin Farrell in “Alexander.”) Wearing a honeyed shag that’s probably meant to evoke Jane Fonda in “Klute” but looks like a repurposed mullet, Ms. Bullock enters grinning and squinting and twitching in a pantomime of frenetic adorableness. When the movie opens, her character, Mary Horowitz, a crossword puzzle creator, is living with her parents while her home is being fumigated. Given her social ineptitude and overworked wackiness — her logorrhea, ubiquitous red boots and a pet rodent that appears to be her only friend — it’s a surprise she ever left the parental nest.  The Steve in question is a news cameraman played by the hard-smiling Bradley Cooper, who materializes during an improbable blind date. Smitten at first sight, Mary breaks out the push-up bra and desperation. And because she’s a female character of a certain age in a romantic comedy, she doesn’t just smooch, she also swoons. Oblivious to the sound of Steve’s screeching tires, she gives chase, a decision that takes her from one news hot spot to another and into assorted humiliations. Happily for us, the inert filmmaking comes with some quirky types whose comic faces and timing provide periodic if slight relief: so thank you, Thomas Haden Church, Katy Mixon, D J Qualls, Ken Jeong, Jason Jones and, for an eye blink, Charlyne Yi.  Ms. Bullock tries her best to keep up with these funny men and women, but she’s wrong for her role, and her performance decisions — the tiny lisp, fluttering hands, trudging walk, mincing run — are equally wide of the mark. You can appreciate her wanting to try something different, but Ms. Bullock became a big star because she perfected an appealing type (likable, unsinkable) that seems to align naturally with her off-screen persona. Her characters often start with a few knocks against them and might even be true sad sacks (“While You Were Sleeping”), but the ability to suffer beautifully has long been a prerequisite for female stardom. We wait in exquisite agony for those trembling lips to transform into a dazzling smile.  Mary’s lips, alas, just flap and flap and flap. A brainiac, she rattles off multisyllabic words like a teenager prepping for college admission tests, bombarding her understandably weary, impatient and even panicked listeners with dictionary definitions, encyclopedic notes and foreign-language phrases. The screenplay by Kim Barker (“License to Wed”) tries to insist that Mary isn’t damaged and simply needs to find the right tribe, so she can let her freak flag proudly fly. But the concept of an intelligent woman is apparently so exotic to Ms. Bullock and her director, Phil Traill,  that they frantically kook the character up, as if female smarts were a kind of disability. This being a contemporary big-studio release, I suppose it is.  “All About Steve” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Parents of girls are particularly cautioned.</text>
      <date>September 4, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>