<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “All the King’s Men,” Robert Penn Warren’s Pulitzer Prize-winning 1946 novel about the rise and fall of a demagogic Southern governor, may be a classic, but it is far from perfect. Diamond-sharp political insights sink into pseudo-Faulknerian hoodoo; plots and subplots entangle like kudzu on a riverbank; and some of the keenest American prose ever written keeps close company with some of the gustiest. “How life is strange and changeful,” Warren’s narrator, Jack Burden, philosophizes at one point, “and the crystal is in the steel at the point of fracture, and the toad bears a jewel in his forehead, and the meaning of moments passes like the breeze that scarcely ruffles the leaf of the willow.”  Doesn’t it though? The frequency of passages like this make the prospect of another screen adaptation of the novel — the first, directed by Robert Rossen, won three Oscars, including best picture, in 1950 — a welcome one, since a screenwriter is free to omit them and concentrate on a sweaty, sinewy tale of corrupted idealism and moral decay. It is not hard to see why Steve Zaillian, whose writing credits include “Schindler’s List” and “Gangs of New York” and who directed “Searching for Bobby Fischer” and “A Civil Action,” was drawn to the material.  Whatever its flaws, Warren’s book, a meaty stew of lurid Southern-gothic pulp and high-minded literariness, seems to provide the recipe for a grand, melodramatic prestige picture, the kind that can both flatter and titillate the audience (and the Academy) while providing at least a half-dozen actors the opportunity to thunder, strut, pine and wail. Lust, power, greed, betrayal, family secrets, dark sedans and crumbling plantation houses, a tremor of illicit sex and a glimmer of political relevance:  “All the King’s Men” has it all.  The problem may be that it has too much. Mr. Zaillian and his editor, Wayne Wahrman, having labored mightily to strain and reduce Warren’s messy gumbo, serve up a platter heaped with starchy, indigestible lumps. A squad of blue-chip performers — including Sean Penn, Jude Law, Kate Winslet, James Gandolfini, Mark Ruffalo, Anthony Hopkins and Patricia Clarkson — sweat handsomely in their Depression-era clothes, illuminated by sunlight slanting exquisitely into dark-paneled rooms and smoky train compartments, while James Horner’s score blasts significance into every corner of the frame.  Nothing in the picture works. It is both overwrought and tedious, its complicated narrative bogging down in lyrical voiceover, long flashbacks and endless expository conversations between people speaking radically incompatible accents. Only Ms. Clarkson, who really is from Louisiana, and Jackie Earle Haley, who utters few words, manage to acquit themselves credibly.  It is rare to see a movie so prodigiously stuffed with fine actors, nearly every one of them grievously miscast. Ms. Winslet, bathed in light or veiled in gauze, looks nearly as dazed as Mr. Ruffalo. Mr. Penn, stepping into one of Broderick Crawford’s great blowhard roles, tries to reconnect Willie Stark, a self-described “hick,” with his rustic origins, emphasizing the character’s diffidence and low cunning as well as his strutting arrogance. What is missing, though, is the full, Shakespearean measure of Willie’s charisma.  Mr. Penn is, fundamentally, an antitheatrical, naturalistic actor, whose great gift is his ability to convey inwardness. His narrow face, with its close-set eyes and thin mouth, seems closed in on itself. Expansiveness does not come easily to him, but Willie is the kind of populist leader who grows larger in public, where he feeds on the anger and adoration of the people.    Mr. Penn rants and shouts and waves his fist in the air — “Your need is my justice,” he bellows — but you never feel the galvanizing force of that essential connection, or the ebullient showboating that is its authentic form of expression. Mr. Penn is in some ways too fine an actor to play a country ham like Willie Stark.  And Mr. Zaillian does not seem quite sure what to make of the character. At its root Willie’s story has the simplicity of a parable, in which a crusader on behalf of the poor and marginal becomes a monster, blighting the machinery of government with graft and vanity and turning public works into self-aggrandizing monuments. In the film (one of whose executive producers is James Carville), Willie, originally modeled on the Louisiana governor and United States senator Huey P. Long, shows a passing resemblance to more recent political figures, from Bill Clinton to Lyndon B. Johnson to Hugo Chávez. He is a creature of high political intelligence, unbridled appetite and a vengeful eagerness to humiliate his state’s traditional rulers. Louisiana’s oil and gas, he declares, belong to the people, on whose behalf he builds highways, bridges, schools and hospitals. With him the era of big government is just beginning.  His rise is narrated — and to some extent propelled — by Jack Burden (Mr. Law), a blandly dissolute former newspaperman with deep family connections to the old aristocracy. Jack’s involvement with the governor leads him back into his own past —  in particular to a moonlit night when he went swimming in the Gulf of Mexico with the luminous Anne Stanton (Ms. Winslet) while her moody brother, Adam (Mr. Ruffalo), looked on — and also into conflict with the elderly judge (Mr. Hopkins) who was like a father to young Jack.  The entwinement of Jack’s life with Willie’s is meant, in Warren’s florid but nonetheless powerful telling, to be a Greek tragedy of modern Democratic politics. In Mr. Zaillian’s velvet-wallpaper version, neither the politics nor the family intrigue makes much sense. We hear much more than we see about both Willie’s grandeur and his ultimate monstrosity, and never grasp the full dimensions of his personality, in triumph or in disgrace.  The camera likes to dwell on the skull-like face and half-concealed sidearm of Sugar Boy (Mr. Haley), the governor’s muscle, but these gestures of menace and foreboding seem as overdone as the leering glimpses of the showgirls with whom Willie sometimes consorts. And poor Mr. Law, an actor of lively wit, is once again asked to mope and maunder, and occasionally purple up the soundtrack with sighing narration.  The picture’s moralism is unconvincing, not only because current sensibilities are unlikely to be shocked by misbehavior in high office (or out of it) but more seriously because Mr. Zaillian’s conception of politics is sentimental and unreal, and his sense of history is ultimately that of a decorator, not a storyteller. Impassioned oratory is a fine thing, but Willie Stark knew that you had to get those roads and bridges built as well. Like an electioneering candidate —  which, given the incipient Oscar race, it is —   “All the King’s Men” makes a lot of promises but fails to deliver the goods.  “All the King’s Men” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some rough language, implied and actual violence and some hints of sexuality.</text>
      <date>September 22, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>