<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “It looks like Vietnam post-napalm.”  That sentence, gravely spoken by a surly, drunken C.I.A. agent (Mark Pellegrino) to his fetching ex-wife  (Gretchen Mol), encapsulates everything that is wrong with the deeply silly movie “An American Affair.”  The agent, Graham Caswell, is referring to the dug-up garden  behind the Washington town house of Catherine, his ex. An abstract painter and sexual free spirit,  Catherine likes to lounge around the house half-naked, smoking cigarettes, seemingly unaware that Adam Stafford (Cameron Bright), the pimply 13-year-old boy from across the way, is ogling her.  A lonely parochial school student whose parents are journalists, Adam is so besotted with his real-life centerfold that he summons the courage to knock on Catherine’s door and ask for work.  She obliges by enlisting his help as a part-time gardener. Before long Adam has turned into a stalker. One night he finds himself peeping through the shutters of her bedroom closet while she has sex.  Catherine is preposterously careless and indiscreet, seeing as one of her regular lovers is President John F. Kennedy, whom Adam spies ducking into the house while a Secret Service detail patrols the entrance. All Washington, including Graham and his sinister C.I.A. boss, Lucian Carver (James Rebhorn), seems to know about the affair.  The movie, directed by William Sten Olsson from a screenplay by Alex Metcalf, is set mostly in the months between the Bay of Pigs fiasco and Kennedy’s assassination. It subscribes wholeheartedly to the history-as-pornography school of thinking, in which all will be revealed if you can figure out who is sleeping with whom, when and where and what they do in bed. Any resemblance between Catherine and Marilyn Monroe  is glaringly intentional.  Because it is crammed with vintage television and film footage of the Kennedy years, “An American Affair” has illusions of itself as a serious docudrama. But as it wades deeper into a conspiratorial swamp that involves angry Cubans, a shadowy C.I.A. plot and Adam’s pilfering of Catherine’s tell-all diary, the movie becomes  a risible fusion of cloak-and-dagger melodrama and prurient coming-of-age story (“Summer of  ’63”?). In the most squirm-inducing scene, the boy and his centerfold, drawn together by grief, actually lock lips.  Were it a farce instead of an earnest, paranoid thriller with pretensions to historicity, “An American Affair” might not seem so offensively exploitative. The fact that it is quite well acted, especially by Ms. Mol, who has the air of a sophisticated 1960s party animal down pat, only compounds the insult.  How far-fetched is it? Take that reference to the backyard garden: in 1963 napalm had long been a weapon of war, but it was not yet synonymous with the American involvement in Vietnam,  then still in the early stages of heating up. “Vietnam post-napalm” was  nearly a decade down the road.  “An American Affair” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and nudity.</text>
      <date>February 27, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>