<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Near the beginning of “American Violet,” when Dee Roberts (Nicole Beharie), a feisty 24-year-old African-American woman, is arrested, handcuffed and roughly dragged by the police from the diner where she works, your heart sinks. We have already watched a police task force conduct a military-style drug raid on Arlington Springs, the housing project in Melody, Tex., where she lives with her mother, Alma (Alfre Woodard), and four children. You grit your teeth in expectation of more cruelty to come.  Thrown into a jail cell with three other women, Dee is stunned to learn she is being charged not for the hundreds of dollars in parking tickets that she owes but with distributing narcotics in a school zone.  Although she is not carrying drugs and none are found in her home, the prosecution claims to have a witness.  Dee’s court-appointed  lawyer urges her to take a plea bargain and agree to a  10-year suspended sentence with a small fine, rather than risk serving a 16- to 25-year prison term. When Dee hotly refuses, even her mother thinks she is a fool.  “American Violet,” which is based on  real events that took place in late 2000, has the quasi-documentary feel of a well-made television drama. Directed by Tim Disney from a screenplay written by its producer, Bill Haney, the film  is beautifully acted by Ms. Beharie,  whose high-strung character is no angel. It is almost impossible for Dee to control her anger, justifiable though it may be. Much of her fury is directed at Darrell Hughes (Xzibit), the father of her two youngest children, with whom she is  waging a bitter custody battle. Making matters worse, he lives next door with a sinister girlfriend who Dee believes is abusing the children when they visit.  The movie’s indictment of injustice and racial profiling in a small Texas town leaves no doubt about who are the good guys and the bad. Dee’s defiance is heroic, as is her concern for the welfare of her children. Also heroic are her minister, Reverend Sanders (Charles S. Dutton), and David Cohen (Tim Blake Nelson), the lawyer from the American Civil Liberties Union enlisted   to defend Dee and sue the district attorney for racial discrimination.  Addressing the congregation, Cohen lays out his interpretation of the local justice system’s oppressive modus vivendi. Drug task forces use military tactics to terrorize black people, he says. Since federal money goes to counties that convict the most people, plea bargains in criminal cases are aggressively pursued. For most people charged with drug-related crimes, the penalties for a conviction after not taking a plea are so frightening that many innocent people plead guilty.  The villain of “American Violet” is the local district attorney, Calvin Beckett, who appears to run the town. Played by Michael O’Keefe as a slicker contemporary version of the hulking, pig-eyed bullies portrayed in earlier films by Rod Steiger and Rip Torn,  Beckett is shrewd enough not to vent his racism publicly, but it still leaks out of him like a bad smell. Navigating between the two sides is Sam Conroy (Will Patton), a local lawyer and former assistant district attorney who has a guilty conscience about past misdeeds.  As Cohen and his assistant, Byron Hill (Malcolm Barrett), build their case, there are no surprises. A more manipulative film would have played up the drama of securing the damning evidence against  Beckett, which is belatedly introduced at his deposition. The movie’s staunchly liberal point of view extends to the 2000  presidential election, which is shown unfolding in the background. Al Gore’s concession speech is used to suggest that the systemic racism in Melody is a symptom of a broader climate of injustice.  “American Violet” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has strong language and racial epithets, and a scene of domestic violence.</text>
      <date>April 17, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>