<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Don’t fool yourself. Any brilliant idea you might have for a reality television series has probably already been imagined and pitched by go-getters like Dave Roberts and Gil S. Ripley, the hotshot comedy-writing team observed peddling their dubious wares in the documentary “American Cannibal.” As the movie observes  them tossing around outlandish concepts, then trying to interest jaded cable network executives in their trashy ideas, you are tempted to wonder if the documentary, directed by Perry Grebin and Michael Nigro, is a put-on.  One concept Mr. Roberts and Mr. Ripley invent: “Virgin Territories,”  in which  10 men, all certified  virgins, share a house where they are bombarded with pornography and tempted  by sexy female visitors but forbidden to touch either the women or themselves. The one who remains chaste the longest gets the ultimate reward: loss of his virginity with a porn star.  Never mind that some men might think that a paltry, if not a dangerously unhealthy, payoff. And never mind that the mechanics  of certifying male virginity  are never addressed, nor the methods of detecting furtive autoerotic release. It’s the thought that counts.  But the concept and its catchy slogan — “when you win it, you lose it” — fire the imagination of Kevin Blatt, a promoter who marketed the Paris Hilton sex tape and is eager to jump into the cesspool of reality television. Mr. Blatt is even more excited about another idea Mr. Roberts and Mr. Ripley pitch to him as a half-joking afterthought: “American Cannibal.” Contestants on this show would be transported to an island, starved and led to think that one of them would  be eaten. The details are never spelled out.  Mr. Blatt invests  $100,000 in development money. Potential contestants are interviewed,  told the show is called “Starvation Island” (minus the cannibal angle) and given a questionnaire in which they are asked if they would be able to eat their own fingers and toes.  For some people, it seems, nothing is too humiliating or painful if it gets them on television. The six finalists are flown with a camera crew to the island of Vieques, off Puerto Rico, to shoot a pilot, and George Gray (of “The Weakest Link”) is signed as host.  Almost immediately upon reaching the island, the project collapses from sloppy planning, union problems and an injury  to a contestant. As one thing after another goes wrong, the documentary itself is sabotaged by acts of God and legal problems. None of the tests  the contestants endure are shown, and the ultimate fate of the injured woman is left unclear.  The documentary illustrates the premise that if you lie down with dogs, you wake up with fleas. Until  everything collapses,  and the filmmakers are left grasping at straws, it’s absorbing in a sick way. The fact that all the people we see in the reality-TV  business appear to sneer at their own genre doesn’t excuse their culpability for perpetuating  that toxic phenomenon. Mr. Ripley, Mr. Roberts and Mr. Blatt, in particular, earn every failure and setback that comes their way.</text>
      <date>March 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>