<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The serial killer in “Anamorph” shows promise, even if some of his best moves are derivative. The same is true of the film’s director, H. S. Miller, who, in making his feature debut, conjures up a nightmarish atmosphere of dread that owes obvious debts both to David Lynch (particularly the later work) and to John McNaughton (namely his notorious  horror show, “Henry: Portrait of a Serial Killer”). Mr. Miller and his co-writer, Tom Phelan, manage to get under your skin largely with borrowed implements, though they receive solid support from Willem Dafoe and the resourceful veteran cinematographer Fred Murphy.  This is the second serial-killer movie opening in New York City today (see the review of "88 Minutes"), and by far the more accomplished. That’s some consolation, I suppose, though it’s also a drag that filmmakers persist in trolling the same brackish waters. In 1990   Mr. McNaughton shook up audiences with the unnerving “Henry,” a creepy, chilly flick with a lot of skill and no heart (though I do believe you can see one peeping through a victim’s rib cage). Jonathan Demme added Hollywood gloss to the subgenre with “The Silence of the Lambs” (1991), and David Fincher broke from the pack with “Seven” (1995). Last year brought  the release of Mr. Fincher’s masterly “Zodiac,” the definitive serial-killer film.  “Zodiac” may well be the last word on serial-killer films, less because it’s a work of genius than because it directly engages with our obsession — our moviegoing, spectacle-seeking, bloodletting obsession — with serial killers. “Anamorph” is a far more modest endeavor in aesthetic and intellectual terms: It’s self-conscious about its influences without being self-reflexive. Mr. Miller and Mr. Phelan filter their ideas through a more rarefied sieve than most mainstream horror guys — in addition to Mr. Lynch, they borrow from the painter Francis Bacon and throw around art-speak — but they show no interest in adding to the discussion (as it were). They’re more interested in the neat-o ways you can slice and dice a body than in trying to construct meaning from its severed parts.  The character charged with putting the pieces together here is Stan Aubray, a zonked-out New York City detective played by an especially cadaverous-looking Willem Dafoe. With his wild eyes and sharp bones, his parchment-thin skin stretched across his face like a drying animal hide, Mr. Dafoe has always made for an unsettling screen presence. He doesn’t have much to work with in “Anamorph” beyond some laborious bits of business and character tics — Stan guzzles his booze out of little airliner  bottles and owns an antique armchair — but he makes even these trivial moments count. Mostly, he plays Stan without a trace of pity, laying bare a man who seems to have been so hollowed out by his gruesome work that he’s as lifeless as a corpse.  The story is largely irrelevant, as are the other characters. There’s a killer, of course, and eviscerated bodies arranged in tableaus that will either cause you to blanch or dredge up memories from Art History 101. Clea Duvall has a small, predictably thankless part as Stan’s token female friend, a former prostitute (naturally) who only meets him when she’s giving blood, which she does in more ways than one. Scott Speedman plays another detective, though his role is more rightly that of a red herring, while an amusing Peter Stormare shows up as some kind of antiques guru with the investigative insight of Hercule Poirot. Me, I haven’t a clue what Mr. Stormare is doing in this film, but it was nice to see him.  “Anamorph” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Gives new meaning to the  term body art.</text>
      <date>April 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>