<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A gentle tale gently told, “When Did You Last See Your Father?” is grown-up, civilized fare. If that sounds like a compliment, it is, even though the whole thing might have been improved with a bit of messiness, a little vulgarity to leaven its tastefulness and tact. This isn’t a groundbreaking work; just a smartly played story, enlivened by drama and spiked with passion,  the very thing that thinking audiences pine for, especially during the summer spectacle season when theaters are clogged with sticky kids’ stuff and television reruns.  Colin Firth, one of the few screen actors who make male decency seem sexy, plays Blake, a successful poet and resentful son. The story, adapted from the British author Blake Morrison’s nonfiction best seller of (almost) the same title, takes the measure of that resentment, which gurgles to the surface when the son learns that his father is dying. Working from David Nicholls’s  screenplay, the director Anand Tucker (who made the wonderful “Hilary and Jackie”) approaches the material from the inside out. He  takes us deep inside Blake’s thinking — both in the present and in childhood flashbacks — to show how this sympathetic, otherwise temperate man developed such prickly, seemingly petty feelings toward his father, Arthur, who seems perfectly harmless if for no other reason than he’s played by Jim Broadbent.  Though often called upon to play blustery charmers (you can imagine him sleeping in tweeds and searching for the bowler already parked on his head), Mr. Broadbent is a sly puss, a nimble  stealer of scenes. He has a great, jowly face for comedy, as his estimable work with Mike Leigh and other directors attests, but there is something about his shrewd eyes that suggests a darting, penetrating intelligence. He uses that face and those eyes to very good effect in “When Did You Last See Your Father?,” creating a complex portrait — executed in broad strokes rather than detailed lines — of a needy, somewhat desperate man whose bullying ways and boorishness obscure his other qualities, particularly from his only, increasingly estranged son.  The movies are filled with epically bad fathers, legendary monsters, destroyers of women and children alike. One reason may be that monsters are inherently dramatic and cinematically easy: A shaking fist or a smack across a downy cheek can goose up even the flattest scene. One of the nicest surprises here is that Arthur isn’t a monster, simply careless, sometimes cruel. He routinely calls the younger Blake fathead and blunders into his son’s private life whenever it suits him. He lies and flirts and, worst of all, routinely and publicly humiliates his wife, Kim, a monument to connubial patience, played by the stellar Juliet Stevenson. It’s no wonder that the adult Blake can’t see his father as just a man — the child never did, never could.  Fluidly edited, the film regularly shifts between the present, with the adult Blake confronting death, and the past, with the younger Blake confronting life. For the most part this oscillation between time frames and emotional registers works well, even if Mr. Tucker, whose sensitive touch with actors is his greatest strength as a director, tends to clutter up the scenes with too much fussy, self-conscious camerawork. It’s a pleasure to watch Mr. Firth — a supremely controlled actor who makes each developing fissure visible — show the adult Blake coming to terms with his contradictory feelings, letting the love and the hurt pour out of him. If only Mr. Tucker had let the tears flow and kept his whirling dervish of a camera on a much shorter leash.  “When Did You Last See Your Father?” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for salty language and chaste fumbling. </text>
      <date>June 6, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>