<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Answer Man” is a movie about the softening up of a curmudgeon: a familiar premise and not necessarily a terrible one. Jeff Daniels, playing a reclusive author of inspirational literature, is a fine curmudgeon (see “The Squid and the Whale,” for instance), and Lauren Graham is a perfectly effective curmudgeon softener (see “Bad Santa”). The cast also includes talented younger performers like Lou Taylor Pucci (“Thumbsucker”), Kat Dennings (“Nick and Norah’s Infinite Playlist”) and Olivia Thirlby (“Juno”).  So far so good, though throwing Ms. Dennings and Ms. Thirlby, two up-and-coming indie sweethearts, into a single movie seems a bit redundant. And neither actress has much to do here. But an excess of youthful charm is hardly the main problem with “The Answer Man,” the first feature written and directed by John Hindman.  The main problem is that the movie, in spite of some nice shots of Philadelphia, just doesn’t work. There are a few interesting ideas and potentially engaging characters, but everything slides around like a plateful of half-set Jello, convincing you of nothing beyond Mr. Hindman’s earnest intentions and uncertain skills.  Mr. Daniels plays Arlen Faber, whom we meet 20 years after his book “Me and God” has made him a literary and spiritual sensation. Apparently an extended Q. and A. between its title characters, the book is like “The Da Vinci Code” crossed with “Chicken Soup for the Soul”; it has spawned shelves full of guides and knockoffs and landed its author’s name on nearly every magazine cover in the world.  But not his likeness, since the publicity-shy Arlen has taken refuge from his celebrity in an elegantly appointed row house where he marinates in misanthropy and nurses a bad back. That malady brings Arlen into contact with a neighborhood chiropractor (Ms. Graham), while his urge to rid himself of accumulated volumes of self-help literature leads him to become the reluctant mentor to a bookstore owner (Mr. Pucci) in need of counseling.  Nothing that happens in “The Answer Man” is especially surprising, which would be all right if the movie were less tedious and its characters endowed with more life. As it is, they possess traits, tics and problems, but no real personalities. Arlen in particular is a mess of contradictory behavior — by turns wise, obnoxious, anxious and courtly — that even Mr. Daniels’s well-honed nimbleness cannot bring into coherence.  The film turns on a preposterous dramatic problem. Everyone in the world seems to take the alleged wisdom in Arlen’s book literally and to suppose that the author possesses a direct line to the Almighty. When this turns out — sorry for the spoiler — not to be the case, a new batch of alleged wisdom is offered, this time involving lessons on how humility is better than arrogance, questions are better than answers, and human fallibility is preferable to divine perfection.  But who was arguing? And beyond that, who cares? Neither an effective satire of New Age quackery nor a bittersweet comedy of connection and healing, “The Answer Man” never shows enough passion to be interestingly bad.  “You are here so God can experience the world through your eyes,” Arlen says  at one point, but in the case of this movie, it isn’t enough of a reason.  “The Answer Man” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It  has a lot of profanity.</text>
      <date>July 24, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>