<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> You have to wonder about a movie called “Anvil! The Story of Anvil.” Is the redundancy in the title self-mocking or just bluntly declarative? It’s a question that lingers around the movie itself, which is either an affectionate chronicle of a Canadian heavy metal band that never quite made it or else a deadpan mockery of the same band.  Or maybe both. Or neither. After a recent screening in Manhattan, two of my colleagues and I spent about 20 minutes on the sidewalk arguing about whether the film was a documentary at all. Evidence that it might have been a clever hoax was suggested by the goofiness of some of the group’s lyrics and album covers (all of which feature, what else? a giant anvil) and by what seemed to be sly references to “This Is Spinal Tap,” the definitive rock-mockumentary. One of the members of Anvil is named Robb Reiner, which is the “Spinal Tap” director’s name with an extra “b.” On a trip to England, Anvil works with a producer whose equipment has knobs that go to 11, and the members of the band make a pilgrimage to Stonehenge. The phrase “who were the Druids?” popped into my head, followed by the question, Who is Anvil?  If my fellow critics and I had better headbanger bona fides we might have known that Anvil is a mighty and awesome Toronto-based quartet that enjoyed a brief heyday in the ’80s and never quite made it big after that. That one of us mistook the group for a put-on is partly a result of the highly theatrical nature of the musical genre itself, even if the musicians’ tongues are everywhere except in their cheeks. It’s also true that Spinal Tap has long since transcended satire and been welcomed into the metal god pantheon.  But there is also a kind of sincerity that can seem to the jaded eye like self-parody, and the earnest, heartfelt striving of the two men at the center of Anvil makes the band’s story more touching than comical. Mockery would be too easy and too mean, and the success of “Anvil! The Story of Anvil” lies in its ability to make you care about an enterprise you might initially have been inclined to laugh at.  The film, directed by Sacha Gervasi (whose screenwriting credits include “The Big Tease” and “The Terminal”), begins with an old clip from a rock festival in Japan, perhaps the high point of Anvil’s early career. After tributes from rockers like Slash of Guns N’ Roses, Lars Ulrich of Metallica and Lemmy Kilmister of Motörhead, we catch up with Anvil at home in Toronto, where after 30 years the band is still thrashing.  Mr. Reiner, who plays drums, and Steve Kudlow, the lead singer and guitarist, who goes by the stage name Lips, turn out to be two nice Jewish boys from Toronto. Now middle-class family men, they seem a bit tired and defeated at times, but they are also open and passionate as well as reasonably talented. They met as teenagers, and the enthusiasm for music that they shared then has hardly waned, even as their partnership has clearly endured some ups and downs.  Their relationship, as complicated and in its way as beautiful as a long, rough marriage, emerges as the film’s dramatic heart, even as its narrative is focused on their attempt to make one last lunge for glory and recognition. They undertake a tour of Europe under the wing of an ardently well-intentioned, spectacularly incompetent manager and then try to drum up record-industry interest in their 13th album. It’s painful to watch them work so hard for so little, though it’s also frequently funny. And their resilience, quixotic though it may be, is also inspiring. How can you not root for them? They’re such nice guys, and so devoted to their art.  “Anvil! The Story of Anvil” (I’m starting to love that title, by the way) may not change your opinion of heavy metal. I confess it did not inspire me to seek out CDs like “Hard ’N’ Heavy,” “Metal on Metal” and “Worth the Weight.” But it might make you think in new ways about a cruel cultural logic that increasingly obliterates the middle ground between success and failure. Mr. Reiner and Mr. Kudlow may not quite merit full-metal glory, but they don’t deserve oblivion either, and “Anvil! The Story of Anvil” makes both a case and a place for their band. </text>
      <date>April 10, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>