<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> As “The Architect” deteriorates from a potentially enlightening exploration of urban development and class conflict  into a preposterous melodrama, your instinct is to curse creative writing courses — the kind that ask aspiring playwrights to inflate paint-by-numbers dramatic tidiness with steroidal histrionics.  That’s because “The Architect,” written and directed by Matt Tauber, was adapted from a play of the same name by the Scottish writer David Greig, and much of what’s on the screen feels like a creaky, tone-deaf classroom exercise in mechanical contrivance.  More is the pity since the movie is well acted, especially by Anthony LaPaglia, who plays Leo Waters, a successful architect whose smug sense of civic virtue is challenged by Tonya Neely (Viola Davis), a middle-aged black woman with an ax to grind. Tonya lives in Eden Court, a decaying housing project on the South Side of Chicago that Leo built decades earlier but hasn’t visited since. The project, based on ideas formulated by Le Corbusier,  has decayed into a drug-infested hellhole ruled by gangs,  and Tonya is leading a campaign to have  it torn down.  When she visits Leo to ask him to sign a petition for its demolition, he refuses. His pride stung, he insists that the problems of Eden Court can be solved through redesign.  Just as “The Architect” seems ready to delve thoughtfully into its subject,  it shifts its focus to Leo’s and Tonya’s conflicted families and turns into a shrill soap opera replete with two suicides. Leo’s wife, Julia (Isabella Rossellini), is a grim, unsmiling neat freak whose years of pent-up rage suddenly erupt  in a crockery-throwing tantrum. His sulky son, Martin (Sebastian Stan), mysteriously drops out of college, and his insecure 15-year-old daughter, Christina (Hayden Panettiere), tests her sexual attractiveness with a truck driver.  In the weakest subplot, Martin is picked up during a visit to Eden Court by Shawn (Paul James), a sensitive young gay black man who carries around a volume of Tolstoy and listens to John Denver. Although he recoils when Shawn puts the moves on him, Martin returns, and they have rough sex on a rooftop. The dynamics of this hookup are as baffling as Christina’s walk on the wild side with the sensitive trucker (Walton Goggins), who rhapsodizes over the John Hancock Center.  For her part, Tonya has two daughters: a sullen teenage single mother who lives with her  in Eden Court and a happy, optimistic A-student who stays with an oncologist from the hospital where Tonya works. The movie’s ear for Ebonics is made of tin.  This seriously overcrowded movie teems with good intentions. But with the exception of Mr. LaPaglia’s Leo, the characters remain theoretical constructions grasping at a reality that no amount of earnest acting can supply.  “The Architect” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>December 1, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>