<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ince he burst "Straight Outta Compton" on the record of that name in 1988, Ice Cube (born O'Shea Jackson) has gone through multiple incarnations as an entertainer, from the controversial front man for the rap group N.W.A. to film roles as the self-destructive gang member in "Boyz N the Hood" and the genial stoner in "Friday" and its sequels (of which he is also co-writer and co-producer). In the "Barbershop" films of recent years, Ice Cube began to reinvent his on-screen persona as a warmhearted family man. In the new comedy "Are We There Yet?," he takes that persona from PG-13 to PG territory, focusing on a new demographic of preteenage fans. Ice Cube plays Nick Persons, the easygoing owner of a sports memorabilia shop in Portland, Ore. Nick is a bachelor and confirmed ladies' man who hates children the way Ebenezer Scrooge hates Christmas: as a matter of principle. But when he casts his eye on a luscious divorced woman named Suzanne (Nia Long), he is forced to reconsider his antichild policy. Unfortunately for Nick, Suzanne's two children, 11-year-old Lindsey and 8-year-old Kevin (Aleisha Allen and Philip Daniel Bolden), have vowed to sabotage their mother's suitors by any means necessary, including booby-trapping the front doorstep with a carpet of slippery marbles. So Nick courts Suzanne while steering clear of the two terrors until, stuck in Vancouver on a business trip, Suzanne asks him to take the youngsters up for a visit. Their journey is predictably star-crossed: luggage is lost, planes missed and cars wrecked and abandoned, until finally Nick is chasing the children on horseback as they stow away on a boxcar. The inexorable logic of breakdown and disintegration in "Are We There Yet?" is the best thing about it; like the John Hughes comedy "Planes, Trains and Automobiles," it posits travel as a Dante-esque ordeal in which the hell of the transportation system serves as a gateway to the paradise of love and family. By the time the battle-scarred Nick and his charges arrive in Vancouver, he has become the children's de facto father. Though the presence of the always charismatic Ice Cube makes "Are We There Yet?" watchable, the movie suffers from one insurmountable problem: as scripted by a too-many-cooks screenwriting team and cloyingly played by the young actors, little Lindsey and Kevin are such insufferable brats that the hero's change of heart remains a mystery. As Nick goes from despising his young charges to dandling them on his knee, viewers are likely to experience the same process in reverse; the children are so relentlessly shrill, their behavior so dreadful and consequence-free, that childless viewers of "Are We There Yet?" (who, to be fair, are likely to be few) may find themselves rethinking their stance on reproduction. "Are We There Yet?" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It contains mild profanity and a few bodily fluid-related jokes.</text>
      <date>January 21, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>