<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> We first encounter Jerome Platz, the hapless hero of Terry Zwigoff's hapless "Art School Confidential," at the business end of a bully's fist. Picked on and misunderstood as a schoolboy, Jerome quickly grows up into Max Minghella (son of Anthony, who directed "The Talented Mr. Ripley" and "Cold Mountain"), a young man whose dark brows and big sad eyes are taken here as the signs of a delicate artistic temperament.  Jerome seeks refuge from all that is crass and phony in the suburbs at Strathmore Academy, an art school in a section of New York City so rough that the smoking laws are never enforced and a serial killer ranges freely, strangling his victims when the mood strikes or the film's rickety plot seems to require it.  Strathmore turns out to be just as crass and phony as anywhere else, only in a more specialized way. Jerome, a gifted draftsman, rooms with a queeny fashion-design major (Nick Swardson) and a boorish film student (Ethan Suplee). Mostly, though, he encounters the kind of cutthroat pretentiousness that Claire Fisher had to contend with in the later seasons of "Six Feet Under."  In his life-drawing class Jerome befriends Bardo (Joel David Moore), a super-jaded older student who identifies everyone, himself included, according to art-school stereotypes. The movie, based on a screenplay by the comic-book artist Daniel Clowes, occasionally tries to rise above such caricature. But in spite of some acute observations and a few interesting performances (most notably from John Malkovich as Jerome's drawing teacher and the ever-reliable Jim Broadbent as Strathmore's least illustrious alumnus), "Art School Confidential" is a dull and dyspeptic exercise in self-pity and hostility.  In their previous collaboration, the near-perfect "Ghost World," Mr. Clowes and Mr. Zwigoff used adolescent misanthropy as both a method of analysis and an object of satire. Enid, their heroine, was mean-spirited but also clear-sighted, and she served as a sympathetic foil for the audience and the filmmakers alike. Jerome is a murkier, mopier character, and the movie grinds its gears, much as he does, between defiant romanticism and nasty cynicism.  For his part Mr. Minghella seems to absorb his character's passivity and indecisiveness. He has a captivating pout, but not much going on behind it. Jerome's ambition to become "the greatest artist of the 21st century" is mocked, but also defended, since Jerome's sincerity is what distinguishes him from the poseurs, careerists and dilettantes who have hijacked the title artist from nobler souls like himself.  The others might say cutting things in classroom critique sessions to score easy points, but Jerome does it because he cares about aesthetics. They might lust after nude models, but Jerome is really in love with one. Her name is Audrey (she's played by the unexpressive Sophia Myles), and that she is the daughter of a famous artist doesn't hurt. Or maybe it does, since Jerome's motives turn out to be as confused as the film's.  At times it seems to be telling a familiar story of idealism and disillusionment, in which a young man's dreams of glory are dashed and his principles corrupted. But the movie also suggests that the chip on Jerome's shoulder is earned, since he is not only purer of heart than his fellow students, but also possesses more talent.  One thing we notice right away is that he can really draw, unlike the pretenders who fill fish tanks with Ping-Pong balls or scribble incoherently on paper. That Jerome's technical skill goes unrewarded is central to Mr. Clowes and Mr. Zwigoff's more or less conservative complaint against the trendiness of the art world, which in their not entirely inaccurate view trails after empty fads and mints undeserving celebrities.    Jerome's main rival is Jonah (Matt Keeslar), a handsome square (to say just how much of a square would be to give away a dumb but amusing plot twist) whose amateurish paintings inspire almost universal enthusiasm. "It's as if he's unlearned everything," gushes one admirer.  The same, unfortunately, might be said of Mr. Zwigoff, whose indifference to basic filmmaking technique seriously undermines his movie's defense of painterly skill. A movie about art does not need to be pretty, but it should at least look like something. "Ghost World" looked, appropriately enough, like a comic book, its shots static and coherent and its pacing deliberate and clear. "Art School Confidential," in contrast, is indifferent to the niceties of framing, lighting and narrative rhythm, as muddled and hectic as a student art project pulled off in a single, desperate, caffeine-fueled all-nighter.  "Art School Confidential" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language, grisly violence and drawing-class nudity.</text>
      <date>May 5, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>