<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is a thin line separating visionaries from fools, and Billy Bob Thornton walks it adroitly in “The Astronaut Farmer,” a disarmingly sincere follow-your-dreams fable from Michael and Mark Polish, twin brothers who have previously specialized in surrealist indie-whimsy. Mr. Thornton, a bit less gaunt than usual, plays Charles Farmer — even his wife calls him by his last name — who is not a farmer at all, but rather a rancher in the small town of Story, Tex. That, at any rate, is his job, but Farmer’s true calling is space travel. In the face of local skepticism and government interference, he builds a rocket in his barn and makes plans to blast into orbit.  The tone of the film (directed by Michael Polish, who wrote and produced it with his brother) is wide-eyed and unapologetically sentimental. Story is a quirky, friendly place, where Farmer’s obsession is viewed with tolerant affection that only occasionally shades into exasperation. With another actor in the title role (Kevin Costner, say, just off the top of my head) the mawkishness would be unbearable, but Mr. Thornton can be relied upon for understated dignity accompanied by an intriguing undertone of serious craziness.  Not that Farmer is nuts, exactly. The loving patriarch of a loving family, he is just unwilling to compromise an ambition that has been with him since childhood and  was derailed by sad circumstances beyond his control. His wife, Audie (Virginia Madsen, glowing in an underwritten role), sticks with him long after a more sensible, less romantic woman would have fled. The couple’s teenage son (Max Thieriot) and two young daughters (Jasper and Logan Polish) worship their dad, and Farmer receives crucial moral and logistical support from his father-in-law (Bruce Dern), a loyal ranch hand (Sal Lopez) and the town lawyer (Tim Blake Nelson).  Among the doubters and obstructionists, who express their doubts with varying degrees of condescension and hostility, are an initially sympathetic Air Force buddy (Bruce Willis) and several departments of the federal government. Farmer’s attempt to buy an enormous quantity of rocket fuel attracts the attention of the F.B.I., and his spread is soon aswarm with black SUV’s and black-suited agents. The head of the Federal Aviation Administration (J. K. Simmons) arrives in Story to hold hearings at the school gym, and the upshot is that solo space flight is strongly and officially discouraged.  As Farmer contends with the feds, the media frenzy that follows their arrival and also the bank threatening to foreclose on his ranch, the movie emits a flicker of cantankerous libertarianism. Invoking the proud history of the American space program, Farmer complains: “Somewhere along the line we stopped believing we could do anything. And if we don’t have our dreams, we have nothing.” Individual initiative, in his somewhat revisionist view, is the engine of such belief, which the government strangles by tying up dreams with rules and red tape. Those darn bureaucrats want to take away a man’s right to launch a rocket from his barn. What will they come after next?  But then again: what if everybody decided to launch his own space capsule? Needless to say, such practicalities are alien to the wide-eyed, can-do spirit of “The Astronaut Farmer.” So too is any real dramatic complication. The Polish brothers, in earlier films like “Twin Falls Idaho” and “Northfork,” have always placed wonderment above storytelling, and the availability of big stars and a reasonable special-effects budget has not entirely blunted their taste for odd, resonant images. The opening shots, of Farmer on horseback in his space suit, hint at a strangeness that the rest of the movie never quite lives up to, but it does have a visual freshness that makes the bromides and clichés palatable.  “The Astronaut Farmer” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some naughty words and a few mild double-entendres about the size of the main character’s rocket.</text>
      <date>February 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>