<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Look, up in the sky! It’s a bird! It’s a plane! It’s Amelia Earhart! No, it’s the strange, somewhat surreal Astro Boy! Faster than a speeding bullet train, more powerful than an adolescent girl or any other gaga creature that comes at him, the Japanese cartoon robot has made the leap to the big American screen, complete with a golly-gee voice (Freddie Highmore), a handful of obligatory action scenes and the usual celebrity add-ons (Bill Nighy, Nathan Lane).  Newly revived, he is again forced to wage battle against evil and, more troubling, endure some awfully cruel parenting. And so he zips and zags, keeping aloft in a movie that can’t always do the same.  Created just six years after the United States dropped the bomb on  Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Astro Boy — originally named Tetsuwan Atomu, or Mighty Atom — made his debut in a 1951 manga, taking further flight first in a live-action television show and then in a cartoon. (The Mighty Atom  was rechristened Astro Boy when the cartoon hit American TV in  the 1960s.) The character was the invention of  Osamu Tezuka,  a medical student turned manga and anime  visionary  who is widely considered the most important and influential figure in post-World War II Japanese animation. (American children who grew up watching television in the ’60s will fondly remember another of his creations, Kimba the White Lion.)  Directed by  David Bowers, making his solo debut (he was one of two directors on “Flushed Away,” from Aardman Animations), the movie serves as an introduction to Astro Boy and his origin story and, no doubt, a wished-for rebooted franchise. The story, set in an indeterminate future, opens with scenes from the life of a whiz kid, Toby (Mr. Highmore),  the son of a goateed  scientist, Dr. Tenma (Nicolas Cage). Before you know it, Toby has gone poof in an experiment gone wrong — involving blue energy, red energy, a giant robot and the insinuating voice of Donald Sutherland — leaving behind only a baseball cap and a strand of hair. Dr. Tenma subsequently pulls a Dr. Frankenstein and, voilà: Astro Boy.  When Dr. Tenma rejects the robot boy, heartache follows, along with  adventure and various high and low cultural references, some obvious (“Pinocchio”), others obscure (“Kiss Me Deadly,” another atomic-age artifact). It’s not inapt for a movie that raises the question of human consciousness to drop Descartes  into the mix — Dr. Tenma believes in the classics,  as do  Mr. Bowers and his fellow screenwriter, Timothy Hyde Harris — but it’s a little kooky in such a kiddie-centric  movie. It’s also a throwaway, as are the nods to Lenin and Trotsky that pop up when Astro Boy, after falling to Earth, as all heroes must, encounters the Robot Revolutionary Front. Moments like these seem mostly designed to flatter the grown-ups. (Didn’t work.)  Like a lot of movies, “Astro Boy” has been designed to function on different levels and serve different audiences, but in this case these multiple meanings and points of address have created a confusion of tone. The story’s undertow of darkness pulls you in one direction, while Astro Boy’s insistent cheerfulness, which seems more commercially motivated than personality-driven, pulls you somewhere else. This jaggedness extends to the visual design, which at times intriguingly recalls the flat, graphic style of the 1950s, yet also often looks thinly conceived, sketchy, even cheap. Somewhat more rounded than the original character, Astro Boy, meanwhile, now brings to mind the chubby mascot for  the restaurant chain Big Boy. Maybe the fuller figure is part of his Americanization.  “Astro Boy” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). A few of the small children in the theater in which I saw the movie occasionally screamed, but it’s unclear if they were frightened, bored or hungry.</text>
      <date>October 23, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>