<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the dreary, claustrophobic drama "Asylum," Natasha Richardson plays a married Englishwoman who falls for a loony-bin hunk. This turns out to be an unwise if moderately entertaining move. As Stella, the 1950's bored wife, inattentive mother and unhinged adulteress at the center of this story, Ms. Richardson initially affects the vacant mien of cinema's classically oppressed women. Like the lonely wives and widows of untold Hollywood melodramas, Stella is a martyr in heels and pearls. She burns from within; we, in turn, wait for her to be consumed in flames.  That wish is granted, after a fashion, in David Mackenzie's adaptation of Patrick McGrath's novel "Asylum." Much like the book, Mr. Mackenzie's film opens with Stella, her psychiatrist husband, Max (Hugh Bonneville), and 10-year-old son, Charlie (Gus Lewis), driving onto the sprawling grounds of a high-security psychiatric hospital as grim as a tomb. Tucked into a home right next to the wards, the small family soon settles into a routine. Max tends to his patients, Charlie larks about the estate, while Stella fretfully smokes one cigarette after another, further polluting the already foul air. With a housekeeper at her disposal, Stella has plenty of time to blacken her lungs, especially since she displays little interest in the usual diversions - books, music, art, other people.  Stella does tend to her garden, as might be expected from a character that originated in a novel, where such overweening symbolism often works better than it does on the screen. Mr. McGrath's morbid book has its attractions, namely a sense of dread gurgling under the controlled prose and a narrator of great and perverse unreliability. The novel's notable achievement is its juxtaposition of that dry, clinical narration with shocking, at times grotesque human behavior for which such language proves profoundly inadequate. "Asylum" is a story about mad love, but it also serves as a rather unsubtle critique of psychiatric arrogance. (Mr. McGrath's father, it seems worth mentioning, was a well-regarded superintendent at the Broadmoor Asylum, the infamous British institute for the criminally insane.)  As sometimes happens in the British countryside, Stella meets the man whose rough hands and ways will change her life, the mental patient Edgar Stark (Marton Csokas). Institutionalized for hammering his wife to a pulp, Edgar has been separated from women for years while under the supervision of one of the hospital psychiatrists, Cleave (Ian McKellen). But when Stella agrees to go cheek to cheek with Edgar at a hospital dance, where staff members and patients freely intermingle, his monkish life takes a radical turn. For her part, the girl can't help it: lost in a crowd of dowdy staff wives whose flower-print dresses make them look like chintz sofas, Stella can only stand out in her sleek black sheath. It's a look designed for seduction and, you suspect, for grief.  Soon enough there are panting trysts, principally in the dilapidated conservatory Edgar is repairing, a place meant for orchids and, as Mr. McGrath writes, "other delicate tropical plants." Stella blooms, as it were, and soon begins to look somewhat like exotic flora herself, what with all the racy lace and satin undergarments she takes to wearing. Save for the panting, an occasional teardrop and the odd scream (Stella is sleeping with a wife-killer, after all), Ms. Richardson plays her role with little affect, perhaps in deference to her character's demonstrative lingerie. As to the men: Mr. Bonneville keeps his upper lip stiff as Mr. Csokas goes for glower. Mr. McKellen, meanwhile, creeps around the edges of the story like a spider. He seems to be having fun.  Mr. Mackenzie worked similar terrain in his last film, "Young Adam," yet another blood-flecked story featuring joyless sex and all manner of lunatics, and based on a novel. Mr. McGrath's book is more complex than "Young Adam," and this may explain why "Asylum" doesn't translate as well to the screen. What makes the book shivery is not simply the dissonance between the overheated story and the cool narration, but that the psychiatrist narrator, Cleave, may be as unstable as Edgar. The screenwriters, Patrick Marber ("Closer") and Chrysanthy Balis, dispense with the shrink's narration, taking the story out of the key of madness and into the key of melodrama. What remains is a routine soap about a woman victimized by her times and her incredibly bad taste in men.  "Asylum" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film includes partial female nudity, sexual clinches and some violence.</text>
      <date>August 12, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>