<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Until it crosses a shadowy line dividing serious comedy from distasteful exploitation, “The Babysitters” has the makings of an incisive satire of greed and lust in suburbia. Katherine Waterston (a daughter of Sam) portrays Shirley Lyner, a cool-headed high school honors student and baby sitter who stumbles into an affair with her employer, Michael Beltran (a miscast John Leguizamo). A middle-aged advertising executive who feels guilty about their first stolen kiss while taking her home, Michael overtips her. When they eventually have sex, he gives her $200. This paves the way for the enterprising Shirley to enlist her best friend, Melissa (Lauren Birkell), as a “baby sitter” for  Michael’s pal Jerry (Andy Comeau). Before long Shirley is running a teenage prostitution ring and demanding 20 percent of her girls’ earnings.  Her business is threatened by Nadine (Halley Wegryn Gross), a new recruit who balks at paying Shirley a percentage and steals her clients, and by the emotional instability of Nadine’s half sister, Brenda (Louisa Krause), who begins to come apart after being given Ecstasy at a weekend orgy. As the war escalates, the director,  David Ross, loses control of his volatile material, which eventually blows up in his face.  Shirley’s instant metamorphosis from insecure high school student to ruthless madam is ludicrous in spite of the best efforts of the talented Ms. Waterston to convince you otherwise.  “The Babysitters” has the increasingly jerky momentum of a film that was butchered in the cutting room, sacrificing continuity and character development to whip the plot forward. And Cynthia Nixon is wasted in the role of Michael’s prim wife, Gail.  The plaintive story of Michael’s unhappy marriage to a once-wild woman is all but buried under the movie’s unsavory portrait of shame-faced middle-aged men drooling over under-age nubile flesh.  “The Babysitters” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for disturbing strong sexual content, language and some drug use involving teenagers.</text>
      <date>May 9, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>