<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Is there a movie role Billy Bob Thornton can't pull off? In Richard Linklater's enjoyable remake of Michael Ritchie's equally entertaining, considerably harder-edged 1976 comedy, "The Bad News Bears," Mr. Thornton  plays a womanizing drunk named Morris Buttermaker. Ornamented with tattoos and sporting a salt-and-pepper goatee, Buttermaker earns his keep by exterminating rats and other pests, a job that cramps neither his style nor his overweening self-regard. The rat catcher has a fondness for pneumatic women, but as a confirmed loner he walks and boozes alone, often while lead-footing through a Southern California wasteland in his wreck of a convertible.  Critics often complain about remakes, but Hollywood was cannibalizing its backlist before the movies started talking and the only things really bad about remakes are the same things that are bad in nonremakes: lousy filmmaking. In its basic outline, Mr. Linklater's comedy hews to the outline of the earlier film in the sense that the story still involves a broken-down former baseball player who, in exchange for an undisclosed sum, agrees to coach a pitifully inept team of young ballplayers. The kids in the new film look somewhat older than those in the original, closer to junior high than elementary school, and the girl who pitches for the team, Amanda Whurlitzer, is now played by an unknown (Sammi Kane Kraft) rather than an Academy Award winner (Tatum O'Neal).  The other obvious difference between the two films is Buttermaker, who as played by Walter Matthau was a vision of perfectly articulated decrepitude. With his banana nose, hunched shoulders and hustling ways, Matthau's Buttermaker had an unmistakably Nixonian cast, as if the disgraced president had made a wrong turn on his way home to California and accidentally landed in the San Fernando Valley instead of San Clemente. Matthau was only about five years older than Mr. Thornton when he starred in the first "Bears," but his character registers as considerably older, as if he had been neutered by disappointment, not just all that hooch. What was particularly striking about Matthau's interpretation wasn't a lack of heat, but an absence of cool. Mr. Thornton's Buttermaker is an altogether different kind of cat.  For one, this cat is actually a tomcat, a man who when he needs a business to buy the team uniforms finds his sponsors down at the local gentleman's club. (In the 1976 film, the uniforms proudly bear the legend "Chico's Bail Bonds.") If Mr. Thornton's coach has a more active sex life than Mr. Matthau's, it is partly because the two men register rather differently on screen. (It's hard to imagine Matthau married to Angelina Jolie, for one.) And, more pointedly, because the cultural climate has become paradoxically more vulgar and more censorious in the decades since the first film opened. So, while Buttermaker now squires around a woman whose eye-popping décolletage may inspire the youngest audience members to snuggle up with their mothers, the language in the original screenplay has been tamped down and sterilized.  Released three years after the wits at National Lampoon threatened to shoot a dog unless you bought the magazine and two years before "Animal House" hit the zeitgeist with yucks and mashed potatoes, the first "Bad News Bears" seemed very much a product of its anarchic times. In some ways, the irreverence of that film is best expressed by a string of epithets lodged at the team by one of the Bears themselves, Tanner, a towheaded squirt with a vocabulary as blue as that of Lenny Bruce. In the mid-1970's, when almost everyone but angry women and a few bomb-throwers seemed worn out by dissent and was rushing into narcissism, this sly sports comedy championed our cherished tradition of flipping the bird to anyone and everything, and during the bicentennial no less.  Despite the softened language, it is no surprise that Mr. Linklater took a shot at remaking a landmark comedy that hit American movie screens  the same year in which he set his own youth comedy, the autobiographical "Dazed and Confused." Working from a screenplay by the team that wrote "Bad Santa," Glenn Ficarra and John Requa, who build on Bill Lancaster's original script without either improving or gutting it, Mr. Linklater guides his story forward as smoothly as he did "School of Rock." Filled with small, cute kids and large, goofy laughs and buoyed by fine supporting work from Greg Kinnear and Marcia Gay Harden, the director's latest effort won't rock your movie world, but the fact that he manages to keep the freak flag flying in the face of our culture of triumphalism is a thing of beauty.  "Bad News Bears" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned).  It has  smoking, drinking,  semicovered breasts and some adult language.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>