<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>The Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution, which convulsed China in the late 1960's and early 70's, has earned a special place in the annals of monstrous modern ideological experiments, not only for its cruelty but also for its absurdity. That second trait figures prominently in the early scenes of "Balzac and the Little Chinese Seamstress," Dai Sijie's  tender, touching adaptation of his own novel of the same title. Ma and Luo are two young men sent to a tiny mountain village for a program of re-education that includes hauling buckets of sewage up a steep, rocky path and working long hours in a broken-down mine. On the day of their arrival, the village chief inspects their meager belongings, tossing a cookbook into the fire - "Revolutionary peasants have no use for your bourgeois reactionary chicken!" - and threatening to do the same to Ma's violin. The young man saves his instrument by playing a sonata, which Luo tells the chief is called "Mozart Is Thinking of Chairman Mao."  "Yes," the chief replies, not wanting to appear ignorant, "Mozart is always thinking of Chairman Mao." "Balzac and the Little Chinese Seamstress," which has spent several years on the festival circuit, is partly about the desire, in such repressive circumstances, to think of Mozart - and, more generally, to think and feel freely. Luo (Chen Kun) and Ma (Liu Ye) are the children of urban professionals who have been declared "enemies of the people" - Luo's father is classified as a "reactionary dentist" - and they do their best to fit in with the suspicious and illiterate peasants. Mr. Dai, who based the novel and film on his own experience during the Cultural Revolution (and who has lived in Paris since the 1980's), avoids easy stereotypes, casting an affectionate, nostalgic glow on all his characters. At the center of his story is the Little Chinese Seamstress (Zhou Xun), whose given name is never mentioned, and who lives with her grandfather, a tailor, in the next village. She is curious about the newcomers, and she develops a special bond with Luo, which is nudged in the direction of romance by their discovery of a cache of forbidden foreign books. As the film's title suggests, the Seamstress's particular favorite is Balzac - "Cousin Bette," to be precise - which awakens her imagination to a world beyond the drab routines of her immediate surroundings. Not that those surroundings are altogether bleak. Mr. Dai, returning to the scene of his own coming-of-age (as Ma does at the end of the film), captures the beauty of its steep gorges and green hillsides, as well as its remoteness. And there is very little bitterness in his reconstruction of the Cultural Revolution, but rather a sense of resilience touched with sentimentality, and a suffusing fondness for youth, beauty and literature. Like "Reading Lolita in Tehran," Azar Nafisi's best-selling memoir about literary discovery in another totalitarian revolutionary society, "Balzac and the Little Chinese Seamstress" testifies to the liberating power of books, Western novels in particular. (In addition to Balzac, the film nods appreciatively at Flaubert's "Madame Bovary" and Dumas's "Count of Monte Cristo," which is a favorite of the Seamstress's grandfather.) It associates them with love, pleasure and individuality, which are all anathema to regimes that try to impose an abstract ideal of collective human perfection on their subjects. At the end of the film, we vault into the future - or at least the more recent past of the 1990's - and find a different China, where there are satellite dishes outside peasant dwellings and where the villages are about to be displaced by the building of an enormous dam.  It is a country that allowed Mr. Dai to make "Balzac and the Little Chinese Seamstress," though not yet a country in which the film can legally be shown.</text>
      <date>July 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>