<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At once unmoored and ruthlessly calculating, the Mexican film "Battle in Heaven" has everything for everyone — or perhaps nothing at all. Among the attractions are sex, class, God, soccer, an ugly man, a beautiful woman, a dead baby, the dirt below them and the wide sky above. The film was written and directed by Carlos Reygadas, who after making a sensational feature debut four years ago with "Japón" has returned with a strangely mesmerizing and off-putting follow-up that finds him at the crossroads between inspiration and risky self-parody.  Above all else, Mr. Reygadas has a superb eye. As often as not in "Battle in Heaven" that eye is turned toward the mundane and, as during several of the film's explicit sex scenes (more on those later), the repellent; there are any number of times when it would be easier, certainly more pleasant, to look at the ceiling, the floor, anywhere but the screen. But while Mr. Reygadas is interested neither in our comfort nor easy entertainment, he clearly does not want to relinquish his hold on us. Working again with Diego Martínez Vignatti, the cinematographer for "Japón," the director doesn't just seize our attention; he commands it — forcing us into a world of terror and beauty.  There is a little of both in the film's opening image of a sweating, corpulent man being sexually serviced by a young woman in an otherwise empty room. The man, Marcos (Marcos Hernández), works in Mexico City as a chauffeur for the woman's father, a general; her name is Ana (Anapola Mushkadiz). Crowned by a tangle of dreadlocks, a ring piercing her lower lip, Ana works as a prostitute, either for kicks or because whores and whoring always interest male directors. Whatever the case, she proves generous to a fault when it comes to her body, giving herself freely, even insistently to this man without explanation or excitement. What Marcos makes of her benevolence is initially as much of a puzzle as almost everything else in the film.  In short order we also learn that Marcos's lumpier unnamed wife (Bertha Ruiz), a woman of Botero proportions if not grace, has accidentally killed an infant the couple had kidnapped for ransom. The murder is presented without evident sentiment; the wife simply says the baby let out a small scream. As he receives this grim news, standing alongside his wife in the subway passageway where they sell clocks and sweets, Marcos's face remains blank even as Mr. Reygadas's camera assumes his point of view, showing us what he sees, beginning — pointedly — with a small child. Again and again, the camera will either stand at a remove from Marcos, watching him as if he were a bug, or present the world as he sees it: as a blur, as a mystery.  Mr. Reygadas's seemingly free-floating images — the massively waving flag, the ponderously  writhing bodies and, somewhat later in the film, the pooling blood — represent not just an attempt to get inside another consciousness, but also into a collective being. Like the soldiers who raise the flag, the religious pilgrims crowding the streets and the soccer fans filling a stadium, Marcos appears simultaneously adrift and captive to rituals drained of meaning. Both a pitiful symbol of modern Mexico and a lump of very human flesh, he stares blankly at a world that offers nothing in return. That might make the film unforgivably bleak if not for the director's ability to turn moments of private, ordinary alienation — the stuff that makes us think we are terminally alone — into shared experience, into cinema.  There isn't much of a story in "Battle in Heaven," just actions, gestures, faces, bodies and snatches of dialogue, some of it banal, some of it unbelievable. The nonprofessional actors sit, stand and repose in the frame awkwardly, as if arranged like obedient children, like furniture, and recite most of the dialogue without the cascading rhythms of real speech, sometimes pausing before delivering a line. Mr. Reygadas has, rather hopefully, sought to explain this performance style by invoking Robert Bresson. The French director used nonprofessional actors, whom he called "models," to deliver nominally affectless, naturalistic performances that depend as much on our interest in other human beings as on the filmmaker's art and world view. Mr. Reygadas's admiration for Bresson is understandable if nowhere evident onscreen.  Namedropping a patron saint of the art like Bresson has its uses, though perhaps Mr. Reygadas actually believes himself so inspired. One crucial difference between the filmmakers is their commitment to their material and the world. Whatever your feelings about Bresson, whether you are pulled into his work or put off, there can be no doubt that what happens onscreen comes from an engaged, penetrating consciousness. Mr. Reygadas's commitment in "Battle in Heaven," by contrast, can feel self-interested. There is a searching quality to his camerawork, but too often he seems to be searching for a meaning (not the meaning),  almost as if he needed to justify his artistry. That helps explain why the sex in the film comes across as more exploitative than not, and also why he throws in a graphic spasm of violence.  This needless, late-act bloodletting is particularly unfortunate because it distracts us from the equally devastating violence that comes before: not only the unseen murder of an infant, but also the soul-killing emptiness of Marcos's existence. Perhaps this is where Bresson comes in. Mr. Reygadas clearly wants to say something about his country, to tap into the spiritual and material desperation of its people, but he never finds a way into Marcos that makes you feel the filmmaker's genuine interest. And he stumbles badly by thinking that a shocking murder can tell us more about how we live and die than a man and woman trying to sell cheap goods to uninterested passers-by. At its finest, "Battle in Heaven" presents life as a series of struggles — it shows us the battle is right here.</text>
      <date>February 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>