<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Battle in Seattle” is a film that leaves bruises. A visceral fictionalized account of the 1999 demonstrations in Seattle against the World Trade Organization, it repeatedly plunges you into the kicking and screaming melee of peaceful protest gone awry. Cries rend the air and bodies crumple as police batons are swung and tear-gas canisters explode. This is what happens, the movie warns, when the powers that be are unprepared for the magnitude of organized opposition and impulsively lash back. Resistance gives way to fury, and fury incites chaos.  The filmmaking debut of Stuart Townsend, an Irish actor,  “Battle in Seattle” makes no bones about where its sympathies lie. Except for the anarchistic fringe, it is wholeheartedly on the side of the demonstrators, a loose coalition of grass-roots activists from the environmental and labor movements joined by students and other groups who opposed globalization.  Some 40,000 demonstrators, far more than were expected, descended on Seattle in late November 1999, determined to shut down the first W.T.O. ministerial conference to be held on American soil. During five days of civil strife they prevented many of the trade ministers from attending the conference.  Stylistically and polemically “Battle in Seattle” is a descendant of Haskell Wexler’s much more complex 1969 movie, “Medium Cool.” Filmed on the streets in Chicago during the 1968 Democratic National Convention, “Medium Cool” mixed scenes of the violent confrontations between demonstrators and the police with the fictional story of a television cameraman. “Battle in Seattle” shoehorns in television footage of the actual protests.  But a drama is only as convincing as its characters. The people awkwardly forced together in “Battle in Seattle” are rhetorical mouthpieces tied to the sketchy plotlines of a so-so Hollywood ensemble movie. As in the much better written but equally schematic “Crash,” you can hear the machinery grind and squeak as the scales are balanced.  At the heart of the story is Dale (Woody Harrelson), a puppy-eyed policeman whose wife, Ella (Charlize Theron), works in a downtown department store and is five months pregnant. When the store closes early after its windows are smashed, Ella, struggling to get home, is caught up in the crowd and randomly struck in the stomach with a police baton. If Ms. Theron conveys almost unbearable pain in this scene, what happens to her is all we really know about her. She is a rhetorical plot device.  As the street battles intensify and Dale is denied time off, his rage and frustration drive him to pursue Jay (Martin Henderson), one of the movie’s three representative demonstrators, into a church where he beats him to a pulp. In the preposterously mawkish scene that sinks the film, he eventually calms down, locates Jay and apologizes, and they exchange words of understanding and forgiveness.  The movie tosses in a half-hearted romance between Jay and Lou (Michelle Rodriguez), a hard-shelled fellow demonstrator, who hook up after they collaborate on a daredevil mission to unfurl an anti-W.T.O. banner from a crane. Django (André Benjamin), the gentlest of the three, is a grinning, guitar-strumming ninny who marches on the street dressed as a turtle.  Other semiheroic figures include Jean Asbury (Connie Nielsen), a television news reporter who joins the demonstrators after observing the police brutality; Dr. Maric (Rade Serbedzija), a representative of Doctors Without Borders who angrily lectures the few W.T.O. ministers who show up about the organization’s preference for profits over people; and Sam (Jennifer Carpenter), a lawyer who argues for the demonstrators’ release from jail.  Trying to mediate between the parties is Mayor Jim Tobin (a miscast Ray Liotta), a fictional surrogate for Paul Schell, Seattle’s mayor at the time. A former Vietnam War protester who insists that the police act with restraint, he is pressured by the governor and the White House to take decisive action after store windows are smashed and intersections are blocked. As he summons the National Guard, declares a curfew and orders mass arrests, the internal drama behind his choices is only perfunctorily acknowledged, and a dramatic opportunity is lost.  The afterword that crawls across the screen at the end of “Battle in Seattle” declares that little has changed since 1999. When W.T.O. ministers met in Cancún, Mexico, in 2003, a heavily patrolled two-mile exclusion zone was established; so much for organized protest.  “Battle in Seattle” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has scenes of violence and strong language.</text>
      <date>September 19, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>