<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A Baxter, in the lingo of the new romantic comedy written by, directed by and starring the comedian Michael Showalter, is the safe choice, the also-ran, the guy who gets left at the altar when the hero shows up, like Dustin Hoffman in "The Graduate," to claim his true love. In "The Baxter," Mr. Showalter plays Elliot Sherman, a dull but good-hearted accountant who can't believe his luck when he manages to land a beautiful magazine editor named Caroline Swann (Elizabeth Banks). He quickly proposes marriage, but when Bradley (Justin Theroux), Caroline's annoyingly perfect ex-boyfriend, shows up by surprise at her engagement party, Elliot must watch as his best chance at happiness is stolen from under his nose. Meanwhile, Elliot's friendship with a bedraggled waif of an office temp named Cecil (Michelle Williams) is developing into a full-fledged flirtation.  The tragic flaw of "The Baxter" is that Mr. Showalter is miscast - or has miscast himself - in the title role. Though his writing is sharp and at times quite funny, and his direction at least reasonably assured, Mr. Showalter seems fundamentally uncomfortable in the role of leading man. He has the broad gestures and goofy grimaces of a sketch comic:  an awkwardness that at its best, lends the benighted Elliot a kind of poignancy and, at its worst, simply makes him seem like a visitor from another movie.  Ms. Williams, an actress with an open, childlike face that recalls the young Shirley MacLaine, is luminescent as Cecil, but the performance of the film belongs to Mr. Theroux (recently seen in a recurring role on "Six Feet Under"). Besides being wealthy, successful and handsome, Bradley can break-dance, quote Keats and weep on cue. Yet Mr. Theroux manages to calibrate the character so precisely that Bradley remains a real human being behind the smarm.  Peter Dinklage is thrown away in a minor role as a gay wedding planner, while David Wain and Michael Ian Black, Mr. Showalter's partners in the sketch comedy team Stella, appear in supporting roles as Elliot's quirky friends. In the end, "The Baxter" is a Baxter of a movie: well meaning and mildly likable, but unlikely to sweep you off your feet.  "The Baxter" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language, but no violence or sexual situations.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>