<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> As he walks - no, make that hurdles - through the electrifying French film "The Beat That My Heart Skipped," the young actor Romain Duris brings to mind another dirty-sexy guy who once vaulted through the movies with barely restrained frenzy. Mr. Duris, who wears a black leather jacket in the film, along with the ankle boots of a tango dancer or a pimp, is playing the character inhabited by Harvey Keitel nearly three decades ago in a cinematic wack job called "Fingers." Summoned as if from a fever dream by the writer and director James Toback, "Fingers" doesn't just get under your skin; it slithers.  Like that film, "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" is the story of an enforcer and would-be concert pianist that hinges on the struggle between the two sides of the male animal, the beauty and the beast. Mr. Keitel's character, Jimmy, given to wearing a black leather jacket and a white silk scarf, plays Bach in his apartment on a baby grand piano; the rest of the time he's a crude hustler of women (a Toback signature) and a reluctant fixer for his monstrous father. In Jacques Audiard's superb remake, which improves on the original significantly, investing it with aesthetic grandeur and emotional depth, Jimmy is now Thomas (Mr. Duris), a real estate entrepreneur with an unlikely dream. As in the original film, music soothes but doesn't fully tame him.  Mr. Audiard, whose films include "A Self-Made Hero" and the art-house favorite "Read My Lips," is a master of indirection. His lyrically titled new film opens with a quiet, uneasy scene that makes sense only in retrospect. Two men sit in a small, claustrophobic room, cigarette smoke curling through the soft light. One of the men is talking about his father, while the other just listens, impassive as a stone. The angry words pouring from the talker soon mellow as he reveals that his father, who once drove him crazy, had been reduced by illness, flipping the parent-child dynamic. "I nursed him like a baby," he says. The listener, whom we will shortly come to know as Thomas, our doubtful hero, barely stirs, even when asked, "Do you believe in God?"  There are all kinds of gods in "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" - old gods, dead gods, gods of power and sex and money, and the fallen god Thomas calls Father. An unshaven wreck with a body gone soft with age and fat, Robert (Niels Arestrup) has seen better if not necessarily kinder days. He trolls the murkier depths of real estate, but he's no longer on his game and leans on his son to close his dirty deals. As he sits across from Thomas in a cafe talking about his hot new girlfriend, dressed in a pale yellow suit jacket with greasy hair curling over the collar, he looks lost, condemned. The disgust in Thomas's face as he sits across from this ruined spectacle is matched only by the unmistakable love.  That's getting ahead of the story, which takes off like a shot. After that quiet, meditative prologue about fathers and sons, the film cuts to Thomas and two others, who are soon entering a derelict building under the cover of night. There, he and the other men, both dressed in suits, release bags filled with squealing rats. The rats are part of the arsenal of weapons that the three use to force poor people from valuable properties. In this dark place, where terrified immigrants scramble for their belongings, moaning and illuminated by the glare of flashlights, we are a long way from tenderness, and from discussions of faith and fealty. Thomas takes in the chaos with seeming disinterest, more like a bystander to a crime than its perpetrator.  Part psychological thriller, part love story (men and women, parents and children), "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" is also about what it takes to escape our own prisons. Written by Mr. Audiard and Tonino Benacquista, with whom he wrote "Read My Lips," the film uses its pulpy milieu as a way to sneak in a meditation on what makes us human, including the ties that choke. Soon after the rats run wild, Robert asks Thomas to help him with a debtor. Thomas secures the money, but only after Robert has been beaten and his son has exacted bloody vengeance. In the film's most chilling exchange, Robert pockets the cash and coolly says, "Not so hard, was it?" No wonder Thomas looks like a man on the run.  One of the outrageous delights of "Fingers" is its far-fetched plot, which is a shotgun marriage between a seedy crime fiction and the story of a classical musician, topped off by some 1970's sleaze. Mr. Audiard keeps Mr. Toback's improbable premise, but fills it out with scenes of Thomas struggling to perfect the Bach toccata he plans to play for an audition. Working with the talented cinematographer Stéphane Fontaine, who beautifully mixes gaudy color with the noir shadows, Mr. Audiard keeps close tabs on Thomas; there are moments when it looks as if the camera is about to jump on the character's shoulder or burrow into his ear. Getting inside Thomas's head turns out to be key because, as it happens, "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" is also an existential mystery.  In time, this restless man, whose spidery fingers and jangling legs constantly tap out separate rhythms, will find harmony. He will embark on an affair with a married woman (Aure Atika) and take lessons with a concert pianist (Linh-Dan Pham), relationships that will pull him out of his prison and just maybe deliver him. Along the way there will be violence, some ugly enough to make your heart skip, and sex that might do the same. Mostly, though, there will be beautiful images, strong emotions and the joy found watching a movie aimed straight at the heart and head. Summertime is meant to be the season of the adult moviegoer's discontent, one reason "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" is more than just a well-timed gift - it's essential viewing.</text>
      <date>July 1, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>