<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ot so much a sequel as an old-fashioned sitcom spinoff squeezed onto the big screen, "Beauty Shop" extends the popular "Barbershop" franchise to Atlanta and provides a sassy feminine counterpart to its cozy men's-club vibe. Queen Latifah, who matched wits with Ice Cube, Cedric the Entertainer and the rest of the crew in "Barbershop 2: Back in Business," returns in this film as Gina, a no-nonsense striver and devoted mother, who has left the South Side of Chicago for the real South. At first, she is working at a fancy salon owned by Jorge (Kevin Bacon, looking and sounding like a refugee from a road show production of "Hedwig and the Angry Inch"), but after a few too many arguments she decides to open her own establishment in a working-class black neighborhood. She assembles a boisterous squad of stylists, including her rebellious niece Darnelle (Keshia Knight Pulliam, who once played the cute-as-a-button Rudy Huxtable on "The Cosby Show"), as well as a token male (Bryce Wilson, who also appeared in the hair-care comedy "Hair Show") and a token white girl (Alicia Silverstone, speaking in one of the least convincing backwoods accents ever heard on screen). Cedric's role as the nutty, lovable old-timer is approximated by Alfre Woodard as Ms. Josephine, who bursts into spontaneous, pop-eyed recitations of Maya Angelou's poetry. Despite some initial setbacks, Gina's shop is soon a hub of neighborhood activity, at once upscale and down-home, where the owner's cappuccino and bottled water is complemented by fried catfish and collard greens dispensed from a cart by a scene-stealing vendor named Catfish Rita (Sheryl Underwood). The customers include local matrons (including one played by Della Reese), divaesque wives of professional athletes (including real-life diva wife Kimora Lee Simmons) and wealthy white women (Andie MacDowell, Mena Suvari) who follow Gina from Jorge's and soon discover that the warmth and high spirits make up for the lack of valet parking. And there's much more: a hunky, piano-playing electrician named Joe (Djimon Hounsou), a corrupt health inspector, and a local ragamuffin who shoots women's backsides with a video camera (thus allowing the director, Bille Woodruff, to balance the feminism of the script with a bit of discreet ogling). The plot of "Beauty Shop" is a loose, rambling affair, and not really the point of the movie. Gina is too hard-working and self-assured to be held back, and in any case, too much intrigue and worry would take precious time away from the relaxed, funny banter that is the movie's main reason for being. Another, of course, is money. The makers of the first "Barbershop" understood that a feel-good tale of small-scale urban capitalism could return revenues in the tens of millions, and in retrospect it is no surprise that that film's combination of hip-hop authenticity, relatively clean humor and commonsense conservatism found such a wide and diverse audience. "Beauty Shop," anchored in Queen Latifah's charisma, may be the biggest hit yet, coming as it does when PG-13 comedies with African-American stars are dominating the box office. The success of these pictures - "Are We There Yet?," "Hitch," "Guess Who," "Diary of a Mad Black Woman" - can no longer be described by the tired pop-cultural term crossover. This is what the mainstream looks like now. "Beauty Shop" is rated PG-13. It has some sexual humor and innuendo.</text>
      <date>March 30, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>