<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Jacques Nolot’s film “Before I Forget” begins with the image of a blank screen with a small dot at the center that slowly expands into a round black hole, a stark image of the void that looms more prominently as we age.  But for Pierre (Mr. Nolot), the film’s 60-year-old protagonist, who lives alone in a modest Paris apartment, the near future is more ominous than for most. Pierre, H.I.V. positive for 24 years, has been advised to take a more aggressive drug cocktail than the medication that has sustained him. He is reluctant because of its toxic side effects, including hair loss. His body may be dilapidated, but his face is still handsome in a hawklike way, and crowned by an elegant gray mane.  With its shots of Pierre, naked,  in the throes of simulated sex, “Before I Forget” is an unblinking portrait of a complicated, solitary gay man who has outlived his working years. A male escort who for decades was kept by a lion of French society 15 years his senior who has just died, Pierre is reduced to paying rent boys for sex, an activity he pursues assiduously even though he doesn’t appear to enjoy it very much.  Sex for pay has been the theme of his life since his late teens, and now the roles are reversed; it is his turn to purchase the kind of ritualized domination found in Jean Genet novels. You sense that he seeks to be punished by versions of his younger self. It doesn’t seem to have occurred to Pierre that there is any other kind of erotic transaction worth pursuing.  “Before I Forget” is the third semi-autobiographical film in a trilogy by Mr. Nolot, a French actor, writer and director closely associated with André Téchiné. This movie follows Pierre around Paris as he visits acquaintances in his circle of johns and hustlers, has sessions with an obtuse psychiatrist and remembers how the family of his longtime sugar daddy closed ranks and shut Pierre out of his inheritance.  It forces us to glean what biographical information we can from details mentioned in conversation. If the closeted way of life the movie describes seems quaint in the age of gay liberation, the human nature it portrays has no shelf life. When you reach a certain age, it emphasizes, money becomes paramount.  Although Pierre, who is writing a memoir, declares more than once that he has contemplated suicide, he doesn’t seem especially unhappy. Even on the erotic front hope springs eternal. He and his friend Georges (Jean Pommier), a married, closeted lawyer, cheerfully compare the costs of hustlers. When the talk isn’t about the price of flesh, it is gossip about estates, how to protect undeclared income, smuggle money across borders and finagle financial security. Because of his bravado and power games with his older lover, we discover, Pierre lost out on his inheritance.  Mr. Nolot’s fictionalized self-portrait is proudly self-lacerating. While Pierre maintains an attitude of haughty independence, Mr. Nolot goes out of his way to puncture any illusions he may have of being desirable to the boys he covets. As the camera studies Pierre from a distance in his dimly lighted apartment and slowly surveys the possessions on his shelves, you sense a man who has accepted the choices he has made.  The picture of Pierre as a tough old bird is reinforced when Marc (Bastien d’Asnières), his regular rent boy, insists on dressing him in drag and taking him to the Pigalle district. He initially refuses. He would have to shave off his mustache, he protests. But he changes his mind.  Outfitted as a female streetwalker, a whole new personality emerges. With his sharp features, vigilant, birdlike gaze, his feet planted in a doorway, the drag version of Pierre is a hardened whore decades past her prime but still defiantly pounding the pavement.</text>
      <date>July 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>