<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Although four stories, three fictional and one real, are folded together in Eric Khoo’s elliptical film “Be With Me,” the tale that gives this delicate, melancholic movie its backbone is the true one of its courageous central character, Theresa Chan. A deaf and blind Singaporean woman in her early 60’s who plays herself in the movie, Ms. Chan is an indomitable life force and charismatic screen presence. Even after she concludes her account of transcending the “silent, dark prison” of her disabilities with the help of gifted teachers, you are left wondering how she did it.  Remarkably self-sufficient, Ms. Chan is shown carefully washing her own dishes at home and teaching pottery to children at a school for the blind in Singapore. Although she can’t hear, she occasionally speaks intelligible sentences in a rough, loud voice.  Her few spoken words notwithstanding, “Be With Me” is a largely silent movie built around a contradiction: it’s a film about communication whose spare dialogue  is scattered among four languages (English, Cantonese, Hokkien and Mandarin), five if you count Braille. More information is conveyed  through reading and physical touch than through speech.  “Be With Me” looks askance at cyber styles of instant communication, with abbreviated words and phrases, in which a relationship can be erased by pressing “delete.” Images of Singapore’s sleek, modern skyline crowded with anonymous, nearly identical towers accentuate the movie’s view of urban life today as a chilly, impersonal wasteland.  The film begins with words pecked out on an old manual typewriter: “Is true love truly there, my love? Yes, if your warm heart is.” The fingers typing them belong to Ms. Chan, who applies the question to the movie’s fictional stories, each of which involves a different generation. One follows the puppyish fling of two teenage girls who meet by computer; another contemplates the plight of a lonely, overweight security guard who silently pines for a yuppie woman who works in his office building.  In the saddest and deepest, an aged shopkeeper (Chiew Sung Ching) cooks meals for his ailing wife and takes them to her in the hospital. When she eventually dies, he still feels her presence in the shop as he silently goes about his daily life, crumpled in grief. His discovers his will to continue after reading Ms. Chan’s autobiography, and through his son (Lawrence Yong), a social worker, sends her his delicious home cooking. She relays a message back that she loves his food.  These three fictional tales are seemingly unrelated until they intersect haphazardly at the end of the movie. Once the young lovers Jackie (Ezann Lee) and Sam (Samantha Tan) connect online, they enjoy a frisky idyll until Sam meets a boy she likes and abruptly cuts off Jackie, who is plunged into a suicidal despair. Meanwhile, Fatty Koh (Seet Keng-yew), the security guard, who is middle-aged, painfully shy and lives at home with his disapproving parents, is fired after falling asleep on the job. He discreetly stalks the young woman who works in his building,  even after he’s fired, and spends much of the movie composing a love letter.  Ms. Chan’s infinitely harder struggle could have been used to throw a harsher light on the younger characters and their unhappiness. But this gentle film examines them with a detachment that is not unsympathetic.  After going deaf at 14, Ms. Chan soon went blind and sank into despair that lasted until the revelatory moment when she realized that “it didn’t matter as long as I was alive.” Helped by two dedicated teachers, she studied in the United States, even learned English (she spoke only Cantonese) and became the strong, unsentimental, amazingly independent woman we see on screen.  The fact that her story of triumph over unimaginable odds doesn’t come freighted with mystical and religious bromides makes it all the more inspiring.</text>
      <date>September 29, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>