<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ook at me -  I'm just dull," Peter Rooker (Marcus Thomas) tells his sister at the beginning of this self-conscious comic drama. And he is. He has a boring art-department job at some unspecified company, and his girlfriend has just left him. His life is bleak, as Al Corley, a first-time film director, heavy-handedly demonstrates by showing Peter cooking for himself and watching television in the dark. But Peter is going to be saved. On his way to the office, he sees a casting notice for a community-theater production of "Cyrano." Although he has no acting experience, he auditions. He is very, very bad, and "Bigger Than the Sky" establishes its low credibility by having the play's director, Edwina Winters (Clare Higgins), so taken with his supposed realness that she casts him. In the title role. This is idiotic because she has talented, experienced company regulars like Michael Degan (the talented, experienced John Corbett) available. But Peter accepts the role and soon has a life that revolves around evening rehearsals and late-night drinking with his new friends. He is attracted to his co-star, Grace Hargrove (Amy Smart), who is playing Roxanne, but Grace and Michael have something going on, which complicates matters. Peter also meets the company's beloved former director, Kippy Newberg (the excellent Allan Corduner), whose counsel is to "play true to the end." "Cyrano" takes over Peter's life, and he finds himself arriving late for work and falling asleep at meetings. In a rash moment, he quits his job, only to drop by the theater and discover Edwina secretly working with another actor, the egotistical Ken Zorbell (Sean Astin), because she has lost faith in Peter. Mr. Astin is playing against "Lord of the Rings" type (he was the lovable, loyal Sam) and participating in a bit of stunt casting. Patty Duke, his mother, plays a dowdy theater-company employee and that woman's identical twin, a chain-smoking wardrobe mistress. Yes, Patty Duke as twins. The surprising thing about "Bigger Than the Sky" is its touching ending. A colleague has died, and the company gathers to honor him in an inventive, life-affirming way. Finally it becomes clear that Mr. Corley's film is meant to be a tribute to the love of theater. It has just been posing as the story of one man's finding himself. "Bigger Than the Sky" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has profanity and discreet sexual situations.</text>
      <date>February 18, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>