<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Like its predecessor, the Sundance hype-magnet “Hustle &amp; Flow,” Craig Brewer’s new film, “Black Snake Moan,” comes cloaked in lurid, pulpy atmospherics. His characters — pimps, prostitutes, nymphomaniacs — seem to have crawled off the drugstore paperback racks of the 1950s or the grind house lobby posters of a slightly later era. His stories are slick with the grease of old-style exploitation, promising the sleazy, easy pleasures of lust, wrath and other deadly sins.  Don’t be fooled though. Underneath the surface of racial and sexual button pushing, behind the brandished guns and bared breasts, is a heart of pure, buttery cornpone. Like “Hustle &amp; Flow,” “Black Snake Moan” joins a dubious stereotype of black manhood to an uplifting, sentimental fable. In the earlier movie the hero was a soulful pimp with dreams of hip-hop glory.  This time he is a retired blues singer with woman  troubles and a vegetable farm. Really, though, the character, played with his usual fearsome wit by Samuel L. Jackson, is a tried-and-true Hollywood stock figure: the selfless, spiritually minded African-American who seems to have been put on the earth to help white people work out their self-esteem issues. No doubt “Black Snake Moan” is a provocative title, but a more accurate one might be “Chaining Miss Daisy to the Radiator in Her Underwear.”  About that chain. You may have seen it, clutched in Mr. Jackson’s fists and looped around Christina Ricci’s bare midriff, in advertisements for this movie. A white woman, a black man and a chain: it’s hard to think of an image more likely to inflame the demons of the American id. But this is not a movie about sexual bondage or payback for slavery — not exactly, anyway. It’s overtly and insistently about recovery and healing, the slaying of personal demons by any means necessary.  Mr. Jackson is Lazarus, whose wife, apparently bored by his upright ways, has run off with his brother. Ms. Ricci plays Rae, a troubled young woman well known around their small Tennessee town for her sexual availability. When her boyfriend, Ronnie (the increasingly credible Justin Timberlake), leaves for the Army, Rae falls into a bad old pattern. She suffers from “spells” of erotic craving that begin with twitching, coughing and fever and compel her to jump on anything with a Y chromosome and a pulse.  One morning Lazarus finds her, badly beaten and barely clothed, at the side of the road near his house. He takes her home, washes her wounds and fetches her some medicine. (Only later will it occur to him to fetch her something to wear besides the white underpants and chopped-off T-shirt the camera prefers to see her in.) When she tries to jump on him, he grabs his Bible and flees into the yard, leaving the Good Book open to the verse (missing in my copy) about chains and radiators as instruments of righteousness.  Whatever works. To their great credit, Mr. Jackson and Ms. Ricci understand that the relationship between Lazarus and his prisoner has its comic side, and some of their scenes together — as when he takes her for a walk in his garden, using the chain as a leash, or when she is reeled in across the porch like an angry wide-mouthed bass — play out like kinky screwball. Whether Mr. Brewer is in on the joke is less clear. In an early review in Film Comment that is at least as entertaining as “Black Snake Moan” itself, Nathan Lee has proclaimed Mr. Brewer a “visionary.” From where I sit, the vision looks pretty blurry, as the movie struggles to square its inherent absurdity with its earnest sense of conviction.  Ms. Ricci, feral and saucer-eyed, throws herself into a role that is ultimately as threadbare as her T-shirt. Mr. Jackson, rarely bothered by characters that make no sense — he was the star of both John Singleton’s “Shaft” remake and “Snakes on a Plane” after all — redeems Lazarus with his wily professionalism, much as Terrence Howard redeemed DJay in “Hustle &amp; Flow.” Mr. Jackson also benefits from the presence of capable character actors like S. Epatha Merkerson, as the pharmacist who is Lazarus’s grown-up, fully dressed love interest, and John Cothran, as his friend the preacher.  For all its willful, shaking-and-shouting intensity, “Black Snake Moan” never lives up to its soundtrack, which is as saturated with the blues as “Hustle &amp; Flow” was with the crunk sounds of Southern hip-hop. The songs from the Fat Possum Records catalog that play under much of the action, and two short archival clips of the great Son House explicating the place of sexual jealousy in his music, contain more pain, humor and wisdom than the entirety of Mr. Brewer’s overloaded, overheated script. As a writer he combines a reasonably good ear for Southern idioms with a weakness for prosy exposition. In spite of Amelia Vincent’s toothsome cinematography and the down-home locations, the movie often has the lumbering, literal-minded rhythms of a second-rate stage play — not a moan or a howl, but a slow, anxious groan.  “Black Snake Moan” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Half-naked nymphomaniac chained to radiator.</text>
      <date>March 2, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>