<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Will Ferrell is a ferocious marshmallow. In his dumb but endearing sports comedies, the spirit may be willing, but the flesh is flabby. As he ricochets from triumph to humiliation and back, he suggests an armchair George Plimpton whose characters, driven by an outlandish grandiosity, are deeply reassuring. For the sake of his career, Mr. Ferrell should never join a gym; buffed up, he would cease being one of us.  In “Blades of Glory” his character  — Chazz Michael Michaels, a preening rock ’n’ roll-style figure skater, hard drinker and self-proclaimed sex addict — is quintessential Ferrell: a macho caricature with a gooey sweet filling that leaks through the cracks of his heavy-metal armor. As he lurches and lunges through a routine to the roar of the Billy Squier anthem “The Stroke,” Chazz is almost fearsome. But by the end of this fast, light, frequently funny comedy, your instinct is to pet his mullet and go “Awwww.”  Mr. Ferrell and Jon Heder (of “Napoleon Dynamite”) play rival skaters who were banned from the ice following a public brawl; Mr. Heder’s character, Jimmy MacElroy, is the whiny, arrogant adopted child of a billionaire (William Fichtner) who abandons him on a roadside after his ouster from the sport. After spending three years in exile, Chazz and Jimmy re-enter figure skating the only way the rules allow: as a team.  As these mismatched egomaniacs develop a fraternal bond, their chemistry jells, and Mr. Ferrell and Mr. Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. Jimmy, with his fleecy platinum hair and downy cheeks,  is a brat itching for a comeuppance, and Mr. Heder’s Bugs Bunny teeth and myopic gaze complete the picture of the sports prodigy as idiotic, self-centered robot. The character seems only a hair’s-breadth away from Napoleon Dynamite.  It comes as a huge relief to find that as “Blades of Glory” speeds along, it avoids going to the obvious, ugly place for cheap laughs. The notion of a male figure-skating team in which one member is a chest-beating, fire-breathing Lothario and the other a persnickety, virginal girly-man cries out for the kind of easy,  gay-baiting jokes that mars comedies like “Wild Hogs.”  It’s not that “Blades of Glory” is entirely unaware of its largely untapped subtext. In Sarah Kawahara’s amusing ice skating choreography, sliding scissor kicks land faces in crotches, and groins grind into groins. But the humor lies more in the ooh-that-must-hurt category than in any suggestion that such collisions might be sexy.  The movie’s satirical take on competitive figure skating, from its music for gliding pas des deux (Andrea Bocelli) to the goofy absurdity of children’s ice shows in which Chazz, exiled from competition, is forced to work, to its tacky space-age costumes, is affectionately knowing.  When Chazz and Jimmy make their comeback, they are pitted against a ruthless European brother-sister team with an incestuous bond, the Van Waldenbergs (Will Arnett and Amy Poehler), who blackmail their meek sister (Jenna Fischer) into using her charms to break up the American partners. This is one of several subplots shoehorned into the movie for strictly mechanical reasons.  The Van Waldenbergs have a potentially great comic moment near the end of the movie that is all but thrown away. In their breathtakingly tasteless routine at the movie’s version of the Winter Olympics, they impersonate John F. Kennedy and Marilyn Monroe as lovers on ice. Alas, all the movie gives us is about 30 seconds of what might have been a classic, “Borat”-worthy sketch.  More successful are a drawn-out stumbling chase on skates through the streets of Montreal, and Chazz and Jimmy’s decision to execute an extremely dangerous (and funny)  maneuver developed in North Korea.  Despite its missed opportunities, “Blades of Glory” introduces some fresh talent into the Hollywood comedy pool. Its directors, Will Speck and Josh Gordon, come from advertising, having created those ubiquitous television commercials for Geico insurance. However tired of the Geico caveman you may be, you must admit that the campaign, when new, had a rare spark of wit. “Blades of Glory” has enough vestiges of that kind of creative cheek to keep you contentedly in your seat.  “Blades of Glory” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has off-color sexual humor and some strong language. </text>
      <date>March 30, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>