<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Julie Gavras’s wonderful film, “Blame It on Fidel,” is a deeply political movie that sidesteps strident polemics by viewing the ideological conflicts within a French-Spanish family through the eyes of a smart, willful child. As the daily life of 9-year-old Anna (Nina Kervel) is drastically revised after her parents, Fernando and Marie de la Mesa, suddenly become radicals, she resists change with the ferocious determination of a youngster who is told that she must part with her favorite toys.  The movie, adapted from a novel by the Italian writer Domitilla Calamai and set in France, begins in 1970 and spans Anna’s school year, then leaps to 1973. It perfectly recreates the excitement of a time when many in the bourgeoisie forsook comfortable lives to dive headlong into radical activism. In the case of the de la Mesas, that commitment entails adopting a much sparer lifestyle, closer to that of their political cohort.  Anna’s father (Stefano Accorsi), a lawyer from an upper-class Spanish family, devotes his professional skills to serving a group of scruffy  left-wing Chilean exiles as they campaign (in absentia) for the election of Salvador Allende as Chile’s president. Marie (Julie Depardieu, daughter of Gérard), a French magazine writer turned devout feminist, works in a family-planning clinic, demonstrates for abortion rights and publishes a book of interviews.  “Blame It on Fidel” is not the pie-in-the-sky paean to its do-gooders that you might expect from the daughter of the left-wing filmmaker Costa-Gavras (it is her first feature film; she has made documentaries), and the de la Mesas don’t metamorphose into a harmonious  Radical Supercouple.  The strains on the couple’s marriage culminate with a brutal domestic battle in which Marie’s feminism clashes with her husband’s unwitting male supremacism, and everything the couple believe is called into question.  Each minute fluctuation in the household’s political weather registers poignantly on Anna’s visage as she tries to grasp events she barely comprehends. Ms. Kervel, her grave, intelligent features scrunched into a worried frown throughout much of the movie, is a marvel. By any measure it is a great performance by a child actor; the movie belongs to Ms. Kervel.  It is a tumultuous year. Among other events, Charles de Gaulle, the hero of Anna’s grandparents, dies; Mr. Allende is elected Chile’s president; and 300 prominent Frenchwomen risk prosecution by signing a petition declaring that they have had abortions.  Though sympathetic to Fernando and Marie’s sudden left turn, the movie is equally sympathetic to Anna, who, with her younger brother, François (Benjamin Feuillet), is dragged along on her parents’ political odyssey. Anna finds herself unceremoniously pulled out of her divinity class at her Roman Catholic girls’ school. Her father informs her that Mickey Mouse is a fascist. When her best friend, Cécile, visits the de la Mesas’ shabby new home, Cécile loathes their simple peasant food and is horrified at Fernando’s casual nudity in front of his children.  The de la Mesas’ political shift is not impetuous. For years Fernando has lived uneasily with the knowledge of his family’s close relationship with the Franco regime. His decision is prompted by an anguished visit from his sister Marga after Marga’s husband, a Communist and the black sheep of the family, is arrested for anti-Franco activities. Leaving Anna with her maternal grandparents in Bordeaux, Fernando and Marie travel to Chile and return charged with radical fervor.  Anna is baffled by these political and cultural crosscurrents. Her beloved nanny, Filomena (Marie-Noëlle Bordeaux), a Cuban exile who lost everything in  Castro’s revolution, regales Anna with her hatred of Communists. After Filomena is dismissed, Anna’s new Greek nanny and then another nanny, from Vietnam, bombard her with creation myths that clash with her strict Roman Catholic education.  In the movie’s tensest scene, Anna’s parents take her to a demonstration that is broken up by riot police tossing smoke bombs. When panic erupts, you fear that the befuddled girl, who barely comes up to her parents’ waists, will be trampled or lost in the melee.  Over time Anna absorbs whatever information makes sense to her. (Because he’s younger, her brother adapts to the changes much more readily.) When a Chilean exile peels an orange and patiently explains to Anna that some people want the fruit all to themselves, while others believe in sharing it, and then hands her a section, she has a glimpse of insight.  Meanwhile, her doting conservative grandparents hold their tongues when she visits them. “Blame It on Fidel” offers convincing, kindhearted portraits of loving relatives on opposing sides of the political spectrum acting responsibly for the sake of a child.</text>
      <date>August 3, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>