<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Bolt” tells the story of a pampered celebrity — a television action star — who is cast out of his cocoon of fame and privilege and forced to deal with the challenges of the real world. The digitally animated real world, that is, in which the hero, a talking dog voiced by the real-life movie star John Travolta, encounters wise-guy pigeons, a cynical cat (Susie Essman) and a worshipful, geeky hamster named Rhino (Mark Walton).  Since puppyhood, Bolt, in the series that shares his name and the movie’s, has played a genetically altered, fearless supercanine who every week must rescue his owner, a girl named Penny (Miley Cyrus of “Hannah Montana” fame), from the clutches of a dastardly villain (Malcolm McDowell).  Bolt’s performance is effortlessly authentic because he is entirely unaware that it is a performance. Somewhat like Jim Carrey’s Truman in “The Truman Show,” Bolt accepts the reality of his Jerry Bruckheimer-like habitat of chases, explosions and special effects because he has never known anything else. Once outside, he is perplexed to discover that he is, after all, an ordinary dog.  With brisk wit and impressive visual brio, “Bolt,” directed by Byron Howard and Chris Williams from a script by Mr. Williams and Dan Fogelman, explores an existential predicament that it also shares. It is at once a knowing, satirical sendup of the Hollywood fame-and-fantasy machinery and a sleek, expensive product of the Disney-Pixar industrial complex.  While artisanal Pixar touches abound in the exquisitely detailed animation, the story shows some signs of repurposing and committee work. Bolt’s situation is a bit like Buzz Lightyear’s in “Toy Story” — he must learn that what he thinks of as his true identity is an artifact of make-believe — and a lot like Lightning McQueen’s in “Cars.” His circular journey of exile and return, during which he acquires a new self that is a better version of the old one, resembles those of Nemo, Wall-E and quite a few of the Disney princess heroines of old. And, as is Disney custom, Bolt is accompanied, and often upstaged, by a goofy chatterbox sidekick, the ridiculous Rhino, who rarely leaves his plexiglass exercise sphere.  But if “Bolt” — originally conceived by the old regime at the Disney animation studios and refurbished after John Lasseter of Pixar took over — does not quite rise to the level of bona fide Pixar masterpieces like “Wall-E,” “Finding Nemo” and “Ratatouille,” it does manage to be frisky, funny and inventive enough to engage the attention of grown-ups as well as children. Perhaps some of the show-biz jokes will sail over the heads of very young viewers, who won’t understand why Penny’s unctuous agent keeps talking about sticking pins in things (I’m not sure I did), or what that mean lady from the network is so angry about.  But then, such knowing insidery humor is hardly limited to self-conscious HBO shows like “Entourage” or “Curb Your Enthusiasm.” Kids’ stuff like “Hannah Montana” and “iCarly” plays the same trompe l’oeil tricks in a more wholesome context, feeding young viewers the illusion that they can see through the clouds of hype and cynicism that make up more and more of the cultural air they breathe.  What keeps “Bolt” fresh is an unaffected exuberance, a genuine sense of fun, that is expressed above all through obsessive attention to craft. The movie has three sets of talking pigeons, each group embodying a regional stereotype, and while I found the dese-dem-dose New York birds amusing, and their aspiring-screenwriter Los Angeles counterparts downright hilarious, it was the uncanny bobbing and twisting movements of the birds’ heads and the shuffle of their little pigeon feet that raised the conceit from clever to sublime.  Similarly, Bolt is a cute enough little fellow with a winning personality and a nice voice, but his physical gestures and facial expressions turn him into a memorable, irresistible character. The 3-D version of the movie, which will be shown in some theaters, is less devoted to the kind of big effects that throw you back in your seat than to a more thorough and understated expansion of cinematic possibilities.  “Bolt,” in other words, is a real movie — not a great one, perhaps, but a more organic and thought-out piece of work than the usual animated hodgepodge that lures antsy children and their dutiful parents into the multiplexes. It has its sentimental strains, but it doesn’t push them too hard, or resort to the crude, pandering humor of, say, the “Shrek” franchise. Like its hero after he wakes up from his Hollywood dream life, it’s friendly, smart and eager to please. Cat people need not worry — hamster fans will be in heaven, but that’s another story — since there is enough sly, predatory feline humor to keep the thing from going entirely to the dogs.  “Bolt” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). Some of the early action sequences, and a climactic scene of danger, may be too intense for small children.</text>
      <date>November 21, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>