<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The synopsis of “Bonneville” makes it sound like “Thelma and Louise” in first gear: A recent widow named Arvilla Holden (Jessica Lange) and her two best friends, Carol and Margene (Joan Allen and Kathy Bates), hit the road in Idaho in a 1966 Pontiac convertible to deliver an urn full of ashes to a funeral in Santa Barbara, Calif., bickering, bonding and facing hard truths along the way.  The 50-something leads and meandering pace distinguish “Bonneville” from other movies of its type. But the film’s most striking characteristic comes to the fore when the women pick up a hunky young hitchhiker named Bo (Victor Rasuk).  Not only is there no furtive hookup, we sense that none of the travelers would seriously consider having one. When the women sit in a diner watching the shirtless hitchhiker wash their car in the parking lot, they’re just window-shopping. We learn the source of their restraint when Bo and the ladies part ways, and Carol offers him a parting gift: her copy of the Book of Mormon.  As it happens, Carol, Margene, Arvilla and many other major characters are devout members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The film’s screenwriter, Daniel D. Davis, and its director, Christopher N. Rowley, treat their characters’ faith as a given — as merely one characteristic among many. It’s the Mormon flip side of a typical Hollywood movie set in a world in which no one ever mentions God, prays or enters a house of worship. The movie’s no-fuss treatment of religion is as deft as it is unexpected.  Good thing too, because the film has many tiresome elements — starting with Arvilla’s brittle antagonist, Francine (Christine Baranski), her dead husband Joe’s daughter by his first wife. Because Joe never amended his will, Francine, who always disliked her stepmother, is set to inherit the couple’s longtime home. She gives Arvilla an ultimatum: Deliver Joe’s ashes to Santa Barbara for burial next to his first wife, or pack and get out. Despite Ms. Baranski’s sharp performance and a few last-minute nuances, Francine remains a resentful killjoy.  Except for Ms. Lange’s silent, expressive close-ups, which render flashbacks unnecessary, the women’s journey is aesthetically and dramatically unremarkable. The three pass through spectacular terrain, cross paths with a charming trucker named Emmett (the silver fox Tom Skerritt) who joins them for dinner in Las Vegas, and visit a casino floor, where Carol obliviously chats with a young female slot-machine player waiting on a client who pays by the hour.  Yet the film’s worldview lends charm, even excitement, to moments that would seem dull or awkward in a Hollywood road movie. When Margene says she and Emmett went dancing, Ms. Bates’s incredulous, delighted tone makes the act sound as reckless as a one-night stand. When Carol offers Bo her Book of Mormon, he politely declines because it’s clearly a keepsake, and because he already has two.  “Bonneville” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested) for  mild language and innuendo.</text>
      <date>February 29, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>