<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> To describe “The Boss of It All,” Lars von Trier’s acidic corporate comedy, as “ ‘The Office’ Viewed Through the Looking Glass” only scratches the surface of the newest film from one of the foremost tricksters of world cinema. At the outset Mr. von Trier, shown standing behind a window, disingenuously announces that the movie is “a comedy and harmless as such: no preaching or swaying of opinion.”  Strictly speaking, that may be true, although throughout the movie you sense a diabolical aesthetic anarchist scheming to upend your expectations.  Unlike his recent pseudo-epics,  “Dogville” and “Manderlay,” “The Boss of It All” is not a nose-thumbing critique of American history filtered through a left-wing European perspective by this Danish director and writer. Mr. von Trier’s first film in Danish since “The Idiots,” it is a small, inexpensive movie without marquee names. Its politics, such as they are, remain safely across the Atlantic and have to do with the supposed antipathy between sentimental Danes and chilly Icelanders.  As this layered satire of power and the relationships of bosses and employees, directors and actors unfolds, Mr. von Trier pops up two more times to assert his supremacy as the movie’s Brechtian puppetmaster. Although the characters wonder out loud about the identity of “the boss of all bosses” of a company that is on the verge of being sold, the honcho in chief is really Mr. von Trier gleefully pulling the strings of a story whose tone he manipulates at his whim.  The movie is organized around a structural joke. It uses a new camera technique called Automavision, whose purpose is to limit human control over cinematography. Shots that begin from a fixed camera position are randomly tilted, angled and zoomed by a computer. A character may suddenly disappear from the frame. The technique is a metaphor for the movie’s vision of a corporate culture running amok in its own insane rules.  But the implications are double-edged, for in human terms there is no boss; technology rules. The screenplay is clotted with jargon that makes little sense, and there is no attempt to explain it or to describe what the company produces,  beyond the clear suggestion that it is a high-tech outfit.  The games begin with the hiring of Kristoffer (Jens Albinus), a sour, unemployed actor, by the company’s director, Ravn (Peter Gantzler). Kristoffer’s job is to impersonate Svend, the company’s top executive, who supposedly runs its day-to-day operations from the United States and communicates only via e-mail.  This nonexistent boss was invented by Ravn to deflect  the heat from disgruntled employees onto someone else. But since the company’s prospective buyer, Finnur (Thor Fridriksson), a hard-nosed Icelandic mogul, insists that Svend appear in person to sign the papers, someone has to play the role.  Kristoffer is a funny caricature of the kind of humorless actor, steeped in theory, who takes his job much too seriously. A slavish devotee of a fictional Italian playwright and madman named Gambini, he sinks into his task with an alarming intensity, trying out various line readings. Initially unaware that he been thrown into a rats’ nest, he treats his encounters with the six senior employees under Ravn as improvisations.  Ravn has told him nothing about the six, who lent him the money to establish the company, and whom Ravn plans to fire without giving them their fair share of profits, once the papers are signed. Lise (Iben Hjejle), an employee who was led to believe that Svend was gay, immediately recognizes the lie  and pressures Kristoffer into having sex on a desk.  Kristoffer discovers that Ravn has represented Svend differently to each of the six, and “The Boss of it All” turns into a deadpan farce of misunderstandings and embarrassments, as several refer to inappropriately intimate communications from Svend about which Kristoffer knows nothing. The story takes another mean twist when Finnur’s lawyer shows up and turns out to be Kristoffer’s scornful ex-wife, Kisser (Sofie Grabol).  Like all of Mr. von Trier’s films, “The Boss of It All” is a cold, misanthropic work that places no faith in institutions and in humanity itself. But it’s also very funny. Those at the top of the corporate pecking order, like Ravn and Finnur, are liars and manipulators. Below them are self-important fools, the blind leading the blind, playing walk-on parts that they delude themselves into believing are starring roles. </text>
      <date>May 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>