<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Bottle Shock,” an easygoing little movie, made with more affection than skill, takes us back to the days when men wore loud plaid suits and people who were serious about wine sneered at the very mention of California. Sticking reasonably close to the historical record, the director, Randall Miller (who wrote the screenplay with his wife, Jody Savin, and Ross Schwartz), reconstructs a watershed moment in the wine world’s acceptance of the Golden State and, eventually, of many other non-French viticultural regions.  In 1976, at a gathering near Paris, a panel of experts conducted a blind tasting at which two California wines emerged victorious over their more pedigreed French competitors. That tasting provides the climax to “Bottle Shock,” and even if the potential surprise of its outcome were not already spoiled by history, the movie’s adherence to the clichés of the triumph-of-the-underdog narrative would be enough to remove any doubt.  There are, indeed, at least two underdogs hungering for triumph. The first is Steven Spurrier, played by Alan Rickman, whose parched low voice and air of beleaguered pomposity are never unwelcome. Spurrier is a British wine dealer vainly seeking a way into the French oenological establishment. Well-trained and sensitive as his nose may be, it’s  always pressed against the glass.  The blind tasting is a stunt he cooks up with his friend Maurice (Dennis Farina), an  expatriate from Milwaukee, whose rough manner and garish clothes belie a sophisticated palate.  At Maurice’s urging, Spurrier makes his way to Napa, where Jim Barrett (Bill Pullman), a lapsed lawyer from San Francisco, fondles grapes, quotes Hemingway and tries to transform his life of bourgeois normalcy into a  Steinbeck novel. A perfectionist and something of a blowhard, Jim takes to the boxing ring to settle arguments with his long-haired son, Bo (Chris Pine).  Bo, along with his pal Gustavo (Freddy Rodriguez), who is one of Jim’s employees, and Sam (Rachael Taylor), a head-turning new intern at the vineyard, represents a new generation of irreverent countercultural wine connoisseur.  Which is cool, but “Bottle Shock” spends too much time cruising the sun-dappled California hills, tripping over potentially engaging dramatic possibilities and leaving them in the dust. An incipient love triangle involving Bo, Gustavo and Sam does not generate much intensity, though we do learn that Gustavo is a winemaker of such skill that one sip of his best red will inspire a woman to jump into bed with him. (Bo, in contrast, must fall back on his raffish surfer charm.) Gustavo’s tense relationship with Jim raises a hint of class resentment and ethnic prejudice, but this theme is no more  persuasively developed than the Oedipal conflict between Jim and Bo.  The filmmakers struggle to shoehorn a fascinating story about wine into some kind of screen genre or another. But “Bottle Shock” is unable to figure out what kind of movie it wants to be, and flops around between madcap comedy and rousing drama. To borrow a wine-snob term of art, it lacks structure. Or, to push the idiom a little further, it’s a little too sweet, with some pleasantly nutty notes and a baloney finish.  “Bottle Shock” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some swearing and sexual situations, and a lot of alcohol consumption.</text>
      <date>August 6, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>