<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The wanton slaughter of mothers, a fixture of Hollywood drama for some time now, is given an international spin in “The Boys Are Back,” which takes place in an Australia of golden meadows and endless beaches. The star is Clive Owen, raffish and charming as ever but with his sex-symbol magnetism toned down in keeping with the melancholy subject. The film, directed by Scott Hicks (“Shine”) from a script by the television writer Allan Cubitt, has a burnished, high-quality look and a heart swollen with maudlin self-regard.  Mr. Owen plays Joe Warr, a British transplant who has become one of the top sportswriters in his adopted homeland. Joe moved to Australia, we discover in due course, to be with his second wife, Katy (Laura Fraser), an equestrienne he impregnated while she was at a match in England and he was married to someone else. Each union produced a son, and when Katy dies of cancer both boys — cute little Artie (Nicholas McAnulty) and anxious teenage Harry (George MacKay) — end up living with Joe in his rambling house in the countryside.  “The Boys Are Back” was adapted from a memoir of the same name by Simon Carr, a funny and affecting book that the filmmakers have somehow contrived to turn into a dreary and unconvincing dead-mama melodrama. Katy, glimpsed alive in a few early scenes that establish the mutual adoration between her and Joe, returns in apparitional form later to give her husband encouragement and advice.  Nobody else — certainly no other woman — is qualified to do so. As Artie and Harry settle in with Joe, whose child-rearing style is permissive to the point of anarchy, a curious mood of juvenile, treehouse misogyny settles over the film. Joe is happy to do things like speed across the sand behind the wheel of his Land Rover with Artie perched on the hood or let the boy cannonball into a shallow hotel bathtub,  and anyone who raises an eyebrow is marked as a controlling, compulsive stick-in-the-mud.  This includes, from the start, Katy’s mother, Barbara (Julia Blake), whose disapproval of Joe is as emphatic as the grim lines around her mouth. Laura (Emma Booth), the mother of a schoolmate of Artie’s, at first seems more sympathetic to this handsome, sad dad, and maybe even willing to sleep with him. But Laura too proves wanting when she fails to embrace Joe’s “just say yes” parental philosophy and also to meet his every household and child-care need. As for the first wife back in England (Natasha Little), her coldness is shown to be far worse for Harry than her ex-husband’s wanton irresponsibility is.  Not that I want to be hard on the guy. The problem is that the movie always takes the easy way, scattering a few heavy, confrontational scenes among acres of picturesque montages. The central dramatic crisis, which involves Joe’s leaving the boys alone in the house, with predictably disastrous results, is painfully unconvincing. The repercussions and resolutions that follow are laughably unconvincing.  And “The Boys Are Back,” which seems at times to want to acknowledge the challenges of raising children, shrinks away from anything too wrenching or difficult. Joe’s house — he and the boys call it “hog heaven” — may be a mess, but the movie is as tidy as can be, with not an unwashed, unkempt hair out of place.  “The Boys Are Back” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some rough language and intense moments.</text>
      <date>September 25, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>