<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The adage that history repeats itself first as tragedy, then as farce is charmingly illustrated by Neil Jordan's picaresque fairy tale, "Breakfast on Pluto." Superficially, the movie might be described as "The Crying Game" redux, in which the director revisits his 1992 political thriller with its gender-bending twist. This time, he reimagines its themes as a sprawling comic epic: "Candide" meets "Tom Jones" in drag heaven.  Once again, the Irish troubles rumble through the film, which is set mostly in the 1960's and 70's. But the violence is filtered through the hearts-and-flowers consciousness of a sweet, feminine boy, Patrick Braden (Cillian Murphy), a foundling who grows up to be a transvestite. Even when he is wrongly arrested and interrogated after a bombing in a London disco, his picture splashed across the front pages under the headline "Transvestite Terrorist," current events barely make a dent in his rose-colored vision of life.  "Breakfast on Pluto" is the second collaboration, following "The Butcher Boy," between Mr. Jordan and Patrick McCabe, who co-wrote this screen adaptation of his novel with the director. It has a similar zany, lurching momentum and vitality.  Throughout the film, Patrick, who prefers to be called Kitten, dismisses all politics as "serious, serious, serious." Or as an Oscar Wilde quotation used late in the movie puts it: "I love talking about nothing. It's the only thing I know anything about."  This is a movie in which the gossip exchanged by a pair of chirping robins is subtitled. Characters argue about the lyrics of the pop novelty "(How Much Is That) Doggie in the Window?" (Is the tail "waggedy" or "waggly"?) The name and image of Mitzi Gaynor loom large. The vintage pop that forms a running commentary on events leans toward sticky sentimentality and includes "Love Is a Many-Splendored Thing" (sung by Jerry Vale), Morris Albert's "Feelings" and, most prominently, Bobby Goldsboro's treacly 1968 hit "Honey," which is Patrick's personal theme song.  This sweetness works in a delightfully subversive way. After a while "serious, serious, serious" becomes synonymous with silly, silly, silly. The violence and oppression through which Patrick passes, oblivious to danger and humiliation, seem like so much ridiculous macho bluster. But the movie's seductive frivolity also has a negative effect. Events, including the disco bombing, a cold-blooded execution and the tragic death of a childhood friend, meant to jolt us into reality, resonate less than they might. It's so much more pleasurable to huddle with Patrick inside his dream world.  With his wide blue eyes and curly hair, Mr. Murphy's Patrick (the actor was most recently seen as the villain in "Red Eye") is an androgynous beauty - poignant, trusting and gently flirtatious, but never predatory. In a year overcrowded with wonderful performances by lead actors, Mr. Murphy's immensely appealing turn ranks among the strongest.  Early in the film, we learn in a farcical fantasy sequence that Father Bernard (Liam Neeson), the parish priest in the Irish village where Patrick grows up, is his biological father. Nine months after the priest's frisky tussle with the housekeeper, a baby is deposited on the doorstep of the parish rectory. From the beginning, Patrick knows who he is and has no inclination to cover it up. The tough, crude pub owner in whose house he grows up, like the priests in his Catholic school, is scandalized by his refusal to act stereotypically male.  His three best childhood friends include a girl named Charlie and two boys, Irwin and Laurence, who has Down syndrome. Over the years their lives intersect.  Patrick begins his odyssey as a teenager when he is rescued from bullies by a gang of dope-smoking druid mystics who whisk him away to safety and tantalize him with a vision of astral highways leading to "breakfast on Pluto." His wanderlust sparked, Patrick tours with a glam-rock band in which he performs dressed as an Indian maiden  . To the consternation of the rest of the band, Billy (Gavin Friday), its lead singer, carries on a romance with Patrick, whom he installs in a run-down trailer in the countryside. Under its floorboards Patrick discovers a cache of I.R.A. weapons, which he blithely disposes of, with disastrous consequences.  Patrick eventually heads to London to search for his mother, whom he calls the Phantom Lady. He finds work dressing up as a Womble at a children's theme park and teams up with Bertie (Stephen Rea), a magician, who saws him in half and uses him in a hypnotism act. Although these episodes unfold as fanciful adventures in a storybook, they are fraught with peril.  Patrick's capacity for denial is stretched to the limit during his brutal interrogation after the bombing. Urged to make a statement, he spins out a fantasy of himself as a femme fatale, clad in shiny black leather, wielding a bottle of Chanel No. 5 as his weapon of choice in a game of espionage. Released after six days of questioning, he begs in vain to remain in the safety of his prison cell.  The mixture of merriment and grotesquerie goes on, reconnections to the past are made, violence flares and ebbs, and the story eventually trails off into a semi-happy ending. Patrick sails through it all, unbowed and unsullied, true to his friends but most of all to himself.  "Breakfast on Pluto" proposes a kind of radical disengagement from the mad, mad world: a fiercely willed, stubbornly held innocence that in the end stands as its own reward.  "Breakfast on Pluto" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has violence and some strong language.</text>
      <date>November 16, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>