<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> What do men want? This reversal of Freud’s famous question drives John Krasinski’s screen adaptation of David Foster Wallace’s 1999 short-story collection “Brief Interviews With Hideous Men” into a blind alley. Compacted into an 80-minute mishmash of interviews, confessions and sketches, melded into a shaky mosaic, the answers from a cross section of men are shallow, self-serving and ultimately unenlightening.  “Brief Interviews” may be verbally dexterous and enthusiastically acted by the likes of Timothy Hutton, Christopher Meloni, Denis O’Hare, Ben Shenkman, Michael Cerveris and Bobby Cannavale. But its composite portrait of the male psyche in the post-feminist era is repellent. Beyond the characters’ desire to know what women want and how to use it to their advantage, there is no unifying motif connecting the fragments.  In the minds of the smug few who imagine they have the answers to Freud’s original question, what women want is to be controlled by men who assume they have mastered the mechanics of seduction and sexual technique. The other subjects who have no such illusions are self-absorbed, deluded combatants adrift on the sexual battlefield.  “Brief Interviews” is the directorial debut of Mr. Krasinski, who plays Jim Halpert in the American version of “The Office,” and who also appears in the film as Ryan, the ex-boyfriend of a female interviewer. Anonymous in Wallace’s book, the interviewer has a name, Sara Quinn (Julianne Nicholson), in the film. An  attractive doctoral candidate in anthropology at an East Coast university, she has been recently dumped by Ryan, and her project is partly a quest to understand what happened.  Many of the interviewees are assigned numbers and sit at a desk in front of a white concrete wall with a pitcher of water and a cassette recorder nearby and respond to questions that have been asked before the camera rolls. Sara remains off screen during the sessions but appears in scenes set at gatherings on and off campus, where she hovers, an unseen observer of male behavior. Even in a confrontation with Ryan near the end of the film, she barely speaks, as he rationalizes his fling with a hippie mystic.  The movie begins on a glaringly heavy-handed note with a subject (Mr. Shenkman) who describes his self-destructive compulsion to shout, “Victory for  the forces of democratic freedom!” at the top of his lungs during orgasm.  There follows a succession of cads and losers of various stripes. A swaggering stud (Mr. Cannavale), who is missing most of his right arm, crows about how he uses his “asset” to seduce women by making them weep with sympathy. In the most incendiary confrontation Daniel (Dominic Cooper), an angry student of Sara’s, furiously argues that abuse and rape can be good for a woman, because they “enlarge” her experience of the world.  The film’s one eloquent moment is the only monologue not devoted to sexual game playing. A middle-aged black man (Frankie R. Faison), standing in the men’s room in the lobby of the luxury hotel where his father (Malcolm Goodwin) worked for decades as an attendant, imagines his father’s humiliating daily routine. If anyone in the film could be called a hero, it is this attendant, who silently appears as his son reminisces with a mixture of shame and grudging admiration.  Privy to the unsanitary bathroom habits and miserly tipping practices of countless wealthy businessmen for whom he provided soap and towels, this humble, uncomplaining man, immaculately dressed in white, and all but invisible to the world, is the film’s ultimate witness to men’s grubby little secrets.</text>
      <date>September 25, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>