<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The low-key comedy “Broken English,” about a romance-scarred professional woman named Nora Wilder (Parker Posey) who invigorates her life with help from a handsome, sensitive, fedora-clad Frenchman (Melvil Poupaud), is a textbook example of an Indiewood film: a Hollywood fantasy wrapped in plain brown paper.  Its contradictory  message is something like: “Listen up, 30-something single women; there is no Prince Charming. Oh, wait a minute ... Yes, there is!”  Written and directed by the first-time feature filmmaker Zoe Cassavetes, daughter of the pioneering independent director John Cassavetes, “Broken English” seems blithely unaware of the bait-and-switch that it will ultimately pull. In its first half-hour, while it charts Nora’s repetitious life as a hip hotel’s guest relations manager and establishes her serial disappointment in love, it promises a bracing response to Hollywood falseness: a comedy about a woman who realizes that she’s unhappy because what she thought were high standards were actually items on a romantic and sexual shopping list absorbed from a bankrupt popular culture.  The right age? Check. Interesting job? Check. Looks like a catalog model? Check. What are you doing Friday?  As played by Ms. Posey, who tamps down the vivacious kookiness that has made her an independent-film darling, Nora is the sort of cute mope that might appear in a screenplay emblazoned with Kate Winslet’s coffee stains.  Her online search for a single man in her age bracket yields no results. She agrees to go on a date set up by her grandchild-obsessed mother (played by Gena Rowlands, John Cassavetes’s widow and frequent leading lady and Ms. Cassavetes’s mom), but finds that her prospective suitor (Josh Hamilton, in a note-perfect cameo) is still smitten with his ex-girlfriend.  And a marriage that she has always viewed as ideal — between her best friend, Audrey (Drea de Matteo), and Audrey’s director husband, Mark (Tim Guinee) — is collapsing, thanks to Mark’s fixation on a prospective leading lady who embodies his own romantic fantasies.  The film’s smartest sequence finds Nora flouting her hotel’s no-fraternization policy to go out with a V.I.P. guest, a rising movie star named Nick Gable (Justin Theroux, in the movie’s most complex and surprising performance).  Nick, a man-child with a mohawk that appears to be woven from Sasquatch fur, presents himself as a truth-seeking artist who craves a simple life with a woman who’s not in show business. We quickly deduce a truth that Nora wills herself not to see: Nick is a pure narcissist who sees his date with Nora as an acting challenge — an audition for a one-night stand.  These early, squirm-inducing scenes portend a film that will refute Hollywood romantic comedy’s wish-fulfillment tendencies with a rude dose of reality. Then the hunky, puppy dog Frenchman shows up, and the film’s daring impulses exit stage left.  Mr. Poupaud’s Julien is like a dreamboat from HBO’s “Sex and the City” without the inevitable neurotic downsides. Aside from a brief, awkward conversation in which Julien declares skepticism about monogamy and then reverses himself, his only apparent flaw is that he’s going back to Paris soon — which means, of course, that Nora will have to quit her job and go to Paris to find Julien, and herself.  This is a studio executive’s idea of risk taking, in the same questionable spirit as the 1987 hit “Baby Boom,” in which Diane Keaton played a career woman who inherited an infant and gave up her corporate job in exchange for a thriving small business, a gigantic country house and the love of Sam Shepard.  “Broken English” is a well-acted, smartly directed film that’s depressing because it could have amounted to so much more. It departs from the studio-financed romantic-comedy template in just one, unfortunately fatal respect: it makes a point of pride out of rejecting cliché, then swoons into its embrace.  “Broken English” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for some sexual content, brief drug use and language.</text>
      <date>June 22, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>