<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Brooklyn Lobster," Kevin Jordan's small family drama, set in Sheepshead Bay, is an unusually pure example of American kitchen-sink realism. With an astutely chosen ensemble led by Danny Aiello and Jane Curtin, it has integrity up to its eyeballs. But integrity and accuracy of detail are not synonymous with clarity or dramatic weight. Mr. Jordan, who wrote, directed and produced this semiautobiographical film, is so close to his material that he often gets lost in it.  As it explores the problems besetting Frank Giorgio (Mr. Aiello), a gruff, stubborn bull of a man who runs a small lobster pound founded by his father in 1938, the movie sometimes plays like a tedious case history adapted from a business-school textbook. Too often, family relationships take a back seat to financial entanglements.  Frank faces putting his beloved shop up for auction because the loan he took out to add a restaurant to his operation has been called. He has adhered to a court order to advertise the future sale, but he has bent the rules by placing inconspicuous announcements in out-of-the-way places. His defensive strategy does not go unnoticed, and when confronted in court, he responds with hostility.  Frank also has domestic problems. Maureen (Ms. Curtin), his tart-tongued, eagle-eyed wife of three decades, has walked out on him, citing poor communication. As she puts it, "There's not much to say about crustaceans."  In the two weeks spanned by the movie, the Giorgio clan has gathered for the Christmas holidays. Frank's son, Michael (Daniel Sauli), who has inherited his father's hotheaded temperament, has returned from Seattle (where he is struggling for a foothold in the dot-com world), accompanied by his girlfriend, Kerry (Heather Burns), whom he wants to marry. While he shares the same pull-out couch with his father, Kerry stays in a seedy Russian motel near Brighton Beach. Maureen, meanwhile, imposes on her daughter, Lauren (Marisa Ryan), and son-in-law, Justin (Ian Kahn), who have a new baby.  "Brooklyn Lobster" is an elegy for a kind of working-class self-determination that the movie portrays as threatened by big business. A proposal that Frank sell out to a fast-food franchise is made and rejected out of hand. The movie is also a muted celebration of family ties. The Giorgios' relationships may be strained at the seams, but the closely knit clan is not about to come apart.</text>
      <date>November 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>