<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A maximalist who loves cramming the screen with noise and raucous nonsense, Terry Gilliam has a history of navigating past treacherous obstacles, including those of his own design. When his films work, these excesses have a liberating, exhilarating effect, allowing you to hitch a ride on the director's ingenious flights of fancy. But Mr. Gilliam's strengths as a filmmaker - an out-of-bounds visual imagination, a tendency to spiral wildly off topic, a fractious wit - can also be his gravest liabilities. Almost invariably there comes the moment in his films when it feels as if you have entered one of those bewildering junk shops stuffed to the rafters with mildew and treasure.  That moment stretches into a seeming eternity in Mr. Gilliam's latest big-screen effort, "The Brothers Grimm," a film that has little to do with the actual folklorists. As played by Matt Damon and Heath Ledger, these brothers are con men who, during the early 19th century, troll French-controlled Germanic towns preying on the superstitions of their inhabitants. Kitted out in period garb and dubious British accents, the actors throw themselves into this flimsy contrivance with energy, but are badly served by a director focused on flipping switches and twirling knobs. Despite a few early sparks of promise (an antiwitch potion made with "baby tears"), "The Brothers Grimm" sputters and coughs along like an unoiled machine, grinding gears and nerves in equal measure.  The story, which is credited solely to Ehren Kruger ("The Skeleton Key"), tracks the brothers as, at the behest of a French general (Jonathan Pryce), they try to solve a series of small-town kidnappings. Mr. Gilliam has indicated that he was unhappy with the original script, which he unfavorably likened to "The Mummy." Although he has said he reworked the script with his sometime collaborator Tony Grisoni, they do not have screenwriting credit. Mr. Gilliam and Mr. Grisoni nonetheless decided to assert their contribution by calling themselves "Dress Pattern Makers," a designation that, if you are still awake when the film ends, you can catch in the closing credits.  Mr. Damon and Mr. Ledger shout their lines and run circles around each other as they try to advance the plot. Like Colin Farrell in "Alexander," Mr. Damon is also forced to struggle with a most disenchanting handicap, namely a hairdo (or wig) that in combination with his sideburns and frock coat make him look ready for a Paul Revere and the Raiders tribute band. The director, meanwhile, ignores the forest while he tends to his magical trees, which look about as scary as breadsticks compared with the pugnacious perennials in "The Wizard of Oz." Mr. Gilliam seems familiar with fairy tales (as the resident villain, Monica Bellucci asks who's the fairest one of all), but expresses no interest in their possibilities. Here, there is absolutely nothing - not dread, not desire, not mystery - under the little red hood.  But as usual in Mr. Gilliam's films, there are lavishly tricked out sets, detailed costumes and props, a darkly ironic if unsteady tone and hiccups of strained surrealism. In classic Gilliam fashion, the brothers are alternately besieged and bewildered by strange forces and creatures, and actively engaged in the imaginative creation of other worlds. Mr. Gilliam's characters often struggle to break on through to the other side, but here that struggle is also assumed - and lost - by the filmmaker himself. Despite his kinks and flourishes, he never manages to stitch together the kidnapping subplot with all his dumb sight gags (a skinned rabbit, an errant hairpiece), cartoon performances and an unfortunate, pop-psychological explanation for the brothers' interest in the uses and abuses of enchantment.  In interviews about "The Brothers Grimm," Mr. Gilliam has scattered a tantalizing trail of bread crumbs that lead from the film - his first to be released in theaters in seven years following the underrated "Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas" - directly to Miramax, the company that took over the production. It is perhaps fitting given this new film's subject that in his version of what happened once upon a production time, Mr. Gilliam bears a striking resemblance to Hansel and Gretel, those two Grimm innocents who, after being forced into the wilderness, hungrily gnaw on a house of bread and sugar only to be almost eaten by the conniving witch inside. Like Hansel and Gretel, however, Mr. Gilliam knows a little something about survival.  Among the most tantalizing crumbs strewn by Mr. Gilliam: Miramax fired his original cinematographer, did not allow him to hire his choice for a lead actress (he wanted Samantha Morton, but ended up with Lena Headey) and put a kibosh on a prosthetic nose for Mr. Damon. The nose, Mr. Gilliam says, made the actor look like a "young Brando." That must have been some nose. After filming was completed, Mr. Gilliam took a six-month break and shot another movie, "Tideland," before returning to the earlier film. He now claims to be satisfied with "The Brothers Grimm," which may be true or may be one of those classic Hollywood fairy tales in which everyone lives happily ever after - at least until the lawyers say otherwise.  "The Brothers Grimm" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has scenes of staged animal cruelty, gun and blade violence and the usual hobgoblin boos.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>