<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There are a couple of ways to read the title of Steven Soderbergh's latest and willfully perverse excursion into experimentation, "Bubble." Set in a small Ohio town, the rigorously minimalist story involves three factory workers whose placid existence is shattered after two in the little group become romantically linked, leading to an act of cataclysmic violence. Murder liberates the three from the bubble of their everyday existence, much as creative experimentation has periodically liberated Mr. Soderbergh from the prison of commercial mainstream filmmaking.  The restlessly imaginative Mr. Soderbergh, whose Hollywood credentials include an Academy Award for "Traffic" and a handful of box-office hits, has never been a director to settle into a groove. Since making his feature debut in 1989 with "Sex, Lies and Videotape," he has ranged across genres and media, pursuing different visual and narrative idioms. He has purposely strayed off the mainstream with films like the critically maligned "Full Frontal," dipped into television (the undervalued "K Street") and found popular success with studio baubles like "Ocean's Eleven." Although "Bubble" has generated sizable notice for its unusual release — it opens in 32 theaters today and plays on the cable network HDNet Movies tonight, hitting DVD next week — in many respects it is just par for the Steven Soderbergh course.  This filmmaker has said that the genesis for "Bubble" was his curiosity about whether he could hack factory work, which may have been inspired by his experiences inside the studio machine. Whatever the case, "Bubble" is nothing if not independent from that machinery, having been bankrolled by HDNet Films, one of the companies owned by Mark Cuban and Todd Wagner. (The two also own some of the theaters, as well as the cable network, that will show the movie.) Written by Coleman Hough, who also wrote "Full Frontal," the script weds Mr. Soderbergh's germ of an idea about routinized labor both to some melodramatic contrivances (a triangle leads to jealousy leads to murder) and to the real-life experiences of its nonprofessional cast,  who all live either near or in Belpre, Ohio, where "Bubble" was shot.  The bare-bones story tracks what happens when a young single mother, Rose (Misty Dawn Wilkins), is hired at a doll factory, where she quickly intrudes on the friendship between Martha (Debbie Doebereiner)  and Martha's self-declared best friend, the much younger Kyle (Dustin James Ashley). The movie — which was shot using the same type of digital camera used for  the  "Star Wars" franchise — unfolds as a series of loosely strung-together episodes that have the flavor of real life, seen through a glass darkly. The mood is muted, almost depressed, and the naturalistic dialogue is as spare as the acoustic guitar fragments, composed by Robert Pollard in the melancholic key of Nick Drake, that bridge the narrative bits and pieces. Nothing much happens until, as is always the case in movies, something most definitely does.  Easier to admire than love, "Bubble" is a fascinating exercise that seems calculated to repel most audiences, which probably suits Mr. Soderbergh just fine. As he has with  many of his films, he shot the movie himself, working under his usual alias, Peter Andrews. Eschewing the loose shooting style he's favored in recent years, he presents this world as a series of exquisitely framed images, almost as if it were a series of tableaux vivants. The ordinariness of the faces inside those frames suggests that Mr. Soderbergh had been riffling through the collected works of photographers as varied as William Eggleston and Nan Goldin, both portraitists of everyday pain, while the milieu and dead-eye gaze show the influence of early Fassbinder. The results are beautiful and bleak.  When "Bubble" played at the New York Film Festival last year, it made an interesting contrast with "L'Enfant," the latest from the brothers Jean-Pierre and Luc Dardenne, the Belgian directors whose earlier films include "La Promesse." The Dardennes live in the area where they shoot their rigorously naturalistic fictions, which all  involve working-class or outsider characters engaged in furious life struggles. But whereas these films feel as if they were made from inside the worlds in which they are set, "Bubble" feels as if it were made from the outside looking in. Mr. Soderbergh is not a naturally warm director, and while that doesn't usually hurt his work, here his native chilliness makes it seem as if he were doing lab work rather than taking the measure of his fellow man.  Again, I'm not sure that Mr. Soderbergh would necessarily mind that take. And, indeed, "Bubble" is a test case of a kind, the first of six digital features that he will make for HDNet Films. These features will all be, like this one, site specific, shot outside major metropolitan areas using nonprofessional casts for what the director called, in an interview last September, "a sort of oblique angle on what it's like to be in America." The politics of that oblique angle come across as both overtly obvious and almost too subdued to bother mentioning. With its somnolent, alienated characters, its violence and a despairing late-act acknowledgment of guilt ("Oh, my God"), "Bubble" can easily be seen as a metaphor for a country that has been forcibly released from its own protective shell. Or not.  If Mr. Soderbergh was interested in floating such a critique, you wouldn't know it from the DVD for "Bubble." Among the disappointing extras included with it is an on-camera interview with the director that is almost entirely devoid of interest, along with an unfortunate faux-documentary in which Ms. Hough, the screenwriter, tries to make casual with the principal cast and comes across like a visiting dignitary. Also on tap are the original interviews with the lead actors by the casting director Carmen Cuba and, best of all, a brilliant trailer for the movie. Consisting solely of still images of doll parts in various states of assembly and decay, without a single human face or whiff of story, it distills the movie's creepy vibe in perfect miniature. The trailer ends with the words "Another Steven Soderbergh Experience," which really says it all.  "Bubble" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has some crude language and some oblique violence.</text>
      <date>January 27, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>