<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is a burning trailer in “The Burning Plain” and also a crashing plane. As literal-minded as much of the movie is, we can safely assume that the title is metaphorical. Important symbols are scattered through this film, which opens in theaters nationwide on Friday after spending about a month as a video-on-demand insomnia cure. Sometimes birds take wing and soar through the sky, though they can also be killed by slingshot and roasted on a makeshift grill. There are physical scars that characters display (or inflict on themselves) to make manifest the pain within.  A tidy little term paper could be written about the motifs in “The Burning Plain” and about the way they wind through a multistranded, chronologically fractured story of loss, guilt, betrayal and general moroseness. Actually, the assignment has already been completed, in the form of Guillermo Arriaga’s screenplay. Like his scripts for “21 Grams” and “Babel,” this one makes heavy use of happenstance and temporal displacement, and like them, too, it depends on ideas about human behavior that can only be called preposterous.  But those movies, which were directed by Alejandro González Iñárritu, balanced their silly conceits with some seriously good acting. (Mr. Arriaga’s best script, “The Three Burials of Melquiades Estrada,” was directed by Tommy Lee Jones, who also starred.) In this case, with Mr. Arriaga in the director’s chair for the first time, the acting is merely serious.  The action swings back and forth in time and place, gathering apparently disconnected scenes into a big, doughy ball of significance. In  Oregon, an unhappy restaurant hostess named Sylvia (Charlize Theron) smokes cigarettes and stares at the waves crashing against the rocks before heading indoors either for a shift of work or a bout of sad, empty sex. An unshaven, nervous-looking fellow (José María Yazpik) seems to be stalking her. Who is he? And who, for that matter, is she?  Meanwhile — also? elsewhere? because? who knows! — a blond woman (Kim Basinger) is having an affair. Before her transgression, or rather as a consequence of it (though in Mr. Arriaga’s world causes usually follow consequences, rather than the reverse),  the trailer where she and her lover (Joaquim de Almeida) have  their trysts goes up in flames, killing both of them. One of his sons (J. D. Pardo, who will grow up into Danny Pino) and one of her daughters (Jennifer Lawrence, who will grow up into Ms. Theron) make eyes at each other, and pretty soon they’re dating. By which I mean killing birds with slingshots and taking turns burning significant scars into arms. In due course, they have a baby.  Have I given too much away? Did you want to know about the plane crash? Eventually, all the mysteries are solved, which is not to say that the movie ever comes close to making sense. It looks terrific, thanks to Robert Elswit’s cinematography, which captures the dust of New Mexico and the damp of Oregon. But the elliptical structure of the narrative can’t cover up its  overheated, half-baked banality.  “The Burning Plain” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sex, nudity and violence.</text>
      <date>September 18, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>