<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Michael Haneke's "Caché (Hidden)" begins, as many films do, with an exterior establishing shot. We are looking down a narrow Paris street at a nondescript house, fairly certain that cinematic convention will soon invite us inside. But there is something odd about this ordinary, even banal, image. The camera, perfectly still, lingers for an unusually long time, and we begin to suspect we may not be alone. Someone is watching with us, and perhaps even watching us as we watch. It turns out that this is not only the opening shot in a movie, but also part of a surveillance video.  Thus, before we even know what is happening, Mr. Haneke, one of the most exquisitely sadistic European filmmakers working today, has deposited his audience at the Hitchcockian junction where voyeurism intersects with paranoia. We are at once innocent and complicit, as if the idle curiosity that brings us into the theater authorized a malignant form of spying. The residents of the house, Georges and Anne Laurent, who have received the video in a bag left on their doorstep, certainly feel violated and intruded upon. Why would anyone do such a thing? What have they - Georges and Anne, a perfectly respectable upper-middle-class professional couple - done to deserve this?  The question turns out not to be rhetorical. The tape is followed by others, and by violent drawings made all the more disconcerting by their childishness. Variations on that enigmatic, implacable opening shot pop up again and again, intensifying the ambience of suspicion and multiplying the film's ironies and implications. Georges (Daniel Auteuil) is the host of a highly rated literary talk show on public television (this is France, remember), and is therefore used to the camera's scrutiny. Anne (Juliette Binoche), who works in publishing, finds her husband's response to their invisible stalker annoyingly secretive and mistrustful. Their relationship starts to crack and buckle, even as they try to maintain an illusion of blithe bourgeois normalcy for their friends and their 12-year-old son, Pierrot (Lester Makedonsky).  As it happens, their domestic drama has large implications. The film's title gestures at realities that are pushed out of sight so that normal life can take its uneventful course. Normal life, that is, as it is lived by affluent, bien-pensant Western folk like the Laurents. Mr. Haneke, an Austrian who works mainly in France (and who makes excellent use of that country's rich deposit of acting talent), has established his reputation by shaming - and shocking - the consciences of sophisticated continental audiences. A mainstay of the Cannes Film Festival, where "Caché" made its debut last spring, he has acquired considerable cultural prestige as a result of rubbing the smug faces of his characters (and, implicitly, his public) in the depravity, violence and sheer moral ugliness that lurks beneath their comfort and complacency.  There is something schematic about his moralizing, but also something undeniably arresting. Tempting as it is to dismiss "Caché" as a liberal guilt trip in the guise of a thriller, it is at the same time hard to deny its creepy, insinuating power. Nor is it possible to tune out its accusatory message. Civilization and barbarism are not antithetical, Mr. Haneke insists, but adjacent, perhaps even identical. He has said as much before - in "Funny Games,"  "Code Inconnu,"  "The Piano Teacher" and "The Time of the Wolf" - but never with such visual polish or rhetorical refinement. There is one shockingly violent scene in "Caché," and another of wrenching emotional brutality, but for the most part the movie works by restraint and indirection rather than by assaultive confrontation.  "Caché" can be interpreted both as a response to the Sept. 11 attacks and, in retrospect, as a prophecy of the riots that convulsed France's impoverished suburbs this fall. What is hidden, above all, from the Laurents and their ilk are the social grievances directed against them. The drawings and videotapes are a form of psychological terrorism, the roots of which lie in Georges's provincial childhood and in the events of Oct. 17, 1961, when as many as 200 Algerian protesters died at the hands of the Paris police, then commanded by the former Nazi collaborator Maurice Papon.  Is Georges and Anne's tormentor seeking revenge or recognition? The drawings trigger dreams and half-suppressed memories, and the videotapes lead Georges to the bedside of his mother (Annie Girardot) and to a shabby apartment inhabited by a man named Majid (Maurice Bénichou), the son of Algerians who worked on Georges's parents' farm. Confronted by this soft-spoken living ghost of his childhood - who denies any knowledge of the videos or the drawings - Georges insists that his conscience is clear, even as his defensive, threatening tone contradicts him.  At times "Caché" resonates, none too subtly, with the oft-repeated post-9/11 question: Why do they hate us? Because we don't hate ourselves sufficiently, Mr. Haneke responds, doing his bit to make up the shortfall. But while this film can seem politically simplistic, it is nonetheless psychologically astute, and more complicated than it at first appears. Mr. Auteuil and Ms. Binoche are too sensitive and agile to be ideological marionettes, and in spite of his finger-pointing it is not really Mr. Haneke's intention to reduce Anne and Georges to stereotypes. While the obvious movement of the film is centrifugal, drawing back from the cocoon of the Laurent household into a world of political violence and social misery, it also pulls in the opposite direction, propelled inward by the mysterious gravity of individual motives and feelings. The initial shot of the movie is answered by the last, which demands close attention and contains the intriguing suggestion that the real story has been hidden all along - that it has been driven not by the noisy public conflict between Arabs and Frenchmen, but rather by the quiet, perpetual war between fathers and sons.  "Caché (Hidden)" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Its single short scene of violence is among the most upsetting in a movie this year.</text>
      <date>December 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>