<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It’s hard to think of a constituency that won’t be offended by the Belgian horror film “Calvaire” (“The Ordeal”). Hard-core horror fans will likely be put off by its arty aspirations (think Gaspar Noé, but without the moves), while more general filmgoers may bristle that this pretentious splatter flick is receiving play time in American theaters even as superior foreign-language offerings remain out of reach. Animal lovers should beware, too, unless they are really, really, really, really sick animal lovers of the kind found in Krafft-Ebing and Kinsey.  Those who derive satisfaction from watching the overemployed actor Laurent Lucas get roughed up, however, are in luck. Alternating between two of his customary modes, creepy and creepy-pathetic, Mr. Lucas plays Marc Stevens, a lounge singer living out of his van who undergoes the sort of abuse often rained on little women with big lungs. That’s intentional since Marc basically ends up playing the girl in an all-male nightmare populated by savagely violent cretins (including Mr. Noé’s favorite slab of beef, Philippe Nahon). When not raping and pillaging, they are dancing and drooling in a grim tavern that looks like those featured in the films of Bela Tarr, which probably makes this extended game of cat-and-mouse sound more interesting than it is.  Directed by the newcomer Fabrice du Welz, who wrote the screenplay with Romain Protat, “Calvaire” is pompous, but not without talent or shivers. The opening scene, which finds Marc twirling his satin cape for some female lonelyhearts, gets the story off to a bad start largely because it’s hard to imagine even the most desperate woman falling for such dead eyes. Although Mr. du Welz and Mr. Lucas can’t sell banal emotions, things improve once Marc loses his way in the dark (a milieu that suits the cinematographer Benoît Debie) and takes refuge with a widower, Mr. Bartel (played by a very good Jackie Berroyer). With his mad smile and beard, Mr. Berroyer looks rather like a lawn gnome come to life, which is itself plenty scary.</text>
      <date>August 11, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>