<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Concise, inventive and unabashedly partisan, “The Camden 28” is a small movie that contains multitudes. Directed by Anthony Giacchino, the film is specifically about a Camden, N.J., antiwar group’s 1971 plot to break into a draft-board office and destroy government records, and the long trial that ensued when the protesters were caught by the F.B.I. It is also about the tradition of left-wing Roman Catholic activism (the Camden 28 was composed mainly of working-class priests and young, devout laypeople) and the threat it posed to those conservative Americans  who wished to conflate Christianity and unquestioning acceptance of government policy. And it is about the F.B.I.’s push to infiltrate and undermine dissident groups — a process that trapped the Camden 28 and that, once exposed in court, led to the protesters’ freedom. Supreme Court Justice William J. Brennan Jr. called the legal proceeding “one of the great trials of the 20th century.” Mr. Giacchino tells the Camden 28’s story with energy, imagination and a nearly evangelical belief in their rightness. The movie endorses every aspect of the group’s motivation for plotting the draft-board break-in — from its certitude that the draft was an example of class bias and a form of government-sanctioned kidnapping to its conviction that Camden’s decayed neighborhoods were economic collateral damage caused by racism, government oppression and the diversion of tax dollars to Vietnam. Seizing control of their own defense, the Camden 28 made the trial a referendum on the morality of the Vietnam conflict and  on whether the F.B.I.’s investigation crossed the line into entrapment. We learn that the bureau’s Camden 28 informer (whose shocking identity is revealed early in the movie) actively encouraged the break-in, participated in the planning and helped the group get supplies that were paid for with F.B.I. money. Although the opening third of the film establishes the group’s political bona fides in no uncertain terms, it errs on the side of excitement. As the movie describes the formation of the team and its attempt to plan the break-in, the anxious tone is part paranoid thriller, part heist picture, and the score — by Michael Giacchino, the director’s brother and the composer for ABC’s “Lost” — evokes John Williams’s ominously percussive music for “JFK.” Then the story shifts gears twice, becoming a meditation on radical disillusionment and betrayal and finally a multifaceted indictment of America’s interventionist tendencies and the tension between the First Amendment and domestic security. Some of the film’s chronological details are muddy. Its parallels between Vietnam and Iraq are ham-fisted and unnecessary, as is Mr. Giacchino’s attempt to integrate clips from a 2002 reunion of Camden 28 members. The score is often intrusive and sometimes maudlin. And the baby-boomer-pandering postscript seems tailor-made for public television pledge drives. But scene for scene,  “The Camden 28” is a brilliant merger of political outrage and filmmaking chops, and the most suspenseful movie in theaters right now.</text>
      <date>July 27, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>