<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The sight of young people going down the drain is never pleasant, particularly when there are needles jabbed in their arms. It isn’t just that watching anyone  probe  his or her veins with a sharp  tends to be pretty gross; it’s also that the ritual of heroin addiction, from the bent spoon to the elastic band snapping against the agonized flesh, has become a cinematic cliché. It doesn’t help matters that stories about heroin addicts are all alike: they shoot up, they nod out, they jones. Some users clobber old ladies for their purses; others roll up to the bank in a sleek   ride and make a painless withdrawal. But it’s always the same story, always.  The Australian film “Candy” doesn’t add anything substantively new to that story, though it has been nicely directed by Neil Armfield,  known in his  country for his theater work, and features striking performances from Heath Ledger and Geoffrey Rush. Mr.  Ledger plays Dan, a low-key charmer with a dewily pretty girlfriend, Candy (Abbie Cornish), and a growing appetite for heroin. The story opens shortly after Candy starts shooting heroin instead of snorting it, a decision that almost ends her life but also seems to strengthen the bond between the couple, who soar high and then higher. To abuse a famous line from another film: they’re young, they’re in love,  and they shoot up, which they do with increasing frequency and with increasingly calamitous effect.  Adapted from  a novel by Luke Davies, who wrote the screenplay with Mr. Armfield, “Candy” unfolds in separate movements rather coyly announced by title cards, including “heaven” and “earth.” Since, as Neil Young sings, “every junkie’s like a setting sun,” Dan and Candy can only spiral down, down, down, which they do in predictable fashion. As they hopscotch from pawn shop to whore house and beyond, Mr. Armfield invests their progressively bleak spaces and situations with a grungy patina that somehow never seems dirty enough, filthy enough,  grotesque enough. Even when the couple are screeching at each other, in the throes of a deep druggy need or drifting along in a narcotic haze, the roses in Ms. Cornish’s cheeks remain disconcertingly in bloom.  Mr. Ledger, by contrast, looks and plays the part of the scheming user exceptionally well. He’s deep in the character’s skin right from the start. If he seems especially comfortable in the role, it may be because he’s speaking in his own accent; he doesn’t appear to be clenching his jaw the way he sometimes does when he plays an American character, or maybe he’s just coming into his own as an actor. He’s very fine, which isn’t half as unexpected as the equally shaded performance delivered by Mr. Rush, who also has the chewiest, densest role. As Casper, a professor with a seemingly endless supply of drugs and lovers, Mr. Rush leads you into a room that, for all its despair, you don’t want to vacate anytime soon.  “Candy” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for  intravenous drug use, prostitution, adult language and nudity.</text>
      <date>November 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>