<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> I must confess that I watched the opening scenes of "Casanova" with some trepidation. A movie that begins with a man in a billowy linen shirt writing with a quill pen by candlelight, accompanied by a plummy voice-over - a "feather film," as my predecessor Vincent Canby  might have said - is rarely headed anywhere very interesting. To make matters worse, this was also "a film by Lasse Hallstrom," a talented enough director, but one whose recent efforts have been more concerned with Quality than with art or insight or surprise. So I sighed and sank down in my seat, preparing for a long, perfumed coach ride to Prestigeville.  Imagine my surprise, then, when "Casanova" turned out to be not a bewigged and brocaded white elephant, but rather a lively, sly and altogether charming farce. Dispensing with the suffocating conventions of the historical biopic, Mr. Hallstrom and the screenwriters, Jeffrey Hatcher and Kimberly Simi (assisted, it has been reported, by an uncredited Tom Stoppard), make liberal and intelligent use of the literary styles and attitudes of the 18th century, when their story takes place. While it takes a few cues from Casanova's notoriously untrustworthy memoirs, "Casanova" seems more directly inspired by the lighthearted, madcap comedies of near contemporaries like Pierre Marivaux and Casanova's fellow Venetian, Carlo Goldoni.  In following those theatrical models, the film feels at once historically faithful and breezily, even pointedly modern. The conflicts that propel its crazy, fusilli-like plot - between pleasure and restraint, between religious repression and sexual freedom, between candor and hypocrisy - are hardly obsolete. Venice in 1753 is in the midst of its own culture war, pitting the bureaucrats of the Inquisition against assorted feminists, philosophers and fornicators, and principally against Casanova, who is all of the above and then some.  He is also a man of mystery, known to his fellow Venetians by reputation rather than by face. Moviegoers will recognize him, of course, as Heath Ledger, the mumbling ranch hand from "Brokeback Mountain," and Mr. Ledger's status as the pansexual art-house heartthrob of the season will only be enhanced by this nimble performance. Whereas Donald Sutherland, in "Fellini's Casanova" back in 1976, played the man as a louche, melancholy degenerate, Mr. Ledger's version is more carefree and less complicated. He speaks softly, squares his shoulders, and the bodices pretty much rip themselves. (One virginal young lady is so overcome by his manly good looks that she reduces a bird cage to splinters.)  But the doge of Venice is under pressure from Rome to clean up his city, and so Casanova is commanded to marry or face banishment. At the same time, a spirited woman named Francesca Bruni (Sienna Miller) is rebelling against the arranged marriage that her widowed mother (Lena Olin) is forcing on her. Francesca's brother, Giovanni (Charlie Cox), is in love with the bird-cage smasher, whom Casanova is courting under an assumed name. There is a duel, and Casanova finds himself smitten - literally! - by Francesca's swordsmanship, as well as by her other charms. She, meanwhile, leads her own double life, publishing tracts on sexual equality under a male pseudonym and debating Casanova on the nature of love.  The movie ascends from pleasant comedy into true farce with the arrival of two out-of-towners. One, a Genoese lard merchant (Oliver Platt) who seems to be sculptured out of what he sells, is Francesca's intended husband, whom Casanova and his manservant (the brilliantly droll Omid Djalili) deflect from the romantic purpose of his trip. Meanwhile, the ruthless Bishop Pucci has come to Venice in the person of Jeremy Irons, a vision of decadent righteousness in purple silk breeches and a ginger-colored flat-top mullet wig.  Mr. Irons, who played the title role in last year's "Merchant of Venice," seems to be making a habit of spending Christmas in that city, something for which we can all be thankful. Pucci's villainy, while ridiculous, also supplies "Casanova" with a few necessary notes of gravity, since there is nothing funny about religious authority that punishes the pursuit of pleasure with torture and death. On the other hand, the best way to defeat such power is to laugh at it, which Mr. Irons and the rest of the cast do with effortless silliness.  Mr. Hallstrom's good taste also proves to be an asset. His direction is brisk and efficient, rather than insistently anarchic, and his visual gags are engineered with sly understatement. Of particular note is a perfectly simple wide shot of Mr. Platt sitting in a gondola, an image whose naughty wit may take a moment to sink in. And while the film is appropriately sexy, it is rarely vulgar or prurient. The most risqué bit is a moment of what might politely be called ocular intercourse. It occurs between Mr. Platt and Ms. Olin  and stands in for the more vigorous variety, which is kept mainly off screen.  In any case, what is on screen is a delightful respite from awards-season seriousness - a feather film, you might say, that actually tickles.  "Casanova" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has many sexual scenes and references, none of them terribly explicit.</text>
      <date>December 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>