<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The past collides with the present in “Catch a Fire,” the story of a man who was simultaneously hailed as a freedom fighter and damned as a terrorist. The director Phillip Noyce, working from a screenplay by Shawn Slovo, revisits the ordeal of Patrick Chamusso, an ordinary black South African who, after being wrongly accused of crimes against the racist government in the early 1980’s, became a foot soldier in the war against apartheid. It’s a film that wants to play  as if it were ripped from today’s headlines, but has been shredded into near incoherence.  The appealing young American actor Derek Luke (the heartbreak kid in “Antwone Fisher”) plays Patrick, a family man who works as a foreman at a fuel refinery some 80 miles southeast of Johannesburg. Avowedly apolitical, Patrick goes along to get along with his white bosses and black colleagues, earning decent-enough wages to support his two daughters, taciturn mother-in-law and well-named wife, Precious (Bonnie Henna), a beautiful pixie who yearns for better furniture for their small home. When white soldiers stop the family on a dusty highway, ostensibly to search for saboteurs, Patrick quickly raises his hands in a gesture of accord. For him, cooperation means survival, no matter how dehumanizing.  His awakening comes in the aftermath of a guerrilla attack on the refinery. Along with two other workers, Patrick is hauled off by the police, who are led by the vicious Col. Nic Vos (Tim Robbins), accused of espionage and subjected to appalling torture. For a man like Vos, whose dedication to the racist regime seems to border on the religious, the color of Patrick’s skin has already marked him as guilty. But in trying to soften Patrick up, using barbaric methods that Mr. Noyce reproduces in squirmingly vivid detail, the police only harden his heart and his resolve. The man spirited away, blindfolded, brutalized and never officially accused bears seemingly little resemblance to the casualty who eventually stumbles back home.  In its rough outline, “Catch a Fire” has all the makings of a gripping tale. Soon after he is released by the police, Patrick ends up first in neighboring Mozambique and then Angola, where he sings songs of freedom under the auspices of the African National Congress. He also learns to march in place and, alongside other anti-apartheid fighters, echo the chant of “Kill the Boer Soldier!” The pulse-quickening music and the righteousness of the anti-apartheid cause might have made this revolutionary fervor feel terribly rousing if the film’s anemic politics and calamitously overwrought editing didn’t, at regular intervals, force you out of the story and down some exceedingly distracting avenues of thought, like: what would it mean if you replaced the word Boer with American?  This nasty game of substitution is all too easy to play in “Catch a Fire,” partly because the film fails to dig into the specifics of Patrick’s story or that of South Africa, and partly because the filmmakers don’t seem to have much faith in the audience’s ability to tell the good guys in this story from the bad. This, at least, seems the most charitable explanation for a scene in which one member of the African National Congress announces, as much to the last row in the movie theater as to the other characters, “We don’t kill indiscriminately.” For those hard of hearing, the same message is more or less repeated when Patrick, newly anointed Hot Stuff, straps on some explosives to do his part for the cause.  Mr. Noyce, whose career ranges from hack work like “The Bone Collector” to thoughtful efforts like “The Quiet American,” knows how to keep the action in high gear. In “Catch a Fire,” however, the action doesn’t just move; it rushes with such chaotic speed that the scenes don’t have time to develop. They play like commercials for a film that never materializes, as if someone had tried to fix a problem in the editing and forgotten to take a breath amid the slicing and dicing. Despite being reduced to hieroglyphs of gesture and grimace, Mr. Luke’s and Mr. Robbins’s performances nonetheless suggest a more interesting story than the one here, even if the cross-cutting that often brings them together does much to tear the film apart.  “Catch a Fire” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has graphic and suggestive violence, including scenes of torture.</text>
      <date>October 27, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>