<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Terrorism and cultural identity are only two of the themes wound into a tight knot of fear and bewilderment in "Cavite," a gripping no-budget political thriller.  Written and directed by two Filipino-Americans, Ian Gamazon and Neill Dela Llana, "Cavite" is a textbook example of seat-of-the-pants guerrilla filmmaking. It was shot on the fly with jiggling handheld cameras that scour the teeming streets, squatter shacks and garbage-clogged waterways of Cavite, an impoverished city on the outskirts of Manila. Cavite is the Philippines' seat of independence, where Emilio Aguinaldo overthrew Spanish rule in 1898, and his statue looms in the film like a silent sentinel.  Taking in these sights for the first time is Adam (Mr. Gamazon), a night watchman at the San Diego harbor, who is summoned to the Philippines to attend his father's funeral. Even before he goes, there are ominous portents. His pregnant girlfriend informs him by telephone that she is having an abortion because she doesn't want the child to be brought up Muslim, even though there are few signs that Adam is faithful to the religion in which he was reared.  When he arrives in Manila, his mother isn't there to meet him, and she doesn't answer the telephone. As he paces outside the terminal, a cellphone that has been mysteriously slipped into his luggage jingles. An ominous male voice, dripping with contempt, informs him that his mother and sister have been kidnapped. If he fails to follow instructions to the letter, they will be killed. From here on, that unseen and apparently omniscient observer, who knows Adam's every move, calls the shots.  If "Cavite" borrows its concept from the empty 2002 thriller "Phone Booth," Adam's subsequent ordeal is grounded in grim political reality. The caller eventually reveals himself as a member of the militant Islamic group Abu Sayyaf.  We hear that Adam's once politically active father betrayed the movement and moved to the United States after some financial double-dealing, only returning to the Philippines to pick up some money he had stashed. Or so the caller insists. He demands that Adam remove the money from the bank and deliver it to him. The drop-off takes place at a cockfighting exhibition.  But first Adam is forced to take a tour of the slums, to have his nose rubbed in the poverty and stink of the culture his family abandoned. The bullying caller, obsessed with manhood, sneeringly questions Adam's heterosexuality and berates him for preferring English to Tagalog and for never having made a pilgrimage to Mecca.  He forces Adam to "taste" Filipino culture by consuming a balut (a fertilized duck egg with a nearly developed embryo) sold on the street. Directed to a pack of cigarettes on a bench, Adam opens it to discover a severed finger, which the caller says belongs to his sister.  Even after delivering the money, Adam finds his work isn't done. In one last, fateful instruction, he is given the grim choice of carrying out a terrorist act or losing his loved ones.  "Cavite" suffers mightily from the fact that Mr. Gamazon can't act. The lead was originally to have been female, but, according to the production notes, no actress would accompany the filmmakers to the Philippines. At the last minute Mr. Gamazon filled in.  He can feign befuddlement, low anxiety and peevish stubbornness. But the deeper emotions of fear, anger and sorrow elude him, as do any signs of illumination; his performance is a blank. Tilting toward the opposite extreme, the unseen (and uncredited) caller sounds like a fiendish villain in a Grade B spy movie.  But this unblinking tour of Asian misery nevertheless offers an unsettling contemplation of life at the bottom of the human food chain. It touches on all the questions about nationality, faith, immigration, assimilation, globalization, poverty and the roots of terrorism that people are asking themselves,  questions that aren't about to be answered either tomorrow or the day after.</text>
      <date>May 26, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>