<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Every character in “Changing Times,” André Téchiné’s rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Morocco, oscillates between two worlds and two ideas about the meaning of experience.  Cécile (Catherine Deneuve), the host of a French-Moroccan radio show who lives in Tangier with her much younger husband, Nathan (Gilbert Melki), a doctor, doesn’t believe in holding onto the past. Moments after her station plays a song whose lyrics insist “we remember nothing,” she receives an anonymous bouquet of roses; without a second thought, she tosses them into the trash.  The roses, it turns out, are  from Antoine (Gérard Depardieu), a former lover she hasn’t seen in three decades. A hard-driving engineer who is overseeing the construction of a media center in Tangier, Antoine has literally counted the time (31 years 8 months 20 days) since he saw her last. After years spent tracking her down, he has come to Morocco expressly to win her back. He is so obsessed that he even considers using witchcraft. The two eventually cross paths in a supermarket when Antoine smashes his nose walking into a glass door and Nathan, who is with Cécile, hastens to his aid.  In “Changing Times,” Mr. Téchiné, the great French director, is near the peak of his form. Weaving a half  dozen subplots, he creates a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. This microcosm of a world in transition might seem painfully schematic had it been conceived by a less subtle filmmaker. But for the most part Mr. Téchiné carries it off without its seeming heavy-handed. When it’s time to end the movie after a swift, compact 95 minutes, he refuses to wind his stories into a tight knot and lets most of the threads dangle.  Much of the movie’s charm lies in its sheer vitality. Mr. Téchiné loves people and life, and every scene is filled with light, music, activity and a sensuous appreciation of landscape. The characters are continually on the move. Even Antoine is too busy most of the time to sit around moping. In the movie’s circular structure, Antoine is buried in a mudslide at a rain-drenched building site near the beginning of the film and then the story backtracks, only letting us know his fate after the accident is reprised near the end. Mr. Depardieu and Ms. Deneuve, who have co-starred many times before, give contained, unsentimental performances.  Cécile’s marriage  —  to Nathan, whose career has stalled and who admits to having had several affairs —  has lost its spark. And Ms. Deneuve plays her as a woman who has buried her youthful dreams and clings to a low-paying job that gives her a sense of independence. She copes with life in a state of mild exasperation.  Antoine, whom she remembers as thin, poor and proud, is now portly, well-to-do and accustomed to giving orders. He has never married, and his obsession with the loss of his great love is the chink in his armor that both humanizes him and makes him a little creepy.  Around the time Antoine arrives in Tangier, Cécile and Nathan’s bisexual son, Sami (Malik Zidi), who lives in Paris, appears unannounced with his live-in girlfriend, Nadia (Lubna Azabal), and Said (Jabir Elomri), her 9-year-old son by another man. While Nadia, who is seriously addicted to tranquilizers, languishes in a funk, Sami dashes off for trysts with his Moroccan boyfriend, Bilal (Nadem Rachati).  Bilal, who briefly lived in Paris and is now the resident groundskeeper of a fancy estate rarely visited by its owners, more or less accepts Sami’s ambivalence. “You’re too indecisive, but I guess that’s normal,” he observes with a tinge of bitterness. “You’re half Moroccan, half French, half man, half woman. It must be difficult knowing who you are.”  Nadia, meanwhile, has accompanied Sami to Tangier hoping to reconnect with her identical twin sister, Aicha (also played by Ms. Azabal), a man-hating observant Muslim who works in a McDonald’s. Their twinship is the most strained of the movie’s several metaphoric pairings.  As is often the case with Téchiné films, the characters hover on the line between cultural constructions and fully drawn people. What does Nadia offer Sami, who obviously prefers men? How did the twins end up living such radically different lives? The movie doesn’t begin to ask such questions; it doesn’t have the time.  That’s one  reason Mr. Téchiné’s films feel so buoyant: no one is weighed down by too much psychological baggage. He accepts that human behavior is mysterious and unpredictable. Even his unhappiest characters are players in a larger vision of a multicultural world in continual flux. The impulse to connect across cultures is a fundamental urge that’s worth the pain and uncertainty; it offers the same rewards as learning a new language.</text>
      <date>July 14, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>