<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Genre mixing is mother’s milk to Hindi films, so it’s no surprise that “Chandni Chowk to China” can so seamlessly add kung fu to the usual blend of comedy, dance and melodrama. After all, the choreographed fighting is dancing by another name, and plays off the same desire to see movie-star bodies in motion.  “Chandni Chowk,” the first Bollywood movie to be financed and distributed by Warner Brothers, starts too frantically but settles down to become an enjoyable if slight Saturday-matinee picture. The affable Akshay Kumar, fresh from the runaway hit “Singh Is Kinng,” stars as Sidhu, a vegetable cutter in the Chandni Chowk marketplace in Delhi, who dreams of being something more. Sidhu, an all-Indian boy and a bumbler whose clumsiness gets him in and out of trouble, travels to China, where he’s mistakenly thought to be an incarnation of a great fighter come to save a village from the evil Hojo (Gordon Liu). Hojo’s best trick? Slicing off heads with the edge of his boomerang bowler hat. (That’s just one homage — to Oddjob in “Goldfinger” — in a film crammed with movie references.)  The plot has long-separated twins (one is named Meow Meow) and long-lost fathers, a potato with the face of the god Ganesh, an interpreter called Chopstick and, most intriguingly, Asia’s two superpowers meeting in the arena of pop culture. The explicit message for the Indian hero is know yourself and be self-reliant, and you will triumph. Sidhu’s best trick? A kung fu move derived from his years of cutting vegetables.  In a film impressed with Chinese gadgetry — including a pair of leg cuffs that help the dance-challenged — and with scenes set in the sleek urban landscape of Shanghai, it’s hard not to see a broader point: India, don’t be afraid of China’s accomplishments. Be yourself. You will succeed.  “Chandni Chowk to China” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for violence and martial arts.</text>
      <date>January 16, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>