<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Ever since he played a forlorn 11-year-old boy in the insufferable 2001 tear-jerker “Hearts in Atlantis,” the Russian-born actor Anton Yelchin has seemed destined to step into the shoes of Hollywood’s favorite quiz kid, Matthew Broderick. And in the precociously articulate title character of “Charlie Bartlett,” he may have found a contemporary equivalent of Mr. Broderick’s beloved hooky-playing high school trickster, Ferris Bueller.  Mr. Yelchin has the routine down pat. He speaks in the elevated, faintly whiny tone and deliberate cadences of an honor student tossing off a difficult oral exam.  Even under stress, he exhibits the composure of a smarty-pants who, beneath his lost-boy affectations, is inordinately pleased with himself. In spite of your qualms, you root for him.  Mr. Yelchin, at 18, is six years younger than Mr. Broderick was when “Ferris Bueller’s Day Off” was released in 1986, and he has a good decade ahead of him to corner the market on adolescent prodigies like Charlie. A rich kid bounced out of prep school for making fake IDs, Charlie is forced to attend the institution of last resort, the local high school. He arrives with ludicrous grandeur by chauffeured limousine, wearing a blue blazer with Latin insignia and toting a fancy briefcase.  An instant pariah who craves popularity, Charlie wins friends and influences people only after he hits on the notion of becoming the student drug dealer. But not the usual kind. Instead of pot, cocaine and speed, he dispenses a pharmacy’s worth of prescription drugs like Ritalin, Xanax and Prozac, obtained by studying physicians’ reference books, then visiting psychiatrists and feigning symptoms the doctors are only too quick to treat with the latest medications.  In the movie’s funniest scene, Charlie and his business partner Murphy, the school bully who beat him up and dunked his head in the toilet when he first arrived, dispense Ritalin to the students and turn a dance into a frenzied free-for-all with bare-breasted girls running down the halls.  The movie, directed by Jon Poll from a screenplay by Gustin Nash, is never more amusingly subversive than in this scene, which suggests the hypocrisy of American attitudes toward drugs without putting it in words. The major difference between physician-prescribed “good” drugs like antidepressants and tranquilizers and “bad” drugs like marijuana and cocaine, it implies, has to do with the sanctification of some by the medical,  pharmaceutical and legal establishments and the outlawing of others, which, given their effects, seems somewhat arbitrary.  From his therapy experiences,  Charlie picks up how to act the role of shrink. Operating from a toilet stall in the boys’ room, he conducts therapy sessions with his troubled peers, who line up for his services and to whom he doles out what he deems appropriate medication.  Most of his advice is empathetic common sense.  It eventually backfires when a troubled student attempts suicide using pills Charlie has provided.  If the attention span of “Charlie Bartlett” didn’t wander here and there, the movie might have been a high school satire worthy of comparison with Alexander Payne’s “Election.” But as it dashes around and eventually turns soft, it loses its train of thought.  One story involves Charlie’s relationship with his flaky, depressed mother, Marilyn (Hope Davis, who also played the mother of Mr. Yelchin’s character in “Hearts in Atlantis”), with whom he sits at the piano singing old television theme songs. As Charlie’s troubles escalate, it dawns on Marilyn that perhaps she shouldn’t have treated him as an adult all his life. Ms. Davis plays her with an off-center joviality that is both charming and creepy.  Wise child that he is, Charlie understands that he is his mother’s emotional caretaker and lifeline to whatever stability she can muster. Barely touched on is Charlie’s estrangement from his father, in prison for tax evasion.  The other major strand of the story is Charlie’s embattled relationship with the school’s principal. A former history teacher who loathes his new job so much it has turned him into an alcoholic, Principal Gardner  (Robert Downey Jr.) runs afoul of the student body when he goes along with the superintendent’s insistence on installing surveillance cameras in the student lounge.  Charlie’s conflict with the principal turns into warfare once Gardner learns that Charlie is dating his rebellious daughter, Susan (Kat Dennings). It worsens when, partly at Charlie’s instigation, organized protest against the surveillance erupts into a riot. Mr. Downey bravely attempts to bring some depth and compassion to the principal. But as the movie dashes from one base to the next, it never coalesces into the character-driven, serious comedy with heart that you want it be.  “Charlie Bartlett” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has glimpses of nudity, strong language and mild violence.</text>
      <date>February 22, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>