<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Abel Ferrara’s ramshackle documentary “Chelsea on the Rocks” is not — I repeat not — a sober history of the Hotel Chelsea, the Manhattan landmark and artist hangout on West 23rd Street. An enraptured fantasia of high times at the hotel, the film is so intoxicated with the Chelsea’s bohemian mystique it virtually consumes itself.  Built in 1883 as an apartment cooperative, the Chelsea began operating as a hotel in 1905 and in the decades since has served as both a welcoming longtime residence and stopover for artists and musicians. Two years ago, Stanley Bard, its artist-friendly manager since the 1970s, was ousted from his position, and its future as shabby palace of art and excess remains in doubt.  The film is madly infatuated with the Chelsea’s notoriety as a nexus of sex, drugs and rock ’n’ roll. As people who have stayed there — some famous, some not — parade through the documentary, Mr. Ferrara, a sloppy interviewer whose off-screen voice is heard, pointedly (and annoyingly) refuses to give them the usual identifying titles. One of the wild men of American cinema, Mr. Ferrara adores them all, demonstrating special affection for the most eccentric, cantankerous and self-destructive.  Structurally the movie is a hodgepodge of reminiscences, conversations, archival footage and feverish re-enactments of famous incidents at the hotel. By far the most attention is given to the unsolved fatal stabbing in October 1978 of Nancy Spungen, who was staying there with Sid Vicious. Bijou Phillips and Jamie Burke play the happy couple who are visited in a re-enacted scene by two drug dealers.  In this disorderly documentary about disorderly lives, outrageousness trumps art. When the camera scans the paintings on the lobby walls, none are credited. Nor does the documentary bother mentioning the scores of great artists from Mark Twain to Bob Dylan who have spent time at the hotel.  Desperate to stir up drama, it brings in recollections of 9/11 accompanied by images of the smoldering twin towers. One employee recalls attending orgies with 60 people. Another man recounts the details of his brain hemorrhage while pumping iron. People relate personal ghost stories.  The hotel’s biggest celebrity fan is Ethan Hawke, who gratefully recalls that Mr. Bard gave him a room when his marriage was breaking up. Eight years ago, Mr. Hawke, who does a decent imitation of Mr. Bard’s New York accent, filmed a fictional homage to the hotel, “Chelsea Walls.” It is marginally better than this one.</text>
      <date>October 2, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>