<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “One who is abnormal must never feel abnormal,” the French novelist Colette once wrote to a friend. Instead, he or she thinks, “What is this world full of monstrous pigs who are different from me?” What words to live — or rather to write — by! Born in an age of corsets and legalized prejudice (1873-1954), Colette scandalized society with her colorful life, lovers of both sexes and demimonde characters. Her inspirations were artists not of the pen but of the bedroom, women whose idea of the bottom line, to quote the critic Judith Thurman, “was 50 thousand a year and a villa of one’s own — with a big garden, a great chef, and a pretty boy.”  One such character is Léa de Lonval, the Parisian courtesan in Colette’s brilliant 1920 novel “Chéri” who’s played by Michelle Pfeiffer in a pretty adaptation from the director Stephen Frears. Over her long career as a professional coquette, Léa has reaped ample rewards and seemingly few serious regrets. Six years before the novel opens, she also acquired a much-younger lover, the fatal beauty of the book’s title — “a graceful demon” in Colette’s words, played by the striking Rupert Friend — whose appeal for her is as openly maternal as it is unabashedly erotic. Léa even goes so far as to call the affair an adoption, a description that seems rather less metaphoric whenever her “naughty child” rests his cheek on her breasts.  The affair between Léa and Chéri is nudged into existence, perhaps knowingly, by her friend and his mother, Charlotte Peloux (Kathy Bates). Herself a former courtesan, Charlotte solicits Léa’s help with Chéri, a 19-year-old who’s cultivating his dissolution. With cheekbones so sharply angled they look like they could slice through a caressing hand, Chéri seems a perilous project. But Léa, who’s known him since he was a child, scoops him up as thoughtlessly as she would a puppy. Years later, the affair takes a sharp turn when he announces that his mother has arranged for him to marry a suitable prospect with a significant dowry, Edmée (Felicity Jones), an innocent who guilelessly upends this world.  Decadence perfumes this deceptively tragic story. Much like the opium smoke that wafts through one scene, Léa and Chéri’s affair has left a great deal of wreckage in its seductive wake. It takes time to assess the damage, and Mr. Frears, working from Christopher Hampton’s intelligently compressed adaptation (the two were also united on the 1988 film “Dangerous Liaisons”), seems in no hurry to break the bad news. Working with the cinematographer Darius Khondji and a host of other talented artisans, he luxuriates in the Belle Époque milieu, with its sumptuous clothes, gaudy homes and heavily bloomed gardens, almost as self-indulgently as Léa lounges in bed. The camera lingers over the silks and furs with an almost sentimental attachment.  Mr. Frears and Léa are each in the business of seduction, of course. And both are extremely gifted at what they do. What’s surprising, at least at first, is how eagerly Mr. Frears wants to please the audience or at least leave it untroubled. Though the film cannot rightly be characterized as soft — the cruel, often funny verbal barbs invest it with pleasurable prickliness — there’s a certain reserve, even hesitancy to his direction that in part may have something to do with the conundrum presented by Ms. Pfeiffer’s casting. After decades of pleasuring others, Léa now faces an empty bed, a state of declining affairs that has taken on extra resonance in the story’s transposition from page to screen.  It’s perhaps inevitable that the film becomes something of a story about what happens to beautiful Hollywood stars. Ms. Pfeiffer is now 51, and her success has largely rested on a combination of extraordinary looks and an underlying fragility that dilutes the threat that great beauty can bring with it. No matter the role, with her watery eyes and slender limbs, she often seems on the verge of breaking. She can seem as brittle as a twig and just as easy to snap. At other times, you see the steeliness that comes with any sustained and successful movie career. In “Chéri” you see the frailty and the strength, yet you rarely experience either with the depth of feeling you might because of the palpable uneasiness surrounding her performance.  That uneasiness is most evident in Mr. Frears’s decision to shoot Ms. Pfeiffer almost entirely in circumspect medium and long shot, as if she were a fine jewel in a shop window rather than a flesh-and-blood woman. Yet in flattering Ms. Pfeiffer, he also ends up insulting her talent. Even a lingering close-up of her face, which is meant to reveal how Chéri suddenly sees Léa in the harsh light of day, backfires and not only because, like most Hollywood stars of her age, Ms. Pfeiffer looks all of 40. There’s something poignant about the image of this actress sitting in a pool of sunlight without a smile or trace of visible makeup. But she’s trying to reach a character that her director seems intent to keep from her grasp.  “Chéri” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Discreet sex and harsh sentiments.</text>
      <date>June 26, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>