<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The most disquieting moment in “City of Men,” a rootin’-tootin’ gangster movie shot in the notoriously lawless shantytowns overlooking the beaches of Rio de Janeiro, is also the most subdued. Acerola, a k a Ace (Douglas Silva), an 18-year-old still carrying baby fat, admits that he is frightened and unprepared to care for his infant son as his wife, Cris (Camila Monteiro), leaves to find work in São Paulo. Although Ace loves his little boy, he is only a child in a man’s body himself, and he begs her not to go. For him to assume full parental responsibility is almost unimaginable.  In “City of Men,” directed by Paulo Morelli, Ace’s reluctance is more the rule than the exception. In the strutting, drug- and gun-infested culture of the favelas, young men who sire children aren’t expected to acknowledge them, and their tough, sullen wives and girlfriends have little choice but to tolerate the situation or leave. That’s just the way it is in a hyper-macho environment with virulent homophobia.  Underneath their swagger, these teenage gangsters brood about the absence of their own fathers. Ace’s best friend, Laranjinha, a k a Wallace (Darlan Cunha), who is days short of turning 18, is especially obsessed with his own paternity. As he approaches the numerical demarcation between child and adult, when he will need an identification card stating his last name, he embarks on a concerted search for his father based on neighborhood rumor.  Mr. Morelli’s film is a companion piece (not strictly a sequel) to “City of God,” the 2002 global hit directed by his longtime collaborator Fernando Meirelles that featured some of the same actors, including Mr. Silva and Mr. Cunha playing 11-year-olds. The new movie, written by Elena Soárez, is spun off from a successful Brazilian television series of the same title that was shown on the Sundance Channel and is available on DVD. (Mr. Meirelles was a creator of the television series and is a producer of the new film.)  “City of Men” has a more humane, you might say bleeding-heart, perspective on this anarchic culture than “City of God.” The first movie offered a startling, documentarylike picture of social decay in which the steady influx of drugs and guns over several generations transformed depressed neighborhoods into war zones. As the weaponry grew more deadly, the age of the warriors fell, and in the movie’s later scenes, the opposing forces were child armies mowing one another down with lethal toys.  Where “City of God” had the hard-boiled attitude of an exposé filmed on site with hand-held cameras and rapid jump cuts, “City of Men” is a more conventionally structured melodrama. The nihilism of the first movie has been softened enough to suggest that this culture of violence may not be quite so extreme as the earlier movie portrayed. Amid the organized sociopathy in which allegiances are continually shifting, and people are literally shooting one another in the back, true friendships are perilous but not hopeless undertakings.  The movie’s all-out warfare begins when Nefasto (Eduardo B R Piranha), a henchman of the charismatic boss of bosses, Madrugadão, a k a Midnight (Jonathan Haagensen), betrays him and with a new posse occupies his turf on Dead End Hill. Midnight mounts an even larger and deadlier response. Like those in “City of God,” the battle scenes show herds of armed juvenile soldiers swarming like locusts down the steep, terraced hills. As the war spreads, Ace and Wallace accidentally find themselves on opposite sides.  Wallace eventually finds his father, Heraldo (Rodrigo Dos  Santos), who served 15 years of a 20-year sentence for murder. The wariness of the father when confronted with the neediness of the son indicates that it is far too late for their bond to become more than superficial. Though probably only in his mid-30s, Heraldo exudes an air of defeat. The thrill of youthful armed combat has faded into fatigue and desperation. Twenty years hence, Wallace, if he survives, will probably be just like him.  That the sins of the fathers are passed on to the sons is the somewhat thudding message of a movie that hammers home its point by having Ace and Wallace reach an impasse in their friendship that parallels the relationship of their fathers two decades earlier. In a society of fatherless boys craving role models, glamorous outlaws fill the void.  “City of Men” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language and scenes of violence but  is not gory.</text>
      <date>February 29, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>