<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A devilishly entertaining curveball thrown at unsuspecting family audiences, “CJ7” is “E.T.” as reimagined by the premier clown of Chinese cinema, Stephen Chow. Whether American viewers will respond with the enthusiasm of their Chinese counterparts remains to be seen. What is clear, however, is that Mr. Chow’s notion of family is decidedly more Addams than Brady.  A simple fairy tale — albeit with a perverseness that no Disney executive would permit —  “CJ7” finds Mr. Chow in a Chaplinesque mood as Ti, an impoverished widower caring for his young son, Dicky (the  9-year-old actress Xu Jiao in her debut). By day Ti works long hours on a construction site to pay for Dicky’s elite private school; at night they return to a sweltering, cockroach-infested shack  with unreliable electricity. Both suffer constant bullying: Ti’s overbearing boss (Lam Tze Chung) berates him for having ideas above his station, while Dicky’s fastidious teacher (Lee Sheung Ching) and snotty schoolmates treat him like a leper.  Scouring the local dump one evening to supplement his son’s wardrobe, Ti discovers a strange green ball that, when placed in Dicky’s curious hands, transforms into a saucer-eyed creature resembling an ineptly groomed cockapoo. Emitting bleep-bloop noises from a waggling antenna, it reveals to Dicky its alien origins and magical powers. In a hilariously inventive sequence, the boy envisions using his new friend to dole out a little cosmic justice to his schoolyard tormentors. The violence is as exaggerated — and reversible — as vintage Hanna-Barbera, but the C.G.I. delivery is state of the art.  Filmed in the seaport town of Ningbo in Zhejiang Province, “CJ7” (the title is a reference to the Chinese space program) has an airy widescreen look that counters the privations of Ti and Dicky’s surroundings. Ceding the limelight to his tiny co-star — who dances in it like a pro — and reining in his everything-but-the-kitchen-sink instincts, a subdued Mr. Chow devotes his considerable creative energy to small, unexpected scenes that showcase his bizarre sense of humor. As father and son bond over a wall of scurrying roaches or Ti stumblingly hits on the gorgeous Miss Yuen (Kitty Zhang), our pleasure derives as much from the moment’s unexpectedness as from the deftness of its execution.  Unlike his previous feature, the deliriously cracked “Kung Fu Hustle” — enjoyed by many under-age fans who slipped beneath the inconvenient R rating —  “CJ7” has a brake pedal, and Mr. Chow uses it. (At one point he hits it so decisively, and so unpredictably, that the action will make you gasp.) And though the subtitles  — and some Eastern child-rearing norms — may dismay, they shouldn’t pose a problem for the average middle-schooler. Above all the movie has a heart, a mind and a gentleness of spirit that parents will welcome, while the frequent flights of fancy ensure that no child will be left behind.  “CJ7” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). Children and toys are squished, pummeled and otherwise humiliated.</text>
      <date>March 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>