<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The 1990’s, you may recall, were a golden age of cheaply made movies about white guys in their 20’s sitting around doing nothing. This is not a genre that has spawned very many sequels. The white guys who made those movies either faded away, went on to bigger things or kept making variations on the same picture again and again.  Viewed alongside his peers, Kevin Smith, the director of “Clerks” and now, 12 years later, of “Clerks II,” seems both typical and exceptional. After the success of “Clerks,” his debut, a black-and-white study in suburban convenience-store stasis  made for $27,000, he did go on to bigger (though not always better) things: among them “Mallrats,” “Chasing Amy,” “Dogma” and “Jersey Girl.” But he also kept coming back to the themes and attitudes — and to a few of the characters — that made “Clerks” an especially durable example of its type.  So “Clerks II” — which begins in familiar black and white, at the familiar Quick Stop minimarket in Leonardo, N.J., before switching to color and a fast-food restaurant down the road — can be taken either as Mr. Smith’s sentimental homecoming or as evidence of arrested development. His filmmaking technique, charmingly rudimentary when he started out, has not developed very far, but then again aesthetic polish has never been among his priorities.  He does however put the money at his disposal (not a whole lot, by the look of things, but certainly quite a bit more than $27,000) to good use, shelling out for some tasty music permissions, an imaginative custom-built set (designed by Robert Holtzman), a trained donkey (don’t ask) and, to give an aerial perspective on his show-stopping musical number, a crane.  Which is not to say that he has sold out. On the contrary, what makes “Clerks II” both winning and (somewhat unexpectedly) moving is its fidelity to the original “Clerks” ethic of hanging out, talking trash and refusing all worldly ambition. If anything, the sequel is more defiant in its disdain for the rat race, elevating the white-guy-doing-nothing prerogative from a lifestyle choice to a moral principle. This principle is upheld by Jay and Silent Bob (Jason Mewes and Mr. Smith), fixtures of the director’s universe, who function as Greek chorus and comic relief, interrupting the usual barrage of non sequiturs and smutty jokes with even more gratuitous filth and absurdity.  But the chief defender of the virtues of obnoxious laziness — most notably in a ringing, utterly sincere speech that provides the film’s emotional climax — is Randal (Jeff Anderson), the less responsible half of the underachieving twosome whose lives seem not to have changed much since the first movie. Along with his best friend, Dante (Brian O’Halloran), Randal has transferred his cynical, lazy carcass from the Quick Stop to Mooby’s, a hamburger franchise whose product names are both revolting and eerily plausible. (The signature dessert is called a Cow Pie.) Dante, always more of a worrier and a planner than his buddy, is finally ready to move on. He is about to quit Jersey for Florida with Emma (Jennifer Schwalbach), his jittery, domineering fiancée, whose father has promised Dante a job.  Complicating the plan is Dante’s devotion to Becky (Rosario Dawson), the Mooby’s manager, whose toenails he paints in the back office. The conventional romantic-comedy outlines of the story emerge almost casually, and they are camouflaged by the film’s humor, which is gleefully and abrasively obscene.  Ms. Dawson, a good sport as well as a nimble actress (her professionalism is really what holds “Clerks II” together) first appears on screen in the middle of a grossly candid discussion of sexual etiquette, to which she contributes her point of view without blushing or breaking stride.  Mr. Smith’s fondness for jokes about excrement, bestiality and related topics is so evidently childish that it is hard to be offended, or even especially provoked, when he tries to test the limits of taste. Unlike “Dogma,” his misunderstood satire on religion, “Clerks II” is not really interested in smashing taboos or exposing hypocrisy. The characters talk dirty as a way of passing the time, dispelling boredom and expressing their squeamish fascination with the messy weirdness of being human.  Randal, blithely stomping through the minefield of contemporary cultural sensitivities, is the most extreme dramatic embodiment of this sensibility. His social interactions are almost entirely abusive, especially when it comes to Elias (Trevor Fehrman), a delicate 19-year-old Christian “Lord of the Rings” fan who completes the Mooby’s work force.  Randal’s jokes at Elias’s expense are cruel (and very funny), but they also point toward the buried spring of pathos that bubbles ever closer to the surface as the movie wanders toward its end. Randal and Dante, after all, are no longer feckless 20-somethings. They are a few years into their 30’s, at an age where a lack of ambition can start to look cowardly and pathetic, less a form of resistance to social norms than a sign of psychic defeat.  As I get older, I find myself less and less sympathetic to movies that celebrate the revolt against adulthood, which have more to do with promoting an endless hedonistic consumerism than with any meaningful assertion of individual freedom. But Mr. Smith’s sincerity is disarming, and his love for his characters, even at their weakest or meanest, is hard not to share.  In the years since “Clerks” he has become a husband (he married Ms. Schwalbach in 1999) and father, as well as something of a Hollywood player, and a glimmer of tolerant adult wisdom shines through the scatology and willful immaturity. “Clerks II” has a dirty mind, but its heart is pure.  “Clerks II” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompany parent or adult guardian). It has abundant obscenity and crude sexual humor. I can’t even talk about the donkey.</text>
      <date>July 21, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>