<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Soldiers’ uniforms are supposed to blur identity and present individuals as cogs in an impersonal military machine. Look closely, however, and underneath the uniforms are people with attitudes. Rebels and cynics don’t adapt as well to enforced conformity as obedient apple polishers. And when the soldiers are young women, like Smadar (Smadar Sayar) and Mirit (Naama Schendar), spirited 18-year-old conscripts in the Israeli Army, whose routine is scrutinized  in the drama “Close to Home,” the rules change color. In countless small ways it’s different for girls.  The movie, written and directed by Vidi Bilu and Dalia Hager, is really a study of people coping with excruciating boredom and the absurd aspects of military life. Smadar and Mirit are assigned, as a team, to patrol  a sector of Jerusalem that includes the gates to the city. As Palestinian workers pour in each morning, the two women are charged with  checking their identification and filling out elaborate forms. It’s stressful work, made more so because they must exercise authority over mostly male strangers who are older, bigger and stronger.  The rules for patrolling the streets are stringent: no sitting down, no leaning on doors or walls, no cellphone calling, no eating, no smoking, no going into stores. As the days drag on, Smadar and Mirit violate them all.  The movie, much of which was shot with hand-held cameras on the streets of Jerusalem, adopts the tunnel vision of impatient, self-centered soldiers gritting their teeth as they fulfill their two-year military obligation. None of the women in the unit seem to have a greater sense of mission, and there is no talk of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict or of politics in general.  Boys and boyfriends are the No. 1 topic, followed by the petty personality conflicts you would expect in a high school corridor. When a superior officer is spotted in the area, the soldiers warn one another by cellphone to be on the alert.  The process of stopping pedestrians and bus riders is portrayed as uncomfortable for both sides. If you’ve ever stifled a bubble of rage while going through airport security, you will recognize the tensions that Smadar and Mirit must face all day, every day. And many of their days are punctuated with explosive emotional confrontations.  One Palestinian woman at a checkpoint with her young son is ordered to throw her pita bread in the garbage because a sign says not to bring food into an inspection station. When she angrily refuses, voices are raised. A man stopped on the street bluntly refuses to give his identification, and his stubbornness escalates into a shouting match involving several other pedestrians.  Of the two soldiers Smadar is the rebel and shirker and Mirit the goody-goody whom Smadar pressures into misbehaving. At one point their mutual hostility drives Mirit to request reassignment. But eventually a bond of friendship develops.  Smadar, her eyes flashing with defiance and contempt for authority, has little tolerance for frustration. During her off hours she has instigated a game in which she and a boyfriend shoplift for sport. When he objects that she hasn’t played by their rules, she turns on him viciously.  Halfway into the film a bomb explodes during one of their patrols. Mirit, knocked to the ground but uninjured, is helped by a handsome stranger who then disappears. After they catch sight of him at another location, he becomes an object of both their fantasies.  If the shock of the bombing momentarily reminds Smadar and Mirit of what they’re doing and why, they quickly forget. Shopping, flirting, haircuts, girl talk: in this small, precisely observed film, it’s the little things that loom large.  What does this all mean for Israeli security? The movie doesn’t say directly, but it acknowledges that any security system is only as effective as the vigilance and dedication of those enforcing it.</text>
      <date>February 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>