<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Enough of the ingredients for a sultry downscale noir are in place in "Coastlines," that once the film turns perversely goody-good, it leaves you feeling vaguely disgruntled, as if after consuming a rich, greasy meal, you were handed a single sugarless mint for dessert. Written, directed, and edited by Victor Nunez, the movie is the third part of his trilogy  set in the least exploited part of the Sunshine State, the Florida Panhandle. This is the scrubby coastal territory where trailers meet the Gulf, where rednecks with guns pilot yachts, where the culture of auto repair shops rubs elbows with drug smuggling and shady tourist development. When the movie pauses to survey the sullen landscape, you can almost feel the humidity dripping off your brow. Like its two forerunners in the trilogy, "Ruby in Paradise," which pushed Ashley Judd toward Hollywood stardom, and "Ulee's Gold," which won Peter Fonda the best-actor award from the New York Film Critics Circle, "Coastlines" features detailed performances that offer unusually intimate glimpses into its characters' mood swings. But if the acting captures their emotional ebbs and flows, the screenplay has  discrepancies and lapses that can't be acted around. A larger problem is the film's attempt to piece together a hard-boiled crime drama with a soft-boiled soap opera, ultimately giving precedence to the suds and adding a sickly lemon scent. Sonny (Timothy Olyphant), an ex-con; Dave (Josh Brolin), the local sheriff who is his best friend; and Dave's restless wife, Ann (Sarah Wynter), a hospital nurse, form the uneasy triangle at the center of the movie. Sonny, unexpectedly discharged from prison after serving only three years of a longer term because of overcrowding, returns home itching with impatience. Having taken the rap for his part in an unspecified drug operation, he intends to get his hands on the $200,000 owed him by his partners in crime. During his three years away, those partners, Fred Vance (William Forsythe) and Fred's  nephew Eddie (Josh Lucas), have become wealthy regional powerbrokers, untouchable by local law enforcement. If anyone reins them in, it will have to be the feds (who so far have expressed no interest) or vigilante justice. As the glowering, trigger-happy Eddie, Mr. Lucas relishes his too-brief turn as a meanie with the temper of a riled copperhead. The Vances have a history of torching their enemies' houses. Once Sonny raises a little too much hell for comfort, they blow up the shack in which he is staying with his father (Scott Wilson), an oyster farmer, killing his dad and injuring Sonny, who moves in with Dave and his family. That's when the triangle heats up. Before long there is hot sex in the kitchen between Sonny and Ann when her husband and his two little girls are out of the house. Although Ann grows increasingly testy and cold to Dave, he has barely an inkling of the affair happening under his nose. Sonny eventually moves out and stays in the back of the auto repair shop of an old friend (Robert Wisdom) who gives him a job painting cars. Sooner or later, a day of reckoning between Sonny and the Vances is inevitable. That confrontation, which takes place on the water, comes and goes too hastily and leaves too few repercussions. Meanwhile, back in the boudoir,  the affair at the movie's center would make sense only if Ann, a devoted wife, responsible mother and capable professional, were not what she appears to be. So unless she and Sonny share some undisclosed romantic history, their striking up  a relationship at this point in their lives is  far-fetched. Until Sonny appears, there are no signs of serious marital discord. Even when Ann erupts with a speech about longing for the old crazy days, it isn't enough to explain her reckless, self-destructive behavior. For all his appeal as a sizzling one-night stand, Sonny is the kind of  loser no sane person (especially a comfortably married mother of two) would invest in emotionally. It all reaches a resolution that is  as synthetic as the sweetness in that sugarless mint passed off as dessert. Instead of chocolate, you're left with the metallic taste of saccharine. The movie is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, profanity and violence.</text>
      <date>May 31, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>