<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> True to its title, “Coco Before Chanel” chronicles the early life of the woman who would become perhaps the single most influential figure in 20th-century fashion. But the film, directed and co-written by Anne Fontaine, bears less resemblance to a standard-issue biopic (like, say, “La Vie en Rose,” to take a recent French example) than to a novel by Émile Zola or Theodore Dreiser. With a mixture of brutal candor and tender sympathy, it charts the rise of an ambitious, difficult woman, taking note of the obstacles and opportunities offered by her time, place and circumstances.  The tale begins in an orphanage, where the Chanel sisters, Gabrielle and Adrienne, have been deposited by their father. An inkling of Gabrielle’s eventual vocation is provided when the audience is directed to notice her noticing the stitching on the nuns’ wimples, but for the most part Ms. Fontaine avoids the easy prefiguring that deadens so many film biographies.  She also steers clear of the kind of literal-minded psychologizing that finds the germ of future greatness in childhood trauma. Gabrielle and Adrienne, grown into Audrey Tautou and Marie Gillain, wind up in a provincial music hall, singing mildly naughty songs — one, about a lost dog named Coco, provides the nickname with which Gabrielle becomes famous — and trying not to be mistaken for the prostitutes who also frequent the place. Gabrielle, chain-smoking and sarcastic, confronts the world, and the men in it, with a wariness that borders on hostility.  She is, from the start, a complicated, frequently uncharming character, and Ms. Tautou’s fierce and sinewy performance represents a decisive break with the dimpled-pixie typecasting she has been struggling against since “Amélie.” One fact of Gabrielle’s life is that a woman without money or status  can only acquire them by attaching herself to a man, ideally as a wife but more plausibly as a mistress. And so Adrienne finds a baron to keep her, while Gabrielle, after some combative flirting, hooks up with a playboy in uniform, a worldly and cynical fellow named Étienne Balsan (Benoît Poelvoorde).  The relationship between them is affectionate, exploitive, transactional and unpredictable, and it is the most interesting aspect of “Coco Before Chanel.” With a mixture of impulsiveness and blunt premeditation Coco shows up at Étienne’s country mansion, where she installs herself as his mistress. His treatment of her is alternately gallant and appalling. For a long time he sequesters her in a back room and instructs her to eat in the kitchen, where she won’t be seen by his high society friends.  But Coco crashes their parties, befriending a flamboyant actress named Emilienne (Emmanuelle Devos) and catching the eye of an English businessman known as Boy Capel (Alessandro Nivola). His soulful sensitivity makes him appear to be everything Étienne is not, and he offers Coco and the film a vision of true love.  Ms. Fontaine indulges this romanticism but also points out the loose strings and sticking points. Boy, Coco’s ideal lover, is also something of an adventurer, a serial seducer whose only advantage over Étienne may be that he has better looks and better game. As far as acting is concerned, Mr. Poelvoorde wins. He plays each facet of Étienne’s repellent, gracious, selfish and sad personality with dazzling relish.  In any case, such judgments are not really on the movie’s agenda. Rather than take a moralizing or pitying view of its characters, who live according to the social mores of their era and the logic of their desires, Ms. Fontaine examines them with curiosity and compassion.  The result is an unusually vivid and convincing account of the historical past, composed in the present tense. Though its mood and methods are different, “Coco Before Chanel” shares with Jane Campion’s “Bright Star” — another new anti-biopic — a fascination, at once intense and dispassionate, with the lives of women in earlier centuries. Coco and Fanny Brawne, the heroine of Ms. Campion’s film, are not victims of oppression or paragons of resistance but rather individuals, made not of ideology or wishful thinking but of flesh and blood.  And clothes of course. Both Fanny and Coco start out as seamstresses with an eye for novelty and a keen aesthetic sense. Coco disdains corsets, sometimes dresses in men’s garments, and adapts simple hats and fisherman’s shirts to marvelously chic effect. The blossoming of her ambition, as much as her love life, drives the story forward, and turns “Coco Before Chanel” into a costume drama worthy of the name.  “Coco Before Chanel” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual situations and a lot of cigarettes. No nudity, though, which would be a distraction from all those lovely clothes.</text>
      <date>September 25, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>