<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Come Early Morning,” Ashley Judd returns to the Southern working-class milieu of her first screen triumph, “Ruby in Paradise,” to deliver her most natural screen performance since that film pushed her toward stardom in 1993. The career lesson it offers to an actor might be summed up in five words: Stick to what you know. In the case of Ms. Judd, who is no Meryl Streep, you can take the girl out of the trailer park, but you can’t take the trailer park out of the girl, so to speak.  Whether the setting is the coastline of the Florida Panhandle (“Ruby in Paradise”) or suburban Arkansas (“Come Early Morning”), this is a world in which Ms. Judd, who was brought up in eastern Kentucky, obviously feels at home. Disaster awaits her when she ventures too far afield, as in “De-Lovely,” the Cole Porter biography, in which she appeared frozen playing the composer’s high-society wife, Linda.  “Come Early Morning,” written and directed by the actress Joey Lauren Adams (“Chasing Amy”) and filmed in Ms. Adams’s hometown, North Little Rock, is an incisive but static and occasionally confusing character study of Lucy Fowler, a disheveled, hard-drinking single woman who has a day job as a contractor and a dissolute night life.  Off hours Lucy gets drunk at the Forge, a local bar where she hooks up for one-night stands with men she contemptuously abandons the following morning to go home to the cottage she shares with her more demure roommate, Kim (Laura Prepon). The only indications that Lucy’s heart hasn’t totally curdled are her rescuing of a stray puppy, her fondness for vintage country music and the respect her boss (Stacy Keach) has for her.  Ms. Judd reveals exactly the degree to which Lucy’s behavior is a self-perpetuating cycle sprung from her rage at her alcoholic, uncommunicative father, Lowell (Scott Wilson), a guilt-stricken womanizer and pathologically shy guitarist who has belatedly begun attending church services. Lucy seesaws between reaching out to him by accompanying him on Sunday mornings and throwing drunken tantrums when he doesn’t respond to her overtures.  As for the possibility of building a relationship with any of the men she picks up, Lucy has only to point to her grandparents (Diane Ladd and Pat Corley). Their marriage is a war of attrition that has settled into an ugly stalemate; they spend their days hurling insults back and forth in a ritual so shopworn that their lethal zingers have lost the power to wound.  These relatives, as well as the young men Lucy uses and discards, are viewed almost entirely through her eyes. If “Come Early Morning” were put on the stage, it would be a memory play whose peripheral characters appeared and disappeared in spotlights as Lucy mused aloud.  “Come Early Morning” is Ms. Adams’s filmmaking debut. She knows how these people speak and has a finely tuned awareness of their relationship to an environment where beer flows like water and the houses have cheap furniture and aluminum siding.  The minimal story follows Lucy as she meets and beds a new man, Cal (Jeffrey Donovan), who is a cut nicer than her usual hookups. Cal, who just moved to the area and is doing roofing for his uncle, treats Lucy with a courtliness that both infuriates and embarrasses her. He takes her frog fishing, cooks up a frog’s-leg feast and enlists her help in painting toy models of old cars (his passion). Her defenses begin to crumble.  The principal question hovering through this teensy but pungent slice of life is whether Lucy’s self-destructive mechanism will kick in. And if it does, how soon will the patience of her potential knight in shining armor wear thin? The mixture of Southern machismo and tenderness in Mr. Donovan’s performance makes his working-class charmer almost too good to be true, or least too good for Lucy, whom Ms. Judd plays with a vindictive edge that risks making her unsympathetic. And that takes courage.  “Come Early Morning” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has some profanity, sexual situations and a bar brawl.</text>
      <date>November 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>