<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Anyone who has cringed while watching the home movies of newlyweds bumbling through their own corny, personalized nuptials will appreciate the comic potential of the British mock documentary “Confetti.” The title is also the name of the movie’s fictional bridal magazine, whose editors dream up a contest in which three pairs of panting exhibitionists, aided by wedding planners, compete to win an award for most original wedding concept. The winning couple will be featured on the magazine’s cover and given an ugly, expensive new house in which to try living happily ever after.  Conceived and directed by Debbie Isitt and improvised by a moderately clever cast of British television regulars, “Confetti” is obviously inspired by Christopher Guest’s “Best in Show,” in which Mr. Guest and his brilliant repertory company turned a dog show into an incisive satirical microcosm of everything wonderful and weird about American pet owners.  But as you watch this pallid British imitation, which has two or three laugh-out-loud moments at best, you long for the American crew’s X-ray vision. “Confetti” lacks Mr. Guest and his company’s shared understanding that each person is a miniature comic planet with its own quirky climate, whirling in its own eccentric orbit.  Content to go only a third of the way to the bottom of its characters, the movie gives each a few comic tics and leaves it at that. The first couple we meet, Matt (Martin Freeman) and Sam (Jessica Stevenson), are tone-deaf sweethearts fixated on the idea of singing their I do’s in a ceremony staged as a Busby Berkeley-style Hollywood musical.  Josef (Stephen Mangan), a fading tennis pro, and his Canadian fiancée, Isabelle (Meredith MacNeill), contrive a tennis-theme wedding with dancing ball boys and a referee for a preacher. Grimly competitive, with a streak of paranoia, Josef is prepared to cry foul if another couple wins.  The final pair, Michael (Robert Webb) and Joanna (Olivia Colman), are dedicated nudists first glimpsed riding bicycles in the buff with other tubs of unclothed flesh. The selection of their “naturist” wedding for the contest doesn’t make sense in view of the magazine’s refusal to put nudity on its cover.  The most fully realized (and Guest-like) inventions are the overtaxed wedding planners, Archie (Vincent Franklin) and Gregory (Jason Watkins), a pair of dowdy, hyperemotional gay fussbudgets who like to dress identically and who take their work with utmost gravity. In the frantic days before the contest each has a meltdown.  The movie throws in subsidiary comic characters, but most contribute little in the way of fun. One happy exception is Matt’s best man, Snoopy (Marc Wootton), a hostile rock ’n’ roller whose notion of an original wedding anthem is a nasty, profane putdown of a girlfriend. (He eventually settles on a rock version of “Cheek to Cheek.”)  The biggest letdown is the contest itself: a tacky three-ring circus that is not nearly exaggerated (or inept) enough to explode into comic madness and is undermined by a lurking sentimentality. Matt and Sam are somehow able to chirp their vows in tune. Josef and Isabelle’s balletic tennis match has an oddly surreal grace. Michael and Joanna’s silly fig-leaf ceremony, at the end of which the leaves are shed, has no maniacal spark. “Confetti” ultimately lacks nerve and imagination.  “Confetti” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has several scenes of nudity.</text>
      <date>September 15, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>