<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ou may recall that in the "Matrix" trilogy, Keanu Reeves played a haunted, expressionless traveler between metaphysical realms whose mission was to unravel a vast, complicated plot to ... well, to do something very bad involving a lot of computer-generated imagery. It may therefore not surprise you to learn that Mr. Reeves, in "Constantine," a new theological thriller from Warner Brothers, plays a haunted, expressionless traveler ... but you get the idea. The thing is, this time his character, John Constantine, wears a skinny tie, white shirt and dark suit combination almost exactly like the one worn by Agent Smith, who was Mr. Reeves's archnemesis in the "Matrix" pictures. I'm still trying to get my mind around that. In the meantime, I will try to reconstruct some impression of "Constantine," which all evidence, save my own memory, insists that I saw not long ago. It's coming back now: a promising opening, somewhere in the Mexican desert, where a dusty scavenger finds a pointy object (a bit of preliminary text has dropped the clue that it might be the Spear of Destiny) and is promptly crushed by a car that drops from the sky. He survives, sprouts an ominous tattoo and sets off for Los Angeles to bring about the apocalypse. Meanwhile, John Constantine is wearily patrolling the border between this world and the one below - a landscape bathed in flaming caramel syrup in which there seem to be an awful lot of cars. (Are cars capable of sin, or do some sinners get to take their wheels with them to hell? This is one of many intriguing doctrinal questions never answered by "Constantine.") His work is pretty routine - performing exorcisms, deporting undocumented demons, glowering - until a conspiracy involving the son of the devil threatens to upset the traditional balance between good and evil and throw the world into chaos. This is similar to the premise of "Little Nicky," an Adam Sandler abomination released in 2000, with Harvey Keitel as Satan, a role here taken by Peter Stormare. But of course "Constantine," directed by Francis Lawrence in glossy music-video style from a script by Kevin Brodbin and Frank Cappello, takes itself much more seriously, with a few clumsy moments of attempted wit. Based on the DC/Vertigo comic book "Hellblazer," the movie tries for a stylized, expressionistic pop grandeur - the kind of eerie, dreamy visual environment that made the first "Matrix" so intriguing - but its look is sticky, murky and secondhand. Its plot unfolds according to the usual numbing alternation of special effects-aided jolts and portentous exposition, most of it involving spurious Bible verses and occultist mumbo jumbo. Assisting Mr. Reeves are Rachel Weisz, as a Los Angeles police detective whose twin sister (also Ms. Weisz) has jumped off the roof of a hospital, and Shia LeBeouf, as Constantine's eager young sidekick and chauffeur. Djimon Hounsou plays a witch doctor and nightclub owner imaginatively named Midnite, Pruitt Taylor Vince plays an alcoholic priest imaginatively named Father Hennessy, and Tilda Swinton is the Angel Gabriel, adding a touch of high-class celestial cross-dressing to this overblown, overlong attempt - which falls just short of success - to make a movie dumber than "Van Helsing." "Constantine" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has many scenes of gruesome violence and occult, demonic themes.</text>
      <date>February 18, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>