<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Conversations With Other Women,” his debut feature, Hans Canosa splits the screen in two as he observes a man and a woman — their names are never supplied — talking themselves and each other into a one-night stand. The visual gimmick may be the most interesting thing about the film, which otherwise has the studied archness of an over-reaching play (the script is by Gabrielle Zevin). But the split-screen technique also makes the brittle, syncopated exchanges between the characters more absorbing than they might otherwise have been.  Occasionally one side of the frame is taken up by a flashback or an imagined scene taking place somewhere other than the hotel where the two principals, played by Aaron Eckhart and Helena Bonham Carter, meet. For the most part, though, the paired images present differently angled, simultaneous views of the same thing: the man and woman flirting, bantering and occasionally saying what is really on their minds.  The seam down the middle of the frame divides the man from the woman even when they’re together, emphasizing their mutual isolation and also fracturing the standard film grammar, in which shot is followed by countershot. Here the wounding or revealing word and the reaction to it occur on the same plane at the same time, so that the viewer’s attention is emotionally and psychologically, as well as literally, in two places at once.  This displacement mirrors — perhaps a bit too closely — the experience of the central, temporary couple. They meet at the wedding of the man’s sister, where the woman has been hastily pressed into service as a bridesmaid. Seeing her sneaking off for a cigarette, he follows with two glasses of Champagne and a devilish gleam in his eye. But this attempted pickup is not quite what it seems, even though the two of them pretend, for a little while, to be strangers. It turns out that they know each other quite well, having been married — we see their younger, skinnier selves (Nora Zehetner and Erik Eidem) meeting, falling in love and parting — some years earlier.  Now in their late 30’s, they have moved on. She lives in London and is married to a slightly older cardiologist, while he is living with a dancer who is barely out of college. Whether their encounter is a discreet roll in the hay for old time’s sake or a desperate, sad attempt to recapture a lost past is not entirely clear — not to them at any rate. They try to sustain the lighthearted naughtiness appropriate to a brief, spontaneous fling, but other, stronger emotions reveal themselves: guilt, regret, love.  None of it is quite believable — the film is too studied, too forward in its conceits to be entirely satisfying — but Mr. Eckhart and Ms. Bonham Carter approach their roles with intelligence and conviction. Their personalities are as different as their accents, but both are convincingly complicated.  He dances along the fault line between sweetheart and jerk, while she swings from fragile to ruthless in the space of a single breath. Their chemistry is volatile and unpredictable, and they engage your curiosity even though “Conversations With Other Women” is too thin and forced to allow you to care about them.</text>
      <date>August 11, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>