<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Couples Retreat” is a comedy of exhaustion. I don’t mean that the four couples in question — three married and one a post-divorce May-September rebound — are suffering from conjugal fatigue. They are, but not in any interesting or revealing way. It is the comedy itself, in both concept and execution, that seems tired.  The cast includes a lot of familiar faces: Jason Bateman, Ken Jeong, John Michael Higgins and a bunch of others. The script was written (along with Dana Fox) by Jon Favreau and Vince Vaughn, who also star. Some of the jokes are mildly risqué, some are mildly funny and nearly all have a slightly dented, tattered aspect, as if they had been dug out of a Hollywood Goodwill drop box for used gags.  Speaking of the needy, I think I mentioned that Vince Vaughn stars in this movie, vacantly ambling through yet another iteration of his neurotic-fussbudget-trapped-in-the-body-of-a-stevedore persona. This time his name is Dave, and he’s married to Ronnie (Malin Akerman), with whom he leads a life overloaded by kids, home renovations and the usual burdens of domestic bliss.  His pals are much less blissful. Jason (Mr. Bateman) and Cynthia (Kristen Bell), supercompulsive yuppies, are on the verge of divorce because they can’t conceive a child. Joey (Mr. Favreau) and Lucy (Kristin Davis), high-school sweethearts whose teenage daughter is about to leave the nest, are on the verge of divorce for reasons that seem to have been left on the editing-room floor. Shane (Faizon Love) has already split from his wife (Tasha Smith), who arises from the editing-room floor near the end to do something that seems surprising only because the film is so haphazardly and incoherently put together.  Shane is with a 20-year-old named Trudy (Kali Hawk), who calls him Daddy. They join the rest of the couples on a tropical counseling vacation on a palm-studded island, during which the hapless eight are subjected to some of the weariest jokes about therapy, yoga, men in saunas and other hilarious matters. The place is run by a guru played by Jean Reno, one of whose minions plays Guitar Hero with Mr. Vaughn, while another one talks with a funny accent. Things take a shocking turn when —  —  Sorry, I was dozing off, thinking of another movie. Things do not take a surprising turn in “Couples Retreat,” which was directed by Peter Billingsley. It seems to have been hastily trimmed down to PG-13 acceptability, which means that some of the raunch implied in the trailers that began running in theaters over the summer has been lost. Not that I miss it. An R-rated version of this mess would be only more gratingly dishonest as it tried to hide its weak sentimentality behind a fig leaf of vulgarity.  Instead, some vague intimations of satire are abandoned, as if therapists, yoga instructors, Guitar Hero-playing twits and married people might have their feelings hurt if anything too funny happened. And so not much does. Mr. Vaughn whines after being grazed by a shark. Mr. Bateman and Ms. Bell argue cutely. Mr. Favreau and Ms. Davis ogle and snarl. Mr. Love is the funny fat guy. The lesson is that everyone should have skipped the retreat and stayed home in bed. I wish I had.  “Couples Retreat” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). People wear bathing suits and talk about sex.</text>
      <date>October 9, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>