<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Because of concerns about climate change, a lot of current environmentalist advocacy — including movies like “An Inconvenient Truth” — concentrates on the dire results of burning fossil fuels. Joe Berlinger’s “Crude,” a thorough and impassioned new documentary, focuses its gaze on production rather than consumption. The film, which follows the fitful progress of a class-action lawsuit undertaken on behalf of the people  of the Ecuadorean Amazon, is not about the unintended consequences of using petroleum.  Instead, it examines the terrible, frequently unacknowledged costs of extracting oil from the ground.  “Crude,” in other words, investigates the local manifestations — cancer, contaminated water, cultural degradation — of a global problem. It also, more by what it shows than what it says, suggests that such a distinction is no longer tenable.  Multinational corporations (like Chevron, this film’s designated villain) move money and commodities from one place to another, often with slight regard for the sovereignty or customs of any place in particular. And so the lawyers and activists who oppose these conglomerates have tried to  become equally mobile and adaptable, moving continually in the zigzagging paths traced by transnational capitalism.  Even as “Crude” dwells on a single, relatively small slice of territory (about the size of Rhode Island), its action shifts from muddy villages in Amazonia to law offices and shareholders’ meetings in the steel-and-glass cities of North America, drawing into its purview a motley cast of scientists, human rights crusaders, civil servants and international celebrities.  Like almost every other recent documentary on a politically charged topic, “Crude” does not pretend to neutrality. Yet while  Mr. Berlinger’s sympathies clearly lie with the oddly matched pair of lawyers — Steven Donziger, a big, outgoing American, and Pablo Fajardo, a wiry, diffident Ecuadorean — who are consumed by the now 16-year-old suit against Chevron, he is fair-minded enough to include rebuttals from the company’s executives and in-house environmental scientists.  And since this is, in part, a courtroom drama, both sides have a chance to be heard. The Ecuadorean practice of conducting parts of the trial in the field generates some oddly theatrical moments as lawyers deliver florid,  impromptu speeches al fresco, in front of huts or at the edges of waste sites.  Too many filmmakers seem to think that a noble cause, a good heart and a digital video camera are all that is required for an effective documentary. Luckily, Mr. Berlinger has both a strong narrative instinct and a keen eye for incongruous, evocative and powerful images. His previous work includes the thoughtful true-crime stories “Brother’s Keeper” and “Paradise Lost” and also the superb heavy-metal psychodrama “Metallica: Some Kind of Monster.” What these films have in common with one another, and with “Crude,” which Mr. Berlinger worked on for three years, is a strong sense of character and an openness to the unexpected.  Even as this film presses its muckraking agenda, it does so with a welcome sense of human foible and contradiction. Mr. Fajardo, who worked in the oil fields as a young man, blames Chevron (current owner of Texaco, which opened up his home region to drilling) for many of the ills that have befallen his family and his people. In the course of “Crude” he becomes something of a star in the Western news and entertainment media, profiled in Vanity Fair, showered with awards and posing for pictures with Sting after a benefit concert.  Meanwhile, Chevron’s Ecuadorean lawyers portray the suit as a money-making scheme bankrolled by a Manhattan law firm, and base their defense simultaneously on appealing  to national pride and   blaming  the state-run petroleum company, which took over from Texaco in the early 1990s. The case takes an interesting swerve when Rafael Correa, a young economist with populist tendencies, is elected Ecuador’s president and publicly supports the plaintiffs’ position.  But “Crude” presents no easy resolution, since the legal struggle — and the public relations war between big companies and those who feel preyed upon by them — is unlikely to end soon. Behind that conflict lies a long and complicated history, and ahead of us lie many more documentaries similar in tone and spirit to this one. We can hope that at least a few of them are as intelligently and artfully made.</text>
      <date>September 9, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>