<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Terrorism and antiterrorism are growth industries in politics, in culture and in the streets. The dispatches from Iraq and elsewhere detailing the latest suicide bombings are now steadily matched by an outpouring of fiction and nonfiction books and films on terrorism, much of which seems designed to freak the rest of us out, either for the sake of information or entertainment. Everybody wants a piece of the action. Five years ago the French novelist Michel Houellebecq capped his novel "Platform" with a terrorist attack; next week John Updike, who has little use for Mr. Houellebecq, will publish "Terrorist," about a would-be suicide bomber from New Jersey.  Nonfiction, of course, is particularly rich terrain for the new terrorist-studies industry, with books like "Terror in the Name of God: Why Religious Militants Kill," "Dying to Win: The Strategic Logic of Suicide Terrorism" and "The Road to Martyrs' Square: A Journey Into the World of the Suicide Bomber." Conveniently, those with neither the time nor the inclination to thumb through hundreds of pages of text can turn to an easier-to-digest précis like "The Cult of the Suicide Bomber," an engrossing if intellectually thin documentary that purports to explain how suicide bombing — which its narrator, Robert Baer, likens to a "pathological virus" — evolved from a weapon of war into a weapon of terror and, finally in Iraq, a "weapon of chaos."  "The Cult of the Suicide Bomber" was made for Channel 4 in Britain, where it was broadcast in August 2005. Mr. Baer, a former operative for the Central Intelligence Agency and the inspiration for the character played by George Clooney in "Syriana," serves as the film's on- and off-camera center of gravitas, fluidly switching from English to Arabic and Persian; its directors are David Batty and Kevin Toolis. Mr. Baer wrote the film along with Mr. Toolis, who has contributed scores of articles to various British publications. In 2004 he wrote in The New Statesman: "In our baffling, violent world, the terrorism expert, discreetly hinting at access to cryptic intelligence material, is the high priest, able to discern within the entrails of atrocity a fingerprint and a culprit."  The high priests of "The Cult of the Suicide Bomber" begin their story in modern Iran, with a cleric speaking before hundreds of male worshippers who are enthusiastically repeating his calls for "death to America." From there we jump to the seventh century and Imam Hussein, the grandson of the Prophet Muhammad, whose martyrdom was strategically adopted by Ayatollah Khomeini in Iran's war with Iraq in the 1980's. Faced with Saddam Hussein's superior military strength, Iran "turned martyrdom into a state religion," Mr. Baer says, using children and the young for suicide missions. This war, he contends, employing the film's unfortunate Guinness records-style taxonomy, created the first suicide bomber. Sometime later Mr. Baer also introduces us to what he calls the first suicide car bomber and the first female suicide bomber.  Like so many political films of this type made for British television, this documentary contains more information than analysis, not to mention predictably spooky music. Despite its title, this is not a film about the cult of suicide bombings in general; rather, it is about a specific cult that has developed in the Middle East over the last few decades.  There is no mention of the Assassins, radical Shiite Muslims, who, in Persia and Syria in the 11th and 12th centuries, committed murder and ritual suicide in the name of faith; no inquiry into Japanese kamikaze pilots. More to the contemporary point, both the Tamil Tigers and Chechen terrorists, including the self-detonating black widows in Russia, are mentioned only in passing.  Despite Mr. Toolis's active editorializing in the British press (he has called President Bush a warmonger, among other names), the filmmakers do their best to appear neutral. That said, Mr. Baer does, somewhat provocatively, say of one Hezbollah bomber who drove a car onto an Israeli military base in 1982, "If he had dropped a bomb from a plane on the Israeli military headquarters, would we think of him any differently?" The filmmakers don't answer this question, maybe because they can't. The weight of all the historical and political analysis in the world may simply not be enough to explain the smiles and pacific mien of the men and women who appear in those pre-mission suicide videotapes with which we have all become so lamentably familiar.  Consider, in this respect, an article by Nasra Hassan, published in The New Yorker in November 2001, in which a member of Hamas who had tried and failed to blow up a bus filled with Israeli passengers described what he had felt before undertaking his mission. "We were in a constant state of worship," said the would-be martyr. "We told each other that if the Israelis only knew how joyful we were, they would whip us to death! Those were the happiest days of my life.</text>
      <date>June 2, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>