<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Almost inevitably, the rising career of a movie star's son will be beset by comparisons with his more famous father. Scott Caan, the 28-year-old son of James Caan, confronts this Oedipal problem head-on in his directorial debut, "Dallas 362," which he also wrote and in which he has a co-starring role. The story - about the son of a rodeo cowboy struggling to emerge from his late father's shadow - cannot help echoing the relationship between Scott Caan and his own father. The film tracks the troubled friendship between Rusty (Shawn Hatosy) and Dallas (Mr. Caan), two boys just out of their teens whose lives have become stalled in an endless cycle of drinking, bar fights and minor arrests. At the end of her rope, Rusty's mother, Mary (Kelly Lynch), sends her son to a pot-smoking psychologist, Bob (Jeff Goldblum). Soon Bob is simultaneously treating Rusty and falling in love with his mother. The therapist's unconventional methods help Rusty to imagine a better life for himself, even as his friend Dallas sinks further into a world of pool-hall brawls and petty crime. As a writer and actor, Mr. Caan seems more comfortable with men than with women; the scenes between him and Mr. Hatosy, in which the insults they trade function as a kind of secret code for their deep attachment, are deftly and movingly sketched. But when romantic subplots intrude, the film's execution feels less assured. Mr. Goldblum and Ms. Lynch are superbly cast as the neurotic middle-aged lovers, but the dialogue in the scenes they share lacks emotional heft. A young blonde named Amanda (Marley Shelton) makes a brief appearance to embody Rusty's dream girl and then disappears from the story entirely. In another less-than-compelling subplot, Val Lauren (who has a recurring role on television's "24") plays a small-time criminal with a persecution complex and a grating, whiny voice, an odd amalgam of Jerry Lewis and Sal Mineo. "It's a whole thing" is this film's catchphrase,  a line the two boys use to gesture inarticulately toward the complexity of any subject they can't understand. Mr. Caan's debut film is not quite a whole thing, but it offers up enough promising fragments to make his sophomore effort worth watching for. "Dallas 362"  is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language, violence and one brief and relatively chaste nude scene.</text>
      <date>June 24, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>