<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  Back in the old, pre-cable days, “Wide World of Sports” on ABC used to promise “the thrill of victory and the agony of defeat.” That famous catchphrase contained an implicit recognition of a fact seldom acknowledged in America’s triumphalist sports culture, namely that failure can be as compelling as success, sometimes even more so.  Maybe England is different. In any case, “The Damned United” is the rare sports movie that deals with — indeed positively relishes — humiliation and disappointment. Its real-life protagonist, the soccer coach Brian Clough (who died in 2004), was, over his long career, a winner with an extraordinary record of accomplishment. But the film, directed by Tom Hooper from Peter Morgan’s script (based on a novel by David Peace), is much more interested in the dramatic flameout that disrupted and almost ended his rise to football glory.  You’ve probably seen a dozen movies — “Hoosiers,” “Glory Road,” even “Slap Shot” — in which a tough coach takes a squad of misfits and underachievers and turns them into champions. Clough (Michael Sheen), perhaps uniquely in the annals of sporting cinema, reverses the process. Hired with great fanfare in 1974 to manage the mighty Leeds United club, he alienates players, fans and management and sends the team into a tailspin. At his very first practice he tells the Leeds stars, who play a rough, mean brand of football, that they are not champions but thugs and cheaters. Oddly, they resist his invitation to reform their ways.  One theme “The Damned United” explores is the difficulty of filling the shoes of a beloved, charismatic leader. Clough takes over Leeds after its longtime manager, Don Revie (Colm Meaney), assumes the leadership of the English national team. Over the years, Revie has become the personification of his team and a hero of West Yorkshire. A hard act for anyone to follow, but especially vexing for Clough, whose obsession with Revie — a combination of rivalry and idolatry, visceral loathing and disappointed love — turns out to be as much a driving force in his career as his own ambition.  The two men are a study in temperamental and generational contrasts. Revie, solid and phlegmatic, is an English bulldog of the old school, while Clough is more like a rooster, crowing and strutting in pursuit of his own celebrity. He is a complicated fellow, and while the filmmakers are fascinated by his self-aggrandizing motives and his self-defeating behavior, they are not entirely sympathetic.  Mr. Hooper switches back and forth between Clough’s doomed tenure at Leeds and his earlier experience transforming a hapless provincial club called Derby County into a respectable upper-division contender. He was helped by Peter Taylor (Timothy Spall), his loyal right-hand man, and frequently stymied by the team’s chairman, a cigar-chewing, Monopoly-board plutocrat played by Jim Broadbent. Needless to say, Mr. Spall and Mr. Broadbent do a great deal to enliven “The Damned United,” in the way that only great British character actors can.  And Mr. Sheen, for his part, expands his remarkable anthology of famous modern Britons, turning the actor’s art into a form of Plutarchan character study. I can’t assess the accuracy of the portrait — provincial American part-time soccer dad that I am, I had never heard of Brian Clough before — and it obviously is not complete. But Mr. Sheen’s performance is persuasive and illuminating not only of the man’s doubts and aspirations but also, as if from within, of his world.  Clough’s vanity and his inability to control his speech or foresee its effects land him in trouble, and the film is wise not to blow these up into tragic flaws. He is not Prince Hal or Coriolanus, but rather a creature of the modern, media-saturated world. “The Damned United” shares with “The Queen” and “Frost/Nixon” not only a writer and a star, but also a precise and satisfying sense of proportion.  In all three films, Mr. Sheen plays a fast-moving, clever, insecure man whose momentum is stalled by a stubborn, somewhat enigmatic older figure. Don Revie is for Brian Clough what Richard Nixon is to David Frost and Queen Elizabeth is to Tony Blair: a nemesis, a symbol, the possessor of an elusive and archaic, almost magical kind of power. As the confrontation between these magi and their would-be acolytes (or usurpers) unfolds, an entire social order snaps into focus.  And so in “The Damned United” we perceive an angry, tired and polarized Britain, split between old ways and new, between North and South, between Labor and Tory. Football is the mirror and outlet for these resentments, but the movie to its credit (if also to the potential dismay of some fans) does not really bother with what happens on the field. That’s a mere diversion from the real drama, which involves power, money and men in suits.  “The Damned United” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). British football fans, players and coaches swear a lot when they’re upset. Also when they’re happy. Pretty much when they’re awake.</text>
      <date>October 9, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>