<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Dare,” written by David Brind, directed by Adam Salky and based on their short film of the same title, stakes out familiar territory and, true to its name, strikes out in some risky new directions. This high school semi-romance, which blends comic and tearful moods, is at once more provocative and more contemplative than most of its big-screen counterparts. On television and in young-adult novels, candor —  or prurience —  about teenage behavior is the norm, but Hollywood movies tend to keep one foot firmly planted in a more innocent world.  Alexa (Emmy Rossum), at least at first, seems to embody an established teen-comedy archetype. She is a modest dresser, a diligent student and generally a cautious, sensible college-track soul. She’s also the star of her drama class, but her interest in acting may have more to do with academic ambition than with creative passion. That, at least, is what she hears from an alumnus of her school, now a successful stage actor (slyly played by Alan Cumming), when he returns to his alma mater to give a master class.  Though Alexa desperately wants to impress this visitor, he is transfixed by Johnny (Zach Gilford), her scene partner, a lazy and distracted student with no apparent interest in acting at all. Johnny does, however, have brooding good looks and a languorous sexuality that might be called Brandoesque. (The scene he and Alexa have prepared is from “A Streetcar Named Desire.”)  And so, at a party she hadn’t planned on attending, Alexa throws herself at Johnny, relieving herself of her virginity in an act of calculated recklessness. Her best friend, a timid, sexually confused nerd named Ben (Ashley Springer), follows suit, and a wobbly bisexual triangle takes shape.  As it develops, “Dare” lays out some interesting psychological puzzles, though the filmmakers lack the technique to explore them as thoroughly as you might wish. The film’s tone falters at times but nonetheless remains focused on intriguing questions about the nature of social and erotic power. Most interesting is the way the perspective shifts, so that Alexa and Ben, who start out as misfits in thrall to Johnny’s charisma, end up using him for their own purposes, even as his vulnerability becomes increasingly apparent.  Ms. Rossum, Mr. Gilford and Mr. Springer handle this material a bit more deftly than the director does and keep the movie engaging even when it slips and wanders. “Dare” feels a bit unfinished, at once overreaching and underrealized. But there is a lot of intelligence, and considerable daring, in the basic conceit. You might say that Mr. Salky and Mr. Brind have tried to combine John Hughes with Rainer Werner Fassbinder, an effort that is much less crazy, and far more persuasive, than it might sound.  “Dare” is rated R. It has sexual situations involving teenagers.</text>
      <date>November 13, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>