<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Make that dark, stagnant water. A dull and occasionally risible remake of an even duller, more risible Japanese horror flick, "Dark Water" stars Jennifer Connelly as a single mother trying to find her bearings. What makes this redo more tolerable than the usual recycled junk isn't the presence of the Academy Award-winning actress, a first-rate weeper who looks good soaking wet. Or that of the respected director Walter Salles, late of "The Motorcycle Diaries," whose deadly serious style here suggests he thought he was remaking "Medea" or, at the very least, a Roman Polanski chiller. It's that this is a horror movie about being shut out of the Manhattan real estate market.  The Web site for Roosevelt Island insists that the East River isle is "a director's dream!," but for Ms. Connelly's character, the soon to be heavily watered Dahlia, it's a nightmare. After she separates from her husband, Kyle (Dougray Scott), who tends to call her "crazy" at every opportunity, Dahlia confronts one of the most brutal truths to face many a New Yorker: she can't afford to live in Manhattan. (The more pragmatic Kyle, meanwhile, has moved to Jersey City.) Bravely steeling herself against this calamity, she takes her daughter, Ceci (Ariel Gade), by the hand and hops a tram to Roosevelt Island. As they glide above the island's hulking towers and grim-faced hoi polloi, rain falling like tears, Ceci cries out, "Mommy, that's not the city!"  Nor is it Oz, despite the somewhat puckish presence of the always-reliable John C. Reilly as a gently sleazy management agent, Mr. Murray. One of the few niceties about "Dark Water" is that though there's nothing to be done with the hopeless screenplay - written by Rafael Yglesias and based on both the original film by Hideo Nakata and a novel by Koji Suzuki - the supporting players are just dandy. Rounding out the cast are Pete Postlethwaite as a skulking janitor, Camryn Manheim as a concerned schoolteacher and, best of all, Tim Roth as a lawyer who takes Dahlia under wing without soliciting either sacks of cash or a freebie. To watch Mr. Roth smoothly steal his scenes is to regret that this forceful actor doesn't appear in more films.  The plot basically hangs on that Japanese horror movie staple, a little girl who may or may not be a ghost. Soon after Dahlia and Ceci move into their new digs, a small ceiling stain starts to spread at an alarming rate. Although the apartment upstairs is supposed to be empty, having been abandoned by its previous tenants, someone keeps running across its uncarpeted floor and leaving the water running. As the pitter-patter continues and the stain grows, creeping across the ceiling like a malevolent hand, Dahlia becomes jittery, almost hysterical, and very wet. Her husband's favorite slur begins to seem like a diagnosis and for a brief spell it's unclear, much as it is throughout "Rosemary's Baby," whether we're watching a horror film or a paranoid-woman movie.  Too bad we're watching neither. Wildly overproduced and filled with fussy flourishes that make even a derelict hallway look like a million bucks, "Dark Water" fails to rustle up either meaning or meaningful scares. Weighted down with some two-bit psychology and portentously soppy flashbacks involving the none-too-terrifying presence of the cult actress Elina Lowensohn, the film ends up neither fish nor fowl. It's absent the heft of A-level horror ("The Silence of the Lambs") as well as the lightness of touch of those few contemporary horror movies that whether pitched at the multiplex or the art house, replicate the no-frills instrumentality of authentic B's ("28 Days Later"). In these films, horror rules, not, as is true of "Dark Water," the filmmakers' palpable distaste for this oft-abused genre.  "Dark Water" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). The film has a few mild "boo!" moments and a couple of bloodless deaths that may be too intense for the young and easily frightened.</text>
      <date>July 8, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>