<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>he title character of "Dear Frankie," a heaping bowl of Scottish blarney, is a sweet-natured 9-year-old deaf boy (Jack McElhone) who lives a fugitive existence with his beautiful mother, Lizzie (Emily Mortimer), and his chain-smoking grandmother, Nell (Mary Riggans). As the story begins, the family, forced to move every few months to avoid being tracked down by Frankie's violent, abusive father, relocates to a shabby new home. Frankie knows nothing of his unhappy family history. He was too young to remember his father or the assaults that drove Lizzie to flee. His happiness revolves around bogus handwritten letters written by his mother posing as his devoted but absent father, who is supposedly a merchant seaman on the H.M.S. Accra, a name she makes up. On Frankie's bedroom wall hangs a map on which he meticulously marks all the ports the fictional ship and sailor have visited. A day of reckoning suddenly looms, when Frankie learns that an actual ship named the Accra is scheduled to make a one-day stopover and begs to meet his dad. Rather than revealing the truth, Lizzie desperately scrounges around for a credible impersonator. Only a movie could come up with the dreamboat she finds through a friend to play the role. When the handsome stranger (Gerard Butler), a member of the actual Accra's crew, appears on the doorstep, he and Lizzie make as pretty a picture as Brad Pitt and Julia Roberts. Mr. Butler (the Phantom in "Phantom of the Opera") proves to be Instant Superdad, a rugged, attentive hero only a tad less wonderful than Superman himself. As he warms to his role, his reserve melts, and he and Frankie establish a touching bond. Mr. Perfect and Lizzie meanwhile have discreet eyes for each other. "Dear Frankie" exhibits a modicum of shame. If it were a Hollywood product, it would have pushed the couple headlong into passion. Even though it doesn't, the movie, directed by Shona Auerbach, remains a fraudulent yarn riddled with plot holes and improbabilities and topped by a cynical final twist that pulls the rug out from under the story. This Miramax movie epitomizes the style some critics jokingly call "Miramax porn." The term refers to manipulative tearjerkers like "Dear Frankie" whose sensitive performances, along with a light dusting of grit, allow them to be marketed as art films. This one is clever enough to fool a lot of people. "Dear Frankie" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>March 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>