<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Thomas Vinterberg, the director of "Dear Wendy," and Lars von Trier, its screenwriter, collaborated previously on the Dogma 95 manifesto, now marking its 10th anniversary, which set out to revitalize cinema by imposing a set of strict and arbitrary rules - a "vow of chastity" - on filmmakers. Mr. Vinterberg went on to direct "The Celebration" (1998), the only Dogma movie made so far with a legitimate claim to greatness. Mr. von Trier has moved on to other provocations, most recently a trilogy, of which two parts ("Dogville" and "Manderlay") have been completed, set in imaginary American small towns.  "Dear Wendy," filmed in Denmark, takes place in an American mining hamlet with the peculiar name Estherslope. Given a harsh, grainy beauty by the cinematographer Anthony Dod Mantle (whose credits include "Dogville" and Danny Boyle's "28 Days Later"), it is an expectedly bleak and violent place. A miner's son named Dick (Jamie Bell, who was also, curiously enough, a miner's son in "Billy Elliot") gathers a group of disaffected young people into a club called the Dandies. They are pacifists obsessed with handguns, which they collect and fire in an abandoned mine building. They refer to their firearms as their "partners" and give them names. Dick's, a dainty pearl-handled revolver that he initially mistakes for a toy, is called Wendy, and the story is presented as a letter he is writing to her.  At least he can be bothered to write. Mr. von Trier, in contrast, seems to have pulled the script out of his ear (which is not especially attuned to the idioms of American English). Though "Dogville" and "Manderlay" have infuriated some critics for their assumptions about American life and baffled others with their minimal sets and eccentric stage effects, they are nonetheless governed by a rigorous narrative economy. Here, the story is laughably incoherent, which would be less bothersome if the movie were not also so unremittingly pretentious. It gestures in all sorts of allegorical directions, but the only idea you can take away from it is that the Zombies, whose music is featured on the soundtrack, were an underrated band.  Fine. In the meantime, it is painful to watch actors as gifted as Mr. Bell, Mark Webber (who plays Stevie, the Trotsky to Dick's Lenin) and Bill Pullman (as the town sheriff) address themselves so seriously to such a piece of nonsense. And it is disappointing to see filmmakers who have in the past been so aggressively forward-thinking take another step toward intellectual bankruptcy.</text>
      <date>September 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>