<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ave Katz is a young white reporter who wants to be black. He works for a magazine called The Mic and is given a dream assignment, to go behind the scenes for three weeks with Jay-Z and Damon, the star rappers of Roc-A-Fella Records. His editor (Rashida Jones) doesn't want the same old stuff, she says. (And she will be the last female character in the film who does anything beyond looking hot in a bikini top.) Watching the rest of Damon Dash's playful movie is like entering a room where a large, too noisy party is going on and never fully adjusting to the dark or the din. At one point, the film presents subtitles to translate the street language, but that was a lot funnier when the disaster spoof "Airplane" did it for Barbara Billingsley ("I speak jive") 25 years ago. Dave (Ebon Moss-Bachrach) puts on his best baggy clothes, bling and street attitude and introduces himself to hip-hop's beautiful people. Dave takes the jitney out to the Hamptons, where, he says, "they just brought the 'hood to the beach." He smokes a joint the size of a flute and apologizes later for getting a little crazy. He watches as Lyor Cohen (the director James Toback) tells Damon (Capone) that his career with Roc-A-Fella is over. With what seems like unnecessary cruelty. "No one works for you anymore," Lyor, an older white man, says. "You're finished. Jay's in and you're out." And after a few more harsh comments: "This is not your life anymore, man. You blew it." All of this access does great things for Dave's career. He ends up with a newspaper gossip column and a radio show. So he feels a little guilty when, at a press event to announce Damon's new record label, Dynasty, serious violence erupts. Before you know it, one character, coughing weakly as he lies on what must be his deathbed, tells Dave, "You the only cat I trust now." And most painfully: "If I don't make it, you still my dog." Shortly after this, the film offers up a surprise ending, which partly justifies the raucous means. All that can be revealed is this: Somebody been played. "Death of a Dynasty" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes drug use, gunfire, hand-to-hand violence, intense sexual suggestiveness and almost nonstop four-letter words.</text>
      <date>April 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>