<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ature documentaries, long a staple of television and the Imax screen, have increasingly found a place on regular film screens as well. "Deep Blue," from the directors Alastair Fothergill and Andy Byatt, delves into the vast, mystifying world of the ocean, which they navigated for years in their acclaimed BBC series "The Blue Planet." The United States theatrical version (following last year's British edition), a more visual and less informative re-assemblage of the mounds of footage shot for the show, is alternately mind-blowing and mind-numbing. Through a trite narration by the eternally suave Pierce Brosnan and a lush, often overdone score by the celebrated British composer George Fenton, viewers are guided to the far reaches of the world, where an assortment of sea critters are displayed in their natural environments. Sharks, whales, dolphins, polar bears and emperor penguins (also the subject of another new big-screen documentary, "March of the Penguins") swim, frolic, hunt and are hunted, in the depths of the ocean and on the surface of the ice. In addition to the usual suspects, some truly amazing specimens are found: plantlike sea horses, lacy jellyfish that resemble psychedelic sliced cucumbers and even a beautiful silver tornado of sardines. Much of what the filmmakers and their team of cinematographers capture is undeniably remarkable, but their overt attachment to certain scenes can make watching a chore. Massive waves, seen just as impressively in every surfing film ever made, and dolphins repetitiously spiraling out of the water are held on-screen far too long. And in the most gratuitous bit, an orca slaughters a baby sea lion and proceeds to throw the carcass high into the air over and over again. It is in the chasms, way beyond the reaches of the sun, that "Deep Blue" is most fascinating. The cinematic locale, which could pass for an alien planet, and the rarely sighted freak show of deep-sea creatures that inhabit it, are so exotic they would be the envy of any science-fiction film. It is certainly honorable to try to raise awareness about the more than 70 percent of planet Earth that is still predominantly unknown (some sections have been explored less frequently than the moon), but the experience of "Deep Blue" is hardly enlightening. In the end, a sliver of knowledge may be gained, or environmental concerns only briefly alluded to might be pondered, but mostly what remains are pretty pictures that quickly fade into oblivion.</text>
      <date>June 3, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>