<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Tom DiCillo’s angry comedy “Delirious” subjects modern celebrity culture to a microscopic examination that shows the toxic virus of fame squirming and multiplying under its lens. Here are the paparazzi posted like ravenous vermin in front of a velvet rope, ready to trample one another in a stampede at the next celebrity sighting.  Here is the quintessential pop star of the moment, K’Harma Leeds (Alison Lohman), a shallow, talent-free Britney-Paris-Lindsay amalgam with the allure of a tarnished rhinestone in the dump that passes for a glamorous nightclub. K’Harma’s albums sell 10 million units, declares a publicist, a detail that suggests the screenplay was completed before the record industry’s precipitous decline. She has also lent her name to a new celebrity scent, Instant K’Harma.  Grimmest of all are the stars’ handlers, haggling by cellphone  in limousines as they approach a premiere at which two media flavors of the week have been programmed in a militarylike operation to arrive simultaneously and fall into a less-than-spontaneous kiss.  To remind the viewer that there is a satiric element in all this, Elvis Costello (playing himself and sounding amused) shows up at a party and announces that he and K’Harma are collaborating on a Broadway-bound musical about the life of Britney Spears. The movie visits a Soap Stars Against STD Convention, at which self-described “STD survivors” mouth icky platitudes. Sometimes, however, the satire goes seriously out of control, as in an impenetrable spoof of daytime drama.  “Delirious” is a crude pop allegory in which a holy innocent named Toby Grace (Michael Pitt) is willingly sucked into the maw of the beast. A homeless drifter and aspiring actor who has moved to New York from Philadelphia, he seems on the verge of starvation when he attaches himself as a volunteer gofer to Les Galantine (Steve Buscemi), a ratty paparazzo. With his buggy eyes and crooked teeth, Mr. Buscemi  (who also appeared in Mr. DiCillo’s 1995 film, “Living in Oblivion”) gives a courageously repulsive performance as a loudmouthed parasite who seriously brags about getting a shot of Goldie Hawn eating lunch.  Les is infinitely condescending and abusive to his meek new assistant, whom he allows to sleep in a storage cabinet in his shambles of an apartment, stuffed with photo equipment. But Toby, with his androgynous charisma, is fated to be a star. The first time he crosses K’Harma’s path, she notices him. By the end of the movie, they are sweethearts and he is a budding soap opera star. But Toby is ultimately as much of a cipher as K’Harma.  His ascent to the charmed circle, which Les is dying to enter, is inevitable and rapid. Spotted by Dana (Gina Gershon), a casting agent attending the soap-star benefit, Toby is pegged as “a natural.” In no time he metamorphoses from Dana’s client to her lover and then her ex-lover. Ms. Gershon’s magnetic, hard-shelled agent is too shrewd to let her wounded vanity interfere with business.  “Delirious” is the second film in recent weeks, following “Interview,” in which Mr. Buscemi  plays someone abrasively rubbing elbows with fame. There, he is a corrupt, downwardly mobile political journalist given a hack assignment to profile a starlet (Sienna Miller) to whom he feels so superior he doesn’t bother to prepare.  Les, who has fewer pretensions, is an unkempt, star-struck bottom feeder who shamelessly tries to worm his way into events where he can pilfer as many goodie bags as he can grab and convince himself that he is not his worst nightmare, “a peon.” His latest coup, circulated on the Internet, is a candid snapshot of a male star hobbling out of a plastic surgeon’s office following penile surgery.  The scenes of Les haranguing Toby with his grubby tales of triumph (a juicy picture can command $700, he boasts) recall Martin Scorsese’s still-underappreciated 1983 satire, “The King of Comedy,” in which Robert De Niro’s character, Rupert Pupkin, ascends by hook and by crook from predatory fan to big-time comedian. If Les lacks the psychotic chutzpah of Rupert, he harbors the deadly potential to become a Mark David Chapman.  Mr. DiCillo’s disgust with this voracious culture is palpable throughout a movie in which there is no glamour to be found. Even though he reserves a spoonful of honey to make this bitter medicine go down, you leave the movie feeling as though you have gazed into a closed circle of hell where everybody feeds off everyone else until there is nothing left.</text>
      <date>August 15, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>