<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It would be unfair to hold a grudge against Yojiro Takita’s “Departures” just because it won the Academy Award this year for best foreign-language film. Admirers of “Waltz With Bashir” and “The Class,” two exceptionally strong runners-up in that category, should not take their disappointment out on Mr. Takita’s entry, which  doesn’t require comparison  with those two formally innovative, thematically daring films. It is perfectly mediocre all on its own.  Overlong, predictable in its plotting and utterly banal in its blending of comic whimsy and melodramatic pathos, “Departures” is, in the end, interesting mainly as an index of the Academy’s hopelessly timid and conventional tastes. It operates, from start to finish, in a zone of emotional safety, touching on strong feelings like grief and loss without really engaging them, and wrapping itself in a protective membrane of tastefulness. Aided by the classical and pseudo-classical music that decorates the soundtrack, Mr. Takita, an auteur of Japanese soft-core “pink” cinema before he turned to more prestigious projects, has made a soft, pretty film streaked with just enough perversity to give it a vague coloration of art.  Art happens to be one of the picture’s ostensible subjects. Daigo Kobayashi (Masahiro Motoki), the smooth-faced protagonist, is a professional cellist who loses his job when his orchestra goes bankrupt.  He and his wife, Mika (Ryoko Hirosue), return to his hometown and move into the small, shut-down bar Daigo’s mother used to run. She has been dead for a few years, and the whereabouts of Daigo’s father, who walked out on the family when Daigo was a young boy, are unknown.  But not all that hard to figure out, once the contours of the story (written by Kundo Koyama) become clear. Desperate for work, Daigo answers an advertisement and takes a job assisting Mr. Sasaki (Tsutomu Yamazaki), a gruff old fellow who is in the business of preparing dead bodies for burial. The disreputable nature of this work makes Daigo something of a pariah, even to Mika, who can’t bear to think that the potential father of her children might earn his keep handling corpses.  It is clear, though, that the ritual of washing and enrobing those bodies is  a rigorous, dignified craft and a source of solace for the bereaved. This is so clear, indeed, that whatever dramatic tension “Departures” might have had is almost immediately stifled. Daigo is such a nice, hard-working young man, and his mentor is so evidently kindly and wise that you never really believe that anyone could hold their vocations against them.  And the movie is so innocuous that you can’t really hate it. There are touching moments, and some well-observed local details and a few interestingly eccentric minor characters. But every turn is signposted so far in advance that you may find yourself wishing for a fast-forward button to confirm your hunches about what’s going to happen. Life is too short to spend two hours waiting for confirmation of what you already knew and didn’t really believe in the first place.</text>
      <date>May 29, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>