<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Rape is power.  “Descent” — starring Rosario Dawson as Maya, a college student who survives a sexual assault — makes this vividly clear, dramatizing the experience and the psychological aftermath of rape with a vividness I’ve never seen in an American film.  The attacker is someone Maya knows: a former pianist turned second-string football player named Jared (the goofy but rakishly charming Chad Faust). Jared flirts with Maya at a party one spring, doting on her for her mixed-race beauty and eventually convincing her to go on a date that ends in a candlelit, makeshift love shack in the basement of his apartment building.  The ordeal is over in minutes. Maya doesn’t report it. But she spends the following summer sitting on a mother lode of rage  that will be unleashed in the film’s finale,  a prolonged retaliatory assault  in which Maya transforms her pain into sadistic pleasure and sinks to Jared’s level.  The first-time feature filmmaker Talia Lugacy — who attended the Lee Strasberg Theater Institute with Ms. Dawson and collaborated with her on short films — is committed to exploring the psychic aftershocks of Maya’s rape and its effect on her senses of autonomy, sexuality and ethnic identity. All three are symbolically annihilated by Jared, who ravages her while grunting sexist and racist epithets in her ear.  This last aspect — the rape’s awakening of Maya’s consciousness as a woman of color — elevates “Descent” beyond case study and into the realm of bomb-throwing polemic. Maya’s personality is transformed during visits to a dance club, where she falls for a macho  African-American  D.J. named Adrian (the musician turned actor Marcus Patrick, who has a bit of Burt Lancaster’s looming physicality), experiments with drugs and tries to reclaim the sexual confidence that Jared  stole. (The latter is suggested rather than shown, in a strobe-lit dance floor montage of Maya writhing with several partners.)  The attack radicalizes Maya in ways that are not immediately apparent because Ms. Dawson — whose intricate, imaginative performance equals those of Robert De Niro in “Taxi Driver” and Hilary Swank in “Boys Don’t Cry” — expresses them through eddies of sadness and rage that we can sense, even though they remain hidden from other characters.  It also shatters Maya’s illusion that she can go through life being judged by her intelligence and character rather than her beauty, gender and skin tone. This seeps in as she spends time with Adrian, a surly hunk who volunteers bits of street wisdom, playfully mimes smacking Maya and bullies a white sycophant who’s in love with Adrian’s talent and his blackness.  While hanging with Adrian, Maya learns the pleasures of intimidation, illustrated in a scene in which Adrian commands the sycophant to smoke a cigarette clenched between Maya’s toes. In moments like this it becomes clear that “Descent” — which was written by Ms. Lugacy and her cousin Brian Priest — is not just about the personal experience of rape, but rape as a metaphor for sexual, racial and cultural dominance, and the inadequacy of cruelty as a response.  This last point is illustrated in Maya’s retaliation against Jared. I won’t describe it here, partly to avoid spoiling a grim surprise, and partly because its Grand Guignol particulars resist euphemism. Suffice to say that it makes the violence in Gaspar Noé’s “Irréversible” seem tame, and that it simultaneously echoes Amiri Baraka’s racial powder-keg play “Dutchman” and the “Sopranos” episode “Employee of the Month” (which ended with a rape victim refusing a chance at revenge).  Astonishingly, though, the film’s brutality never plays like a stunt, thanks to Ms. Dawson’s revelatory performance and Ms. Lugacy’s adventurous direction (which includes lots of long takes and metaphorically apt compositions). Hard to watch but essential to see, “Descent” is at once realistic and rhetorical, and driven throughout by righteous anger that comes from an honest place.    “Descent” is rated NC-17  (No one under 17 admitted) for  brutal rape, graphic violence, profanity and drug use.</text>
      <date>August 10, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>