<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Two years after his feature film debut with the cult horror hit "House of 1,000 Corpses," the heavy-metal musician Rob Zombie, founder and lead singer of the band White Zombie, continues his experiment in art-house schlock with this second installment of the adventures of the murderous Firefly family.  "The Devil's Rejects" opens with a police raid on a decaying farmhouse somewhere in the South. After a bloody shootout culminating in the capture of Mother Firefly (Leslie Easterbrook), the only escapees are Otis (Bill Moseley) and his sister Baby (Sheri Moon Zombie, the director's real-life wife). These two sadistic siblings hit the road, eventually hooking up with their father, a deranged clown known only as Captain Spaulding (Sid Haig).  The three flee to a roadside motel and, later, to a brothel run by Captain Spaulding's pal Charlie (Ken Foree). Along the way, the Fireflies find time to pursue their favorite hobby: torturing and killing innocent bystanders in elaborately cruel ways. But they finally meet their match in Sheriff John Wydell (William Forsythe), a renegade lawman intent on seeking vengeance for the long-ago murder of his brother at the hands of the Firefly clan.  Despite its nearly nonstop torrent of gore, "The Devil's Rejects" is not really a horror film. It's a compendium of tributes and references to horror films of the past, as well as to Sergio Leone westerns and 70's road pictures like "Bonnie and Clyde." Mr. Zombie's love for, and encyclopedic knowledge of, the exploitation genre is evident in every detail, down to the Super-16 film stock he's chosen to give this film the grainy texture and washed-out color palette of a drive-in B-movie.  "The Devil's Rejects" is a trompe l'oeil experiment in deliberately retro filmmaking. It looks sensational, but there is a curious emptiness at its core. The director seems uncertain whether we should root for his gleefully evil protagonists or their righteous avenger, Sheriff Wydell (played by Mr. Forsythe with grimly unironic intensity). Because the film's mood shifts so quickly from playful perversity to primal dread, and because the Firefly family's wickedness seems unmotivated by anything but pure caprice, "The Devil's Rejects" soon devolves into a tedious moral muddle: Who's good? Who's evil? Who cares?  The film ends with a climactic coda straight out of a Sam Peckinpah film, in which the beleaguered Fireflies drive straight into a police trap, all guns blazing, to the strains of the Lynyrd Skynyrd rock anthem "Free Bird." If the film had earned its stripes by making us care about the characters, this could have been a gloriously satisfying (if hopelessly corny) ending. Instead, like much of the rest of "The Devil's Rejects," the meticulously staged final shootout is a triumph of style alone.  "The Devil's Rejects" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sadistic violence, strong sexual content, strong language and drug use.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>