<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>iary of a Mad Black Woman" is so oblivious to genre that it occupies its own special stylistic niche, if you can imagine such a thing as a romantic revenge farce. As the story of a cruelly abandoned wife's re-ascendance zigzags from soap opera to slapstick to church sermon and back, it goes from A to Z on the all-things-to-all-people meter: Cinderella meets Amos 'n' Andy in Sunday school, so to speak. Playing every end against a shamelessly mushy middle, the movie's producer, writer and composer, Tyler Perry, inhabits three major roles, including Madea, a wisecracking, gun-toting grandmother of immense girth. Like Flip Wilson's Geraldine or Martin Lawrence disguised as Big Momma, Madea is an uncensored matriarch and ferocious comic tornado. When the dumped wife, Helen (Kimberly Elise), shows up on her doorstep after being physically ejected from the Atlanta mansion she shared for 17 years with her bigwig lawyer husband, Charles (Steve Harris), Madea springs into action. With Helen at her side, she marches to Charles's home, shotgun in hand, and proceeds to divide the couple's possessions in half - literally, with a chainsaw. A closet full of fancy dresses belonging to the floozy Charles has installed as Helen's replacement is ripped to shreds. Mr. Perry, the show-business impresario who wrote the play from which this movie is adapted, is a commercial phenomenon who has produced, directed and starred in seven theater works that have grossed more than $75 million, according to the film's production notes. For the African-American crowds who lap them up, their mixture of unedited rage and raucous hilarity promises a vicarious letting off of steam. Because Helen was a faithful, devoted wife to the brute who turned her out, when the tables are turned and she becomes Charles's tormentor, the movie offers jilted wives and girlfriends a guilt-free pass to crow. Waiting in the wings for Helen is a handsome, courtly Prince Charming, Orlando (Shemar Moore), with all the right Christian values. Helen becomes the recipient of two marriage proposals (accompanied by achingly sincere "I love you's") on bended knee from this impossibly perfect hunk. Helen, now sanctified by romance and the church, to which she drags a newly humbled Charles, triumphs as an unblemished, bling-free Christian goddess, living happily ever after with her courtly hottie. "Diary of a Mad Black Woman" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for strong language and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>February 25, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>