<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In "Dirty," a nasty little genre film about corrupt cops in the Los Angeles Police Department's anti-gang task force, Cuba Gooding Jr. sheds the halo that has threatened to strangle his career and makes a desperate leap to the bad side. His character, Salim Adel, is so loathsome he makes Matt Dillon's Officer Ryan in "Crash" look as cuddlesome as a neutered house cat. But if Mr. Gooding's break from Mr. Nice Guy allows him to kick over the traces and play the bully, his inner teddy bear keeps getting in the way of his outer rat.  Adel gleefully harasses and humiliates white drivers in fancy cars who have gotten lost. In the most sickening scene, he manually rapes the girlfriend of a teenage skateboarder. After that, you wait for this rotten egg to be smashed in the gutter and flushed into the ninth circle of hell.  The story, apparently inspired by the Rampart scandal, follows Adel and his not-quite-so-hateful Mexican-American partner Armando Sancho (Clifton Collins Jr.) through an especially stressful day. Sancho, a former gang member, is so haunted by the shooting of an innocent bystander at a crime scene that he has premonitory flashes of the victim's corpse coming back to curse him. Unbeknownst to Adel, he has decided to confess his crimes to Internal Affairs.  All the eggs in the partners' unit turn out to be rotten, including their bosses, the thundering, authoritarian Captain Spain (Keith David) and his weaselly lieutenant (Cole Hauser). When the lieutenant asks the partners to remove a bag of heroin from the evidence room as part of a scheme that could make everybody rich, Adel jumps at the opportunity while Sancho has misgivings.  The operation, which the muddled screenplay fails to clarify, is just an excuse for the movie to lurch dizzily through the Los Angeles underworld, guns popping to a hip-hop soundtrack, as competing black and Mexican hierarchies in the drug trade go at each other.  And what is the civics lesson being taught? As Sancho declares in an introductory voice-over, the only thing separating gangbangers from the police is a badge. "Dirty," directed by Chris Fisher ("Nightstalker"), is a facile exercise in nihilism posing as an indie "Training Day" with street cred. Don't believe it.  "Dirty" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It is violent, sadistic and jam-packed with profanity.</text>
      <date>February 24, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>