<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It is tough to pinpoint the precise moment when "Domino," an action-movie pastiche from Tony Scott, a modern maestro of the cinema of big bang, ceases being just another guns-and-poses divertissement and becomes a lollapalooza of delectable cheap thrills. A tongue-in-check, elbow-in-ribs interpolation of the real life and nasty-girl times of a privileged London brat turned South Central bounty hunter named Domino Harvey, the film has to its great credit absolutely no social value outside of a feverish will to entertain, though that might prove tricky, since its assaultive wild style seems designed to repulse as well as attract.  Civilized movie types may well find "Domino" repellent if not reprehensible, but then, what are those types doing at a Tony Scott movie? As the auteur of such cultural touchstones as "The Hunger" and "The Last Boy Scout," Mr. Scott has always been more popular with general audiences than with serious, or at least serious-minded, critics. Received critical wisdom seems to have it that while he has made, if almost by accident, an occasional good flick, his work presents little of real interest or value. Never mind the badly kept secret that Mr. Scott's films are generally entertaining as hell  and that some of us would rather watch the unrepentantly lowbrow "Top Gun" for the seventh or eighth time than slog through the usual middlebrow folderol.  Written by Richard Kelly, the diabolically clever boy wonder behind "Donnie Darko,"  "Domino" unfolds like a fairy tale, one conceived along the consciously exploitative lines of Aaron Spelling rather than the Brothers Grimm. Like the 1970's television show "Charlie's Angels," Mr. Spelling's famous contribution to jiggle and bad hair, "Domino" hinges on the outlandish image of a gorgeous woman engaged in some of the most brutishly macho work conceivable, which in this case means delivering, for a fee and with shotgun at the ready, suspected criminals to law enforcement. Roger Corman built an empire of sorts on similarly outlandish imagery, as have Luc Besson ("La Femme Nikita") and Joss Whedon ("Buffy the Vampire Slayer"). Mr. Scott is a late but welcome addition to this strange sorority by proxy.  Mr. Scott and Mr. Kelly spin their improbable story of Domino Harvey through the familiar frame of an interrogation. Arrested for reasons that emerge as the story unwinds, Domino (Keira Knightley) sits in a cramped room opposite an F.B.I. agent (Lucy Liu) whose questions take the story back to once upon a time when she lived with her jet-setting mother (the model Pauline Stone, here called Sophie and played by Jacqueline Bisset), and her father, the movie actor Laurence Harvey. Most famous for his role as the tragic villain in the original version of "The Manchurian Candidate," Harvey died when Domino was a toddler, an event that may have had everything, something or nothing to do with his daughter's gradual immersion into a life of reckless danger.  At first, though, it's all fun and guns. Deploying a whirlwind of skewed-angled, slamming cuts, saturated colors, and slowed and accelerated motion, Mr. Scott takes us on a speedy, jittery tour through this A-list dropout's early years - a stint on the catwalk, a catfight in college - then drops us into the rough-and-tumble netherworld of bounty hunting, Cali style. Along with the picturesquely scuzzy Ed (Mickey Rourke) and Choco (Edgar Ramirez), Domino cruises Los Angeles's mean palm-lined streets, looking for and generally finding trouble. In one of her first tours of duty, the three end up in the middle of what looks like most of the city's notorious 18th Street gang. Faced with all those shaved heads and pistols, our quick-witted heroine does what any bounty hunter would do: she offers the gang leader a lap dance.  It gets weirder, deliriously so. Having relinquished any claims on verisimilitude from the get-go ("This is based on a true story ... sort of"), Mr. Kelly cuts loose with all manner of pop-surrealist goofiness and Mr. Scott happily follows suit. The nuttiest development involves the producer of a reality show who hopes to turn the bounty hunters into the WB network's newest stars. The producer is played by (of course) Christopher Walken; the fictional hosts, in turn, are two alums of "Beverly Hills 90210" who are actually played by two alums of that show, the cheerfully game Brian Austin Green and Ian Ziering. Afghanistan, Las Vegas, Dabney Coleman, Macy Gray, Tom Waits, Delroy Lindo and a fabulous Mo'Nique also figure into the mix, but never mind how or why.  How all these pieces do and do not add up is part of the delight of "Domino," as is watching a film tear wildly, at times heedlessly, from one illogical setup to the next, then slam on the brakes to teeter on the brink of self-parody before taking the full-on plunge. Like Domino, who will on occasion wave her gun around with little regard for her  or anyone else's safety, Mr. Scott wields his camera here with an even greater disregard for storytelling niceties than he usually evinces. His filmmaking is always fast and loud, alternately intensely ugly and strangely beautiful to behold, while the stories he tells often fall into the alpha and omega extremes of the modern action movie: the smart-enough pop thriller ("Enemy of the State") and big-budget studio exploitation ("Man on Fire").  What makes "Domino" the ultimate Tony Scott movie - or as a friend put it, "It's all the Tony Scott you could possibly want in a Tony Scott movie!" - is its uncharacteristically sharp screenplay. Mr. Scott has worked with talented writers before, but this is the first time he has shot a film written by a screenwriter who both cops to the great enjoyment that can be had from the modern action movie - perhaps best illustrated here by the sight of Ms. Knightley unloading two machine guns at once - and blows the action-movie tropes to smithereens.  The real Domino Harvey, who died at 35 in June from a heart attack with a toxic level of painkiller  in her system, lived her life  as if she were a character in a Tony Scott movie. That  life was stranger than fiction, but perhaps not so strange as this.  "Domino" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). There is a lot of gun violence and a scene in which someone's arm is forcibly removed from his body, but relatively little gore.</text>
      <date>October 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>