<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A magnificent ruin: that's how the American West is pictured in "Don't Come Knocking," a surreal epic-manqué that reunites the playwright and screenwriter Sam Shepard with the great German director Wim Wenders more than two decades after their auspicious 1984 collaboration, "Paris, Texas."  That description also applies to the visually majestic but dramatically inert new movie they've made together, and to the ravaged but still-handsome face of its 60-something writer and star. As impassive and craggy as a granite monument, Mr. Shepard has physically aged into a symbol of the stubborn, cranky individualist who has been a constant presence in his plays and films. Nowadays, he merely has to squint into the camera to suggest a tired, suspicious cowboy who has spent decades riding the range, roping steers and peering into the horizon for signs of trouble.  Mr. Shepard did not star in "Paris, Texas" (Harry Dean Stanton stood in for him), but in "Don't Come Knocking" he is everywhere and nowhere at once playing Howard Spence, a burnt-out star (a Clint Eastwood type) who flees the Utah set of his latest picture to embark on a rambling exploration of his past. Howard has spent a lifetime boozing, drugging, brawling and womanizing, and it shows  Video: Movie Minutes Stephen Holden reviews "Don't Come Knocking," a surreal epic-manque that reunites the playwright and screenwriter Sam Shepard with the great German director Wim Wenders.  The first leg of Howard's odyssey takes him from the desert movie set to the Elko, Nev., home of his mother (Eva Marie Saint), whom he hasn't visited in 30 years. When she jolts him with the news that a woman from Butte, Mont., once contacted her saying she had borne him a son, he impulsively decides to drive to Montana.  In Butte, depicted as a shabby former boomtown whose streets are nearly empty, Howard meets his fly-by-night former lover, Doreen (Jessica Lange), who owns and operates a local bar. He also encounters the grownup son he knew nothing about until a day or two earlier. That son, Earl (Gabriel Mann), is a bitter, hotheaded musician who is so unsettled by his father's sudden entrance into his life that he goes ballistic and tosses all his possessions out the window.  Howard also meets a second child, Sky (Sarah Polley), his daughter by an unidentified woman whose ashes Sky carries around with her in an urn. The character is so sketchy (and ultimately unnecessary) that she seems to have been tossed into the movie as an afterthought.  "Don't Come Knocking" tantalizes us with ghosts and mysteries and the promise of psychic adventure until Howard reaches Butte, whereupon the movie grinds to a halt, mired in the mud of unsettled family business. From there it hems and haws, spinning its wheels trying to work up enough momentum to go somewhere, but it never budges  During his journey, Howard is trailed by Sutter (Tim Roth), a poker-faced insurance investigator determined to drag him back to Utah to fulfill his contract. In this metaphoric chase, Howard is an outlaw who must literally be brought back in handcuffs by a city-slicker sheriff. But Mr. Roth's Sutter, like Ms. Polley's Sky, is a one-dimensional projection that has no life beyond a stick-figure representation.  For all the nuance Ms. Saint pours into her portrayal of Howard's mother, her role is also more symbolic than real; mothers, in Mr. Shepard's world, may scold their errant sons, but always protect and forgive, and cook them breakfast, before sending them on their way. Ms. Lange's Doreen spits fire, but the actress can't sort through her character's sudden changes of attitude, and because the upper half of Ms. Lange's face appears immobilized by cosmetic work, she is only able to give half a performance.  Yet there is much to admire in "Don't Come Knocking." Mr. Wenders and the cinematographer, Franz Lustig, fill the screen with pictures whose shimmering, mirage-like intensity reflects the name of Howard's movie-in-progress, "Phantom of the West." For "Don't Come Knocking" is finally a meditation on cultural ectoplasm, on phantom cowboys and outlaws and the potent myths surrounding them. To Howard, fatherhood is just as ectoplasmic, until he confronts its reality, and even then he is dumbstruck. It's far easier for the western loner to skip town and never look back. When Sutter retrieves the rebel star, Howard appears relieved.  "Don't Come Knocking" is filled with haunting visual panoramas. One of the most resonant is a nighttime shot of the Elko skyline dominated by a glittering casino. Evoking a once and future gold rush, it says more about the Old West and the New West than all of Mr. Shepard's elliptical, stagy dialogue can muster. Such powerful images make "Don't Come Knocking" well worth contemplating.  "Don't Come Knocking" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity.</text>
      <date>March 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>