<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Down in the Valley" is a neo-western with dreams as big as the fantasies that consume its protagonist, a Stetson-wearing suburban cowboy who calls himself Harlan Carruthers. Portrayed by Edward Norton (one of the movie's co-producers) with the same queasy mixture of ingenuousness and cunning he brought to his career-making performance in "Primal Fear," Harlan claims to be a rancher from South Dakota transplanted to the San Fernando Valley, where he lives by himself in a crummy motel.  A walking anachronism, Harlan politely mutters "aw shucks," "ma'am" and "sir" when addressing strangers. Although his cold, flinty eyes hint at sociopathic derangement, we initially cling to the image he presents of himself: the modern embodiment of Hollywood's laconic, soft-spoken cowboy hero. He's a gust of clean air in the polluted jungle of strip malls and freeways that the movie's stunning cinematography paints as a gorgeous hell with hidden pockets of rural heaven.  While pumping gas, Harlan meets Tobe (Evan Rachel Wood), a bored, sullen teenager on her way to the beach with friends. When she invites him along, he impulsively quits his job and joins them. The couple's first day together develops into a romantic idyll that lifts Tobe (her name is short for October) out of her perpetual sulk.  Beautiful and rebellious, Ms. Wood's Tobe is almost as complex as Mr. Norton's Harlan. And as the cracks in his perfect image widen into crevices, we empathize with her reluctance to admit disenchantment. The first serious signs of trouble come when Harlan takes Tobe to the country for a ride on a white horse that belongs to an eccentric rancher (Bruce Dern) he claims is a friend, and the "friend" pursues them with a gun.  "Down in the Valley" begins semirealistically, then veers off course, hurtling into the wild blue yonder of myth and allegory. On the way to a climactic shootout that begins on the set of a Hollywood western and ends on a foggy hillside, it makes several screeching, hairpin turns.  Whether you want to remain on board till the end of the ride will depend on your appetite for the kind of cultural metaphors that David Jacobson, the writer and director, flings onto the screen with abandon. "Down in the Valley" is the third movie written and directed by Mr. Jacobson, whose small-budget films "Criminal" and "Dahmer" (a biography of Jeffrey Dahmer) hinted of what was to come. Whether or not you like it, you have to admire his courage in going for broke.  Tobe and her shy younger brother Lonnie (Rory Culkin) live in too-close quarters with their father, Wade (David Morse), a sharp-eyed law officer, bruiser and fierce parental watchdog. When Wade meets Harlan, he immediately smells a rat, despite the young man's obsequiousness.  Both Wade and Harlan are revealed to be gun fetishists. Wade keeps a valuable collection of firearms in the house. Harlan spends hours alone in his motel room in front of a mirror, spinning dual Colt .45's and practicing two-handed draws. In an obvious quotation from "Taxi Driver," he sneers defiance into the dead air like a cowboy Travis Bickle. He also becomes a big brother to Lonnie, a forlorn 13-year-old who still sleeps with the lights on. A disquieting scene in which he gives the frightened Lonnie shooting lessons sends mixed signals, since Lonnie laps up the attention he so badly needs.  "Down in the Valley" would like nothing less than to be seen as the ultimate deconstruction of the Hollywood western and of the cowboy archetype, lost in the wasteland of the New West. Reckless and smart, it juggles nostalgia (lyrical echoes of "Red River," "My Darling Clementine" and "Shane") and disgust (Harlan, with his Colt .45's and no wide-open spaces to patrol, is a destructive product of the bogus idealized frontier hero).  Like a gunslinger himself, Mr. Jacobson strides into territory where Sam Shepard put down roots decades ago (and which Mr. Shepard reassessed in his screenplay for the recent film "Don't Come Knocking"). Mr. Jacobson claims it with a boldness that Mr. Shepard has long since forsaken.  "Down in the Valley" seriously loses its way in a mystifying sequence that delves into Harlan's real background and includes a shooting that appears lethal until the victim emerges absurdly unscathed. But once it regains its footing, it leaves you pondering questions about the American character that continue to haunt us: What's the difference between a rugged individualist and a psychotic loner? Where does puritanical morality shade into gross intolerance? And why is it our national fate to be so gun crazy?  "Down in the Valley" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual scenes, strong language and violence.</text>
      <date>May 5, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>