<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The movie's official, unwieldy title is "Dreamer: Inspired by a True Story" - which could mean anything, really.  In any case, the story, in its rough outlines, is certainly a familiar one; its themes are the overcoming of past disappointment, reconciliation between parent and child and the triumph of the underdog, which in this case is a horse. Parents who accompany their children to this film,  written and directed by John Gatins (whose other writing credits include "Coach Carter"),  will find themselves anticipating just about every plot turn, and nodding as each premonition is fulfilled. Nodding through tears, I should add. Yes, "Dreamer" follows a formula, but the formula, when applied with skill and intelligence, as it is here, is pretty much foolproof.  Set in the green horse country around Lexington, Ky., the movie concerns a farm family fallen on hard times. Most of its land has been sold off, and Ben Crane (Kurt Russell) trains horses for spoiled princes and their coldhearted minions. Ben barely speaks to his crusty father (Kris Kristofferson), and does not have much time for his daughter, Cale (Dakota Fanning), who has inherited  the family's horse-whispering gene and more than a bit of her dad's stubbornness. (Her blond cuteness must come from her mother, played by Elisabeth Shue.)  One day at the racetrack, a filly Ben has been training breaks a leg, and rather than stand by as the horse is put down, he impulsively decides to take her home. Her name is Sonya, short for Soñador, which is Spanish for dreamer, a piece of information that takes a curiously long time to emerge. In any case, Ben and Cale, with the help of a wisecracking groomsman (Luis Guzmán) and a sweet-natured jockey (Freddy Rodriguez, late of "Six Feet Under"), nurse Sonya back to health, after which ...  Well, I'll leave it there, since even a story that ends with a long-shot entry in the Breeders' Cup deserves to have its twists and turns protected. Children will worry at occasional reversals of fortune and sigh happily when things come right again. Adults, meanwhile, can relish the fine work of the cast, thoroughbreds all, who do the material the honor of not condescending to it. Mr. Russell seems temperamentally incapable of dishonesty or overstatement, and his dry, taciturn presence inoculates the picture against mawkishness. (He performed a similar service as the fiercely reserved hockey coach in "Miracle"). Ms. Fanning, neither kidnapped by bandits (as in "Man on Fire") nor menaced by aliens (as in "War of the Worlds"), gives a similarly quiet performance, restraining the impulse to be cute and winsome in favor of some serious acting. Cale, who idolizes her father, pointedly imitates his mannerisms and habits of speech, and Ms. Fanning, a quick study, absorbs Mr. Russell's quiet warmth.  David Morse, in a silver beard and a dark suit, is delightfully mean as the main villain, essentially a suave update of the archetypal top-hatted plutocrat. His presence allows "Dreamer" to shake off some of the aristocratic airs of its chosen sport and find a strain of populism. This has to be fudged a bit once the matter of Breeders' Cup entrance fees, which run into six figures, comes up. But  never mind. The film's basic moral distinction is between those who come to horse racing for reasons of egoism or greed and those who do it for love. Maybe all that really needs to be said about "Dreamer" is that it  was made for the right reasons.  "Dreamer" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some scenes of human and equine distress.</text>
      <date>October 21, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>