<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At the moment it seems as if no major Hollywood studio will release a comedy without Judd Apatow’s name somewhere on the label. This is perhaps overdue vindication for a man who once languished making brilliant television shows that too few people wanted to watch, but it also carries risks of backlash and brand dilution.  As an admirer, mostly, of Mr. Apatow’s oeuvre, I was inclined to believe that “Drillbit Taylor” was a cheap knockoff, that the producer credit Mr. Apatow receives at the beginning was akin to the Rolex insignia on the watch I bought for  $20 on Canal Street a while back. But it makes more sense to think of this dumb little picture, with Mr. Apatow’s wife, Leslie Mann, in a supporting role, and Seth Rogen, one of his alter egos, sharing credit for story and screenplay, as part of the Apatow discount line. “You get what you pay for,” the tag line on the advertisement says. I saw it free, and I still feel cheated.  The premise is a mélange of familiar and somewhat more esoteric elements: the television sitcom “Freaks and Geeks,” of which Mr. Apatow was an executive producer; the 1980 high school drama “My Bodyguard”; Jean Renoir’s “Boudu Saved From Drowning” (or at least Paul Mazursky’s remake, “Down and Out in Beverly Hills”). Worthy influences all. But “Drillbit Taylor” is so ploddingly directed (by Steven Brill) and lazily written that it adds up to little more than a diffuse collection of second-hand gags and jokes, few of them funny.  Three nerdy high school freshmen —  a fat one (Troy Gentile), a tall one with glasses (Nate Hartley) and a shrimpy one with braces (David Dorfman) —  find their pathetic efforts at coolness met with abuse from a pair of bullies. These are not just run-of-the-mill jocks but full-fledged sociopaths, in particular the one called Filkins (Alex Frost). To fight back the boys enlist the help of the title character (Owen Wilson), a good-natured homeless man who claims to be veteran of the  Army Special Forces.  Various entirely predictable, rarely amusing things happen, including a lot of punches  to the face and groin. The only reliably funny thing in the movie is Mr. Wilson’s zoned-out, improvisational riffing, but his oddball comic intensity is shamelessly exploited rather than given material on which to feed. This is too often the way lazy filmmakers deal with gifted screen comedians. Point the camera at Mr. Wilson (or Will Ferrell or Ben Stiller or Jim Carrey), write a check and figure that the shtick will carry a movie at least as far as a decent opening-weekend gross. That’s a waste of talent, and “Drillbit Taylor” is a waste of time.  “Drillbit Taylor” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some puerile sex jokes and drug references.</text>
      <date>March 21, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>