<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One of the beautiful things about the movies is how they can burrow into our beings, turning a public expression into a private ritual. Once, that might have meant strutting across a room like James Cagney or drooping like Ali MacGraw. The charmingly low-key Mexican film "Duck Season" changed the way I pour soda. In this  hymn to friendship, a young teenage boy fills two glasses with Coke for himself and a friend. As the dark, fizzy liquid precariously climbs toward the rim of each glass, the boy gives the signal: "Finger." His friend places a digit above the rim, a gesture that stops the foam from brimming over and yields perfectly equal shares. You can pour a single glass of soda, but how much nicer it is to pour for two.  Sly, droll fun, this unexpectedly fine first feature from Fernando Eimbcke creeps to life slowly with a series of static images — a broken-down bicycle, a graffiti-embellished stretch of concrete — that suggest a postapocalyptic wasteland. Happily, this isn't the setting for some dystopian nightmare, the stomping ground for zombies and thugs, but the exterior courtyard of a vast, anonymous housing complex. Look closer, though, peek inside one of the blank windows that puncture one of the block buildings, and that's where you find the two teenagers, Moko and Flama (nicely played by Diego Cataño and Daniel Miranda). Fourteen years old, the boys are still very much children, with gangling limbs and wide-open eyes, but also on the verge of making a touching swerve into adulthood.  Left home at Flama's with video games and gallons of Coke, the boys begin playtime ordinarily enough. But as late morning gives way to early afternoon and then night, the two are joined first by a next-door neighbor, the lovely Rita (Danny Perea), a somewhat older, much more mature-looking teenager, in search of a working oven. (She wants to bake herself a birthday cake.) Sometime later, a pizza-delivery guy waggishly named Ulises (Enrique Arreola) joins the party, turning three into a neatly symmetrical four. Like the others, Ulises is on a voyage, the implications of which he cannot fully grasp until he (with us riding shotgun) arrives at its end. And so, after some hesitation and pettiness, a little spilled blood and a few badly separated eggs, these four join forces, becoming an island of castaways.  The critic J. Hoberman has pointed out that "Duck Season" is, essentially, a retelling of "The Cat in the Hat," and so it is, though I don't remember the two tots, the goldfish or even that troublemaking feline scarfing down pot brownies. Sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll play a part in "Duck Season" and its fab four's magical mystery tour, as do a wealth of detail and a haunting story about a dog pound, a tale told with an agitated camera and accompanied by howls. Shot in black and white in 35-millimeter film, "Duck Season" has a formal elegance that belies its poverty of means. Inside this small canvas — almost the entire film unfolds in the  one apartment — Mr. Eimbcke turns each character into an epic.  Mr. Eimbcke, who also wrote the fine screenplay, throws a precise frame around a world, which emphasizes the sterility of the characters' lives and makes their gradual deliverance from that sterility all the more meaningful. A story about friendship and the ecstasy of communion (not coincidentally, the story opens on a Sunday morning), "Duck Season" suggests that transcendence arrives when you least expect it — sometimes it comes with a pizza, sometimes it materializes in a kitsch painting and, sometimes, in a pan of chocolate-flavored euphoria. More important, transcendence comes in small moments of kindness, in a hand offered with gentleness,  in a kiss delivered without regret. In the end, we are always home alone. But as "Duck Season" reminds us, we don't have to live there forever.  "Duck Season" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Think of it as a PG-13 with pot and no guns.</text>
      <date>March 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>