<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Eagle vs Shark,” the feature debut by the New Zealand director Taika Waititi,  is one of those movies  — “Napoleon Dynamite” is an obvious recent precursor  —  that invite you to laugh at its misfit characters and empathize with them at the same time.  Jarrod (Jemaine Clement) and Lily (Loren Horsley), the couple whose passive-aggressive, on-and-off romance anchors the film, are easy targets of mockery. At the fast-food restaurant where Lily works, her co-workers laugh behind her back and sneer in her face. Only the unconditional love of her equally eccentric brother (Joel Tobeck) saves her from a complete loss of dignity.  Jarrod, for his part, may be even easier to laugh at because, like Napoleon Dynamite, he is convinced, against all evidence, that he is a cool, complicated warrior-stud. Lily, infatuated with him from the start, is amenable to this view. And when, later on, she sees through his poses, her affection is only deepened.  But I’m ahead of the story, which is a small, intermittently charming, sometimes tiresome celebration of quirkiness, complete with cute animated sequences featuring apples and ants. Lily, noting that she and Jarrod have matching moles on their upper lips, catches his eye at a party where he is dressed as an eagle, she as a shark. She nearly beats him at a video game, he shows her his collection of homemade candles, and they go to bed.  So far, so endearingly quirky.  But the quirk stakes are raised considerably when Jarrod announces that he must go on a “mission” that takes him back to his hometown, a seaside enclave of oddness and frustration. His stated goal is to find the bully who tormented him as a schoolboy and deliver some payback.  Really, though, he must face down the memory of his super-achieving dead brother, Gordon (played in home video flashbacks by Mr. Waititi), and their father, whose favorite son was certainly not Jarrod.  This is some heavy emotional baggage for such a slight movie to manage, and “Eagle vs Shark” cannot quite escape the twin traps of forced whimsy and sticky sentimentality. That it comes close is the result of Mr. Waititi’s dry, efficient direction and the devotion of Mr. Clement and Ms. Horsley, who believe absolutely in the integrity of their characters long after everyone else, in the movie or watching it, has grown tired of them.  “Eagle vs Shark” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has some swearing, a brief sex scene and glimpses of violent video-game action. </text>
      <date>June 15, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>