<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It’s not often filmmakers are thoughtful enough to include a critique of their work in the title, so for that, at least, the creators of “Eating Out 2: Sloppy Seconds” are to be commended. But in case avid fans of the first opus require further enticement, you should know the slop in question is both pervasive and highly visible.  A Rubik’s Cube of shifting sexual orientation and elaborate sex fantasies, “Sloppy Seconds” gathers all the accouterments of soft pornography — cheesy music, low-rent acting and attractively framed genitals — into a plot of stunning imbecility. When the insecure Kyle (Jim Verraros) is casually dumped by his narcissistic boyfriend, Marc (Brett Chukerman), he seeks comfort with the best friends Gwen (Emily Brooke Hands) and Tiffani (Rebekah Kochan). It’s safe to say neither woman would be your mother’s first choice for daughter-in-law.  While Gwen hunts for “a little boy-on-boy” action to increase her viewing pleasure, and Tiffani just hunts, Kyle homes in on a sexually ambivalent nude model named Troy (Marco Dapper), a molded lump of muscle and tan lines with no more brain power than is strictly necessary to achieve orgasm. In hopes of seeing more of Troy than is currently available in art class, Kyle pretends to be an “ex-gay” and invites him to a meeting of Homo No More, a group whose mission is to stop the spread of homosexuality.  As its title suggests, “Eating Out 2: Sloppy Seconds” is less about sexual confusion than sexual gluttony. With its jauntily crass aesthetic and wine-waiter line readings, the movie is most focused in its zeal to show the fruitlessness of right-wing efforts to reorient gay men. To that end, the support-group scenes are amusingly dimwitted, and the legendary Mink Stole (still game after 40 years in the business) gives her all as Kyle’s ebullient, gay-friendly mother.  The other women fare less well under Phillip J. Bartell’s direction and a script, by Mr. Bartell and Q. Allan Brocka, that sags with sexual explicitness. “Did my vagina scare you away?” asks a perplexed Tiffani. Perhaps we should ask the audience fleeing the theater.</text>
      <date>November 24, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>