<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "The Edukators," Hans Weingartner's second feature film, concerns three young Berliners whose frustration at the iniquities of global capitalism leads them, not quite intentionally, to cross the line that separates provocation and protest from serious crime. The film is, to some extent, a sympathetic exploration of the state of political idealism in the contemporary West, where all avenues of resistance seem blocked or co-opted by the system. But it is also a sometimes mocking exposé of what the old left used to call political infantilism. The director is clearly fond of his  radicals - and the terrific actors playing them do so with exemplary conviction - but he also points out the blind spots and contradictions that distort their view of the world and turn their self-styled heroism into self-dramatizing foolishness.  We first meet Jule (Julia Jentsch), who works as a waitress in a fancy restaurant, at an anti-sweatshop protest in front of a sneaker store. Her boyfriend, Peter (Stipe Erceg), and his roommate, Jan (Daniel Brühl, one of Germany's finest young actors), express their discontent with the system a little differently. They break into suburban villas and rearrange the furniture, leaving behind notes that say things like "your days of plenty are numbered" (the film's German title) and then scan the papers for news of their exploits.  When Jule takes part in one of these actions - at the home of a wealthy businessman named Hardenberg (Burghart Klaussner), whose Mercedes she once wrecked in a car accident - things go a bit further. Hardenberg, to whom Jule is still paying off an onerous debt, returns home unexpectedly, and the careful vandalism of his house turns into a sloppy and panicked kidnapping.  This event interrupts and exacerbates the development of a romantic triangle, as Jule finds herself increasingly attracted to Jan, who is more cerebral than Peter and less impetuous. Jan, whose smile expresses more anxiety than joy, is the intellectual in their two-man revolutionary movement, spouting elaborate theoretical justifications of the break-ins and fantastical (though to his mind perfectly logical) elaborations of their consequences. He also possesses at least a degree of historical consciousness. "The rebellion is difficult now," he informs Jule. "Before, all it took was long hair and dope." But, he insists, "the best ideas survived."  "The Edukators" is a Germanic-English rendering of the name that Jan and Peter give their group, and Mr. Weingartner's script lives up to the title's pedagogical implications. The German appetite for dialectics is freely indulged, as Hardenberg and his captors spend much of the movie's second half debating ethics, history and political strategy. Hardenberg, it turns out, is - or at least claims to be - a former radical himself, a veteran of the German SDS  and the student militancy of 1968, and a onetime commune-dweller no less. He professes admiration for his kidnappers' ideals, though not their methods, and seems to treat his captivity in a mountain cabin as a kind of vacation, recalling his  longhaired days and accepting an occasional joint that is passed his way.  His debates with Jan are banal and schematic - a standoff between adult common sense (or "bourgeois ethics," as Jan would have it) and the ardent dogmatism of youth. Along with the flat, digital-video cinematography, these plodding exchanges give the film a blunt realism that is sometimes a bit tedious. Its long, hectic scenes and visual harshness make "The Edukators" look, at first glance, like yet another application of the stripped-down Dogma 95 aesthetic, but this appearance disguises a tenderhearted (and perhaps also a softheaded) romanticism. Like Jan, Peter and Jule - and perhaps like Hardenberg as well -Mr. Weingartner, a former left-wing radical, harbors his own nostalgia for the 60's and 70's, for "Bonnie and Clyde" and "Jules and Jim" and "Band of Outsiders," as well as for the early work of New German cinéastes like Rainer Werner Fassbinder, Wim Wenders and Werner Herzog. The spirit of that tradition, combined with Mr. Weingartner's filmmaking skill, rescues "The Edukators" from  intellectual confusion.  To take this seriously as a political film is to risk working yourself up into a useless lather - either at the cruelty of capitalism or at the arrogant ridiculousness of those self-alienated children of the system who take it upon themselves to oppose it. But to get hung up on such matters would be to scant the pleasures of a slyly effective thriller and of a deft comedy of romantic confusion. Whatever its shortcomings as a consideration of globalization and its discontents, "The Edukators" succeeds brilliantly in telling the story of a man  who falls in love with his best buddy's girlfriend and doesn't know what to do about it.  In his first film, "The White Sound," which starred Mr. Brühl as a  schizophrenic, Mr. Weingartner showed himself impressively adept at handling emotional complexity and exploring the intimate contradictions of an insolubly difficult situation. The only thing that felt conventional about that film was its ending, which is also the case here.  "The Edukators" wraps up with a series of montages set to a pop song, a bit of a surprise given how little music has previously been superimposed on the action, and also, in this case, a sign of creative fatigue. The song happens to be a version of Leonard Cohen's "Hallelujah," which you may recall hearing put to oddly similar use in another, very different recent movie. In other words, it may be difficult to watch the denouement of this serious, ambitious movie without being reminded of "Shrek." There's a lesson in that: resistance is futile; the system always wins.  "The Edukators" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual scenes and strong language.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>