<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Eight Below" stars Paul Walker as Jerry Shepard, a rugged yet soulful Antarctic guide, and Bruce Greenwood as Davis, the ambitious geologist he leads on a quest to recover a fallen chunk of Mercury. Jason Biggs co-stars as a kooky cartographer, and Moon Bloodgood plays a pilot. Completing the ensemble are Maya, Max, Shadow, Buck, Dewey, Truman, Shorty and Old Jack, eight wildly talented, inhumanly adorable huskies who live only to please their masters   — both the ones on screen and the ones buying tickets for this megadose of Disney schmaltz. Can you guess who gives the credible performance here?  Cat people are directed to, well, any other movie at all. "Eight Below" is Grade A pooch porn, an orgy of canine cuteness. Based on a true story, not that it matters, the movie putters around for an hour in search of that pesky rock, with the inevitable misadventures, animal heroics and imminent arrival of "the biggest storm in  25 years!" Everything else goes to the dogs. Abandoned by the fleeing humans, they are instantly anthropomorphized and leap into the blinding white landscape to scavenge for food, tangle with sea lions and practice their sentimental reaction shots.  Meanwhile, Jerry knocks on doors from Capitol Hill to Pasadena in an attempt to drum up funds for a rescue trip. Come on, people, there are dogs to be saved 9,000 miles away in the middle of apocalyptic weather! Super-cute dogs! But no. At home  in oceanfront Oregon, where he lives in manly splendor and solitude, Jerry gazes at snapshots of his furry friends. Will no one come to the rescue? Of course they will. And will they make it in time? Dog nerds with kids   can find out for themselves.  "Eight Below" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). Doggy deaths may upset the littlest ones, but even grown-ups will be startled by the attack of the computer-generated leopard seal.</text>
      <date>February 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>