<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> On the evidence of “El Cantante,” in which he plays the salsa singer Héctor Lavoe, Marc Anthony is not much of a screen actor. When the character is not in front of an audience, Mr. Anthony seems to recede behind his high, delicate cheekbones and tinted glasses, as the director, Leon Ichaso, buries him in distracting formal gimmicks and camera stunts. For the viewer Mr. Lavoe remains out of reach, an artist whose inner life remains locked inside the actor’s diffidence.  Whenever Héctor  takes the stage, however, Mr. Anthony unleashes his charisma, and shows that, whatever his limitations as an actor, he is a brilliant performer. Singing new versions of hits from various periods in Mr. Lavoe’s career — from records he made with Willie Colón and the Fania All-Stars in the late ’60s and early ’70s as well as from later solo projects — he demonstrates that this music is a complex and captivating form of drama in its own right.  As the main vocal line swoops and dips above the throb of percussion, the chatter of horns and the chanted background voices, his voice negotiates a dizzying array of emotions and attitudes. He is by turns boastful and vulnerable, nostalgic and defiant, sentimental and sarcastic.  Mr. Ichaso’s generosity with these musical moments compensates both for Mr. Anthony’s shortcomings and for the frenetic incoherence of his own storytelling. It also helps that Jennifer Lopez, married to Mr. Anthony and a producer of “El Cantante,” does enough acting for the two of them in her role as Puchi, Héctor’s wife. The film is structured around scenes of Puchi in 2002, reminiscing to a film crew about her life with her husband, who died of complications from AIDS in 1993.  A hectic rush of flashbacks take us to the ’80s and then back to the ’60s, when young Héctor Perez, as he was then known, is preparing to leave his native Puerto Rico for New York. His father tells him not to go, and the next thing you know he’s arriving in the city (apparently along with the Beatles). He meets some musicians, makes eyes at Puchi (whose own eyes are decorated with some impressive false lashes) and moves quickly from his first puff of marijuana to full-blown heroin addiction.  This story, which quickly comes to resemble the plot of nearly every other musical biopic of recent memory, develops through an exhausting, confusing series of montages punctuated by short, crude moments of ham-fisted melodrama. Shortly after Héctor  meets Puchi, he takes her to meet his sister, and the scene lasts long enough for two thoughts to cross your mind: Wait, he has a sister? and, What are she and Puchi fighting about?  Ms. Lopez brings a lot of fight to her performance, a hard, skeptical edge that makes Puchi a more interesting and plausible character than her husband. It falls to her to explain him, since neither Mr. Anthony nor Mr. Ichaso seem able or willing to do so. She tells us that Héctor  had a great sense of humor, that he was “corny” and that “the more he grew as an artist, the deeper he sank as a person.”  “El Cantante” shows us the second half of this process, as Héctor  takes more drugs (each dose accompanied by slow-motion filming and ominous sound effects), shows up late to more and more gigs, cheats on Puchi and flies into paranoid fits at the thought that she might be cheating on him. Missing, though, is any insight into his achievement as an artist. We hear it proclaimed that salsa was a revolutionary sound, a groundbreaking synthesis of Puerto Rico and New York, but the musical and historical information that would flesh out this assertion is missing. As with most movies of its kind —  a notable recent exception is “Ray” — “El Cantante” fails to enrich our understanding of the music that should be its main reason for being.  Still, the music itself can hardly be ruined, and the evident love for it shown by Ms. Lopez, Mr. Ichaso and Mr. Anthony make it possible to forgive their other lapses. It may be best to approach “El Cantante” less as a movie than as a two-hour promotional video for a must-have soundtrack album.  “El Cantante” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity, drug use and some violent and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>August 3, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>