<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Lush, lurid and completely besotted with itself, "Eternal" is one of those movies normally found slinking around the ether of late-night cable television. A heady combination of kink and bloodletting, the film claims inspiration from the undeniably intriguing life of Erzsebet Bathory, a 16th-century Hungarian countess whose anti-aging routine required frequent immersions in young, female blood, a set-up that should guarantee at least a little visual excitement. But "Eternal" is quite possibly the dullest, least sexy lesbian vampire movie I have ever seen.  In a ghostly mansion in present-day Montreal, Elizabeth Kane (Caroline Néron) and her comely assistant, Irina (Victoria Sanchez), seduce unwary young women who have yet to learn the perils of Internet dating. Distracting her prey with aggressive cleavage and husky European vowels, Elizabeth slices their compliant throats with a cunning little claw-tipped thimble. "Thank you for your beauty," she whispers politely before each exsanguination. A lady never forgets her manners.  Unfortunately, her latest victim was married to Raymond Pope (Conrad Pla), an oafish cop with a taste for bondage and his partner's wife - usually at the same time. As Ray, assisted by Interpol, sets out to prove Elizabeth's guilt by drooling at her relentlessly, Irina tries to allay her mistress's fears. "They're just human, they can't do nothing to you!" she insists, proving that fresh blood may boost a girl's beauty but it doesn't seem to be much help with grammar.  "Eternal" is the debut feature of Wilhelm Liebenberg and Federico Sanchez, who have aimed for Dario Argento and ended up with Bob Guccione. Opulent but empty, the film's softly pornographic visuals frame thoroughly unlikable characters and complete narrative idiocy. While the director of photography, Jamie Thompson, whips back and forth between high heels and low necklines, the actors struggle against their limitations to bring some heat to the proceedings But not even the killer combo of chains and a leather bikini can break through the film's patina of cold artiness.  Straining desperately to be "Interview With the Vampire," "Eternal" succeeds only in being the kind of movie that pauses any time a young hottie feels like dancing in her underwear. By the time we get to a costume ball in Venice, complete with masks remaindered from "Eyes Wide Shut" and a hot tub filled with blood, most of us are more likely to be asleep than aroused. Yet, despite all evidence to the contrary, there is an audience for this film. You know who you are.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>