<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Even Money,” a scare movie about gambling addiction, is as grim and lurid as any in the recent spate of films about the evils of crystal meth. Once you’re hooked, it suggests, you’re a goner. The zombie face of Kim Basinger, her vacant eyes glued to a slot machine, tells you all you need to know. The elusive quest of her character, Carolyn Carver, for a cascade of jangling silver soon leads to roulette, blackjack and high-stakes bets placed with a murderous bookie.  Carolyn, a writer working on her second novel, wastes her nights in the casino while lying about her whereabouts to her husband, Tom (Ray Liotta), a college teacher. Meanwhile their neglected 13-year-old daughter (Carson Brown) is turning into a sex fiend. Unbeknown to the absurdly credulous Tom, Carolyn is not at Starbucks straining to tap out the great American novel but at the casino draining the last of the family savings. She is eventually befriended by Walter (Danny DeVito), a ratty, washed-up magician who lives in a trailer and hangs around gambling dens pestering patrons for spare dollars in exchange for stupid tricks.  The Carvers’ tale is one of several interlocking horror stories in “Even Money,” which was directed by Mark Rydell from a screenplay by Robert Tannen. The format is similar to that of “Crash,” which also carried the name of Bob Yari as a producer. More than “Crash,” this film sacrifices realism to forced plot mechanics.  In the saddest vignette, Clyde Snow (Forest Whitaker), a handyman in debt to his bookie, pressures his much younger brother, Godfrey (Nick Cannon), a college basketball whiz, to shave points. Mr. Whitaker’s Clyde is a shambling nice guy regularly visited by thugs who administer savage beatings. Adding to the pressure, Godfrey’s coach (Charlie Robinson) catches on to the scheme and goes ballistic. The volatile mix of devotion and desperation in Clyde and Godfrey’s fraternal bond has a raw poignancy that is missing from the rest of the movie.  At the high end of the economic scale (and the low end morally) are the bookies. Augie (Jay Mohr) and Murph (Grant Sullivan), a pair of young hotshots, rationalize their dirty work by arguing that they are merely performing a service. They break up when Augie, who can no longer stomach it, goes under cover and agrees to wear a wire for a shady detective (Kelsey Grammer).  Tim Roth plays Victor, the master manipulator and gambling king of kings, a suave, cackling monster with a pet bird. In Mr. Roth’s uncontrolled performance, Victor is a creature who would be more at home in a “Saw” movie than in “Even Money,” which wears a thin veneer of respectability and social concern.  I don’t buy that facade. “Even Money” is so devoted to sustaining shock and awe that it doesn’t bother to offer clues about the causes and treatment of gambling addiction. Except for the Snow brothers’ story, it is a swatch of cinematic schadenfreude that invites you to gloat over the downfall of fools who deserve every humiliation that comes their way.  “Even Money” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has extreme violence and strong language.</text>
      <date>May 18, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>