<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Warning: A putatively heartwarming dramatic comedy like “Everybody’s Fine” can be hazardous to your health. The queasiness produced by this sentimental weepie builds into a wave of nausea during its interminable finale, in which a family with the usual array of problems and disappointments (I refuse to use the term “dysfunctional” anymore) reunites for Christmas, all lovey-dovey.  Written and directed by Kirk Jones (“Waking Ned Devine,” “Nanny McPhee”), “Everybody’s Fine” is an adaptation of a 1990 Italian film directed by Giuseppe Tornatore, himself no slouch when it comes to pouring on the corn syrup. The original movie starred Marcello Mastroianni as a retired Sicilian widower who pays surprise visits to his grown children on the Italian mainland. His American counterpart, Frank Goode (Robert De Niro), is a retired worker (at a wire factory) and a father of four who suffers from an unspecified ailment brought on by the toxic coating applied to the wire.  Because his recently deceased wife, the children’s confidante and collaborator in deception, regaled him with rose-colored accounts of their achievements, a beaming Frank (and nobody beams like Mr. De Niro) boasts about their successes to one and all. Frank is mildly abashed when he invites them to a family reunion and excitedly purchases a grill and some fancy steaks, only to have them telephone, one by one, with terse excuses for why they can’t come. Although disappointed, Frank figures that they must have excellent reasons.  Determined to get closer to them, Frank goes against his doctor’s orders and sets out to pay unannounced visits to the four, traveling by train and bus from his suburban home in somewhere U.S.A. to New York, Chicago, Denver and Las Vegas. His first letdown is his discovery that one son, David, a painter, isn’t living in his surprisingly shabby New York tenement apartment. We quickly learn in awkwardly inserted scenes of anxious telephone colloquies among the siblings that David is in Mexico and may be in serious trouble.  Frank’s second stop is a Chicago suburb where one daughter, Amy (Kate Beckinsale), a glum, high-powered advertising executive, lives in a hideous modern house that is as sterile as it is enormous. Amy, who has a mouthy brat and a husband who arrives with Chinese takeout, is not pleased to see her father and can’t wait to get him out of there.  In Denver he surprises his other son, Robert (Sam Rockwell), a percussionist for a symphony orchestra, in the middle of a rehearsal. Frank is shocked to discover that Robert is not the world-class conductor he was led to believe. During their tense encounter, Mr. Rockwell, in the film’s best performance, conveys the bitterness of an adult child who grew up terrified of displeasing an impossibly demanding parent. Their meeting suggests what a scary father Frank must have been when the children were young.  In the final stop, Las Vegas, his other daughter, Rosie (Drew Barrymore), a dancer, greets him with another elaborate charade. Ms. Barrymore is as ingenuous as ever in a small role that raises unanswered questions about Rosie’s actual circumstances. In a movie whose plot turns are signaled from miles away, Frank has the inevitable health crisis. This one occasions a dream sequence so clumsy and overwrought you want to avert your eyes.  “Everybody’s Fine” heralds the entrance of Mr. De Niro, now 66, into geezer territory. In a hammy movie that practically demands a hammy lead performance, he is relatively restrained. The De Niro tics are present of course, including the crinkly, secretive smile that camouflages hurt feelings as well as possible menace, and the jocular attitude and tone of voice that go with the smile.  If the film weren’t so mechanically contrived — you can feel its rusty machinery cranking away — Mr. De Niro might have lent Frank a dimension that transcended the cliché of a well-meaning but clueless control freak whose fantasies of having raised perfect children are methodically dashed. But Mr. De Niro doesn’t bring much to the role beyond a seriocomic affability that is a toned-down version of his character Jack Byrnes from “Meet the Parents.”  The only credible scenes in a movie that is pathologically afraid of being a bummer belong to Mr. Rockwell. Otherwise “Everybody’s Fine” is false to the core.  “Everybody’s Fine” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>December 4, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>