<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Here is an idea worth pondering from “Everything’s Cool,” a breezy polemic about the politics of global warming: The fossil fuel industry doesn’t care who wins or loses the debate about the reality of global warming,  as long as the public continues to feel that it is debatable.  To put it differently, doubt means delay. On television, where every issue is presumed to have two sides, shills from the fossil fuel industry glibly dispute the overwhelming scientific evidence for global warming. Casual viewers can thus reassure themselves that they don’t have to worry about climate change. Given the warnings that the world has a narrow window of opportunity to reduce carbon emissions drastically, who doesn’t wish that those oil and coal flacks and their well-funded political supporters were right?  “Everything’s Cool,” a documentary directed by Daniel B. Gold (who narrates) and Judith Helfand, and adorned with clever animations by Jeremiah Dickey and Emily Hubley, traces the politics of  global warming politics back to 1987, when the phenomenon was more commonly called the greenhouse effect. According to the movie the issue didn’t become politicized until the oil and coal industries recognized a threat to their economic well-being and undertook a misinformation campaign that continues to this day.  Although the underlying outlook of “Everything’s Cool” is dire, the movie adopts a cheerful comic tone to avoid scaring audiences. Instead of the grand overview of global warming offered by Al Gore in “An Inconvenient Truth”  it leans toward the Michael Moore school of activist filmmaking while avoiding Mr. Moore’s rabble-rousing stunts.  The directors’ attitudes parallel those of Michael Shellenberger and Ted Nordhaus, who rattled the environmental movement three years ago with their critical essay “The Death of Environmentalism.” Those writers, who appear in the movie, disparage what they call the “I have a nightmare” tone of doomsayers who think that pictures of polar bears stranded on ice caps will move the public. Doom and gloom prophecies promote passivity, they argue. People have to be informed of the potential economic and social benefits from developing  clean new energy technologies.  In its determination to entertain, “Everything’s Cool” sometimes slips into frivolity. A segment about the eco-disaster movie “The Day After Tomorrow” is neither enlightening nor amusing. The film wastes too much time observing Bish Neuhouser, a snow groomer at a Utah resort who converts his vehicles to bio-diesel fuel. It observes Heidi Cullen, the Weather Channel’s resident climatologist, as she is taught to dumb down her climate reports and deliver them in an easy conversational tone. Like putting pills in applesauce, the frivolity at least makes the movie’s bitter medicine easier to swallow.  In scenes of more serious uplift, Bill McKibben, the activist and author of “The End of Nature,” is shown organizing a grass-roots demonstration in Vermont. And Ross Gelbspan, who has written extensively about  global warming, is seen addressing high school students in Brookline, Mass.  But the forces feeding the resistance to change remain intractable. The movie retells the appalling story of Philip Cooney, a lobbyist for the oil industry hired by the White House to head its Council on Environmental Quality, who edited and softened alarming scientific reports on climate change to make them appear ambiguous. Two days after The New York Times published an article about his alterations, he resigned and was quickly hired by Exxon Mobil.  Just below the movie’s attitude of pep-rally cheer is a mood that approaches despair. Mr. Gelbspan  has probably amassed as much hard evidence of climate change as anyone alive. He intimates that, realistically, it is too late for fundamental changes that would halt global warming to be put into practice within what he sees as a 10-year deadline.  “It is a curse to know this stuff,” he says. And it is a curse to even think, “Why bother?,” which would mean abandoning the fight. And so he persists.</text>
      <date>November 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>