<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> For much of its 87 minutes, “Explicit Ills,” an episodic movie about a number of Philadelphians living, working and often struggling in the same neighborhood, appears to move from life to life without particular reason. Its first-time writer and director, Mark Webber, doesn’t immediately reveal the story’s structure or his intentions: he simply places you among some dozen characters — children and young adults of different colors and with differing economic contexts — without introduction. A young boy buys a soda in one scene, an older boy explains the benefits of a vegan diet in another; one man sells pot while another sells colonics.  These are a few  of the souls  finding and losing themselves in a neighborhood in uneasy transition alongside a bohemian wife (Naomie Harris) who steals puffs off blunts in between yoga poses and a poor mother (Rosario Dawson) trying to care for her asthmatic son. In time, themes (financial distress, self-medication, existential isolation) emerge from their lives, and seemingly casual moments begin to take larger shape, much as the dots in a pointillist painting do as you step back from the canvas. Though some  of his visual choices can seem arbitrary (the  long shots tend to feel more like art-cinema tics than formally organic), Mr. Webber, working with the talented cinematographer Patrice Lucien Cochet, persuasively transforms a group of portraits into a group portrait.  As the story’s design and Mr. Webber’s intentions come into focus, it becomes evident that this is yet another of those multistranded narratives that have come into vogue again. In some  recent films of this type, most of which come with a veneer of politics and invariably embrace humanism, the characters are connected by a gun (“Babel”), ethnic and racial tensions (“Crash”) and immigration (“Crossing Over”). Yet what binds them isn’t just that they’re all hurting human beings joined by their common pain, but that the filmmaker also wants you to know that they’re all hurting human beings and he feels their pain. Mr. Webber at least offers a solution, as  evidenced by a man who spray-paints the word “revolt” in letters so large they fill the entire frame.  Even so, no matter how ostensibly profound their differences, the characters in all these movies end up hoisting the exact same banner for the filmmaker. In the case of “Explicit Ills,” this banner-carrying becomes literalized when the  characters  take to the streets in the final scene during an organized demonstration, a neighborhood of atomized individuals transformed into a coalition of the righteous and united on behalf of medical care, housing and peace. It’s a beautiful message: surely there’s no arguing with “Hey, hey, ho, ho, poverty has got to go!” But there is much to argue with, and much to regret, about a film whose director thinks he needs to drop an anvil on our heads when art would suffice.  “Explicit Ills” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Physical violence, recreational drug use and some health-care horror.</text>
      <date>March 6, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>