<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Express” is an honorable example of a tried-and-true formula, squarely aimed at a presumably large cross-section of the moviegoing public: people who love football and hate racism. Like “Glory Road,” “The Great Debaters” and numerous other similar movies, it packages a real-life story of athletic triumph and social progress into an accessible, rousing melodrama that is no less potent for being almost entirely predictable.  And this is true even for viewers — the majority, I’d guess — whose knowledge of college football in the early 1960s is hazy or nonexistent. The pivotal moment in “The Express,” solidly directed by Gary Fleder, is the 1960 Cotton Bowl, where Syracuse faced the University of Texas. The Syracuse team, coming off an undefeated season, was notable for the presence of Ernie Davis, a supremely talented running back who would go on to become the first black winner of the Heisman trophy.  “The Express” is more or less a biography of Davis, played by Rob Brown in a likable if somewhat stiff performance. The stiffness comes in part from the script, by Charles Leavitt, which is more inclined toward homily than toward psychological nuance. Ernie, who overcomes a childhood stutter, is raised by his mother (Aunjanue Ellis) and especially his grandfather (Charles S. Dutton), a Pennsylvania coal miner. After a flurry of expository scenes that supply a basic sketch of the young man’s background and temperament, he arrives at Syracuse, where he falls under the tutelage of Ben Schwartzwalder (Dennis Quaid), the gruff but decent head coach.  Davis faces a double challenge. Even though he is something of a pioneer — one of a handful of black students on campus (another is his teammate and friend Jack Buckley, played by Omar Benson Miller) — he also has to fill the shoes of Jim Brown, who preceded him as Syracuse’s star black rusher. Relations between Brown (Darrin DeWitt Henson) and his coach were not exactly harmonious, and Davis must deal with a legacy of tension and suspicion in the locker room and on the practice field.  He finds some time for romance (with a Cornell student played by Nicole Beharie) and for a death in the family, but most of “The Express” is taken up with alternating set pieces, the Big Game followed by the Big Scene in which prejudice is confronted and attitudes are changed. Davis, with his idealized mixture of stubbornness, amiability and grace, is both the film’s symbol of progress and its dramatic catalyst, but you don’t get much sense of his internal struggle. It’s the coach, and thus Mr. Quaid, who carries the main dramatic burden of undergoing a significant change.  The scenes in which racism erupts on the football field — including at that Cotton Bowl — are the most powerful, and the most effective in infusing sports nostalgia with a sense of historical consequence. The end of the film is inevitably somber — Ernie Davis’s life was foreshortened by leukemia — which adds to a general feeling of sentimental overload. But if a movie of this kind didn’t traffic in overstatement, it wouldn’t be doing its job, which is to provide a strong dose of simple, rousing emotion.  “The Express” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some moderately brutal football sequences, a few fights and strong language.</text>
      <date>October 10, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>