<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the world of celebrity do-goodism, Angelina Jolie is hot to trot the globe for the United Nations. George Clooney raises dollars and sense on behalf of Darfur. And Mike Judge? Well, the funnyman behind the cartoon yukfests “Beavis and Butt-Head” and “King of the Hill” and the very funny cult movie “Office Space” appears to have joined the ranks of celebrity do-gooders with his increasingly aggressive attempts to eradicate stupidity, one barbed, mean and sometimes hilarious joke at a time. With the barbarians clawing at the gate, somebody’s got to do it, right?  Mr. Judge’s most pointed attack on our perceived national calamity is his 2006 comedy, “Idiocracy,” about an average white guy who, after being put in a deep freeze, wakes up 500 years later to find that he’s the smartest person alive and that people  are dumb as slugs, including the president, a “smackdown” champion (and an African-American). Mr. Judge’s most recent attack on the same subject is “Extract,” another big-screen comedy about an affable white guy, Joel (Jason Bateman, predictably pleasant), an Everyman and factory owner. (He makes flavorings.) His natural decency is under constant assault by a miscellany of indignities, including a wife, Suzie (Kristen Wiig), who won’t sleep with him; a droning neighbor who can’t shut up (David Koechner); and a factory populated by lazy, dense workers.  Fitfully funny with a low joke-to-minute ratio, “Extract” plays like two irreconcilable and unfinished sketches, neither particularly fertile comedic terrain. The first revolves around Joel’s beef that his wife has sexually closed for business by the time he comes home from work, a weak bit that Mr. Judge tries to exploit with repeated close-ups of Suzie cinching her sweat pants. At the urging of his friend Dean (Ben Affleck, delivering a real performance), Joel hires a part-time pool cleaner and full-time moron, Brad (Dustin Milligan), to service her. The second sketch involves the attempts of a vamping con artist, Cindy (Mila Kunis), to scam Joel by cozying up to a dim factory worker, Step (Clifton Collins Jr.), who’s suffered an-on-the-job injury.  What’s most striking about “Extract,” beyond the scarcity of  jokes and absence of actual filmmaking, is its deep well of sourness, which at times borders on misanthropy. In his first live-action feature, “Office Space,” a comedy about the indignities of that modern hell we call a desk job, Mr. Judge took aim at the dehumanization of organizational life. In “Idiocracy” he expanded his sightlines to include corporations and consumer culture. The received wisdom remains that 20th Century Fox, which backed the movie, dumped “Idiocracy” into the marketplace because of its anti-corporatism: it mocks Fox News along with brand-name companies that run ads on media outlets belonging to Fox’s parent company, the News Corporation.  What was often left unsaid amid the ruckus is that the movie conceives of its own audience as cultural dopes.  “Idiocracy” expresses the kind of fear lampooned, consciously or not, in the old joke about revolting masses. (Messenger: “The masses are revolting!” King: “You’re telling me!”) It opens with a comparison between trailer-trash types, with low I.Q.’s, who freely propagate, and smarty-pants types who fret about conceiving, using every excuse to find the perfect time to have children. In the end the low I.Q.-ers overrun the intelligent, who die off, which is funny if you think that only certain kinds of people should reproduce. An equal-opportunity offender, Mr. Judge can wield satire like a sledgehammer, so it’s no surprise that he doesn’t bother with the complexities of class and representation in a bit about the dire consequences of a birth dearth.  In “Extract” Mr. Judge reserves many of his biggest digs for Joel’s workers, who are never more foolish than when they  confusedly attempt to organize. Their grievances are foolish and grounded in misinformation and greed. A bigger company is wooing Joel, and the workers want a piece of the action. Joel perseveres (this is an American comedy, not a French one, after all), winning them over with common sense. The only laborer who seems reluctant to join the fray is a hard-working Latino (Javier Gutierrez), who barely speaks a word. He doesn’t have to. Joel does the talking for him and then, with a smile, orders everyone back to work.  “Extract” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). What do you think? It’s a blankety-blank Mike Judge movie.</text>
      <date>September 4, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>