<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Just to clear up any confusion: the four stars in the box accompanying this article do not represent a rave review, though I did quite enjoy the movie in question. Really, what sort of a critic do you think I am? Certainly not one who resorts to nonverbal, quantitative means of expressing opinions. This just isn’t that kind of newspaper.  Nor, however, is it the kind that will permit me to print the title of Steve Anderson’s rowdy and contentious new documentary, which consists of a single, highly versatile English word. I have been known to use the word in mixed company and even, I blush to admit, around my children — but only pedagogically, to call attention to the laxity of other drivers on family car trips. Never in front of the readers, though.  Which is as it should be. Mr. Anderson’s movie is staged as a talking-head culture-war skirmish between embattled upholders of propriety (or repression, if you prefer) and proponents of free expression (or filth), but its real lesson is that the two sides depend upon each other. Or rather, that the continued vitality of the word —  its unique ability to convey emphasis, relieve stress, shock grown-ups and function as adverb, noun, verb, intensifier and what linguists call “infix” —  rests on its ability to mark an edge between the permissible and the profane. If that boundary were to disappear, who would care anymore? Allowed free rein in the pages of respectable publications —  however much my fingers may itch, at this very moment, to type its four constituent letters —  the word would quickly lose its power, its flavor, its interest. And then, lovers of the mother tongue, where would we be? Don’t answer!  “****” collects a motley panel of opinionators, who address the camera front of a black backdrop, their interviews occasionally cut together to suggest actual debate. (At one point Judith Martin, a k a Miss Manners, appears to be so disgusted with remarks made by the porn actor Ron Jeremy that she takes off her microphone and rises from her seat.) Their frequently predictable points —  protect the children; protect free speech; bless you; no, bless  you —  are sorted into chapters on history, religion, movies, politics and so on. The visual texture is varied by some amusing animations by Bill Plympton and by snippets from several movies I still can’t believe my parents took me to see.  The designated scolds include conservatives like Alan Keyes, Michael Medved and Pat Boone (who reveals that he uses his  last name as an epithet, a usage that the rapper Ice-T is later inspired to try out). They are, on the whole, pretty good sports, since they must have had an inkling that the movie, being a 21st-century documentary, would be tilted against their side. But perhaps that suspicion only confirmed their sense of the cultural landscape, in which comedians working blue and blue-state liberals conspire to spread corruption in the name of freedom.  On the other side are pornographers, comedians and other champions of desublimation, many of them worshippers at the shrine of Lenny Bruce, whose fearlessness made the comedy clubs of America into what Bill Maher calls “the freest free speech zone” in the nation. (Not all of the partisans of profanity are political liberals, by the way. And not all the advocates of restraint are right-wingers.) The movie is most interesting when it detours from polemic into analysis. Linguists and lexicographers are on hand to debunk some common misconceptions,  like  the persistent legend that the word is some kind of acronym having to do with the sexual whims of monarchs, or the idea that it appears in Shakespeare. (Rochester and Burns are another story.)  All in all, the title of the movie is invoked around 800 times, and one of its more systematic areas of inquiry is quantitative. The first Hollywood studio film in which the word was heard was “MASH,” in 1970,    and from there it was a short trip to “Scarface” (182 times), “Jay and Silent Bob Strike Back” (228) and the HBO  series “Deadwood” (861 utterances in the first season).  Gosh! Is this evidence of cultural decline? It’s hard to think of a short answer that wouldn’t be made more vivid by the insertion of the forbidden word. So skip it. No, not the movie. What,  are you kidding me? No way. Go. Help yourself.</text>
      <date>November 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>