<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> All happy families resemble one another, Tolstoy famously wrote, and each unhappy family is unhappy in its own way, but Tolstoy didn't know the Stones, who are happy in a Hollywood kind of way and unhappy in a self-help kind of way. This tribe of ravenous cannibals bares its excellent teeth at anyone who doesn't accommodate the family's preening self-regard. Its most recent target is Meredith Morton, an executive played by Sarah Jessica Parker, who probably hopes to marry into the clan, little realizing that this will leave no Stone unturned and all aimed straight at her head.  Written and directed by Thomas Bezucha, "The Family Stone" opens inside a crowded department store, with Meredith talking nonstop into a cellphone while her boyfriend, Everett Stone (Dermot Mulroney), buys a gift. Meredith steps out of her bubble only long enough to correct Everett's gift choice brusquely and make the salesgirl feel bad. (In some flicks, cellphones are the new cigarettes, a sure sign of incivility.) There are few character types Hollywood loves to hate more than the female business executive, what the movies once called a "career woman." And with her brittle efficiency and tight chignon, Meredith looks precisely like one of those types for whom comeuppance and a more relaxed hairstyle are right around the corner.  That corner and that comeuppance will be revealed inside the studiously tasteful Stone family manse, to which Everett squires Meredith home for the holidays. Located in a picture-perfect New England college town (actually, Madison, N.J.), the house looks more persuasively lived in than many big-studio interiors, perhaps because of all the books crammed onto shelves and piled on night tables. The Stone patriarch, Kelly (Craig T. Nelson), is a professor, and the family's vaguely bookish, boho vibe is reinforced by the Susan Sontag-style splash of white that punctuates the otherwise dark head of his wife, Sybil (Diane Keaton), a woman of multiple moods, if not personalities. If Kelly serves as the family's foundation, Sybil is a lot like the house itself, a warm womb in which each family member can seek refuge.  There is, of course, something irresistible about having a maternal womb of one's own, and not just as a pretext for cheap puns. The hitch here is that Mom is fairly monstrous, and most of her five kids fairly unbearable. The exceptions are Susannah (Elizabeth Reaser), who, perhaps because she has her own family, is merely bland, and Ben (Luke Wilson), whose laid-back charm owes much to the actor playing him. Less appealing are the baby Stone, Amy (Rachel McAdams), and Thad (Ty Giordano), who is deaf and about to adopt a child with his partner, Patrick (Brian White). Shrouded in saintliness and as neutered as geldings, Thad and Patrick offer further proof that as far as pop culture representation is concerned, gay men are fine, as long as they're redecorating or straighter than straight.  It takes a while for Sybil's monstrosity to emerge, mainly because the reliably appealing Ms. Keaton, with her fluttering hands and gorgeous smile, radiates such likability. The film doesn't present the character as a monster; this is, after all, a paean to that beloved fiction called the sanctity of the family. More interesting, though, the film is also a clear attempt to bottle the manic energy and generous spirit of madcap classics like George Cukor's wonderful 1938 "Holiday." This partly explains Mr. Bezucha's unfortunate attempts at broad physical comedy (flying casseroles, etc.), which even a dexterous performer like Ms. Parker has trouble with. This actress fares better facing off against Ms. Keaton, whose character carries a dark secret that will be a secret only to those who don't notice the rampaging elephant in the room.  In a better movie, these strong-willed women would be ready-made friends rather than instant combatants. A better movie would also bring Amy, the second most unbearable family member, into a sisterhood, rather than turn her into the resident baddie. (Amy carries a National Public Radio tote bag, a red flag for intolerance, if ever there was one.) Like Meredith and Sybil, Amy is the other putatively difficult woman in this film, a shrew-in-training who spews bile at Meredith as readily as Linda Blair once spewed pea soup. Like Ms. Keaton and Ms. Parker, Ms. McAdams is such an engaging screen presence that she holds your attention and sympathy despite the handicap presented by her character's personality or, rather, sex, which here are one and the same thing.  The female troubles that bedevil "The Family Stone" are by turns exasperating and fascinating. Save for the boring sister, the women are pills, but they're also far more fun to watch than the men, who all are terribly kind and dull, dull, dull. (Ben is by far the most appealing, but he also seems permanently stoned.) The women make "The Family Stone," especially Ms. Parker, whose nimble performance is reason alone to see the film: not since Philippe Petit has anyone walked a tightrope with such finesse - and in high heels, no less. Of course, her character will eventually be added to the Stone pile, and like everyone else in this fairy tale, she will be paired with her ideal mate, as if she were set for Noah's Ark instead of one leaking, creaking vehicle.  "The Family Stone" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). The language is lightly spiced.</text>
      <date>December 16, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>