<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Like father like son: exploratory variations on that old saw are the thematic heart of the Argentine filmmaker Daniel Burman’s  “Family Law.” The third installment of his semiautobiographical trilogy of films about fatherhood, which began six years ago with “Waiting for the Messiah” and continued with “Lost Embrace” in 2004, this delicate, bittersweet comedy prepares you for an eruption of high drama that never arrives.  That withholding of catharsis is deliberate. In a printed interview that accompanies the film’s production notes, Mr. Burman comes forth as an outspoken champion of understatement. The signals conveyed by body language and silence, he maintains, are truer than the words that come out of people’s mouths. And this likable, if undramatic film  — the antithesis of Hollywood movies in which father-son Oedipal conflicts are resolved in embarrassing, teary-eyed clinches  — makes a case for reticence.  Bernardo and Ariel Perelman, the father and son under the movie’s microscope, are both lawyers of Polish-Jewish extraction living in Buenos Aires. Bernardo (Arturo Goetz), a widower in his mid-60s, is a successful lawyer who follows a strict daily routine that  the 30-something  Ariel (Daniel Hendler) describes in detail in an introductory voice-over.  Ariel, rather than join his father’s business, teaches law. And in the film’s classroom scenes, the younger Perelman (both men are called by their last names) comes across as a talented underachiever adrift in a postgraduate limbo.  As the story unfolds, Ariel goes through several  life passages, including his marriage to Sandra (Julieta Díaz), a law student who teaches Pilates, and fatherhood. But neither the wedding nor the birth of their child, Gastón (Eloy Burman, the  director’s son) is shown. True to his aesthetic,  Mr. Burman looks for the truth of his characters in the texture of their daily lives. That Ariel often goes to bed wearing his suit, for instance, looms as a significant detail.  The movie is a casual detective story in which Ariel, observing Bernardo from afar, speculates about his father’s mysterious ways. Is Bernardo’s longtime secretary, Norita (Adriana Aizenberg), his lover? All the signs suggest that she is, although Ariel would never inquire.  “Family Law” is also the portrait of a marriage that involves an unusual amount of secrecy. Ariel selects Sandra as his future wife long before she is aware of him as a potential suitor. To get to know her better, he signs up for personal Pilates instruction. He wins her love after she is sued for practicing Pilates without a license and he volunteers his legal advice.  Unbeknownst to Sandra, Ariel consults his father, who bends the law in her favor; Ariel allows her to think he did it himself. Late in the movie, when he confesses his deception, she barely registers a reaction. When a construction accident at the law school where he teaches forces him to take sabbatical while repairs are made, he doesn’t tell his wife that he is spending his days idle.  This reflexive secrecy mirrors his distance from Bernardo. When Bernardo turns 65, Ariel forgets it is his birthday. And when Bernardo unexpectedly reaches out to Ariel and insists on showing him around the office, the son doesn’t realize that a serious, hidden agenda lies behind the gesture.  The film’s most touching moments find Ariel bonding with his  2½-year-old-son while Sandra goes on a Pilates retreat. In the scenes of this adorable, happy little boy reaching out to his father, you can feel a bond of trust and devotion deepening into a lifelong attachment. That attachment, if it follows the family tradition, may leave much unspoken. Thirty years hence, Ariel may be a mystery to Gastón as Bernardo is to Ariel. But Gastón will know that he is loved, and that’s what matters.</text>
      <date>December 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>