<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A plaintive portrait of a gay high school student looking for love in a small Texas town? Or a warmed-over John Waters-style farce that ridicules easy targets like evangelical Christians and petty high school bureaucrats? “Fat Girls” doesn’t know which it wants to be and ends up stranded between two concepts, either of which might have yielded a more satisfying film.  “Fat Girls” was written, directed and co-produced by Ash Christian, a 22-year-old Texan filmmaker of some promise. Mr. Christian also plays Rodney Miller, the self-aware, virginal sad sack who narrates the story and who by the end of the film has developed some badly needed self-esteem. To Rodney “fat girl” is a catchall term for a teenage pariah; it is, he says, “a state of mind.”  At lunchtime Rodney’s companions are two fellow outcasts: 300-pound Sabrina (Ashley Fink), who is being brought up in a trailer by lesbian parents, and her boyfriend, Rudy (Robin De Jesus), a Cuban refugee adopted by an African-American family. When a guidance counselor summons Rodney to her office, she reacts with undisguised contempt to his stated career goal of being a Broadway star.  To his shock Rodney is befriended by Joey (Joe Flaten), a handsome, insolent new kid in town from England who gives him his first real kiss and takes him to a gay bar, where he discovers one of his teachers (Jonathan Caouette, the director of “Tarnation”) performing in drag. As a lark Joey agrees to be Rodney’s date to the high school graduation dance (which for some reason is never referred to as a prom). In the anticlimactic dance scene, which cries out to be a confrontational set piece, nothing much happens.  For all its veneer of sensitivity, “Fat Girls” turns ugly in a farcical sequence in which Sabrina gets stuck inside a Volkswagen Beetle while making out with Rudy. Even on the crudest finger-pointing level, it isn’t funny.  “Fat Girls” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for strong sexual content including graphic dialogue, language and some drug and alcohol use, all involving teenagers.</text>
      <date>November 2, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>