<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “You’re a good woman, Fay,” declares Jallal (Anatole Taubman), an Osama bin Laden surrogate. “Someday when all this is over and we have destroyed Western civilization. ...” he continues, without finishing the sentence.  Jallal’s dream girl, played by Parker Posey, is the title character of Hal Hartley’s spy spoof “Fay Grim,” and his come-on distills the facetiously deadpan tone of this laborious sequel to Mr. Hartley’s 1998 cult film, “Henry Fool.”  Too light-headed to qualify as satire, too poker-faced to register as comedy, “Fay Grim” belongs in its own stylistic niche: the Hal Hartley film. As self-referential in their way as the works of Guy Maddin or David Lynch, movies emanating from Planet Hartley are an acquired taste shared by hipper-than-thou insiders.  You may not remember “Henry Fool,” Mr. Hartley’s allegorical sendup of literary celebrity that won the best-screenplay award at Cannes in 1998 and was hailed by some as a landmark of independent cinema. Its cult status owes as much to Mr. Hartley’s reputation as a free-spirited one-man band working with minimal resources as it does to its artistic merits.  “Henry Fool,” which skewered fame-mongering and the deification of art, was a whimsical mock epic but had enough of a soul to make you care about its cast of oddball eccentrics from Woodside, Queens. Since then Mr. Hartley, now based in Berlin, has filmed several smaller, quirky fables that registered only as faint blips on the radar of international cinema. With “Fay Grim,” filmed in high-definition video in New York, Paris and Istanbul, he updates the “Henry Fool” characters (played by the same actors) as they converge in one of the most convoluted spy stories ever concocted.  Seven years have passed since Fay’s husband, the no-talent novelist Henry Fool, fled the United States with the help of Fay’s brother, the Nobel Prize-winning poet Simon Grim (James Urbaniak), after accidentally killing a man. Simon is serving a 10-year prison sentence for aiding and abetting. Fay, still living in Woodside, is raising her sullen 14-year-old son, Ned (Liam Aiken), who is expelled from school for showing his classmates a pornographic movie on a hand-cranked toy viewer that mysteriously arrived by mail.  Fay’s life is upended by a visit from Fulbright (Jeff Goldblum), a grim C.I.A. officer who produces evidence that before she married him, Henry was a spy working the hot spots of the world from South America to Europe to the Middle East. Henry’s “Confessions,” which were deemed to be of no literary value, are suddenly a hot property. They may be coded, top-secret texts that could threaten national security.  Henry’s whereabouts are unknown. If he’s dead, Fay — played by Ms. Posey as a flouncing, vinegary, thoroughly modern woman who is the antithesis of the damsels in distress and slinky double agents usually found in spy movies — will have legal possession of his notebooks. She agrees to fly to Paris to retrieve them if Simon is immediately released from prison.  The two-hour film flashes back and forth from Fay’s journey — which takes her from Paris to Istanbul and during which she is besieged by gun-toting spies and counterspies from several different countries — and Woodside, where experts try to decode one stray notebook from clues found in the movie in the toy viewer.  While deftly working the visual tropes of the spy-thriller genre, “Fay Grim” carries them into the realm of the absurd. With an endless plot whose details and reversals are laid out in indigestible gobs of exposition, it suggests an uneasy fusion of “Syriana,” “Casino Royale,” “Zelig” and “The Da Vinci Code,” with an Austin Powers smirk. But beneath its mockery, the movie is a commentary on the rampant paranoia that grips the post-9/11 world.  Mr. Goldblum’s humorless intelligence agent is a demented logician whose thinking is so contorted that everything and everyone is presumed to be part of a vast terrorist conspiracy. Mr. Goldblum invests Fulbright with an owl-eyed gravity that suggests a caricature of the Dick Cheney mind-set.  But “Fay Grim” gets so carried away with the intricacies of its plot that it gets lost in its own excessive cleverness. In the decade since “Henry Fool,” it implies, fear has driven the United States stark raving mad.  “Fay Grim” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language and some sexuality. </text>
      <date>May 18, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>