<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Whether or not Jet Li has retired from the martial arts movie, as he recently announced, “Fearless” may come to be remembered as a late specimen in a different genre: the China-as-underdog flick. For the moment, the notion of a Chinese freedom fighter defending the honor of his nation against a seven-foot Yankee muscleman named Hercules O’Brien (Nathan Jones) remains more or less credible. But tomorrow? Such narratives may lose their punch when China rules the universe.  Set at the turn of the previous century, as imagined through state-of-the-art production values (the film keeps one eye on old-school chopsocky and the other on new-school superproductions), “Fearless” breaks into three neat acts, each of them charmingly anachronistic. In the first, the legendary martial artist Huo Yuanjia (Mr. Li) aspires to be the champion of Tianjin street fighting. His hubris, however, leads to retaliation from a rival, and a tragic turn of events sends Huo into self- imposed exile in the country.  The following lovely, lyrical stretch of the picture is devoted to his spiritual rehabilitation (cue meditative farming montages), a resting of the muscles before they’re called back into service against the enemies of Tianjin. Naturally, Act 3 largely consists of Mr. Li meting Tumbling Fist, Eagle Claw Boxing and Righteous Indignation, against multiple opponents.  Ably directed by Ronny Yu, a veteran of Hong Kong cinema (“The Bride With White Hair”) who has taken unfortunate steps into Hollywood (“Freddy vs. Jason”) as well as sprightly ones (“Bride of Chucky”), “Fearless” sustains the tradition of ethically inflected Chinese action movies. Physical kinesis is inseparable from spiritual dynamism; the question is not whether Hou can beat everyone to a pulp,  but whether he can do so with proper discipline and honor.  “Fearless” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for virtuoso bone breaking.</text>
      <date>September 22, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>