<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Playing a canny old papa bear dispensing nuggets of advice to a flock of unruly cubs in “Feast of Love,” Morgan Freeman, Hollywood’s sage for all seasons, has a role he could act in his sleep. Early in this serious comedy, directed by Robert Benton and adapted by Allison Burnett from Charles Baxter’s popular 2000 novel, “The Feast of Love,” Mr. Freeman’s character, Harry Stevenson, observes that when the Greek gods were bored, they invented humans. Still bored, they invented love, which wasn’t boring, so they tried it too. Then they invented laughter so they could stand it.  Harry is a semi-retired philosophy professor living in Portland, Ore., with his stately wife, Esther (Jane Alexander). The recent death of their only son, Aaron, from a heroin overdose has shaken but not shattered them. They carry on like benign surrogate parents, or therapists, solemnly monitoring the behavior of the film’s mixed-up younger folks.  Remarks about Greek gods and the foibles of humanity may have their place over brandy and cigars. But despite the kindly gravity Mr. Freeman puts into them, they sound portentous and condescending in the context of “Feast of Love,” a hollow  contrivance masquerading as a wise and witty contemporary gloss on “A Midsummer Night’s Dream.” This is a movie in which the characters’ beliefs in haunted houses and fortunetelling are taken half-seriously. Mr. Benton, now in the twilight of a distinguished career (“Kramer vs. Kramer,” “Places in the Heart”), should have known better.  Mr. Burnett’s clumsy screen adaptation of the novel has merged the author’s voice with Harry’s and relocated the story to Portland from Ann Arbor, Mich.  The city shown in the movie looks as leafy and placid as the Springfield of “Father Knows Best.” This quasi-suburban Everycity is apparently insulated from the global terrors of today. There are few signs of the urban rat race, and real estate is affordable. It could almost be 1975.  Harry’s superior insight is first glimpsed in Jitters, a Starbucks-like coffee shop owned by his friend Bradley  (Greg Kinnear), who boasts of his perfect marriage  to Kathryn (Selma Blair). The three of them are having coffee when Jenny (Stana Katic), seen in a women’s baseball game moments earlier, plunks down beside Kathryn and puts the moves on her under her husband’s nose.  Bradley is oblivious, but Harry notices.  When Kathryn storms out of the house to live with Jenny not long afterward (and disappears from the movie), Harry gently tells Bradley that the evidence was right in front of his eyes, if he had bothered to look.  Mr. Kinnear, like Mr. Freeman, is recycling a stereotype he has played before: a bland, wagging puppy who is smugly clueless and (despite one sweaty lovemaking scene) sexless. Bradley’s tinny shtick becomes the movie’s theme: Is love just nature’s plot to give us lots of babies, or is it the only thing that gives our crazy lives any meaning? It could be a Barry Manilow song.  Even after Bradley’s eyes have been opened, he goes on to repeat a variation of the same mistake. He meets and marries Diana (Radha Mitchell), a beautiful real estate agent who has been carrying on an affair with a married man (Billy Burke) that is too hot to give up. When these dogs in heat get riled up, they slap each other in the face. Bradley would sooner die than slap anyone in the face.  The marital woes of this cardboard man and his search for the perfect mate are the rickety spine around which the movie spins its undercooked dramas. (Another thing undermining “Feast of Love” is the proliferation of multicharacter stories on television that allow room for character development.) The least satisfying story line involves Oscar (Toby Hemingway), an ex-jock and recovering heroin addict in his late teens who works in Jitters, and Chloe (Alexa Davalos), a new girl in town with whom he falls in love the moment she enters the shop. Oscar lives with his abusive father (Fred Ward), a mean, knife-wielding drunk. To stay out of his reach, the cash-starved lovers resort to making a pornographic video, of which a tidbit is shown.  A more accurate name for “Feast of Love” might be “Feast of Breasts.” At every opportunity, Mr. Benton, a director who has always relished showing the female form, turns the camera on his actresses’ gleaming torsos. These beautifully lighted soft-core teases lend an erotic frisson to a movie that in most other ways feels enervated.  “Feast of Love”  is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has nudity, sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>September 28, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>