<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> When F. Scott Fitzgerald remarked that the rich “are different from you and me,”  he might have been thinking of someone like Ogden C. Osborne (Donald Sutherland), the reclusive, moody billionaire who casts a long shadow in Griffin Dunne’s film “Fierce People.” With his blue-eyed, wide-as-the-sky stare, white beard and patriarchal rumble, Mr. Sutherland is the embodiment of a proud old aristocrat, slowly going to ruin, who knows too much about the dark side of human nature for his own comfort. He knows, for instance, that many if not most fortunes begin with crimes.  That’s why a thoughtful response to Fitzgerald’s statement is not as simple as repeating Ernest Hemingway’s disingenuous retort, “Yes, they have more money.” Great wealth confers power, and power changes people. Ogden presides like Louis XIV over his sprawling private kingdom of woods and fields in Vlyvalle, N.J. His wealth not only entitles him to do pretty much as he pleases but also exerts an irresistible force on everyone living within his radius. In “Fierce People” that force is like an invisible toxic gas with a seductively sweet scent that immobilizes people and poisons their souls.  The film, adapted by Dirk Wittenborn from his novel, follows a working-class mother and her teenage son from New York into Ogden’s magic kingdom for a season of disenchantment in the summer of 1980. Liz Earl (Diane Lane), a physical therapist who once treated Ogden, has a drug and alcohol problem. She and her son, Finn (Anton Yelchin), are sheltered in a guest house on his estate after Finn is arrested when he buys cocaine for her. With one phone call to Ogden, who adores her, Liz makes their troubles disappear, and they are whisked away in a limousine driven by a policeman.  Until the drug bust, Finn had planned to spend the summer with his father, “the Elvis of anthropologists,” studying the Ishkanani, a primitive people in the Amazon rain forest known for their cruelty and barbarism. The intriguing conceit of “Fierce People” is that the idle superrich and the Ishkanani, whose rituals are shown on reels of film sent from South America by Finn’s father, are equally vicious.  This is a nifty idea that is laboriously overworked. As “Fierce People” nervously skitters between documentary scenes of the Ishkanani and the story of a mother and son absorbing the tribal customs of the New Jersey gentry, your instinct is throw up your hands and shout, “Enough already; we get it!”  Living on the Osborne estate are Ogden’s terminally sour daughter, Mrs. Langley (Elizabeth Perkins, whose character is even more rancid than the detestable Celia Hodes, her character on the Showtime series “Weeds”), and two seemingly golden grandchildren, Bryce (Chris Evans) and Maya (Kristen Stewart). Viewed through Finn’s eyes, the pretty heir and heiress (with whom Finn has an affair) metamorphose from a storybook prince and princess whom Finn observes with awed fascination into monsters whose sense of entitlement permits them to break any rules they please.  The insistent tribal comparisons render the movie choppy and undermine its narrative momentum. One brief scene of the Ishkanani and another of the young people on the estate playing with body paint and trying on headdresses would have sufficed to establish the analogy. The crucial dramatic turning point, a brutal assault that wrenches the movie in a different direction, is so mishandled that its full horror never registers. The subplot of Liz and Ogden’s relationship, which everyone (including Finn) assumes to be sexual, is underdeveloped, and a sub-subplot involving Liz’s romance with a handsome doctor she meets in Alcoholics Anonymous should have been discarded.  Ms. Lane, as always, is wonderfully complicated to observe. Liz is beautiful and tense but unstable. As she tries to clean up her act, her insecurity registers in subtle twitches of the mouth and glances of stifled anxiety. Mr. Yelchin’s Finn, however, is problematic. The actor infuses Finn with the same Quiz Kid  know-it-all attitude he brought to Byrd Huffstodt, the precocious son of a psychiatrist he played in another Showtime series, “Huff.” A little of his whiny voice musing out loud in a too-deliberate tone goes a long way.  “Fierce People” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes profanity, drug use, nudity and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>September 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>