<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>   "I'm no gangster, I'm a gagster," crows Giacomo (Jackie Dee) DiNorscio, the goombah antihero of Sidney Lumet's gripping courtroom drama "Find Me Guilty."  Wearing a reddish-brown wig, his gut protruding over his belt loops, a goofy leer spreading across his mug, Vin Diesel's Jackie could be the cutup baby brother of Tony Soprano. The role of a wisecracking wise guy  embellishes Mr. Diesel's menacing force field with stand-up comedy and macho sentimentality. At last he plays a real character instead of a swaggering cartoon of testosterone on the rampage.  "Find Me Guilty" resurrects a notorious 1987-88 court case in which 20 men said to be members of the New Jersey-based Lucchese crime family were prosecuted by the federal government on more than 75 criminal counts involving the usual assortment of mob activities. After dragging on for nearly two years, the trial ended with a shocking  outcome.  Jackie alone  insisted on representing himself. While driving both the judge (Ron Silver) and the mob kingpin Nick Calabrese (Alex Rocco) into paroxysms of rage and anxiety, Jackie, whose real-life nickname was Fat Jack, clowned and charmed his way into the hearts of the jury like an uncensored late-night talk show host. Mr. Diesel also succeeds in making a dangerous thug almost lovable with his sensational performance.  Video: Movie Minutes Stephen Holden reviews the courtroom drama "Find Me Guilty," Sidney Lumet's first feature film in seven years.  Mocking conventional courtroom decorum, Jackie portrays himself as a free spirit, brazenly and fearlessly cutting through the official rigmarole to tell it like it is in profane street language spiced with dirty jokes. Face to face with a witness who is a former associate, he accuses him in the most graphic terms of having always lusted after him. Another witness is ridiculed for not knowing the difference between a Lincoln and a Cadillac. Such details skillfully puncture the prosecution's pose of infallibility.  Jackie also skewers  the prosecution's careless ethnic profiling. When a federal agent recalls his surveillance of a room of Italians, Jackie jokingly baits him to describe exactly how he was sure they were Italian.  At the time the indictments are handed down, Jackie is already serving a 30-year sentence for an earlier crime. Offered a reduction in jail time in exchange for becoming a prosecution witness, he bluntly refuses. His insistence that he would never rat out a colleague, even one who had betrayed him, gives him the moral advantage when confronting the feds' star witness, his cousin Tony Compagna (Raúl Esparza). We meet this nervous, drugged-up underling in the movie's opening scene,  when Tony bursts into Jackie's home, dashes upstairs and shoots him several times, failing to kill him. Facing his cousin in court, Jackie expresses only a magnanimous pity for a sick family member, and the witness, humiliated and guilt-stricken, withers before our eyes.  "Find Me Guilty," Mr. Lumet's first feature film in seven years, catches him near the top of his game. Now 81, this master surveyor of the urban jungle still has the machinery of police work and courtroom ritual down cold. His skill at conveying the feel of federal offices, jail cells and the eateries where cops and criminals gather to shoot the breeze is so precise you can almost smell the paint on the walls and the food in the kitchen. Where it can, the screenplay he wrote with T. J. Mancini and Robert J. McCrea uses dialogue taken from court transcripts.  Thanks to "The Godfather," "GoodFellas," "The Sopranos" and their countless imitations, the characters in contemporary mob dramas are now such beloved clichés that they are almost like family. Or rather, they are cherished fantasy projections of ourselves in a shadow version of a society obsessed with family values and corporate upward mobility.  With its herd of 20 defendants and nearly as many lawyers, "Find Me Guilty" suggests a panoramic episode of "The Sopranos," with a little casting overlap. The most incendiary cameo belongs to Annabella Sciorra (who played Tony Soprano's suicidal girlfriend, Gloria) as Bella, Jackie's bitter ex-wife. It is only one of many excellent supporting performances. Mr. Silver, directing his eyes like drills into a mudflat, personifies cold judicial imperiousness. Peter Dinklage's chief defense attorney projects a more gentlemanly and well-spoken but equally ferocious gravitas. Linus Roache's smug chief prosecutor slowly and subtly begins losing his cool as Jackie's outrageous courtroom antics captivate the jury.  Looked at in a different way, "Find Me Guilty" could be taken as a serious comedy about the baleful impact of television on the criminal justice system, as the next step to media madness after Mr. Lumet's film "Network." Because the events in the movie preceded the Menendez  brothers and O. J. Simpson murder trials and the debuts of Court TV and "Law &amp; Order," the film offers a tasty prelude to the era when crime and punishment expanded from part-time television entertainment into a fulltime spectator sport that merged fiction and reality.  In other words, Jackie Dee was a reality-star-in-waiting  while the demonic recipe for a mediathon immersion was still being perfected.  "Find Me Guilty" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian).  It has abundant profanity and scenes of intense violence.</text>
      <date>March 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>