<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> If the title “Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas” didn’t already belong to Hunter S. Thompson, it would perfectly fit Peter Tolan’s viciously funny satire, “Finding Amanda.” Set mostly in Sin City, it offers a through-the-looking-glass vision of confused Americans losing their already shaky bearings in the world’s gaudiest honky-tonk.  On the ground floor of a luxury hotel, the title character (Brittany Snow), a perky, wholesome-looking 20-year-old blonde, cheerfully accosts potbellied middle-aged tourists for quickie oral sex as they step out of the elevator. When her sad-sack uncle, Taylor Mendon (Matthew Broderick), arrives from Pasadena to beg Amanda to go into rehab (although she insists she doesn’t take drugs, except for the occasional tab of Ecstasy), she excuses herself for a few minutes to turn a quick trick with a geezer in a Stetson hat.  Amanda boasts that she can earn more in one weekend servicing eight customers than she made in a month working at the International House of Pancakes. And the work is so easy, she chirps. She has even bought a house. In a nasty running joke, no one believes Taylor when he introduces himself as Amanda’s uncle. The assumption that he is a pesky john lands him in trouble with security guards and pimps eager to demonstrate their protective gallantry to the pretty lady.  “Finding Amanda” is an easy movie to reject because its microcosm of a society obsessed with commercial sex and fast money is so relentlessly, uncomfortably and casually dark. Everyone is for sale, even the garishly attired middle-aged bartender at  the Aztec casino who wrongly assumes that Taylor is referring to him when  he asks about finding paid companionship.  The only comparably cynical recent film set in Las Vegas was Peter Berg’s savage 1998 comedy, “Very Bad Things,” in which a bachelor party  takes a tragic turn. That film wasn’t as funny as “Finding Amanda,” because the dialogue, sharp as it was, lacked the absurdist razor edge of this curdled screwball comedy. Here the characters’ outlandish utterances (especially Amanda’s) will make you gasp.  Mr. Broderick’s Taylor is an updated version of a Dudley Moore character on a bender, but sadder and far less energetic. An about-to-be-fired writer for a failing sitcom,  he is a recovering alcohol, drug and gambling addict and congenital liar whose wife, Lorraine (Maura Tierney), throws him out after he lies to her about betting at the track. Underneath everything, he is a befuddled 43-year-old lost boy who knows right from wrong but is helpless in the throes of his gambling addiction.  Taylor decides to find his niece to placate Lorraine by demonstrating his selflessness. But the trip is really an excuse to revisit Las Vegas and slip back into his old ways. Because he used to be a big-time loser in the hotel’s casino, he is welcomed like a returning hero. His credit card having been taken away, he finances his gambling binge with a check stolen from Lorraine. As he wheedles more money from the casino host (Steve Coogan), his compulsion crushes his common sense.  The movie’s sleaziest character is Amanda’s monstrous live-in boyfriend, Greg (Peter Facinelli), a selfish tyrant who lives off Amanda, cheats on her in her house while she is away and smacks her around when she protests. After one beating she screams, “Don’t ever hit me again!” and he furiously retorts, “Don’t make me!”  Two-thirds of the way in,  “Finding Amanda” takes a screeching turn into pathos in a scene  where Amanda’s happy-go-lucky facade suddenly crumbles and her misery and self-loathing pour out. The smidgens of self-awareness that Taylor and Amanda exhibit make their destructive personal choices seem all the more appalling. The misanthrope in you will chortle;  these fools deserve every setback that comes their way and every laugh at their expense.  “Finding Amanda”  is rated  R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, profanity and drug-taking.</text>
      <date>June 27, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>