<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At once funnier than it should be and more witless than it should have been, “Fired Up!” is the latest addition to the wave of cheerleader movies that first hit way back in 2000 with “Bring It On.” Although the deeper reasons for this sub-genre’s new popularity remain obscure — a character in “Fired Up!” does mention that George W. Bush was a cheerleader before he was president — it’s clear that the spectacle of flexible and lithe young female hardbodies stretching and jumping and bending over to salute the camera with their derrières constitutes its own rationale, particularly when a studio is in the stupid business.  Hence “Fired Up!,” a kind of dumb but also kind of smart-about-being-dumb comedy centered on two teenage horndogs on full sniff at a cheerleading camp. Football players and best friends, Shawn (Nicholas D’Agosto) and Nick (Eric Christian Olsen), both of whom look well north of 20, join their school’s cheerleading squad in order to spend part of their summer at a camp surrounded by little ladies  in tiny tops and micro shorts. Though the boys are in it for the honeys, the story gets sticky when Shawn develops a crush on the squad’s leader, Carly (Sarah Roemer), a predictable turnabout that allows the filmmakers to indulge in all sorts of ha-ha sexist blather and high jinks before Mr. Porky makes way for Mr. Sensitivity.  The director, Will Gluck, making his feature debut, hasn’t a clue where to put the camera, but he gives the pop-culturally savvy lines rhythm and zing. “You know what John Lennon said,” one teenager says in a typical exchange. “Not really,” says the other, “I’m not in my 50s.”  Someone behind the scenes here appears to have ambition, at least on the page: the script also includes an out-of-context and -character riff pegged to Hepburn and Tracy, which suggests that the anonymous screenwriters, working under the team name Freedom Jones, are taking a few cues from that screwball postmodernist Diablo Cody. (A clip from “On the Waterfront,” by contrast, seems like a bid to prove that the filmmakers aren’t as shallow as their movie.)  Still, no matter how meta and self-consciously knowing, teen  comedies like “Fired Up!” are basically just recycling the same jokes, plots and mating rituals that fueled the Frankie and Annette beach party flicks of the 1960s. These new parties tend to be racier, of course, but they nonetheless boil down to a scantily clad boy going gaga over a scantily clad girl amid the usual cacophony of thudding music, a phalanx of adolescent wisenheimers and at least one wacky, sexually ambiguous authority figure. Paul Lynde took on that role, if without much ambiguity, in the 1965 Frankie and Annette romp “Beach Blanket Bingo,” and here John Michael Higgins does same as Coach Keith, pompom royalty.  “Fired Up!” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Double-entendres and triple-time raunch.</text>
      <date>February 20, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>