<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Ice Cube’s recent movie roles, in the “Barbershop” and “Are We There Yet?” franchises, have emphasized his cuddly, family-man side. In “First Sunday,” which is not  a new installment in the earlier “Friday” series, he departs a bit from the upright-citizen persona, playing a man driven to crime by desperate circumstances.  But “First Sunday,” the first   theatrically released feature film written and directed by David E. Talbert, is a comedy. Like Tyler Perry, Mr. Talbert has had a successful —  and to the white media, nearly invisible —  career as a playwright and theatrical entrepreneur, and his movie debut fuses social observation and raucous, clean humor with a message of redemption.  Ice Cube, not exactly a mirthful performer, requires an antic sidekick, and he has a pretty good one here in Tracy Morgan. Mr. Morgan plays LeeJohn, the feckless stoner half of a hapless pair of robbers. Durell, Ice Cube’s character, is the more  practical half of the team. Because he needs $17,000 to prevent his ex-girlfriend from moving with their son from Baltimore to Atlanta, Durell decides to rob a church.  What kind of person would rob a church? This question occupies most of the movie’s slow, talky middle third, in which an easy in-and-out safecracking scheme turns into a hostage drama. Durell and LeeJohn’s captives include the wise pastor (Chi McBride); his pretty, headstrong daughter (Malinda Williams); a shifty deacon (Michael Beach) and the flamboyantly queeny choir director (Katt Williams), among other easily recognizable church-movie stock figures.  Mr.  Williams pretty much steals the movie by rolling his eyes and muttering under his breath. And if Mr. Talbert does not quite manage the shift in tone from rambunctious comedy to earnest uplift, he is nonetheless generous with both the characters and the audience. “First Sunday” sometimes feels more like a script read-through than like an actual movie, but its warmth is likely to carry you through the stretches of cliché and tedium.    “First Sunday” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has mild profanity and drug references.</text>
      <date>January 11, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>