<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A pointed little thriller with metaphysical pretensions, “First Snow” is shrewd enough to approach basic philosophical questions in sneaky, offhand ways. Are our individual fates sealed, or can we alter them by changing our behavior? In trying to shape our destinies, are we just bringing them on? Is knowing the future a blessing because it allows us to plan ahead and make amends, or a curse that can’t be shaken?  “First Snow,” the directorial debut of Mark Fergus, filters such questions through the unlikable character of Jimmy Starks (Guy Pearce), a shifty, sharp-shooting flooring salesman based near Albuquerque whose desperate edge recalls Mr. Pearce’s memory-challenged character in “Memento.” In his latest scheme to hit the jackpot, he is raising money to buy up a cache of vintage Wurlitzer jukeboxes and sell them to bars around the country.  Putting the kind of  fast-talking salesman who would be at home in a David Mamet play through the existential wringer suggests that “First Snow” is an examination of the all-American karma of greed and the self-made man, but it’s only partly that. A noirish thriller that revels in ominous visual moods, deepened by Cliff Martinez’s spare, shivering guitar score, this heartland “Appointment in Samarra” is a mind-teaser that speaks the flat, evasive language of its seedy characters. Mr. Fergus and his screenwriting collaborator Hawk Ostby belonged to the writing team on “Children of Men.” They may not have Mr. Mamet’s acute ear, but their dialogue captures the vacant cheery tone of salesmen on the make.  Gaunt, rat-eyed and sweaty, with greasy, shoulder-length hair, Jimmy lives with his girlfriend, Deirdre (Piper Perabo), in desert high country dotted with ugly fake-adobe houses. At the beginning of the movie, he fires his protégé, Andy (Rick Gonzalez), for skimming money off the top, even though it was something Jimmy had taught him how to do. Jimmy also balks at moving to Taos with Deirdre (an underwritten role) to live a more settled existence.  One afternoon while waiting at a depot for his car to be repaired, Jimmy notices a trailer with a sign offering $10 fortunetelling and decides to plunk down the cash. When he asks  Vacaro (J. K. Simmons), the grizzled, hangdog-eyed seer, to predict the outcome of a basketball game, he is assured that the New Mexico Wolves will win —  unlikely, since the team’s star player has been injured. Vacaro also tells him that a windfall will arrive by way of Dallas, but Jimmy knows no one there.  Suddenly Vacaro goes into a seizure. When he recovers,  he insists that Jimmy take back his money. Jimmy dismisses the incident until the Wolves pull off a surprise victory, and he learns of unexpected backing for the jukebox enterprise from a source in Dallas.  Shaken, Jimmy returns to the trailer, points a gun at Vacaro’s head and demands to know the vision that produced the seizure.  After a pause, Vacaro says wearily: “I saw no more roads, no more tomorrows. But you’re safe until the first snow.”  Jimmy begins to come apart. Winter is approaching, and the radio warns of a blizzard. The landscape is charged with a sullen foreboding. Threatening drawings arrive in the mail, along with eerie, static-filled  phone messages that suggest that Jimmy is being stalked.  He decides that Andy is out to get him. Or could it be Vince, his best childhood buddy, who was recently discharged from prison after serving three years for a money-laundering scheme concocted by the two of them? Jimmy had betrayed his friend to avoid going to prison.  As Jimmy, besieged by paranoia and guilt, desperately pursues answers, you half expect the movie to take a turn into horror, but it remains on its circular track inside his tormented mind. When it turns a little soft, you wonder if it will tumble into mawkish “Touched by an Angel” territory, but it remains dry-eyed.  The story slowly builds to a pained reunion of Jimmy and Vince, whose life is now in shambles.  Finally, when the first real snow begins to fall, it’s almost a relief. For better or for worse, this is it.  “First Snow” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, strong language and violence.</text>
      <date>March 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>