<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Flannel Pajamas” is the unassuming title of a film that might more accurately have been called “Scenes From a Mixed Marriage” or “Annie Hall Without Laughs.” The twin specters of Ingmar Bergman and Woody Allen hover over this talky history of a relationship between two New Yorkers — from courtship to marriage to separation —  yet it conveys little sense of the volcanic emotional upheaval evoked so memorably in Mr. Bergman’s ’70s masterpiece, “Scenes From a Marriage.”  Instead of opposing armies clashing in a primal battle of the sexes, or mismatched romantics wistfully waving at each other from a distance, the film portrays domestic discord as a series of tiny skirmishes in a civilized and ultimately banal power struggle between two people with incompatible agendas. The combatants, Stuart (Justin Kirk) and Nicole (Julianne Nicholson), who meet on a blind date, are garden-variety urban neurotics who express their disharmony in snits and sulks instead of rages and Shakespearean soliloquies.  To put it another way, we are these people, or rather those of us who have difficulty expressing full-blown anger. Passive-aggression is the prevailing (and sometimes cringe-inducing) psychological mode.  The personal issues bedeviling Stuart and Nicole may not be your issues or mine, but the couple’s mild-mannered approach to dealing with them may feel uncomfortably familiar if you belong to the college-educated class of New York professionals that believes in talking things out. You might call it the modern, pragmatic, couples-counseling approach to problem solving, as opposed to, say, primal scream therapy or (God forbid) domestic violence.  The adage that the Devil is in the details applies to Stuart and Nicole’s marriage, whose success or failure  depends on things as trivial as one partner’s dropping everything to fetch coffee for the other at a stressful moment. The tone of “Flannel Pajamas” is the same hyper-articulate one that Jeff Lipsky, who wrote and directed the movie, brought to his 1997 debut film, “Childhood’s End.”  In the mixed marriage under the film’s microscope, Stuart, a cocky, Long Island-born Jewish promoter of Broadway shows (who weirdly seems to have no social life), courts and marries Nicole, an aspiring caterer, chef and cookbook writer from Missoula, Mont., whose Irish Catholic family has a history of alcoholism.  It isn’t until very late in the film when Nicole’s mother, Elizabeth (Rebecca Schull), bluntly voices her anti-Semitism that the differences in their cultural backgrounds snap into focus as a residual force driving them apart.  Mr. Lipsky’s screenplay, a messy collection of fragments arranged chronologically, adds up to one of the most intimate screen portraits of a relationship ever attempted. The movie literally strips its characters naked, with full frontal nude shots of both (they’re reasonably attractive people in their 30’s) and unvarnished if not very graphic sex scenes that convincingly demonstrate the characters’ erotic chemistry.  In assessing Stuart’s and Nicole’s characters, the movie wants to play fair but ends up favoring Stuart, a glib romancer who pays off Nicole’s student loans and encourages her to set up a catering business in his 36th-floor Manhattan high-rise (with river view). When things go wrong, he says all the right things to try to win her back.  The first major sign of trouble appears when Nicole announces that she would like to start a family immediately (she wants three children), and Stuart asks her to wait for two years so they can enjoy each other without distraction. She agrees reluctantly, as long as they can have a dog in the meantime, but he resists even that.  “Flannel Pajamas” teems with more subsidiary characters than it can comfortably handle. They include Stuart’s mentally unstable brother, Jordan (Jamie Harrold),  who infuriates Nicole by having loud, combative trysts when he stays at their apartment. Stuart detests Nicole’s cynical best friend, Tess (Chelsea Altman), a nurse who sleeps around.  Although the film includes some lovely set pieces (the couple’s wedding in Missoula is a triumph of ensemble acting), its loose structure makes much of it feel haphazardly thrown together. The 124 minutes  would be considerably more absorbing had greater care been taken in developing a coherent narrative momentum.  “Flannel Pajamas” nevertheless maintains a stubborn integrity, and its comfortably lived-in lead performances feel authentic. It is also slightly dispiriting.</text>
      <date>November 15, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>