<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Flash of Genius” is a doggedly workmanlike variation of an old story: the lone crusader doing battle with the big bad establishment.  Picture Jimmy Stewart as a passionately outraged everyman speaking truth to power, then take away the passion.  What gives the movie a frisson of freshness is that the little guy is based on an actual person, Dr. Robert W. Kearns (Greg Kinnear), an electrical engineer and college professor who in the late 1960s invented and patented the intermittent windshield wiper. After he presented his invention to the major Detroit automakers, Ford demanded a sample unit, then adopted his system without paying him or giving him credit. He ultimately sued Ford and then Chrysler for patent infringement.  Like the invention at the heart of the story, “Flash of Genius” is a meticulously constructed mechanism, one that wants to convey the same mixture of idealism, obsession and paranoia found in whistle-blower movies like “Silkwood” and “The Insider.” Adapted from a 1993 New Yorker article by John Seabrook and directed by Marc Abraham from a screenplay by Philip Railsback, it has the tone and texture of a well-made but forgettable television movie.  At least in its climactic courtroom scenes “Flash of Genius” evenhandedly lays out the opposing arguments of Ford and Kearns, who acts as his own defense lawyer. It also does an exemplary job of articulating the legal issues, with an assist from Charles Dickens’s “Tale of Two Cities,” which is used to illustrate an important point.  The scenes of Kearns’s domestic life with his wife, Phyllis (Lauren Graham), a schoolteacher, and their six children convey the family’s messy, unglamorous ’60s existence. During his final push for a trial by jury, after he is offered generous settlements but no credit for his invention, several of his children work as his assistants.  The visibly aging children, played by different actors as they grow older, are the movie’s principal indicators of how much time has passed. Mr. Kinnear, appearing baggy-eyed and anxious throughout the film, and Ms. Graham, looking drably attractive, barely change. The movie  doesn’t specify the year or even the decade in which events are taking place except by pop music cues and changing car models. “Flash of Genius” would have been more gripping had it pinpointed events and conveyed the harrowing physical, emotional and financial cost of Kearns’s quest.  It is encouraging to see Mr. Kinnear, who was so perfectly cast as a screwball rake in “Ghost Town,” undertaking more serious adult roles in which he doesn’t play cute or bratty. But he is no Jimmy Stewart. You never have the feeling that he represents a cause larger than his character’s own personal grievance. Mr. Kinnear is a small-scale screen presence comfortable projecting worry, frustration and even nagging obsession; moral heroism is beyond him.  Kearns is first seen being escorted by Maryland state police off a Greyhound bus headed for Washington, where he intends to plead his case. Taken to a mental hospital, he is treated for a nervous breakdown and released as soon as his doctor decides his obsession has subsided.  The story backtracks to his days in his basement tinkering on the invention, which he and his skittish business partner, Gil (Dermot Mulroney), hope will make them rich. Those dreams are dashed when Ford suddenly and suspiciously loses interest. The final moment of truth arrives when he crashes a Ford dealers convention at which the Mustang is unveiled with the intermittent wiper as a prominent selling point. From then on his pursuit  of recognition for an invention he calls his Mona Lisa is relentless.  But it all feels like déjà vu. If we must have stories about heroic little guys going after bullies, maybe it’s time for a true story of a shareholder in a bankrupt investment company suing its filthy rich  chief executive for his golden parachute and winning. To be a true story, of course, it  would have to happen.  “Flash of Genius” is rated  PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>October 3, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>