<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Flawless” is a mildly diverting period heist movie in which an odd couple conspire to loot an  evil London diamond company, for which they both work. In the story, set in 1960, before the term glass ceiling was coined,  Demi Moore plays Laura Quinn, a grimly ambitious company executive of 40 whose career has stalled. Early in the movie she learns that the pompous, corrupt gargoyles who stole her ideas intend to fire her.  An Oxford-educated American with a  British-American accent, Ms. Moore’s Laura is a forerunner of Meredith Johnson, the barracuda she played with such fearsome intensity in “Disclosure.” Where Meredith wielded sexual harassment charges as a weapon for career advancement, Laura has no tools with which to fight. The world of “Flawless” predates the very  expression sexual harassment. Steely in mind and body, this apparently loveless, friendless woman has sacrificed everything for success in business.  Her unlikely partner in crime, Mr. Hobbs (Michael Caine, in a role he has played before), is the company’s sneaky janitor. Abjectly shuffling through the corridors with his pail and mop, Hobbs, who lost his wife to cancer 15 years earlier, is such a harmless-looking creature that he is able to steal virtually unnoticed into executive suites and rifle through personnel files. But as we eventually learn, he has a serious personal ax to grind. Hobbs is the one who discovers that Laura’s days at the company are numbered, and he uses the information to enlist her in a robbery scheme.  The movie, directed by Michael Radford (“Il Postino”) from a screenplay by Edward A. Anderson, works at cross-purposes. It wants to transport us  to the innocent, carefree days of traditional British caper movies in the Age of Bond, when the game was the thing. But since the product being marketed is diamonds mined in South Africa, it also feels obliged to tip its hat to the Age of “Blood Diamond”  and affect a political consciousness.  We hear of a riot by striking miners in which many were killed. But that information has no resonance. It is just another signal that the London company is rotten to the core.  During its first third “Flawless” ticks along like an inexpensive watch. Hobbs approaches Laura to get the codes to the vault holding the diamonds. In a last-minute glitch the company installs a  surveillance cameras. But Hobbs finds a solution, and the crime’s execution is reasonably suspenseful.  It is only after the robbery that “Flawless” becomes more complicated and unpredictable. The bosses fight among themselves about whether to pay a ransom, and the thieves come under the scrutiny  of a suave insurance investigator, Finch (Lambert Wilson), who shows a slight romantic interest in Laura, whose relationship with Hobbs ruptures. None of it makes much sense. In an extra, unnecessary layer, “Flawless” is told as a flashback in which the aged Laura brings her story to a magazine editor.  The movie’s strongest moment is the opening sequence of hands foraging for diamonds in a muddy stream and coming up with a rock that is chiseled, sanded and polished into a 168-carat monster stone with 58 facets. The scene reminds us that diamond dealing begins with dirty hands scrounging in the muck.  “Flawless” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>March 28, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>