<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Girl meets horse yet again in “Flicka,” an entertainingly ridiculous update of Mary O’Hara’s 1941 children’s novel, “My Friend Flicka.” Alison Lohman stars as Katy McLaughlin (a boy named Ken in the original story), a boarding-school student on the verge of flunking out because her head is in the clouds, where she has apparently been huffing pure oxygen since last semester.  That, at least, might explain why this pouty miss with an unruly mane and a thing for horses spends much of her summer break flouncing around the male help with jail-bait insouciance, sassing her parents (the country-music star Tim McGraw and a wide-smiling Maria Bello) and almost killing the object of her sublimated desire.  Set on a horse ranch in a spectacularly pristine, mountainous swath of Wyoming, far from the madding crowd and any vestige of polluting contemporary life, “Flicka” looks as fetchingly unreal as a presidential campaign commercial designed by Martha Stewart. Ms. Bello’s ripely amusing performance, with its blend of no-fuss professionalism and twinkling-eye intensity, adds to the strikingly thin air of unreality, whether her character (whom Mr. McGraw risibly calls Mama) has rustled up wild gooseberry pancakes with crème fraîche for breakfast or is gardening in the afternoon sun with a flashing grin and an impeccably coiffed fall of hair (no ponytail) worthy of a Wisteria Lane hausfrau. She’s not desperate, but she very well may be stoned.  Ms. Bello is welcome company, particularly because her presence among all the cowboy hats and manure summons memories of David Cronenberg’s “History of Violence,” an equally otherworldly if considerably superior and knowing fiction about the clash between old-fashioned values and modern-day pragmatism. Here, Katy wants to live free or at least break the beautiful black mustang she happens on while out riding. For his part, her father, a man of few words, simple thoughts and no discernible personality, wants Katy to go back to daydreaming in school, not yet realizing that her hunky brother, Howard (Ryan Kwanten), who likes to lounge around with a bare chest and perfectly fitted cutoff jeans, would sooner become an Abercrombie &amp; Fitch model than take over the ranch.  What’s a family to do? Not a whole lot, as it happens. Directed by Michael Mayer and written by Mark Rosenthal and Lawrence Konner, “Flicka” is padded with minor incident and a wealth of beauty shots that inspire intense vacation-home envy, but the parts never cohere dramatically. Mr. Mayer dutifully draws lines between Katy’s efforts to tame her wild horse and her father’s more cumbersome attempts to corral her, but he can’t spin this metaphoric hay into gold. What he does do very nicely, however, aided and abetted by an expression of unfettered ecstasy on Ms. Lohman’s face that gives her the aspect of St. Teresa of Avila, is confirm that nothing should ever come between a girl and her horse, especially a saddle.  “Flicka” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some very mild language.</text>
      <date>October 20, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>