<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Don’t get me wrong: I’m looking forward to the next James Bond movie as much as anyone else. But it strikes me as unlikely that any British action picture released this year will surpass “Flushed Away.”  Yes, the 007 franchise has the gadgetry, the babes and the dry martinis, but does it have google-eyed, rubber-mouthed leeches (unless they were slugs, or maybe some kind of aquatic worm) singing “Don’t Worry, Be Happy” in splendid choral harmony? (I know, I never wanted to hear it again either, but trust me, you haven’t really experienced the song until you’ve heard it performed by leeches.) Does Mr. Bond have Kate Winslet as his love interest? (Playing a sewer rat, yes. But still. Kate Winslet.) Is his nemesis a giant toad with a fondness for royal family paraphernalia and an obsessive hatred of rodents?  I could go on, but I’ve made my point. “Flushed Away,” directed by David Bowers and Sam Fell, is the first computer-animated feature to come from the very English whimsy factory that is Aardman Animations, progenitors of Wallace and Gromit, Rex the Runt and “Chicken Run.” (DreamWorks, a co-producer of “Chicken Run,” was also involved with “Flushed Away.”)  The technological shift from the traditional Aardman stop-motion animation, using plasticine models, has given the filmmakers new freedom and flexibility — for instance, in confecting sequences that take place in and under water — but the eccentric, handmade “Wallace and Gromit” aesthetic remains happily intact. And at a time when all-ages three-dimensional animation seems to be in a serious rut (how many more movie-star-voiced pleas for interspecies understanding must we be subjected to?), it is a relief to encounter such exuberant and infectious silliness.  At first, “Flushed Away” does not seem so different from its lesser competitors, even as it dares to aim a few mocking jabs at Pixar, the top dog in the computer-animation world. At one point the sentimentality of “Finding Nemo” is grazed by a satirical harpoon, and the story begins in an expansive London house whose clean spaces and tidy right angles recall “Toy Story.” So, at first, does the situation in which the hero, a pet mouse named Roddy (Hugh Jackman), finds himself when his young owner and her family have gone on vacation. He cavorts with the Barbies and the Kens, but this is a lonely, empty pastime — they’re just toys, after all — and it seems to promise a boring movie.    As it happens, a less boring movie would be hard to imagine. Roddy’s life, as they say, is changed forever when an uncouth rat named Sid (Shane Richie) pops up through the plumbing. Roddy, trying to rid himself of the interloper, finds himself sent down the pipes, where he is accidentally introduced into a world of subterranean urban vermin delights.  In spite of the title and the necessity of using a toilet as a portal to the London sewer, the humor in “Flushed Away” is mostly clean. The narrative, on the other hand, is gratifyingly messy, as Roddy, washed up in a miniature London built out of trash and flotsam beneath the actual city, becomes embroiled in some fairly complicated intrigue. He falls in with Rita (Ms. Winslet), who pilots an old boat, and who is harassed by the grandiose toad (Ian McKellen) and his minions, a veritable charcuterie platter of voice-over excess featuring Bill Nighy, Andy Serkis, and Jean Reno as the toad’s French cousin, who is (naturellement!) a frog.  As is the custom with Aardman productions, there is a sweet and modest decency — a wry celebration of Traditional British Values, if you will — peeking out amid the clamor and craziness. (The pop-cultural references and canny music selections, meanwhile, mark “Flushed Away” as an all-American DreamWorks animation product.)  The filmmakers also take evident pleasure in topping themselves, and in conceiving a structure that is less like a roller coaster ride than a ski jump. The picture relentlessly picks up speed, zooming from drollery to anarchy to complete — albeit brilliantly controlled — comic chaos, and before you know it, you’re airborne (even if, strictly speaking, you’re still in the sewer), carried aloft on the wings of leeches.  “Flushed Away” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has a few mildly naughty jokes.</text>
      <date>November 3, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>