<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One way to enjoy “Forgetting Sarah Marshall” — at least vicariously — is to think of the movie as the Judd Apatow Stock Company’s Hawaiian vacation. Those pasty-faced funny guys have been working awfully hard over the past few years, so who can begrudge them a few weeks of surf, sun, babes and fun? I don’t know if Mr. Apatow himself, a producer of this movie (the director is the first-timer Nicholas Stoller), went along for the trip. The members of his troupe who did managed to squeeze in enough work to placate the I.R.S., and also that segment of the audience, myself included, whose appetite for naturally sweetened raunch has not yet abated.  Jason Segel, author of the film’s screenplay and a fixture in Mr. Apatow’s universe since the television series “Freaks and Geeks,” takes his allotted turn as the romantic lead, which is to say as a slobby, goofy but basically decent fellow navigating the uncertain waters of modern sexual ethics. He does so at an island resort where the evening sun bathes the palm trees in honeyed light and imparts a gemlike sparkle to the Pacific Ocean.  Supporting Mr. Segel are some of the usual gang — Jonah  Hill as a waiter, Paul Rudd as a surfing instructor, Bill Hader as the brother back home in Los Angeles — and a few newish dudes (notably Jack McBrayer and Da’vone McDonald) stepping up to deliver YouTube-ready riffs on matters of eros and pop culture. (Politics, the actual YouTube obsession of the moment, doesn’t really exist in Mr. Apatow’s world.)  Not that everything is breezy and casual. “Forgetting Sarah Marshall” is, after all, a breakup comedy, and its overall jollity is streaked with some raw emotions, including jealousy, heartache and humiliation. A few minutes in, Peter Bretter (Mr. Segel), a composer who writes the music for a television cop series, is peremptorily dumped by Sarah Marshall (Kristen Bell), his girlfriend of five years, who is one of the show’s stars. Sarah has taken up with a louche, longhaired British rocker, Aldous Snow (Russell Brand), with whom she escapes to the same vacation spot where Peter, after a montage of meaningless hookups, goes to heal his battered soul. An important axiom is thus established early on: To a single, gainfully employed man in Los Angeles, sex comes easily. Love, however, is hard.  Or complicated, anyway, which is not the same thing. Once in Hawaii, Peter meets — in addition to a beachful of amusing bit players — the friendly, dark-haired receptionist you kind of suspect will be Sarah’s replacement. Her name is Rachel, she is played by Mila Kunis, and she has, for purposes of symmetry, her own history of romantic trouble. But the bad boyfriend in her past may not be quite enough to establish the enabling conceit that a woman like this would be (a) unattached and (b) likely to fall for Peter.  Still, “Forgetting Sarah Marshall” does not entirely play by the established conventions of its genre. Its willingness to explore states of feeling and modes of behavior that tamer romantic comedies never go near is decidedly a virtue, though this same sense of daring and candor also exposes its limitations.  Speaking of which, the filmmakers forgo the cheap and easy thrill of female nudity, preferring the display of male flesh for comic effect. Ms. Bell, Ms. Kunis and Maria Thayer (as a voracious honeymooner in an amusing subplot) keep their tops and bottoms covered even when vigorously feigning naked passion. Mr. Segel, however, appears, near the beginning of the film and again toward the end, in his unclothed entirety, a spectacle that I must report did not entirely impress a quite vocal woman a few rows behind me at the sneak preview. Mr. Segel’s willingness to face the kind of criticism she voiced is surely to his credit.  So is his ability to display both Peter’s charms and his unappealing traits — he is a loose-faced, needy, ingratiating Labrador retriever of a man — and to orchestrate a comedy of betrayal and cruelty that rarely feels meanspirited. For much of the movie’s first half, Sarah seems to be a climber and a two-timer, cheating on her devoted, unglamorous boyfriend and then ditching him for an oversexed celebrity. But at least briefly the perspective is flipped, as Sarah, accompanied by illustrative flashbacks, gently and persuasively explains to Peter what a drag he was when they were together — what a mopey, self-absorbed loser.  Which, curiously enough, is what catches Rachel’s eye in the first place. Her attraction to Peter originates not in lust but rather in pity. Something similar happened in “Freaks and Geeks,” when Linda Cardellini’s character started going out with Mr. Segel’s  largely because she felt sorry for him. In that case, though, the girl’s point of view was much more central, and the shakiness of the ensuing adolescent relationship was both funnier and truer than this grown-up variation on it.  The Rachel-Peter romance is charming but not, in the end, especially credible or interesting. That the contrastingly but equally gorgeous Rachel and Sarah end up as rivals for Peter’s favor is likely to flatter the self-esteem — or at least feed the fantasies — of doughy, underachieving regular guys across America. Which is nice for them, us, whatever.  But the schlub-hottie pairings that have become ubiquitous on screen lately also reinforce a dreary double standard. Guys are permitted to be flabby, lazy emotional wrecks, but as long as they crack jokes, some action will come their way. Girls, ideally, should have a sense of humor — mainly so they can laugh at those jokes — but for the most part they should look good in a bikini and like sex (though not too much and not anything too weird). Maybe someday, though probably not under Mr. Apatow’s aegis, a relatively ordinary-looking woman will have a sex comedy of her own.  “Forgetting Sarah Marshall” is rated R (under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has crude sexual humor and full-frontal male nudity.</text>
      <date>April 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>