<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A silly-sweet, gay romantic comedy aimed primarily at teenage and college-age audiences, "Formula 17" placed ninth in Taiwan's 2004 ranking of highest-grossing Chinese-language films. Partly because of its bouncy, bubblegum soundtrack and enormously appealing leads, this tiny indie has connected with a generation typically critical of homegrown talent. And by studding her film with signifiers of generic infatuation - like using a mirror to rehearse a kiss, or learning to say "I love you" in different languages - the director, DJ Chen, has breached barriers of sexual orientation with surprising success.  Armed with a red suitcase and his lucky condom, the virginal Tien (the soap star Tony Yang) arrives in Taipei looking for love and a summer job. Tien, whose favorite book is "Love Is a Kind of Faith,"  is a bit of a priss. "I despise people who toy with love," he tells Bai (Duncan Chow), a smooth playboy with a come-hither gaze and seductively feathered hair.  The two are frantically attracted to each other, but their courtship is hindered by Tien's inexperience and Bai's understandable reluctance to reveal his "serial one-night-stander" dating philosophy. So when Tien's tasteful, soft-focus deflowering precedes the L word, the stage is set for heartache, misunderstanding and more pouting than an episode of "Desperate Housewives."  Working safely within the familiar romantic framework of desire, consummation, loss and reconciliation, Ms. Chen has created a charmingly cosmopolitan world where characters express themselves in a polyglot of Mandarin, Cantonese, English and occasionally French. Though Tien's ebullient bartender friend, Yu (the delightful King Chin, whose expressive face is that of a natural clown), has a white boyfriend, the difficulties in their relationship are work- rather than race-related. This gay paradise may be rife with stereotypes - and completely devoid of women - but the movie's breeziness and buoyant good humor (as when Tien is propositioned by an amorous plumber, played by Yang Tze-Long) are difficult to resist. No one here is mean or spiteful; everyone just wants love to prevail.  More interested in romance than sex, "Formula 17" swoons with youthful innocence. The film's Chinese title translates as "17-Year-Old's World," and Ms. Chen, a savvy 24-year-old, has peppered her movie with cellphones, e-mail and instant messaging - the essential tools of teenage dating. Cleverly using humor to nail the self-centeredness of adolescence, she has created a protagonist who needs a tailor's dummy to break down intimacy barriers. And if the movie's melodramatic conclusion doesn't leave you with a silly smile on your face, it's probably because you're not human.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>