<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Given the tasty cocktail of self-amusement and self-contempt  that Vince Vaughn brings to almost every on-screen party, it seemed possible that this was one guy who would just say no to Merry Christmas. Forget it: “Fred Claus” is a tacky would-be comedy about family dysfunction that fronts some Scrooge attitude only to dissolve into slobbering sentimentality and canned uplift. Neither here nor there, the film is “Elf” without the goofy jokes, Will Ferrell or heart, “Bad Santa” without the smut, Billy Bob Thornton or spleen.  Mainly it’s a lackadaisical mess, though one graced with welcome talent, including Paul Giamatti and Miranda Richardson. (Here’s hoping these indie stalwarts pocketed decent  studio checks for keeping their gifts in idle.) Mr. Vaughn plays Fred Claus, the disgruntled eldest brother of Nicholas Claus a k a Santa Claus a k a St. Nick a k a Mr. Giamatti, wearing a fat suit and snowy clouds of hair and beard.  Once upon a storybook time the Claus boys were born (to Kathy Bates), only to subsequently go their separate ways. Somehow Nicholas grew up to become Santa, and Fred turned into a Chicago motormouth with pouchy eyes and a hot girl (Rachel Weisz) who in real life would chuck him along with her unflattering wardrobe.  Instead, this lovely meter maid has to play  constant   kiss-and-make-up with Fred, a hustler by inclination and verbal dexterity who talks big, talks fast and tends to go belly up. Hustling ain’t easy, which is how he ends up in the clink and, shortly thereafter, at the North Pole trying to make good on a loan from his generous baby brother. There, to Fred’s astonishment, he discovers that all the elves in Santa’s workshop are Chinese laborers who earn 25 cents an hour churning out lead-coated toys for the American market at backbreaking, soul-crushing speed. Whoops! That’s the movie I was making in my head as the colors and shapes, and the strings of words were arranged and rearranged from shot to shot, scene to scene.  Lessons are learned, smiles are cracked, as are mirthless jokes, most at the expense of the shorter members of the cast. The director, David Dobkin, who did far better with “Wedding Crashers,” never settles into a coherent or workable groove, trying on moods (breezy, frantic, maudlin) that never stick or develop. (It’s difficult to reconcile the film’s ugly, alternately over-lighted and under-lighted photography with the cinematographer Remi Adefarasin’s professional work in “Elizabeth: The Golden Age.”)  The screenplay, credited to Dan Fogelman, feels similarly incoherent, a confusion of shtick and schmaltz. The less said the better about the digital wizardry that sticks famous heads on nonfamous bodies, Frankenstein-style. If you’ve ever wondered what the rapper Ludacris would look like if he were a dwarf, now’s your chance.  With “Fred Claus,” Mr. Vaughn seems to be trying out a more audience-friendly, mainstream persona, something he can cultivate when he’s too old to play naughty. It doesn’t work, partly because the film reeks, partly because nice isn’t (yet) in his on-screen DNA. There’s a touch of the con man to many of his characters, and it often feels as if he’s selling  something to someone. Here, though, he doesn’t seem to have conned even himself into thinking this movie a good idea. It’s no wonder when its most memorable scene finds Fred teaching an elf, Willie (John Michael Higgins’s head, Jorge Rodero’s   body), how to slow dance, a task that involves the kind of intimate eye-to-crotch gazing not usually seen in Christmas movies.  “Fred Claus” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). Sexual innuendo and ninja elf violence.</text>
      <date>November 9, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>