<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the audacious 10-minute opening sequence of the Israeli director Amos Gitai's "Free Zone," the camera scrutinizes the face of Natalie Portman, who is weeping quietly in the back of a car parked just outside the Western Wall in Jerusalem. On the soundtrack, a singer chants a Passover song "Had Gadia," whose allegorical lyrics describe how a lamb purchased for two pennies is eaten by a cat that is choked by a dog that is beaten by a stick that is burnt by a fire that is doused by water.  The director uses that song as a bitter  metaphorical evocation of Middle Eastern strife.  It is considerably more resonant than much of what follows in  this  deliberately murky film about the crossing of borders and the blurring of national identities. That blurring is made too literal in the cinematography, where gimmicky double exposures overlay scenes from the present and the past.  Ms. Portman's distraught character, Rebecca, is a young American woman with an Israeli father and a non-Jewish mother, who is searching for her identity. For reasons only partly clear, she has just broken up with her Spanish-Israeli fiancé. The film's three main characters, all women, are an American (Ms. Portman), an Israeli (Hanna Laslo) and a Palestinian (Hiam Abbass) whose lives intersect. The best hope for a constructive dialogue in the Middle East, the movie suggests, may lie in the ability of women from every faction to ignore political and ideological differences and communicate in the "free zone" of their common humanity.    The Israeli, Hanna, is the kind of aggressive Jewish matriarch who fearlessly stands up to any obstacle. Ms. Laslo's portrayal of this intrepid powerhouse won her a best actress award at last year's Cannes Film Festival. As the movie begins, she is about to embark on a grueling eight-hour car trip from Israel to the economic free zone in eastern Jordan to collect a debt. Rebecca, at loose ends, decides to accompany her.  Bordered by Syria, Iraq and Saudi Arabia, the free zone, an actual place  that has no customs or taxes, is a Middle Eastern hub of car sales where Arabs and Israelis live peacefully side by side. Hanna intends to collect $30,000 owed to her husband, Moshe, by a car dealer identified only as the American. The movie intimates that the free zone is also a center of war profiteering, if the selling of armored cars to whoever wants them qualifies.  Hanna is substituting for Moshe (Uri Klausner), who has been seriously injured in a terrorist attack. In one of the movie's several lengthy speeches, she regales Rebecca with the history of his frustrated attempts to make a living in agriculture. A man who once sold flowers now runs an armored-car dealership.  At the Israeli border, the women are grilled  as if they were  potential terrorists, but at the Jordanian border they are waved on through. On reaching the office where she is to collect the debt, Hanna is greeted warily by the American's wife, Leila (Ms. Abbass), who tells her that neither her husband nor the money are there.  Determined not to return empty handed, Hanna insists Leila take her to her husband. When they arrive at his farm, they find it set on fire by Palestinian militants, including Leila's angry stepson,   who reviles her for her modern ways. Eventually we meet the American, who is actually a Palestinian (Makram Khoury). Relating a peripatetic history that has carried him from Jordan to the United States and back, he describes a life as scarred by the ceaseless ebb and flow of war as Moshe's.  If the strong performances of its three stars infuse this metaphorically clotted movie with some life, the screenplay (some of which was improvised) has a weak narrative pulse. This political essay posing as a movie makes the mistake of confusing longwinded storytelling with compelling drama.</text>
      <date>April 7, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>