<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Savvy moviegoers know that the early part of the year is when big studios turn much of the country's movie theaters into a dump; it's the big-studio equivalent of early spring cleaning or, if you're feeling less charitable because life can seem particularly short when the movies are so bad, throwing out the trash. This week's contribution to our national slag heap and an early candidate for worst film of the year is "Freedomland," an inept, lethally dull drama directed by Joe Roth and written by Richard Price, based on his novel, about a white child who may have gone missing in a New Jersey public housing complex, where the residents are all black.  Samuel L. Jackson plays Lorenzo Council, a detective on the job in the projects when the call comes in. Along with his partner, Boyle (William Forsythe, always a sight for sore eyes), Lorenzo helps keep the peace in a tough neighborhood, where the white working-class town next door seems to pose as much of a threat as the usual social ills, if not more. Neither apparent saint nor evident sinner, Lorenzo soon proves himself a thoroughly lousy cop after he takes charge of a witness, Brenda Martin (Julianne Moore). Having wandered into a hospital at night, her hands slicked with blood, Brenda initially tells a story about being carjacked in the projects by a black man. Then she adds an explosive detail: her 4-year-old, Cody (Marlon Sherman),  was asleep in the back seat.  Boom! Lorenzo starts bellowing at Brenda and flailing for his asthma inhaler as the camera starts flopping around like a newly hooked trout. As inexplicable as it is inappropriate, Mr. Jackson's eardrum-rattling delivery can't help but bring to mind Dave Chappelle's lethally funny sendup of the actor's performance style in a phony beer commercial on "Chappelle's Show." In that bit, the comic plays Mr. Jackson dressed in old-fashioned garb à la Samuel Adams and madly engaged, at full roar, with getting restaurant patrons to drink his beer. "Can you stop yelling at me, please?" one customer pleads. "No, I can't stop yelling," the imitation Mr. Jackson replies between expletives. "Cause that's how I talk! You ain't never seen my movies?" Apparently, Mr. Roth has.  Mr. Jackson is certainly capable of doing better, as is Ms. Moore, who here delivers one of the few authentically awful performances of her career. Wildly miscast as a grammatically challenged former drug addict, the actress wanders through much of the movie in a blanked-out daze, pausing only to deliver a morsel of exposition and, in one scene, a soliloquy in which she explains how she ain't done nothing right in her life but had this kid.  It's no wonder that Mr. Price, who shows up for a brief cameo, looks embarrassed. There's more, including a severe-looking Edie Falco as part of a missing-child organization, some implausible dramatic turns and a handful of fine actors — including Aunjanue Ellis, Anthony Mackie and Clarke Peters — who all deserve permanent deliverance from the Hollywood ghetto.  "Freedomland" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). There is a fair amount of profanity and some violence.</text>
      <date>February 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>