<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> IN the final scene of Nicole Holofcener's "Friends With Money," a bittersweet comedy about the drama of being alive — with and without a fistful of dollars — the actress Jennifer Aniston summons up a small smile that looks a lot like a frown. It would be a stretch to say that at that moment her character, a vaguely depressed pot-smoking housekeeper named Olivia, is actually happy, but neither is she exactly unhappy. It's just that she, much as the rumpled man tucked into bed next to her says about himself, has "some issues, you know ... problems."  Most of Olivia's problems involve money, though she also has serious man troubles (she doesn't have one) and career woes (ditto). What she does have are three older married friends — played by Frances McDormand, Catherine Keener and Joan Cusack — who live in degrees of cocooned comfort in the kinds of Los Angeles neighborhoods where the only people of color are either taking care of the children or white folks working on their Malibu tans. Unlike her friends, Olivia seems to expect little from life and never seems surprised when that's what she gets. Having left her high school teaching job (the brats tossed her quarters for food), she now cleans up after other people, restoring to their lives a sense of order lacking in her own.  As might be expected, "Friends With Money" is about friendship and money and about how having one sometimes, maybe always, interferes with the other. Materialism and its discontents is a favorite American worry, but with its melancholic low-frequency buzz and roster of navel-gazers, this film feels particularly contemporary. Ms. Holofcener never suggests that her characters need to get out of the house and start ladling chowder down at the local soup kitchen; even  the cars in this film don't wear peace signs. But she obviously wants to say something about people who have too much of everything for their own good.  (And clearly knocking about  the movie business for years, as well as Los Angeles, has given her plenty of material.)  Maybe it's the sprawl, but like many Los Angeles-based stories, including Ms. Holofcener's last film, "Lovely and Amazing," this one radiates in many different directions at once. In addition to Olivia, there's Jane, a splenetic clothing designer (a sensational Ms. McDormand), and Christine, one  half of an unhappily married screenwriting team (Ms. Keener). Both women appear to be struggling through what Gail Sheehy called the "forlorn 40's," while the third married friend, Franny (Ms. Cusack), a stay-at-home mom with full-time help, has apparently skipped that passage and gone straight to heaven with a fat bank account, a vigorous sex life with her own husband (Greg Germann) and two kids who seem like pleasant afterthoughts. Rarely has Ms. Cusack's googly-eyed, otherworldly vibe seemed so right for a role.  One of those films in which the narrative emerges from the characters and through the performances, "Friends With Money" unfolds as a succession of vignettes organized around meals, shopping trips and lonely nights, and is punctuated by some laugh-out-loud bursts and a few punches to the gut. Ms. Holofcener is a first-rate portraitist and something of a miniaturist, and she likes to use a single telling detail, a bad habit, say, or a fixation — like Olivia's fondness for costly lotions or Jane's sudden refusal to wash her hair — to get at the larger meaning. If on occasion, as with Christine's ritualized clumsiness, this tactic slips into contrivance (for someone in pain, she whimpers "ow" a little too often), most of what's here nonetheless feels startlingly honest.  At times repellently so: Ms. Holofcener's willingness to show women at their most unpleasantly needy — like the serial loner in her first feature, "Walking and Talking," who waits for the phone that doesn't ring — can seem almost sadistic, as well as precariously familiar, the stuff of chick-lit clichés. But it's this very nakedness that gives her work bite. There's something unsettling about her films, all of which involve women who are, one way or another, flapping around inside cages largely of their own making. The image of Jane eating her guts out with fury, despite her loving family and fabulously cool career, just doesn't jibe with the standard glossy-magazine cant about wanting, having and keeping it all until death (or divorce) do us part.  Too bad Ms. Holofcener never really taps into Jane's rage. Although she gives the character a late-act speech about the sorrows of aging, this wan explanation never takes hold, partly because the character seems too angry (and the actress looks too good) to be worried about another birthday. Unlike Jane, Ms. Holofcener isn't one to blow her stack. Out of caution or courtesy, she instead offers gentle hints that all may not be right with this world, as when she lets the camera linger on the photo of a monkey, its fingers plugged in its ears, shortly after Franny and her husband walk past it with their arms laden with Christmas gifts. When you're as rich as Franny it's easy to hear no evil — no sadness or sorrow.  "Friends With Money" is greatly appealing if not especially adventurous, either for its director or for her admirers. Ms. Holofcener writes wonderful, recognizably real women characters, but the narrowness of their worlds and the continued modesty of her canvases suggest that, much like Olivia, she would prefer to stick her head under the covers than out the door. It's understandable that the filmmaker would be ambivalent about the choices women face, but it would be nice if she herself expanded on those choices a bit, or at least wrote a character that occasionally checked out Arianna Huffington's blog. After all, while Olivia and the rest have been drifting and freaking out, Ms. Holofcener has directed three very good features that, in themselves, prove there's more to the modern woman's life than her neuroses.  "Friends With Money" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). A little sex, a little dope.</text>
      <date>April 7, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>