<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Full Battle Rattle,” a new documentary by Tony Gerber and Jesse Moss, gives a remarkably thorough and detailed account of the difficult conditions facing American soldiers in Iraq. The filmmakers follow an Army battalion under the command of Lt. Col. Robert McLaughlin as it tries to bring a semblance of order and stability to a fractious Iraqi town menaced by violence. The soldiers must adjudicate disputes between Sunni and Shiite Muslims, prop up the local authorities and fight off insurgents, who are hidden in plain sight in the middle of town and carry out roadside bomb and rocket attacks at the worst possible moments.  Since there have already been quite a few ground-level Iraq documentaries, all of this might sound like a familiar scenario. Except that in the case of “Full Battle Rattle,” a scenario is literally what is involved. The Iraqi village of Medina Wasl is, in effect, a movie set, part of a training site built and operated by the Army in the Mojave Desert. Colonel McLaughlin’s earnest  campaign to win hearts and minds and fight a successful — or at least nondisastrous — counterinsurgency is an exercise, a preparation for the real dangers he and his soldiers  will face when they deploy to the actual Iraq.  Medina Wasl is populated by actual Iraqis: refugees from that country who role-play various officials and civilians. The insurgents are American soldiers, some of whom clearly relish a chance to be the bad guys. In the course of three weeks the battalion moves through several stages of engagement, identified in chapter titles (“Reconstruction,” “Insurgency” and so on) that suggest a microcosm of the larger war. The soldiers travel between their temporary base and the town, spending time at checkpoints and in long meetings with the mayor, the deputy mayor and the chief of police.  Meanwhile, a group of coordinators in civilian clothes controls events in the town, toying with human fates like fantasy gamers or Olympian gods out of Homer. They plot “inserts” — unexpected but never implausible events that complicate the mission. Medina Wasl, with its hand-lettered signs and functional architecture, starts to feel more and more like an unpredictable, even hopeless place, and Colonel McLaughlin’s stoical self-confidence takes a beating. He takes his job of bringing “peace and prosperity” and “a brighter future” to Medina Wasl seriously and is dismayed to find  that a straight-talking can-do attitude will not necessarily get him very far toward this goal.  It has been more than five years since the war began and about four since the first documentaries about it began to come out. The predominant style has been modified cinéma vérité, in which portable digital video cameras give a feeling of intimacy and immediacy and political views are implicit or omitted altogether.  Like many of its predecessors, “Full Battle Rattle” takes no overt side in any arguments about the cause and course of the war. Instead the film emphasizes the strangeness and complexity of the conflict, and also the endlessness that seems to be its most salient feature. Military personnel rotate through Medina Wasl en route to and from tours of duty in Iraq. Iraqis who have fled their country recreate fragments of it in the California desert, and the surreal encounters between them seem like a fact of life, or an episode of reality television.</text>
      <date>July 9, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>