<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>arnie (Kate Dollenmayer) is 23, and she drifts through "Funny Ha Ha," Andrew Bujalski's low-budget first feature, in search of love and employment - with pretty disappointing results. The young men she is drawn to don't reciprocate, and she can't quite bring herself to respond to the one guy who seems to be genuinely smitten with her. After temping for a while, she finds a job doing research for a professor, which seems reasonably tolerable. What gives this film its quiet pathos is not so much the relative bleakness of Marnie's circumstances but the modesty of her expectations. At one point, she makes a to-do list, and its lack of ambition - "spend more time outdoors," "make friends with Jackie," "learn to play chess" - is both funny and sad. Marnie would never admit to anything more acute than mild depression, and Mr. Bujalski captures the ache of her existence without pity or melodrama. She is lonely, but far from alone, because "Funny Ha Ha," much as it is the story of a few difficult, uneventful months in her life, is also a deft group portrait of recent college graduates - her friends, co-workers and would-be lovers - groping their way across the flatlands of early adulthood. Their conversational tics sound at once stylized and improvised, and the movie's narrative rhythms are loose and ambling. It feels as artless and scattered as Marnie and her cohort, who wear old T-shirts with holes in them and decorate their apartments with nondescript furniture, some of it probably hauled in from the sidewalk. But this scruffiness is a bit deceptive, as "Funny Ha Ha" has both a subtle, delicate shape and a point. Like John Cassavetes, whose influence is apparent here, Mr. Bujalski is an acute and intelligent dramatist who uses the appearance of chaos as a means of emotional exploration. I would bet that the ragged, swerving scenes in his film are much more tightly scripted and carefully rehearsed than they sometimes seem, which was almost always the case with Cassavetes. The main difference is that while Cassavetes's characters are often at the mercy of their feelings and pushed to the point of eruption, Mr. Bujalski's are cut off from theirs, and able to communicate only by painful, semi-ironic indirection. If it were not so resolutely modest, and so rigorously confined in its minute observations of individual behavior, you might almost call "Funny Ha Ha," which was completed in 2002, a generational statement. But that would be false to both the film's aesthetic and to its insights. Mr. Bujalski's characters do not make statements; they barely make eye contact with one another, and they communicate in a hesitant, noncommittal idiom, prefacing every utterance with phrases like "I don't know" and "I'm sorry." They spend their days working in grungy offices and their evenings drinking beer and eating hummus at impromptu parties. The anomie of middle-class 20-somethings is hardly an unexplored subject in American movies, and "Funny Ha Ha" might at first glance be taken as yet another example of post-"Slacker" indie solipsism. But Mr. Bujalski's artistic self-confidence and the low-key idiosyncrasy of his cast resist such easy labeling. This movie feels less like a careerist calling card than like a genuine effort to use film - and it is film, rather than the more modish digital video - to probe and reveal the curious facts and stubborn puzzles of contemporary life. It is a small, plain movie, shot in 16 millimeter in dull locations around Boston; but also, like its passive, quizzical heroine, it is unexpectedly seductive, and even, in its own stubborn, hesitant way, beautiful.</text>
      <date>April 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>