<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The documentary "Enron: The Smartest Guys in the Room" wrested only tragedy from the corporate scandal of its title, but it probably should come as no great surprise that now Hollywood is looking to mine big laughs from the same. Hence the sort-of-new Jim Carrey vehicle "Fun With Dick and Jane," what may be the first post-Enron comedy. Based on the 1977 Me Generation laugh-in of the same title with Jane Fonda and George Segal, this comic redo doesn't so much update the plight of its fast-sinking upwardly mobile couple as dust off the story's central conceit: namely, the flip side of the American dream is a nightmare but, you know, also kind of funny.  Set in and around Los Angeles, the film pivots on the plummeting fortunes of Dick and Jane Harper (Téa Leoni plays the missus), a happily married couple with a cute kid, a subdivision house stuffed with shiny consumer goods and a German import parked in the driveway. Jane works for a travel agency, though Dick brings home the big bucks from a company called Globodyne, which has something to do with consolidation and media properties but is really just an enormous Enron-like shell game. When the company goes up in shredded paper and smoke, and its chief operating villain, Jack McCallister (the invaluable Alec Baldwin), flies the coop in his helicopter, Dick's brand-new promotion to vice president, along with his family's financial safety net, goes bye-bye too.  It takes a few months for the full impact of Dick's unemployment to affect the family's status and rhythms. They don't plunge into poverty; they descend gradually, one indignity at a time. When the electricity is shut off, it's inconvenient but not a calamity: the housekeeper just stops vacuuming. It's more worrisome when Dick scrambles for one job with dozens of other identically suited and suitable applicants with the ferocity of an action hero. In the battleground of the executive unemployed, briefcases and empty water-cooler jugs are the weapons of choice, and a warrior like Dick isn't just jobless, but he is also on a rescue mission to save his family from doom or at least from poverty, which here mean more or less the same thing.  The fun in the film's title initially comes from watching comfortably middle-class people do without the usual buffers and privileges. This tacky, comic Schadenfreude works as long as the family's woes make for quirky gags, as when the three, soaped up and wearing bathing suits, shower under their neighbor's lawn sprinklers. But as the Harpers' fortunes continue to decline, the light tone darkens precipitously. By the time Jane mentions rising early to eat at the local soup kitchen, a pall has settled over the film. Mr. Carrey's and Ms. Leoni's sprightly performances can't obscure that the adversity endured by their characters mirrors some very real suffering. But before there's time to feel too bad, Dick and Jane pick up a couple of guns and start making like Bonnie and Clyde, ushering the proceedings into full-blown absurdism.  One of the film's insights is that poverty stinks, which could be news only in the la-la land of Los Angeles big-studio moviemaking. It's nonsense to expect social commentary from a high-concept comedy, especially one as self-congratulatory as this one (they care, they really, really care), but this is the rare studio comedy set in something like the real world. If the film never settles into a groove, zigging and zagging from belly laughs to pathos, it's because Enron remains raw as a wound. Too many cooks probably didn't help: directed by Dean Parisot, "Fun With Dick and Jane" has a screenplay credited to Judd Apatow and Nicholas Stoller, and, according to The Los Angeles Times, includes the efforts of David Koepp, Ed Solomon, Ted Griffin, Peter Tolan, Alec Berg, David Mandel and Jeff Schaffer.  Mr. Carrey's admirers may not mind the zigging and zagging, since he spends most of his screen time slaloming from one high jink to the next, really misting up with actorly sentiment only once. His spasmodic riff to the song "I Believe I Can Fly" is even better than the overexposed television advertisement suggests, while a tabletop freakout in a sepulchral club would work at twice the length. Mr. Carrey is such an attention hog that most actresses have a hard time holding on to their corner of the screen when he's onboard, especially in broader comedies. But Ms. Leoni never cedes her ground. Both performers exude such acute neediness - there's a touch of Jerry Lewis and Lucille Ball in their mutual frenzy - that not to love them even a little would seem cruel.  "Fun With Dick and Jane" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). A gun is waved around a few times.</text>
      <date>December 21, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>