<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Gabrielle,” a film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, printed words sometimes fill the screen, almost obliterating the puny creatures struggling beneath the  type. Directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau, a French filmmaker perhaps best known in  the United States for the historical pageant “Queen Margot” and better remembered for “Those Who Love Me Can Take the Train,” this startling drama recounts the dissolution of a marriage of a couple from the haute bourgeoisie, Jean and Gabrielle Hervey, played by the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory  and Isabelle Huppert.  Based on Joseph Conrad’s very dry, very vicious long short story, “The Return,” the film concerns a man (Alvan in the original) who, having married a woman for whom he apparently feels nothing, becomes undone when she leaves him for another. Conrad narrates the story  in a claustrophobic   third-person voice  that immerses us fully in the husband’s point of view while simultaneously allowing us to see the woman hovering at the periphery. Working with the screenwriter Anne-Louise Trividic,  as he did with two of his finer efforts, “Intimacy” and “His Brother,”  Mr. Chéreau opens the story up, dividing it more equally between the characters but without compromising Conrad’s meaning or emotional brutality.  Mr. Chéreau sets the story in Paris around 1912 (the original, written around 1897, comes without any such place or time markers), two years before the war that will violently sweep away the last vestiges of the 19th century. Madame and monsieur, childless and sometime past their fertile prime, live in a mansion filled with the kind of luxurious trappings — allegorical paintings and gleaming white statues of women frozen in classical poses — that give such homes the chill of a mausoleum. A fleet of maids, impeccably dressed in matching black and white, keep the crypt running; every Thursday an army of  bohemians invades, providing amusement and social cachet, and filling the air with chatter and smoke.  For Jean, whose fastidious swoop of hair telegraphs his vanity long before his words do, the maids and the bohemians, the statues and the wife are interchangeable.  Each has been bought, paid for and arranged in a consciousness as carefully ordered as the mansion’s great rooms. Uninteresting in and of themselves, they exist only to advance his position, so much so that when he thinks of his wife and his guests while strolling  one day, it’s as if he were itemizing the contents of a safe. And yet, when his most prized possession goes missing, having left a farewell letter propped up on  a dressing table,   the blow hits Jean with unexpected force, prying him from his facade  like a snail from its shell.  As Mr. Chéreau fluidly moves back and forth in time, using different color  schemes  and editing rhythms to express what the characters themselves cannot always say,  he  forces air  into a story that  in the writing and the subject can feel moribund on the page. Although you wouldn’t know it to look at most of his films, he has a long history directing  for  theater and  opera, experience that he has mostly used to his advantage in his work for the cinema. His theater background may help account for the consistently fine acting in his films, while his  staging of Wagner  may explain the wonderful fearlessness with which he embraces melodramatic excess.  Here,  Mr. Chéreau pushes his characters to the limits of emotion, turning  Gabrielle’s face various shades of pink and forcing Jean’s swoop of hair to tumble. Ms. Huppert, one of the screen’s great criers (second only to Juliette Binoche), spends much of  the film  with a flush  and damp face, suffering in sepulchral silence while Mr.  Greggory brilliantly rages. Both actors keep you riveted, even when Mr. Chéreau blows up passages from Conrad’s text, cutting away entirely from the performers (making you all the more anxious for their return) or obscuring their images with a well-chosen word (“Stay!”). Together with his extraordinary performers, Mr. Chéreau breathes  life into characters who long ago set a course for death.</text>
      <date>July 14, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>