<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Abdellatif Kechiche's first film, about a young North African immigrant's adventures in Paris, was called "It's Voltaire's Fault." His second, "Games of Love and Chance" (known in France as "L'Esquive"), takes place in the drab high-rise Paris suburbs (called banlieues) where many North Africans live. Its English title, and much of its inspiration, comes from a play by Voltaire's contemporary the 18th-century French writer Pierre Carlet de Chamblain de Marivaux. Mr. Kechiche's interest in connecting France's classical literary heritage with its contemporary social reality is intriguing, and it has resulted, in this case, in a spirited and insightful comedy of manners.  That is not the genre usually associated with the banlieue setting, typically the backdrop for grim exercises in realist melodrama. Mr. Kechiche's naturalistic, almost documentary style certainly does not relieve the ugliness of the housing projects, and a late confrontation between some of the characters and the local police temporarily jolts the picture from its youthful reverie. But for the most part "Games of Love and Chance," a hit in France and the winner of several César awards, is a graceful and sympathetic look at how the lives of teenagers intersect with a work of literature. Its script, which Mr. Kechiche wrote with Ghalya Lacroix, choreographs a dizzying series of collisions between the hip-hop influenced, Arabic-inflected staccato of working-class youth slang and the decorous melodies of Marivaux's prose.  The story is deceptively simple. Krimo (Osman Elkharraz), a shy, sweet 15-year-old, has a crush on Lydia (Sara Forestier), who is as outgoing and theatrical as he is quiet and reserved. Nonetheless, he takes on the male lead in a school production of Marivaux's play, which he seems to hope might serve as the script to his own seduction of Lydia, who is playing the female lead. Krimo's protective cousin, Nanou (Nanou Benhamou), does not approve, and a complicated series of games ensues, as the reversals and obstructions of Marivaux's comic plot are filtered through the confused mores and conflicting desires of various girls and boys.  That adults figure only tangentially in this world makes it seem both risky and enchanted. There are times when the possibility of violence and real pain hovers like a cloud, and others when the air sparkles the silly, self-serious impetuosity of adolescence. Mr. Kechiche shows remarkable sympathy for his young cast and takes them seriously enough to keep "Games of Love and Chance" free of any hint of mockery or condescension.</text>
      <date>August 31, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>