<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Recovery time is recommended after seeing “Gardens of the Night,” a harrowing, obliquely told story of kidnapping and forced child prostitution that conjures a world entirely populated by predators and prey. Written and directed by Damian Harris (“Deceived,” “Bad Company”), who researched the subject for a decade, “Gardens of the Night” has a ghastly air of authenticity.  The movie’s first and better half portrays events as seen through the eyes of a frightened little girl who doesn’t really know what is happening, which makes it all the more sinister. In these scenes “Gardens of the Night” taps into childhood memories of straining to understand the mysterious ways of the grown-up world when things go wrong.  After the blond, pretty,  8-year-old Leslie Whitehead (Ryan Simpkins) is cajoled into a car on her way to school in Wilmington, Pa., she is shuttled from one hideout to another by kidnappers who convince her that her parents don’t want her anymore. One piece of proof is a bogus cellphone number she is free to dial, which her abductor Alex (Tom Arnold) tells her is her father’s. After weeks go by and no one answers, she crumples up the paper on which he scrawled the number and gives up hope.  Mr. Arnold is frighteningly believable as an obsequious child pornographer with a hearty, hale-fellow manner who loves his victims in a sick, diabolical way. He wins Leslie’s trust by enlisting her help in finding a lost dog and gives her a ride to school. The next day he reappears and spirits her away.  All we know of Alex is what Leslie observes. Overweight and sweaty, bellowing through a stopped-up nose but unflappably cheerful and solicitous, he insists he is her protector, though she soon realizes he is not. Alex, who has a sullen, hothead sidekick, Frank (Kevin  Zegers), wheels and deals with a distributor of child pornography (Jeremy Sisto).  (None of  the pornography is seen in the film or is shown being made.)  Once in Alex’s thrall, Leslie shares quarters with Donnie (Jermaine Scooter Smith), a fellow kidnap victim who becomes her only friend. As she reads aloud from “The Jungle Book,” they find temporary solace in an imaginary animal kingdom.  In one creepy scene Leslie is pimped out to a judge (Raynold Gideon), whose wife (Cornelia Guest) shepherds her into an upstairs room where she silently waits for the unknown with three other girls, all wearing numbed expressions. In the ugliest scene Leslie is taken to a motel room where a sweet-talking john (Harold Perrineau) cajoles her into letting him touch her, then turns violent when she resists.  As she is about to be brutally raped, Alex bursts into the room with a gun. Left uncertain is whether the scene was an assignation gone amok, or was staged as part of Alex’s brainwashing program.  “Gardens of the Night” loses much of its power when it leaps ahead nine years to find Leslie and Donnie (now played by Gillian Jacobs and Evan Ross) working the streets of San Diego as homeless teenage prostitutes who sleep on the beach and under bridges. As the soundtrack changes from music-box delicate to hard-edged punk, the movie becomes a sad but conventional study of throwaway street kids. What happened to them in the intervening years is left to the imagination. Neither Ms. Jacobs nor Mr. Ross infuses their characters with much personality beyond projecting a ravaged numbness.  “Gardens of the Night” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity, sexual situations and one scene of violence.</text>
      <date>November 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>