<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At one point during “Gentlemen Broncos,” a misfire from the filmmakers who brought the world “Napoleon Dynamite” and, more happily, “Nacho Libre,” I began to wonder how many evacuations a comedy can deliver before they ruin the joke. The spray of vomit that inspired this question had just shot out of the mouth of the hapless teenager at the center of the new movie, an emission preceded or followed by (I lost track) a geyser of snake feces and some nonreptilian, if equally repellent, defecation.  The problem, of course, as great gross-out comedies from “Monty Python’s the Meaning of Life” to “American Pie” have proved time and again, has nothing to do with waste matter and everything to do with timing, good jokes and characters you can laugh with and at, all mostly missing from “Gentlemen Broncos.”  Directed by Jared Hess, who wrote the screenplay with his wife, Jerusha, the film turns on  Benjamin (Michael Angarano), a 17-year-old loner who lives with his widowed mother (Jennifer Coolidge) and aspires to be a science-fiction author. He’s a rotten writer, to judge from his magnum opus, “Yeast Lords: The Bronco Years,” a turgid, rather inexplicable fantasy that’s periodically dramatized, schlock-cinema style, in vignettes featuring Sam Rockwell as the hirsute Bronco, a hero patterned after Benjamin’s dead father.  Benjamin doesn’t know he’s bad, and the filmmakers don’t admit he is either, which is part of the joke. This lack of self-awareness is the point of almost all the laughs in a movie filled with unpleasant, unattractive characters whose every facial tic and item of clothing seems contrived for yuks. That was true in “Napoleon Dynamite,” as well, but the crucial difference is that Napoleon is so aggressive and so self-assured that he doesn’t leave any room for pity. He might look funny, with his glasses, lopsided clown hair and gasping mouth, but he doesn’t behave as if he were a joke waiting for either a punch or a punch line, a disconnect between appearance and being that the Hesses smartly exploited.  In “Gentlemen Broncos,” by contrast, the characters, including the inert, enervated Benjamin, are basically lumps, even the usually reliable Mike White, who shows up with a long fall of blond hair and that incontinent snake. The film’s few bright spots are largely due to Jemaine Clement (from Flight of the Conchords, both the HBO show and the musical duo) as Dr. Ronald Chevalier, a haughty science-fiction author who wears a cellphone earpiece he never uses and dons an American Indian choker when he writes.  Chevalier enters the picture largely to furnish Benjamin some Oedipal anxiety and invest the story with dramatic tension, but he also gives the movie a spark of life because he’s the only recognizably human character around. He’s a dandy villain, and the workshop he conducts for aspiring science-fiction writers will make a terrific YouTube excerpt.    “Gentlemen Broncos” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Poop and puke (kind of says it all).</text>
      <date>October 30, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>