<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Georgia Rule,” in which Jane Fonda washes Lindsay Lohan’s mouth out with soap, might easily have been a tepid, sudsy puddle of easy sentiment and soft comedy. Three generations of women — Ms. Fonda and Ms. Lohan are Georgia and Rachel, grandmother and granddaughter, with Felicity Huffman in between them as Lilly, Georgia’s daughter and Rachel’s mom — fuss, fail to communicate and, in the end, forgive one another. Small-town values triumph over flashy, big-city California relativism, as happens exclusively (and frequently) in Hollywood movies. You’ve seen it all before.  Except that you haven’t quite. From the opening scene, which catches Ms. Huffman and Ms. Lohan bickering on a lonely stretch of road near the Idaho state line, “Georgia Rule,” directed by Garry Marshall from a script by Mark Andrus, swerves and spins, taking its predictable plot in some surprising directions. Working against its maudlin impulses with lively humor, and at the same time undercutting its laughs with some hard, ugly themes, this movie is neither a standard weepie nor a comforting dramedy. It’s an interesting, maddening mess — not a terrible movie, and by no means a dull one.  With “Pretty Woman” (1990),  Mr. Marshall pulled off the unlikely, somewhat distasteful feat of turning prostitution into a pretext for romantic bliss. If anything, this film pushes such incongruity even further, using the sexual abuse of a girl by her stepfather — a crime suspected, denied and affirmed in a dizzying series of reversals and revisions — as fodder for domestic farce as well as therapeutic melodrama. The man who brought us “Laverne and Shirley”  ventures into territory better suited to Todd Solondz or Lifetime, and, as you might imagine, he has some trouble finding a consistent and appropriate tone.  But the incoherence of the movie is a sign of life, evidence of an emotional energy percolating beneath the glib “very special episode” surface. The source of that vitality lies with the actors, and with Mr. Marshall’s inclination to give them space and time to explore their characters’ idiosyncrasies.  Ms. Huffman, playing uptight as easily as she plays drunk, does well with the least sympathetic of the three principal roles, that of a woman who must incarnate the worst attributes of filial rebellion and maternal rigidity. And Dermot Mulroney is quiet and wry as a small-town veterinarian who also treats human patients, and who serves as an all-purpose shoulder to cry on, in spite of his own grief.  But the movie really belongs to Ms. Fonda and Ms. Lohan, actresses whose formidable skill is often underestimated and overshadowed by off-screen notoriety. Ms. Lohan in particular has been subjected recently to the prurient, punitive gaze of an Internet gossip culture that takes special delight in the humiliation of young women with shaky discipline and an appetite for fun.  The joke in “Georgia Rule” is that she is playing a version of her tabloid persona: a needy, reckless young woman whose self-confidence verges on self-destructive. The surprise is that she does it with such poise and intelligence. As written, Rachel is complicated to the point of contradiction: lost child, femme fatale, brainiac and brat squeezed into a series of short dresses. Somehow Ms. Lohan connects these disparate, clashing elements into a single convincing performance.  At the start of the movie, Rachel is on her way from San Francisco to Hull, Idaho, for a summer under the supervision of her grandmother. Georgia runs her own life (and everyone else’s) according to strict standards from which she tolerates little deviation. Ms. Fonda’s straight back and piercing eyes, the righteous jaw line she inherited from her father and a reputation for humorlessness all serve her well here, but it is her warmth and comic timing that make Georgia more than a provincial scold.  Rachel, similarly, evades easy caricature. She’s neither a tramp nor a victim. Her initial predatory interest in a local hunk named Harlan (Garrett Hedlund) turns chaste once she discovers his vulnerability. Her own is fairly evident, especially once she casually makes the accusation that Lilly’s husband, Arnold (Cary Elwes), a rich lawyer, molested her when she was younger.  This news is really too much for the movie to assimilate, especially given its generally lighthearted take on Rachel’s sexuality, but “Georgia Rule” is nonetheless trying to acknowledge the awful as well as the amusing dimensions of experience in a way that very few mainstream comedies would dare. It doesn’t succeed, but there is nonetheless something admirable and honest in the effort.  “Georgia Rule” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual references and situations and profanity. </text>
      <date>May 11, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>