<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Reviewing a movie like “Get Smart” is pretty much like writing about the new packaging of a laundry detergent. The box may be a brighter orange, the label a little louder (Improved! Kind Of!), but the stuff inside is pretty much the same as the stuff inside every box of detergent. And, in this case, the stuff inside consists of exactly what most Hollywood movies based on old sitcoms are made of, namely feeble and funny jokes, brand actors and enough special effects to give you some bang for your summertime buck.  The most crucial of those recognizable faces in the “Get Smart” movie belongs to the comic actor Steve Carell, putting an amusing deadpan spin on the blundering CONTROL spy Maxwell Smart, or Agent 86, the role originated by Don Adams.  Created by Mel Brooks and Buck Henry amid a pop-culture spy craze fueled by the cold war and Ian Fleming, Max was the borscht belt Bond, the seemingly inexpert, ambiguously ethnic  American operative who, starting in 1965 and armed with broad jokes, slapstick and a capable female sidekick, Agent 99 (Barbara Feldon, a cool number), somehow for five seasons managed to come out on top. He was the original revenge of the nerds, a goofball answer to all those Yale-schooled spooks.  Despite some nips and tucks and a back story involving a fat suit, the updated movie Max isn’t that different from the television version. Everything looks pricier, of course, what with the shiny sets filled with blinking screens and busy-looking extras, many of whom are on hand only so that they can be blown to smithereens. Max appears somewhat costlier too, sleeker, as does 99 (leggy, pretty, harmless Anne Hathaway). A pleasant-looking man whose dark, pleading eyes suggest reserves of decency and a deep well of panic, Mr. Carell makes for a markedly different presence from Mr. Adams, a stand-up comic who delivered all his dialogue like one-liners and seemed two jokes and one unfastened brassiere away from a gig at the Playboy Mansion.  Mr. Carell’s deadpan and implied decency go a long way toward making “Get Smart” work as well as it does. He has been given a boost by the filmmakers — the director Peter Segal and the writers Tom J. Astle and Matt Ember — who, while making sure that you laugh at Max, also make sure you never laugh too hard or for too long. It’s one thing for Max to be funny, to be an intermittent impotent foil. But if he’s to carry the day and maybe even a franchise, he has to be genuinely heroic. He has to fill up the big screen with action, not just laughs and dusty catchphrases. He has to deliver the goods by also throwing a few hard punches.  For the most part Mr. Carell does just that, going through the formulaic paces without wilting, despite the exhausting 111-minute run time. The movie is far from terrible: it’s amusing in spots (Bill Murray shows up for an eccentric cameo) and visually painless, notably during the nighttime beauty shots of Moscow that show the digital video format off to fine effect.  There are also diverting supporting turns from the hard-working Dwayne Johnson, as CONTROL’s resident smooth-groover and Alan Arkin as its hot-tempered boss. Terence Stamp’s somnolent turn as Siegfried, an agent for KAOS — an enemy agency — with no notable kinks other than a love of Beethoven, only adds a touch of nostalgia for real Terence Stamp performances.  Having ended before Watergate-fueled paranoia could seep in, “Get Smart” is, like all shows in syndication, an imperfect time capsule, less a reflection of its historical moment than of its commercial imperatives.  It probably seemed ready for a big-screen redo because operatives and agencies are headline news again, but there’s too much money at stake in a movie like this for reality to intrude. The filmmakers take tiny, tinny digs at the vice president and cook up a subplot about yellowcake uranium and a pathetic bit about a guy in a turban on a plane. They even have a president (James Caan) who can’t pronounce nuclear properly and reads “Goodnight Moon” to the kiddies as the country teeters on the brink. None of it sticks.  Stanley Kubrick could have made doomsday funny (wait, he did), but a movie like “Get Smart,” engineered for big laughs and little pain, can only lob cotton balls. It flounders whenever it tries to weave the real world into its fantasia, partly because it isn’t really about anything other than making money, partly because the spy-versus-spy battle doesn’t entertain the way it once did.  There was nothing particularly innocent about the time period when “Get Smart” was originally broadcast, but neither was the spy game shrouded in cynicism. Secret agents were still glamorous then, grist for romance and ripe for parody. But watching Max and company run amok just gave me the creeps. I don’t know about you, but I’m sick of bumbling spies.    “Get Smart” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Gun violence without the blood. </text>
      <date>June 20, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>