<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Giuliani Time," Kevin Keating's new documentary about the former mayor of New York City, begins several years after its subject has left office, at the 2004 Republican National Convention. In his speech there, Rudolph W. Giuliani evoked the  Sept. 11 attacks, and recalled that on that dreadful morning he had turned to Bernard B. Kerik, his police commissioner at the time, and said, "Thank God George Bush is president."  Who knows how many of Mr. Giuliani's constituents shared that sentiment — or how many fewer would endorse it now. But my own recollections of that day suggest that a lot of New Yorkers, including many who were far from fond of Mr. Giuliani, were thankful that he was their mayor. Certainly, his response to the attacks has burnished his image in the national media, and helped to make him a plausible — or at least a discussable — contender for his party's presidential nomination in 2008.  The intention behind "Giuliani Time," which was begun in 1998, early in Mr. Giuliani's second term, seems to be to tarnish this luster. The title suggests as much, referring as it does to a phrase that Abner Louima, a Haitian immigrant tortured and sodomized by officers in a Brooklyn station house in 1997, claimed one of his tormenters taunted. Later, he retracted that claim, which makes Mr. Keating's use of it all the more provocative, and signals that the movie's agenda will be to associate Mr. Giuliani's tenure with brutality, racial revanchism and contempt for civil liberties.  The film, while hardly unbiased, is not entirely one-sided. Its main voices are those of the mayor's detractors, led by Wayne Barrett, the Village Voice reporter and author of a highly critical biography of Mr. Giuliani. But some of his allies and admirers also have their say, including Donald Trump, Representative Peter T. King, and Heather Mac Donald and Myron Magnet of the Manhattan Institute, the conservative intellectual hothouse where many of the policy ideas of the Giuliani administration were aired and debated.  The most famous of these was the "broken windows" theory of policing, advanced by the criminologist George L. Kelling (who also appears in the movie), which held that the enforcement of laws against minor "quality of life" infractions like graffiti, public drinking or subway-fare evasion could prevent more serious crimes from occurring. "Giuliani Time" does a good job of presenting the arguments for and against this idea, which the mayor and his supporters believe was the key to the dramatic reduction in crime that took place while he was in office.  The debate is likely to continue, even as New Yorkers continue to enjoy a city that is safer than anyone 20 years ago would have thought possible. Over all, most of the talking heads in "Giuliani Time" are rather grudging in giving Mr. Giuliani credit, or, for that matter, in granting the importance of crime as an issue in urban politics.  The history presented in the film is sometimes selective. Noting that crime had begun to fall under Mr. Giuliani's predecessor, David N. Dinkins, the movie wonders why Mr. Dinkins was perceived as ineffectual, and wonders also how Mr. Giuliani, who had lost a close election to Mr. Dinkins in 1989, was able to exploit this perception when he narrowly won their rematch four years later. And yet no mention is made of the violence in Crown Heights in 1991, which a federal report found  Mr. Dinkins's administration had mishandled, and which had a lot to do with swinging some votes in the 1993 election against him.  In general, and in spite of its deft use of archival video clips and interviews, "Giuliani Time" offers a superficial reading of recent New York history, zeroing in on the headlines while often missing the context. We hear about the low turnout in the elections Mr. Giuliani won, information that implicitly minimizes the extent of his popular support but that might just as well be evidence that his Democratic opponents — first Mr. Dinkins and then Ruth W. Messinger — failed to inspire their own partisans. The people of New York, we are told, were fooled, bullied and "bamboozled" by Mr. Giuliani, who beat Ms. Messinger (in her own account) because he refused to conduct a substantive debate on the issues.  These are the things people tend to say when their ideological enemies win. Left unexamined is how the Democratic Party, with its overwhelming demographic and institutional advantages in New York, has managed to lose four mayoral elections in a row.  As someone who voted in all of those elections — and, no, I won't say for whom — I can hardly claim neutrality. But, like a lot of New Yorkers who lived here through the Giuliani era, I can confess ambivalence, and I'm grateful to Mr. Keating for reminding me, perhaps to some extent inadvertently, of what a complicated figure Mr. Giuliani was and remains.  The film shows that, while his decisiveness,  forensic intelligence and  wit could be impressive,  they could easily shade into high-handedness, arrogance and meanness. His success in fighting crime was always shadowed by his failure to establish any real rapport with the city's black and Hispanic citizens, and by his unwarranted harshness when dealing with artists, welfare recipients and the homeless. He had a knack for turning allies into critics, as demonstrated in this film by William J. Bratton, police commissioner during Mr. Giuliani's first term, and Rudy Crew, schools chancellor from 1995 to 1999.  Mr. Giuliani is not interviewed; the filmmaker has said his repeated requests were denied.  "Giuliani Time" makes the case that Mr. Giuliani's true ideological identity is conservative, and makes this case in a way that is sure to appall liberals who felt queasy about him in the first place (or guilty when they voted for him). But of course Mr. Giuliani, if he does run for president, will want to make the same case to Republicans, and in some ways "Giuliani Time" might work to his advantage, since it never mentions, say, his support for gay rights or his endorsement of Mario M. Cuomo in the 1994 governor's race. Mr. Giuliani was always a hybrid and, in some ways, a paradox:  something both he and this movie might prefer that we forget.</text>
      <date>May 12, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>