<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A fantastic bestiary inhabits “The Golden Compass,” prowling and flapping and slithering and fluttering. The animals, most of which are called daemons and are manifestations of the human soul, hover at the side of their people and near the story’s edge, where their coos and barks mix with the ambient clatter and clang. Every so often, an animal leaps forward, its fur raised in alarm, its feathers fanned in flight. And because these are no ordinary animals, they also offer words of comfort, advice, warning. In this otherworldly realm, humans have no dominion over these creatures, yet they are not merely equals, either. They are one.  This beastly attitude and the conception of the soul as being somehow separate from its corporeal vessel are, as far as I can tell, the most irreligious conceits in the movie adaptation of “The Golden Compass,” a novel that was first published in Britain as  “Northern Lights.”  Written by Philip Pullman, it quickly became a critical and commercial success for the most obvious of reasons: It’s a charming romp set in a parallel universe stuffed with magical creatures, spooky villains and mythopoetic conceits, and propelled by a young  orphan, Lyra Belacqua, who embarks on the hero’s journey with her shape-shifting daemon, Pantalaimon (Pan for short). The book has attracted voluble criticism for equally obvious reasons: Its army of darkness is a totalitarian institution called “the Church.”  That ecclesiastical entity is pretty much nowhere evident in the film, which otherwise hews as close to the original source as can be expected from a 114-minute, big-screen translation of a 400-or-so-page novel. Directed by the American Chris Weitz, who wrote the heavily condensed script, “The Golden Compass” has many of the virtues of a faithful screen adaptation and many of the predictable flaws. Agnostics and atheists may, for starters, regret the explicit absence of the Church (others may see lingering traces), but the movies have never been a particularly good pulpit for any gods other than those of cinema’s own creation. It’s a tradition that this film honors with a goddess of icy perfection played by the wickedly well-cast Nicole Kidman.  As Mrs. Coulter, an emissary of the reigning powers (known only as “the Magisterium” in the film), Ms. Kidman has rarely looked more beautifully and exotically alien. When she first appears, she pours across the screen like liquid gold, her body provocatively shifting inside a shimmering, form-fitting gown, her gilt-blond hair and alabaster skin all but glowing. She’s the film’s most spectacular special effect (her wonderfully vicious little daemon-monkey runs a close second), and for once, the smooth planes of her face, untroubled by visible lines, serve the character. This masklike countenance  helps hide Mrs. Coulter’s malignant designs from Lyra (the newcomer Dakota Blue Richards, spunky and serviceable), who, not long after the story lifts off, falls into her care through a series of complicated developments.  Mr. Weitz crams so many events, characters (computer-generated and otherwise), twists and turns, sumptuously appointed rooms and ethereally strange vistas into his film that he risks losing you in the whirl. It zips from the Gothic grandeur of Jordan College, the Oxford institution where Lyra has been raised and somewhat educated by her guardians (“Scholars”), to Mrs. Coulter’s swank London home, where the Art Deco touches bring to mind the dreamiest Astaire-and-Rogers cheek-to-cheek. Much like the neo-Victorian aristocrats in Neal Stephenson’s science-fiction novel “The Diamond Age,” the characters in “The Golden Compass” populate a world that resembles our own,  despite being also seductively foreign. In Lyra’s universe zeppelins putt-putt through a period twilight zone, evoking both a knowable past and a possible future.  Despite the pit stops and lovely clutter, some of it visibly influenced by David Lynch’s “Dune,” the story unwinds in fairly straightforward fashion. Lyra, using a nifty, compasslike device called an alethiometer, must face danger and destiny, along with some hard truths. Among the hardest and headiest are those involving her uncle, Lord Asriel (Daniel Craig), an adventurer who dashes in and out of her life accompanied by an elegant snow leopard for a daemon. Aided and abetted by assorted quirky types and acting legends (Tom Courtenay in person, Ian McKellen in voice), Lyra follows Lord Asriel to the snowy north, where further perils await, along with a creepy intrigue involving stolen children and hints that the book’s two sequels are ready for their big-screen close-ups.  The sequels are a welcome idea, if only because they might persuade Mr. Weitz and his team to take it slower next time. “The Golden Compass” is an honorable work and especially impressive, given the far smaller, more intimate scale of his last film as a director (with his brother, Paul), “About a Boy.”  But it’s hampered by its fealty to the book and its madly rushed pace, which forces you to dash through the story like Lord Asriel.  Among other things, I would have liked to spend some quality time with Lyra’s friend and protector the warrior bear Iorek Byrnison (voiced by Mr. McKellen), a gorgeous creature whose ferocity is, alas, tempered by his resemblance to some familiar cuddly polar bears. It is, I discovered, hard to keep your mind off the concession stand when you are waiting for Iorek to offer Lyra a Coke.  “The Golden Compass” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Some intense scenes involve children in danger and warfare between bears and humans.</text>
      <date>December 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>