<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Good Night” might be described as a Dudley Moore movie without its namesake, who died five years ago. You know the subgenre: a bumbling, tippling fantasist becomes besotted with a dream girl and forsakes reason to wallow in his fantasy. In this variation, the farce has been tamped down to whimsy.  Sometimes he is married, sometimes not. In “The Good Night,” written and directed by Jake Paltrow, the Moore surrogate, Gary Sheller (Martin Freeman), is a single guy in his mid-30s whose relationship with Dora (the director’s sister, Gwyneth Paltrow), his nagging live-in girlfriend of seven years, has turned to ashes. Gary is not the kind of buffoonish drunk that Moore excelled at playing, but he has the same collapsed self-image as a dilapidated specimen of manhood genuflecting before perfectly shaped goddesses.  Like many of Moore’s characters, Gary is also a British musician. Although Gary has a rock ’n’ roll background, he composes for television commercials, and lives in New York City. When his serious artistic side is finally heard late in the movie, the original piano piece he plays is the kind of characterless schlock that movies often try to pass off as modern classical music.  Perhaps to make Gary seem sympathetic, “The Good Night” gives him an obnoxious sidekick in his producer, best friend and former band mate, Paul (Simon Pegg), a slick, self-infatuated misogynist who patronizes lap-dance clubs and mistreats his girlfriend, Terry (Amber Sealey). Compared with this rat, Gary is an angelic sad sack for whom you almost begin to feel sorry.  The kind of humor in which “The Good Night” traffics is the sort that produces smirks of uncomfortable recognition, but hardly any laughter. The object of Gary’s affection is a beautiful woman (Penélope Cruz) who communicates with him telepathically in his dreams. When he first glimpses this phantom lover, who calls herself Anna, she is a shining figure in white strolling on a deserted beach. Their eyes meet, and their instant rapport is so complete that her amorous thoughts register as subtitled words. Anna becomes such a powerful fantasy that Gary would rather sleep than continue living his ordinary domestic life with Dora, who works in an art gallery.  Dora is a role guaranteed not to advance Ms. Paltrow’s screen career. The actress has bravely forsaken all her glamour to play the kind of drab, sullen partner whose whining voice you dread hearing first thing in the morning. Nevertheless, each night before turning off the lights, these miserable people exchange tired, dutiful “Love you” ’s.  Gary becomes so obsessed with having uninterrupted sleep during which to cuddle with the sexually insatiable Anna that he soundproofs the bedroom. He also begins to consult dream experts and settles on Mel (Danny DeVito), an eccentric motormouth nut case who spouts torrents of wacky dream theory in his “lucid dreaming” therapy group. Mr. DeVito’s Mel  is, in a word, unbearable.  What ought to be the story’s kicker arrives when Gary sees Anna’s image on perfume ads plastered on New York buses. Through Paul, he meets this creature, whose real name is Melody. A chain-smoking, tequila-swilling hedonist who is all hard edges, Melody immediately sizes up Gary as a jealous, crazy loser on their abortive date and wisely beats a retreat. Ms. Cruz, as ever, loses much mystique the moment she speaks English.  The comedy of male midlife angst dates back at least to “The Seven-Year Itch,” when it was sweet and innocent. Each time it is recycled, it gets more sour and joyless.    “The Good Night” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has some strong language and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>October 5, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>