<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At one point during “The Goods: Live Hard, Sell Hard,” a grubby-looking comedy about the art of the sale, two alligators crawl across a car lot. Who brought the alligators? a bewildered man asks. We’re the only ones who can hear his question amid the shrieks of the customers and salesmen and the whir of a buzz saw that brings a guy on stilts and in an Uncle Sam costume down to size. From one angle this frenzied moment looks like a metaphor for the American auto industry, but it’s just a throwaway in a comedy without a shred of obvious filmmaking and an endless stream of good, bad, sometimes terrible, often absurd jokes.  The alligators make no sense, which is part of why the sight gag works. (They also look inherently funny, especially when crawling among a crazed mob.) So, who brought them? The filmmakers, of course, who, as they do with everything else in this movie, throw the bit against the wall but don’t wait to see if it sticks. Instead they race to the next joke and the one after that, busily tossing one-liners, surreal asides, cheap and gross insults, false apologies for such insults, semi-naked ladies, sex toys and multisyllabic expletives like confetti. Unlike the errant tiger in “The Hangover,” which is only truly funny because it belongs to Mike Tyson, which also makes it somewhat tragic, the alligators are a genuinely madcap touch.  Neal Brennan, an alumnus of “Chappelle’s Show” making his big-screen directing debut, could use better technical support and some alone time with a box of Jerry Lewis DVDs, but it takes talent to keep so many parts in play and without much letup. Anarchy and its threat are the twin engines of many comedies, though it must be said that the anarchy here doesn’t always feel particularly planned. There’s a jerry-built feel to the movie, as if it had been hatched by the screenwriters Andy Stock and Rick Stempson over a long caffeine-addled weekend and shot while its star, Jeremy Piven, had a few hours to spare between  HBO and Broadway. You keep waiting for the whole thing to collapse, but that’s also part of the fun.  The story doesn’t matter  — this is a movie about the pitch, not the goods  —  but for form’s sake: Mr. Piven, his shuddering uvula and three sidekicks (David Koechner, Kathryn Hahn and Ving Rhames), play car salespeople who cross the country moving wheels off slow lots by yelling and waving the red, white and blue in exchange for wads of green. James Brolin plays a lot owner who hires this itinerant sales force. And Jordana Spiro, Rob Riggle, Ed Helms, Wendie Malick, Craig Robinson, Tony Hale and other funny people play the attendant crazies. Mr. Piven basically shouts a lot while pumping his limbs with the same tight gestures that are familiar from his showboating as Ari Gold on “Entourage.” He’s funny there, he’s funny here.  Will Ferrell, who, with his frequent director Adam McKay, served as  a producer on the movie, shows up in mutton chops.  “The Goods: Live Hard, Sell Hard” is rated R. (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian.) The film has dirty, nasty jokes galore and two pretty special lap-dancing routines.</text>
      <date>August 14, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>