<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In his genre pastiche “The Good German,” Steven Soderbergh has tried to resurrect the magic of classical Hollywood, principally by sucking out all the air, energy and pleasure from his own filmmaking. Based on the well-regarded Joseph Kanon novel, this film stars a distracted, emotionally detached George Clooney as Jake Geismer, an American journalist who, following World War II, returns to Germany to check out the doings at Potsdam and find his lost love, Lena, a frau who, as played by a vamping Cate Blanchett, recalls Rainer Werner Fassbinder’s postwar heroine Veronika Voss by way of Carol Burnett.  As it turns out, they don’t make them like they used to even when they try. Mr. Soderbergh has explained that with “The Good German” he was seeking to make a film that looked and sounded like an old studio picture, but without the old studio prohibitions. In the name of verisimilitude and creative freedom, his actors talk a blue streak in black-and-white images captured with period-era camera lenses. More lewdly, Tobey Maguire, who plays Tully, one of those smiling sadists of the type once played by Dan Duryea, helps the film earn its R rating by doing the kinds of things to Ms. Blanchett that audiences could only dream of doing to Ingrid Bergman.  Here’s looking at you kid, flung over the bed and on your knees.  With one startling and critical difference, Paul Attanasio’s screenplay follows the general direction of Mr. Kanon’s novel, which, embroidered with historical detail, zeroes in on the mid-1940s moment when the United States and the Soviet Union were racing to scoop up German scientists in preparation for the long, cold war to follow. The novel stacks up  the various acts of wartime violence — genocide, carpet bombing, postwar raping and pillaging committed by the respective German, American and Soviet players  — as if they were poker chips. In this game of high-stakes moral relativism, the Germans clearly have amassed the most chips (six million and counting), though the thuggish Soviets and slick, smiling Americans are doing their best to catch up.  Mr. Attanasio, whose credits include “Quiz Show,” attempts to work all this murk and mess into a compressed screenplay that also leaves room for the stars. When not chasing after Lena, Jake races around the impressively dilapidated sets trying to put all the geopolitical pieces together. When an American soldier winds up dead in Potsdam, Jake thinks he has the makings of an ideal you-are-there story. His zigzag pursuit of his long-cooled love quickly dovetails with a boiling-hot story involving Nazi war crimes, the details of which are helpfully provided by assorted secondary types, including Beau Bridges as the American military officer running part of Berlin, Leland Orser as an American Jew hunting down Nazis and Ravil Isyanov as a watchful Soviet officer.  Despite Mr. Soderbergh’s attempt to mimic the classic studio style, notably through the deliberate editing patterns and fairly restrained camerawork, “The Good German” bears little resemblance to a Hollywood film of the period. Tonally his cinematography is particularly off-key, characterized by hot whites and inky blacks that can put faces into harsh light and swallow bodies whole; neither Ms. Blanchett nor Mr. Clooney is flattered by his attentions. Although he tosses in an occasional beauty shot, framing Jake against a mottled nighttime sky in one scene, the film’s high-contrast austerity owes more to the anti-aesthetic of the modern art house than it does to the back-lot Expressionism of Hollywood noirs  or one of the filmmaker’s favorite touchstones, “The Third Man.”  In “Casablanca,” another of the golden oldies Mr. Soderbergh samples  for “The Good German,” Humphrey Bogart cozies up to Bergman in flashback on a Parisian bed. The lovers remain dressed throughout their abbreviated affair, though one suggestively uncorked bottle of Champagne and several coy dissolves  suggest realms of adult possibility. Yet while the language routinely waxes raw in “The Good German,” the most striking difference between it and a Hollywood film like “Casablanca” aren’t the expletives, the new film’s calculated cynicism or even that glimpse of bedroom coupling; it’s that the older film feels as if it was made for the satisfaction of the audience while the other feels as if it was made for that of the director alone.  In the film laboratory that is Mr. Soderbergh’s brain, ideas boil, steam and sputter. In 1989 he conquered Cannes and launched a thousand Harvey and Bob Weinstein stories with his independently financed sensation “Sex, Lies and Videotape,” quickly becoming a legend before his time. He subsequently flopped and floundered before he brought his independent ways to bear on the studio apparatus, a metamorphosis that involved turning a television actor into the sexiest man alive, repurposing the Rat Pack and winning  an Oscar.  It has been a second act that, until recently, seemed as smart as the man living it but that has grown gradually more disjointed as Mr. Soderbergh’s penchant for experimentation has become an end in itself rather than a means to aesthetic liberation. That’s too bad for us, for him and for Hollywood, which frankly could use all the help it can get.  In a recent interview Mr. Soderbergh said that he would have been happy with a career like that of Michael Curtiz, a workhorse who spent decades  churning out entertainments like “Casablanca” for Warner Brothers. The idea that the extremely self-motivated Mr. Soderbergh might be satisfied with a career like Curtiz’s is rich nonsense. Curtiz had next to no say on the personnel who worked on “Casablanca.” By contrast, for “The Good German” Mr. Soderbergh persuaded the same studio, now owned by a media conglomerate for which movies represent only a thin slice of the pie chart, to cough up millions for what is essentially a pet art project.  Increasingly, Mr. Soderbergh’s oscillation between glossy divertissements like the “Ocean’s” films and modest diversions like “Bubble” seems less like the natural workings of a restless imagination than a disengaged one. Even more than “Bubble” or “Ocean’s Twelve,” “The Good German” feels like the product of a filmmaker far more interested in his own handicraft — in the logistics of moving the camera among the characters with a dip and a glide — than in the audience for whom he’s ostensibly creating that work.  Manufactured for mass enjoyment, “Casablanca” runs wonderfully more than half a century after leaving the factory. It’s sentimental and contrived. It’s also the kind of well-wrought, pleasurable film that Mr. Soderbergh can do beautifully (see “Out of Sight”) and seems recently reluctant to pursue.  The extent of that disengagement is most evident in the new film’s wildly feel-bad denouement, in which the paradoxically good German of Mr. Kanon’s title, the one who looked away from atrocities, is transformed into a duplicitous Jew. The most charitable explanation for this offensive, historically spurious character is that Mr. Soderbergh and Mr. Attanasio, in trying to cram the novel’s nearly 500 pages into a 105-minute film, decided to conflate two different clichés into one.  Rather unfortunately, and perhaps with an eye to the present, they end up suggesting that in wartime everyone’s hands can become slicked with blood, even a Jew in Nazi Germany. Somewhere, Jack and Harry Warner, who stopped doing business with Nazi Germany before any other studio in Hollywood, are spinning. They aren’t the only ones.  “The Good German” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film includes some gun violence and fisticuffs, a little sex and a lot of raw language.</text>
      <date>December 15, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>