<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> For most of its 85 minutes “Grace Is Gone,” a small, tender film about contemporary parenthood in wartime, carries off a delicate balancing act. How do you portray the tragic effects of the Iraq war on the home front without sounding shrilly partisan or evasively neutral? How do you avoid jingoism, cynicism or mawkishness?  The film, written and directed by James C. Strouse,  evokes the daily lives of a father and his two children in perfect, unassuming performances and with a close attention to detail that makes you feel like a fifth member of the family.  The household consists of Stanley Phillips (John Cusack),  the blocky, good-hearted manager of a home-supply store, and his daughters, the 12-year-old Heidi (Shelan O’Keefe) and  the 8-year-old Dawn (Gracie Bednarczyk).  Their mother, Grace (Dana Lynne Gilhooley),  whose presence haunts the movie, is a soldier in Iraq. Except for snapshots and a brief flashback, she is only a chipper voice heard on a telephone answering machine. Early in the movie we learn that Stanley had joined the Army. He was so gung-ho to fight in Iraq that he cheated on his eye exam by having a friend memorize the letters, but was quickly found out and discharged. A scene in which he gathers his store’s clerks in a huddle that ends in a motivational group cheer suggests that he might have made an excellent officer.  While Grace is overseas, the other Phillipses studiously pretend that she is not in harm’s way. Watching television coverage of the war is forbidden in their home, although Heidi sneaks occasional looks. Before Grace left,  she and Dawn synchronized the alarms on their watches so they would beep simultaneously;  when the signal comes, the little girl closes her eyes in prayerful communion.  Stanley’s own state of willful denial ends with a knock on the door. An Army captain and a chaplain stiffly deliver the dreaded “regret to inform” news that Grace died bravely in combat. Stanley reacts with numbed shock. Because the girls are in school, he has several hours to decide how to tell to them.  But when they return, he is at a loss for words. He impulsively decides to prolong their innocence and announces that the three of them are going on a trip to wherever the girls desire. Dawn pipes up that she wants to visit Enchanted Gardens, a theme park in Florida.  Much of the movie follows  the three on their journey from Minnesota to Florida, during which we are shown a revealing picture of highways crowded with chain stores and shopping malls. As Stanley improvises their erratic route, Heidi begins to sense that something is terribly amiss.  Ms. O’Keefe’s portrayal of a serious girl on the verge of adolescence captures the smallest nuances of Heidi’s doubt and confusion. As she catches her father in inconsistencies and white lies, her poker face becomes graver, and her attitude more remote; outside the motels they visit, she spends hours sitting curbside and brooding.  Without overly dramatizing the emotional distance between Stanley and his daughters, the screenplay signals that until now the girls have been much closer to their mother. Stanley buys them pretty dresses and allows them to have their ears pierced.  In the film’s most treacherous scene, Stanley and the girls try to visit his mother (who is away) and find his scruffy younger brother, John (Alessandro Nivola), a floundering student and bitter opponent of the war, sprawled on the couch. The movie allows John’s sarcastic criticisms to stand without serious counter-argument beyond Stanley’s professing his loyalty and trust in the powers that be. One of Donald H. Rumsfeld’s more stirring speeches is later seen on a hotel television.  Mr. Cusack demonstrates once again that he is Hollywood’s second-most-reliable nice guy, after Tom Hanks. Devoid of vanity, with no hidden agendas, he never strains to be likable. Good will, integrity and a native common sense ooze out of him.  The accumulation of detail in “Grace Is Gone,” which is Mr. Strouse’s directing debut (he wrote the screenplay for Steve Buscemi’s “Lonesome Jim”), is so seamless that any prodding of the story calls attention to itself. The most glaring moments of manipulation are Stanley’s phone calls home to hear Grace on the answering machine and to leave a personal message.  It is perfectly plausible that Stanley  would want to hear her voice now and again, but those heartfelt messages in which he vents his grief and sorrow are another matter.  “Grace Is Gone” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). The theme of a parent’s death in battle could upset young children, and there is some strong language.</text>
      <date>December 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>