<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A screwball comedy with a lesbian twist: if that sounds familiar it is because “Gray Matters” is the second such movie, following “Puccini for Beginners,” to open in New York in less than a month. Is it coincidence or a minitrend?  Both films were written and directed by women (“Gray Matters” by Sue Kramer and “Puccini” by Maria Maggenti); both contemplate fluctuating sexual orientation. In “Puccini” the gay antiheroine goes bi, then backtracks; in “Gray Matters” the suppressed lesbian desires of a woman who has assumed she is straight are awakened by an impulsive kiss. Both stories are romantic triangles in which a straight, nonmacho Cary Grant surrogate remains blissfully ignorant of the games being played by beautiful women behind his back.  And both movies pretend to be high-end French Champagne, but are really midpriced domestic vintages. If “Gray Matters” is more effervescent and has a drier taste, it is also far more detached from reality. Its lovingly photographed portrait of upscale Manhattan may look familiar, but this strangely deracinated Gotham feels like New York in an alternate universe.  The principal characters, Gray (Heather Graham), an advertising copywriter, and Sam (Tom Cavanagh), an up-and-coming heart surgeon, are an attractive, perky brother-sister combo whose sibling bond is so tight they like to finish each other’s sentences. In their spare time they do Fred-and-Ginger routines for their friends’ amusement (the first song  we hear is “Cheek to Cheek”) and chatter fatuously about old movies. The spirit of Carole Lombard hovers over the film;  in this world,  Madonna never existed.  Gray and Sam’s perfect relationship begins to curdle when they decide to show the world they’re not co-dependent by finding marital partners for each other.  They begin making checklists of the essential qualities  of an ideal mate,  like Sam’s demand for a woman who is not afraid to eat a hot-fudge sundae.  Presto: they discover Sam’s dream girl one sunny afternoon in Central Park in the person of Charlotte, a k a Charlie (Bridget Moynahan), a gorgeous new arrival from the West Coast who works at an aquarium and studies the homosexual behavior of fish. After the three spend a blissful day together swapping movie trivia, Sam, obviously smitten, dismisses Gray and vanishes with Charlie into the night.  When he reappears the next morning in the splendid loft he shares with his sister, he announces that Charlie is The One and that they are flying to Las Vegas to get married. Gray, the designated maid of honor, is not as pleased as she should be.  After a drunken girls’ night out in Vegas  —  during which they join Gloria Gaynor onstage to sing “I Will Survive” —  Charlie and Gray return to the hotel and fall into a  steamy kiss. Charlie, the drunker of the two, has no memory of the clinch the next morning. Gray, jolted to her core, is now madly in love.  If “Gray Matters” follows the standard screwball comedy format, the two halves of its hybrid style — part early ’40s romp, part “The L Word” lite — don’t mesh. Compared to “Gray Matters,” even a Nora Ephron bonbon has the weight of urban neo-realism.  Ms. Graham’s Gray may be fetching, but she tries so strenuously to charm that her ditziness begins to pall. Mr. Cavanagh’s Sam is a suaver, blander version of his former television character Ed, from the show of the same name; you can’t imagine him wielding a scalpel. Sissy Spacek is wasted in the minor role of Gray’s therapist. As Gray’s cheerfully self-effacing office sidekick, Carrie, a type originated on “The Bob Cummings Show” by Ann B. Davis, Molly Shannon throws in a dash of ’50s sitcom zest.  Stealing every scene in which he appears, Alan Cumming twinkles and grins as a wise, friendly cab driver besotted with Gray. He is such a good sport that even after she rejects him, he dresses in drag to accompany her on her first excursion to a lesbian bar.  “Gray Matters” is rated  PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has racy talk.</text>
      <date>February 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>