<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Life after wartime does not snap back to normal. In the opening scene of “Grbavica: The Land of My Dreams” the camera slowly pans across the stony, careworn faces of the women in a therapy group in the Sarajevo neighborhood that gives the movie its name. One of them can’t stop giggling uncontrollably but is ignored by the others, who remain sealed behind walls of private grief and resignation. Some, like Esma (Mirjana Karanovic), the movie’s central character, attend only on days when financial aid is distributed.  During the war in Bosnia, Grbavica was the site of a prison camp in which torture and rape were epidemic. A decade later mass graves are still being opened, and survivors flock to identify the bodies of husbands and lovers.  Jasmila Zbanic, who wrote and directed “Grbavica” (pronounced grr-BAH-vee-tsah), lived near the camp, and her film conveys the anguish of a community struggling to move on even though its wounds remain unhealed. A single mother who lives with her tomboyish 12-year-old daughter, Sara (Luna Mijovic), Esma barely makes ends meet from her job in a shoe factory. She takes a job as a cocktail waitress in a sleazy nightclub run by Caran (Bogdan Diklic), a thug with a shaved head, a hair-trigger temper and a gambling habit.  Violent and superstitious, Caran pressures her to use her intuition before he places his bets. When one of her guesses yields him a windfall, he adopts her as his good-luck charm. But the moment her intuition fails, he relapses into a brute.  Everywhere the anarchic forces unleashed by the war still run rampant. Caran casually deals in murder to settle scores. Prostitution flourishes at his club. Sara is a defiant, wild child, who alternately screams at her mother and clings to her. She is at exactly the age when boy-girl roughhousing begins to change from combative to erotic. Her first boyfriend, Samir (Kenan Catic), who also lost his father in the war, proudly shows off the gun he inherited. The weapon excites her.  The tension between the present and the recent past is embodied in the volatile relationship between mother and daughter, which comes to a boil over the issue of Sara’s paternity. She is desperate to know more about her father, whom Esma has assured her was a war hero, or shaheed. But Sara, unlike Samir, hasn’t been told the details of her father’s death, and she relentlessly badgers her mother for more information.  A school trip is approaching that the children of shaheeds can join for a discount if they have certification of their dead fathers’ heroic status. As Esma delays producing a certificate, Sara is taunted by her schoolmates because she is not on the list of martyrs’ children, and she grows increasingly suspicious of her mother’s evasive answers. Without a certificate, she can go on the trip only at full cost: 200 euros, which Esma doesn’t have. As the day of departure looms, Esma goes from friend to friend begging for a loan. Eventually the truth spills out in a melodramatic and too-abrupt but shattering scene.  Much of the emotional power of “Grbavica” comes from the exceptional performances of Ms. Karanovic and Ms. Mijovic, as they act out an age-old conflict exacerbated by the horrors of recent history. Esma deeply loves her daughter but doesn’t hesitate to slap her sharply across the face when she flies into an abusive tantrum.  And when Pelda (Leon Lucev), a bouncer in the club, begins pursuing Esma romantically, Sara is terrified of being abandoned. Esma responds tentatively to Pelda’s attentions, fending him off while keeping his interest. Her relationship with this tender, softhearted goon in Caran’s criminal enterprise isn’t entirely credible.  At once intrepid and beaten down, Ms. Karanovic’s Esma is a woman slowly breaking through the layers of anguish and defeat that the world has heaped upon her, and the actress (so memorable in the films of Emir Kusturica) invests her with an embattled nobility expressed without a trace of grandstanding. Ms. Mijovic is a live wire spitting sparks against Ms. Karanovic’s brick-wall defenses.  Throughout “Grbavica” the desire to forget and the need to remember are at loggerheads. At Sara’s school the psychological wounds of the war are being handed down to her generation through the separation of heroes and nonheroes. Fathers pass their weapons down to their sons. Even as you leave a war behind, you bring it with you.</text>
      <date>February 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>