<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> About the only thing to be said on behalf of "The Great Raid," a tedious World War II epic that slogs across the screen like a forced march in quicksand, is that it illustrates a depressing similarity between reckless war-mongering and grandiose moviemaking. Historical films with vainglorious ambitions, like ill-fated imperial ventures, often overlook the human factor, a miscalculation that usually results in a rout.  This 132-minute Miramax film, completed two years ago and dumped into the marketplace during the dog days of August, reputedly cost $80 million. Not since Ted Turner's stillborn boondoggle "Gods and Generals" has a war film squandered so much on such emptiness.  A sense of futility is the last thing "The Great Raid" would like to convey. The film, based on true events, aspires to the heroic dimensions of "Saving Private Ryan" and "The Bridge on the River Kwai." The story meticulously re-enacts the against-all-odds liberation of 500 American prisoners of war from the heavily guarded Japanese camp at Cabanatuan, in the Philippines, by a band of untested American soldiers in January 1945.  Those American prisoners were survivors of the notorious Bataan Death March, in which 70,000 Allied troops who had surrendered to the Japanese Imperial Army at Bataan in 1942 were forced to embark on a nightmarish 63-mile trek through the jungle; thousands died. Dispatched to various Japanese camps, many of the remaining soldiers were starved and some burned alive by their captors.  With its radically desaturated color, which drapes everything in hues of mud and dust, "The Great Raid" flaunts a visual stylization of the gritty look of 1940's black-and-white war films. Its scenes of torture and murder also unapologetically revive the uncomfortable stereotype of the Japanese soldier as a sadistic, slant-eyed fiend.  The story is narrated by Capt. Robert Prince (James Franco), who led a hand-picked force of more than 100 deep into enemy territory. Assisting the Americans are members of the Filipino resistance, led by Capt. Juan Pajota (Cesar Montano), whose familiarity with the terrain was critical to the raid's success. Overseeing the plan, Lt. Col. Henry Mucci (Benjamin Bratt) views the raid as an opportunity to erase the shame of the American defeat at Bataan, although he concedes that it is not essential to the war effort.  The film's problems begin with the mismatch of its story, based on two books - the historian William B. Breuer's "Great Raid on Cabanatuan" and "Ghost Soldiers" by Hampton Sides - and its director, John Dahl. Assigning a filmmaker known for turning out cynical noirish melodramas like "The Last Seduction" and "Red Rock West" to supervise the re-enactment of a heroic, little-known chapter of World War II is a little like asking John Waters to be Steven Spielberg.  Mr. Dahl, to put it kindly, has no inner John Wayne or Tom Hanks to call upon for inspiration and no larger-than-life vision of war as a glorious adventure or hell on earth. The first-time screenwriters Carlo Bernard and Doug Miro are so busy piecing together the movie's three interlocking stories that they forget to create characters who amount to more than gung-ho boilerplate or the aforementioned fiends.  One strand of the story follows the raid and its preparations. Another, set in the prison camp, focuses on Major Gibson (Joseph Fiennes), a malaria-stricken officer. The third, poorly integrated into the movie, follows Major Gibson's sweetheart, Margaret Utinsky (Connie Nielsen), a Lithuanian-born nurse, war widow and heroic real-life leader of the resistance movement in Manila who smuggles medicine into the camp.  It is not the actors' fault that their characters fail to establish any emotional connection; they aren't given the words for the task. Mr. Bratt's officer suggests a shallow, snippy recycling of Detective Rey Curtis, his character on "Law &amp; Order," and Mr. Franco's a blander recycling of the 8-by-10 glossy portrait of James Dean he introduced four years ago in a television docudrama.  When Ms. Nielsen is first seen, you may sigh with relief at the prospect of some warmth. Just a hint of Ingrid Bergman in "Casablanca" might have done wonders for the movie. But all this fascinating Danish actress is allowed to do is appear by turns stoic, imperious and enigmatic.  The actual raid, when it finally happens in the movie's last 40 minutes, provides no visceral release; the prolonged, soggy fireworks display is devoid of suspense, excitement or human drama. The movie's fizzle is cruelly set in relief by the vintage newsreel of the actual raiders that concludes the movie; here, for a moment, is some human feeling.  "The Great Raid" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has scenes of violence, including torture, and strong language.</text>
      <date>August 12, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>