<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Its steadfast humanity, its literacy, its passionate belief in education, its faith that history teaches invaluable lessons and its strong, emotionally grounded performances: There are enough things to admire about “The Great Debaters,” the heavily fictionalized true story of The Little Debate Team That Could, that your impulse is to forgive the movie its shortcomings.  The second film directed by Denzel Washington, “The Great Debaters” may not aspire to be more than inspirational pop entertainment in the Oprah Winfrey mode (Ms. Winfrey is one of its producers), but unlike so many films of its ilk,  it doesn’t insult your intelligence. And it reminds you that social history airbrushed for the screen by Hollywood is preferable to none at all. Despite its cosmetic embellishments, “The Great Debaters” obviously emanates from the heart. It makes you nostalgic for prototypes like Stanley Kramer’s socially conscious message movies of the 1950s and ’60s and for the era that produced them.  As an enduring American myth, the triumph of the sanctified underdog, an intrepid spirit who doesn’t compromise his integrity on the slippery path to victory, may be much the worse for wear in these Darwinian times, but it can still produce a lump in your throat. The real tale  of the unlikely ascendance  of the debate team at Wiley College, a small all-black institution in Marshall, Tex., in 1935, follows the template of countless sports movies. Perseverance and teamwork lead to untarnished glory.  In its tone, though not in its content, “The Great Debaters” is the sequel to Mr. Washington’s 2002 directorial debut, “Antwone Fisher,” in which he played a Navy psychiatrist whose tough love helps save a broken soul. Here he portrays the noted poet, social activist and educator Melvin B. Tolson, who coached the Wiley College team. Righteous, autocratic and fearless, Mr. Washington’s Tolson is a screen descendant of the stern East London schoolteacher played by Sidney Poitier 40 years ago in “To Sir, With Love.” If Mr. Washington’s two films are considerably richer in content than that civil rights-era weepie, at heart they are no less sentimental.  Tolson is not only a ferocious coach but also a political firebrand (there are mutterings about his being a Communist) who runs afoul of the local sheriff (John Heard) for his organizing of the mixed-race Southern Tenant Farmers  Union. But whether Tolson is teaching or organizing, Mr. Washington imbues him with the authority of a persuasive orator and a moral Rock of Gibraltar.  “The Great Debaters” is aware that debating, an activity synonymous with nerdiness, needs a shot of adrenaline to be sexy to a mass audience. Early in the movie Tolson barks with the ferocity of a Marine Corps drill instructor, “Debate is a blood sport.” As the team starts winning, his severity never diminishes. The debates themselves are swiftly edited compendiums of best-of moments.  The four teammates handpicked by Tolson are Henry Lowe (Nate Parker), a handsome,  clean-cut youth with a lurking bad-boy streak; Hamilton Burgess (Jermaine Williams), a dutiful eager beaver whose family pressures him to drop out when Tolson’s radical political organizing comes to light; Samantha Booke (Jurnee Smollett), a strait-laced aspiring lawyer and soft-edged proto-feminist; and James Farmer Jr. (Denzel Whitaker), a preacher’s son whose father (Forest Whitaker) keeps him on a tight leash.  Despite his name, the actor playing James Jr. is unrelated to either Mr. Washington or to Forest Whitaker. It is worth noting that the senior Farmer was the first African-American in Texas to earn a doctorate. His son, a leader of the civil-rights movement in the 1950s and ’60s, founded the Congress of Racial Equality.  This being Hollywood, a soupçon of romance is required. The movie dawdles only as long as necessary on the pudgy, cow-eyed young James’s hopeless infatuation with Samantha, who becomes romantically involved with Henry.  “The Great Debaters” doesn’t shy away from showing the humiliation and persecution of blacks in the Jim Crow South. When James Farmer Sr., accompanied by his family, accidentally runs over a pig, his humiliation at the hands of the owner and his redneck buddies makes your stomach turn.  Later, Tolson, driving home from a debate with his students, comes upon a lynching. The flashes of the hideous atrocity sear your mind, and when the mob, still riled with blood lust, chases the car, your heart is in your throat. Afterward, Henry’s shame and stifled fury drive him to a self-destructive spree.  Robert Eisele’s screenplay imagines a smooth historical arc. The characters’ reactions to these events, it implies, sow the seeds of the civil-rights movement, which is also foreshadowed in the debates, whose topics too conveniently address civil-rights issues. Strangely, the Wiley College team always argues the progressive view. Its initial push to break the color barrier in college debating by competing with a white college in Oklahoma is too neatly paralleled by the debate topic: whether blacks should be allowed to attend state universities. A more intellectually subtle, less manipulative movie would have had the Wiley team arguing at least once against African-American interests.  Even though the film makes it clear that the team’s speeches are prepared in advance by Tolson, the literary and historical references blithely tossed around by the team members show astounding erudition, and their speaking voices carry only the tiniest hint of an East Texas twang.  For dramatic purposes the setting of the climactic debate has been changed in the movie to Harvard from the University of Southern California, where it actually took place. Again the issue is too neatly selected: nonviolent civil disobedience versus the rule of law.  The wonder is that “The Great Debaters” transcends its own simplifying  and manipulative ploys; it radiates nobility of spirit.    “The Great Debaters”  is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has mild sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>December 25, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>