<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the break room of a bland corporate office suite somewhere in Manhattan, an accountant (Jim Gaffigan) undergoes therapy with a curiously passive-aggressive psychologist (Tony Shalhoub). Elsewhere, an attractive 30-something couple (Judy Greer and Tom McCarthy) struggle to deal with their overweight, antisocial son, and an ambitious pastry chef (Maggie Gyllenhaal) prepares the pitch that, she hopes, will make her the new queen of the competitive New York cake scene.  On the other side of the East River, in Brooklyn, an older woman (Olympia Dukakis) fixes supper for her husband, and then sits at the kitchen table making collages out of old magazines as he smokes a cigarette out on the balcony. Two Indian immigrants (Naseeruddin Shah and Sharat Saxena), neighbors as well as colleagues, work security for a visiting dignitary.  These characters, who cross paths glancingly if at all (and are joined by Stephen Colbert and Edie Falco in distracting if amusing cameos as a private school headmaster and a diva of dessert), occupy the quiet, tidy vignettes that make up "The Great New Wonderful," a new film directed by Danny Leiner and written by Sam Catlin.  What links the stories is that they occur simultaneously at a moment that seems at once meaningless and portentous: September 2002, a year after the terrorist attacks. Not that Sept. 11 itself is ever mentioned in the movie — that would be too obvious, too literal, and thus contrary to the filmmakers' apparent intention to tease and mystify. Every now and then, somebody will gesture toward this great unspoken, alluding to how everything is different "since then," or noting that "we are all" subject to the same vague emotional affliction.  But otherwise we are left to wonder about causes and effects. Is Satish (Mr. Saxena), the stouter, less talkative of the two security guards, in such a bad mood because of Al Qaeda, or is he just generally a grouch? Is his partner and pal, Avi (Mr. Shah), obsessed with staring at women's backsides as a result of the attack, or does he just happen to share an interest with whoever is operating the camera? Do the tears, sex and mild violence that erupt at the movie's low-key climax represent a form of catharsis, a purging of the rage, grief and terror that have been repressed and numbed by unthinking adherence to routine?  Maybe. The moments in "The Great New Wonderful" that feel truest are the ones that reveal how habit at once stabilizes and stultifies. Doing the same thing every day is both a comfort and a trap, and the actors (Ms. Greer and Ms. Gyllenhaal especially) betray, with small gestures and tics of speech, the fatigue that comes from being stuck in the same self 24 hours a day.  Mr. Leiner, who has previously directed the coarse (and very funny) comedies "Dude, Where's My Car?" and "Harold and Kumar Go to White Castle," has a good eye for the small absurdities of ordinary life, and in particular for the unacknowledged (and unattractive) emotions that lie beneath the careful neutrality of everyday behavior. (When I say he has a good eye, I mean it metaphorically, since the look of this film is uniformly drab and unevocative.) Envy, disappointment, the fear of failure and the expectation of compromise — these, more than love or sympathy or even ambition, are the engines that drive Mr. Leiner's New Yorkers from one scene to the next.    That residents of this city — in particular white, relatively privileged Manhattanites — are capable of a certain degree of self-absorption will hardly come as news, even to those unfamiliar with New York magazine or the films of Woody Allen. The twist "The Great New Wonderful" offers is the implication that Sept. 11 made this condition more acute, and perhaps even provided justification for it. We never learn about the specific effects of the World Trade Center attacks on particular characters — whether any of them lost a friend or happened to be downtown that morning — an omission in keeping with the film's coy, abstract treatment of recent history.  It may be that in the long run, Sept. 11 drove New Yorkers deeper into themselves. But it also awakened a long-dormant sense of civic solidarity, as well as sharpening the local appetite for disputation. That none of Mr. Leiner and Mr. Catlin's carefully cultivated urban specimens expresses a political opinion — or even the slightest hint of curiosity about or engagement with the larger world — creates a ringing silence that also amounts to a glaring false note. We are invited either to identify with them or to feel superior, which is not much of a choice. It may be that our mockery is meant, by the end, to melt into sympathy, but it is hard to feel much warmth toward people whose most salient feature is their disconnection from reality.  "The Great New Wonderful" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It contains profanity and sexual references.</text>
      <date>June 23, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>