<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Great Buck Howard,” an agreeable show business satire with a warm heart, was inspired by the career of the Amazing Kreskin, a k a George Joseph Kresge Jr., the 1970s television mind reader who still pops up on the tube now and then. Playing Buck Howard, an entertainer with a similar career trajectory, John Malkovich exaggerates the familiar mannerisms of this self-described professional mentalist to create a barbed but affectionate portrait of a second-string trouper struggling for a comeback.  A peripatetic entertainer who boasts of having logged 61 performances on Johnny Carson’s “Tonight” show, Buck greets people with an exaggerated arm-pumping parody of Kreskin’s vigorous handshake. As interpreted by Mr. Malkovich, who is at least a decade too young for the role of a showbiz old-timer, Kreskin’s courtly geniality assumes a slightly creepy edge of self-deluding egomania.  Offstage, Buck can veer in seconds from a charmer to a nit-picking, tantrum-throwing diva. But he is less a tyrant than an eccentric. If Mr. Malkovich locates the demons inside a character who is apparently too self-absorbed to have enjoyed any kind of love life, he portrays his quest for redemption as well intentioned. Buck can exude a witheringly icy hauteur one moment and  a disorienting aura of not being entirely present the next. In front of an audience, however, he is shamelessly, happily obsequious, and the crowds eat it up.  Much of Buck’s sense of self-worth depends on his successful execution of Kreskin’s signature stunt of inviting audience members to hide the fee for his performance while he is secluded offstage. When he returns he uses his gifts — extrasensory powers, Sherlock Holmes detective skills, or whatever  they are  — to find the money. In a 2007 interview, Mr.  Kresge, now 74, boasted that he had failed only nine times in his career to locate it. Buck, however, has a perfect record.  His difficulty in sniffing out the money at a Las Vegas lounge where he is making his big-time comeback  is the movie’s dramatic turning point.  Written and directed by Sean McGinly, “The Great Buck Howard” also stars Colin Hanks as Troy Gable, a law-school dropout and aspiring writer who impulsively takes a job as Buck’s road manager. As Troy, Mr. Hanks (the son of Tom, who is a producer of the movie and appears in two scenes as Troy’s sternly disapproving father) narrates the story while following Buck from city to city,  watching him perform a shopworn potpourri of magic tricks and hypnosis for half-full houses. Mr. Hanks exudes the same easygoing likability as his father, without the magnetic star quality.  Buck selects Cincinnati, a stronghold of fan support, as the place to recapture show business glory (and perhaps an invitation to appear on Jay Leno’s “Tonight Show”) with an exhibition of mass hypnosis. While in Cincinnati, Troy has a fling with a hard-boiled publicist (Emily Blunt) who stands up to Buck when he turns petulant.  Ms. Blunt, who has the officious, mechanical airs of a contemporary publicist down pat, lends the movie pungent comic undertones, as do Debra Monk and Steve Zahn as a pair of foolishly besotted Buck Howard fans who insist on shepherding their idol around the city.  In the end “The Great Buck Howard,” despite its many satirical thrusts, insists on being nice. The film might be described as “The King of Comedy” with its fangs removed; it leaves a tiny but discernible afterglow.  “The Great Buck Howard” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested) for some language including suggestive remarks and a drug reference.</text>
      <date>March 20, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>