<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In "Green Street Hooligans," a feature-length folly about the terrors and self-affirming joys of football (that is, soccer) hooliganism, the young British actor Charlie Hunnam enters in full swagger. A fine-boned beauty who holds the screen with ease, Mr. Hunnam plays his character, Pete Dunham, a full-time teacher and part-time thug, as a sexual predator. But here's the rub: the object of Pete's desire isn't the pretty girl (or boy) next door, but the sneering, shouting and swearing fans across the stadium. Like his equally hopped-up friends, he can't wait to have his way with them.  Along with war, sports has long been the arena for straight men to work out their issues with one another, and while not stated outright, it's brutally clear that all the punching, pounding, shoving, stomping and head-butting in this film are the vehicle for some serious sublimation. The love that dare speak its name here is for football. The love that dare not is among nominally heterosexual men who prefer hoisting a few pints, and generally more, with their mates down at the pub rather than staying home with the little woman. Such is the case in "Green Street Hooligans," an accidental advertisement for Alcoholics Anonymous and the somnolent pleasures of cricket that, in the end, is mostly about the pleasures, both visceral and visual, of violence.  The trace of a plot wedged between all the body blows involves a young American, Matt Buckner (Elijah Wood), who, after getting booted out of Harvard, ends up in London ladding about with Pete in support of West Ham United Football Club. The two are in-laws and apparently a match made in buddy heaven. This implausible conceit is meant to explain how this whiny American washout (and would-be journalist) ends up roughing it with men whose appetite for destruction is more whetted than their love for the game. What it doesn't remotely explain are the social whys and logistical hows of such hooliganism. For this, interested parties are directed toward Bill Buford's book "Among the Thugs," a vastly entertaining account of football fandom gone horrifyingly amok.  "Green Street Hooligans" was directed and written by Lexi Alexander, a former karate and kickboxing champion from Germany with a couple of films under her black belt. Her latest offering certainly possesses energy: it starts fast and rarely lets up. This pumped-up, accelerated pace works for its seemingly innumerable fight scenes, but the truth is that once you have seen one glass bottle shatter over a guy's head, you have pretty much seen them all. When toward the end of the film Ms. Alexander shows the hooligans at their day jobs - behind desks, in ties and suits - these shards of normalcy register as both surprising and disappointing since, at long last, the filmmaker seems to be acknowledging that there really is more to life than boozing, brawling and sports. Who knew?  "Green Street Hooligans" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It features a full menu of bloodletting, though there are no guns.</text>
      <date>September 9, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>