<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> As a realist filmmaker, Edward Burns knows that an intimate knowledge of the old neighborhood can’t be acquired from a crash course in local customs; you have to have grown up there. In “The Groomsmen,” his latest of several trips back to an Irish-American enclave on the outskirts of New York (in this case, City Island in the Bronx), he paints a scathing portrait of raucous high school buddies clutching at their rock ’n’ roll glory days as they push 35.  Observing this pack of swaggering overgrown babies guzzling beer, dropping the names of 1980’s rock bands and making ragged music together in a garage, the movie evokes the creepy mixture of comfort and suffocation that a reunion of the old gang can produce.  What gives Mr. Burns’s movies their spark is his gut-level empathy for these people, most of whom he understands deeply and relies on for inspiration.  In “The Groomsmen,” just when it seems as if he might have pulled off an American “I Vitelloni,” his X-ray vision glazes over, and he resolves the anxiety and despair hanging over the reunion with tearful hugs and phony reassurances.  At his most insightful, Mr. Burns knows his characters’ every tic. You can almost smell the cooking odors buried in the couches of the modest middle-class homes with basketball hoops in the driveways. But in “The Groomsmen,” Mr. Burns, as he has since “The Brothers McMullen” in 1995, is unable (or perhaps afraid) to contrive a story to match his attunement to place and personality. You tolerate the false sentimentality and his characters’ one-dimensional troubles the way you tolerate the conventions of a sitcom.  The dramatic catalyst is the imminent wedding of Paulie (Mr. Burns), a self-supporting writer, and Sue (Brittany Murphy), his 10-months-pregnant girlfriend. Paulie’s miserable, envious older brother, Jimbo (Donal Logue), who runs a small, struggling business, loudly advises him not to go through with the wedding. Mr. Logue offers an unsettling portrait of a repressed, uncommunicative alcoholic whose childless marriage is beginning to unravel.  Just as pathetic is Paulie’s cousin Mike (Jay Mohr), the group cutup, who still lives with (and works for) his father. The most infantile and nostalgic of the five, Mike is a menace who keeps hounding his ex- girlfriend Jen (Jessica Capshaw) to take him back until her younger brother steps in. When T. C. (John Leguizamo), the lead singer of their high school rock band, returns for the wedding after a mysterious eight-year absence, Mike is still so steamed at him for having stolen his precious Tom Seaver baseball card that they immediately get into a shoving match.  T. C. warily confides to his friends his reason for leaving the neighborhood: he’s gay. Mr. Leguizamo is miscast as this underwritten one-note character, and the blasé reactions to his confession ring false. Mike, whom T. C. remembers as the group’s relentless gay baiter, seems strangely unfazed.  Dez (Matthew Lillard), the most contented of the five, is married with two young sons and owns the neighborhood bar. He embodies the idea bruited about of what it means to be a male adult in this hidebound culture.  That leaves Paulie, whose sudden case of premarriage jitters feels cooked up for dramatic effect. The biggest hole in a movie that falls sadly short of being another “Diner” or “Trees Lounge” is Mr. Burns’s failure to make his alter-ego character anything other than the best-looking and most affluent member of the pack, standing there and discreetly gloating.    “The Groomsmen” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has lots of profanity.</text>
      <date>July 14, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>