<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Amid the continuing deluge of documentaries about the war in Iraq, Patricia Foulkrod’s film “The Ground Truth” stands out as an especially pointed indictment of the American military’s treatment of its own people on and off the battlefield.  The film also addresses deeper questions about modern methods of creating efficient soldiers and their long-term consequences. It asks: how could anyone imagine that the intensive molding of human beings into killing machines wouldn’t affect the rest of their lives? The film’s 10 main talking heads (9 men and 1 woman from various socioeconomic backgrounds) agree that that kind of radical personality change, once instilled, can’t be reversed as easily as turning off a faucet.  “The Ground Truth” proceeds swiftly from scenes of recruitment in Venice, Calif., to a Marine Corps boot camp, to the killing fields of Iraq, to the home front. The scenes in which recruits are regaled with promises of the benefits of service, without any mention of killing, aren’t all that surprising. How could a volunteer wartime army be mustered any other way? But there is a difference between misleading advertising and outright lying. One National Guardsman dispatched to Iraq recalls being promised that he would never see combat.  The scenes in boot camp will also surprise no one who has seen “Full Metal Jacket” or “Jarhead,” in which personalities are broken down and reconstructed through systematic humiliation, deprivation and depersonalization.  The movie comes to a boil with its firsthand stories of combat. One soldier after another recalls being encouraged by senior officers not to distinguish between civilians and the enemy. The film’s most gung-ho marine, who went to Iraq for the thrill of combat, recalls his personal turning point: when he killed an Iraqi woman who was approaching his tank only to discover afterward that she was clutching a white flag. Another tells of being screamed at by an Iraqi civilian carrying his brother’s head, which had just been blown off.  But the film’s most disheartening testimony comes from soldiers  who returned from Iraq emotionally and mentally shattered only to encounter resistance when seeking treatment for posttraumatic stress disorder. One tells of being dismissed by a counselor with the words, “We don’t treat ‘conscientious objectors,’ ” after he voiced his anguish at having killed innocent civilians. These collected stories portray the Defense Department and the Veterans Administration as understaffed, underfinanced agencies responding with a shocking indifference to the needs of those who have served honorably.  “The Ground Truth,” which was made in association with several antiwar veterans organizations, including Iraq Veterans Against the War, tries to do too much in too little time. It would be a stronger film if it devoted more detailed attention to the plight of the returning veteran. As it stands, it is a scattershot antiwar polemic that doesn’t bolster its arguments with any historical perspective or statistical evidence. No one from the government or the military is trotted out to give an opposing view.  This is not to say that  “The Ground Truth,” on its own terms, isn’t devastating. There’s nothing sadder than to hear a disabled, disillusioned soldier, his life in ruins, wondering what he was fighting for.  “The Ground Truth”  is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity.</text>
      <date>September 15, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>