<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “You’re not going anywhere.” That’s what young Dito Montiel (Shia LaBeouf) hears again and again from his father. Like many sensitive young men in rough circumstances, Dito, growing up fast in Astoria, Queens, in 1986, dreams of flight. He says he wants to go to California with his new friend, Mike (Martin Compston), but really it seems as if any place other than Astoria will do.  And even as he gets lost in the big brown eyes of his girlfriend, Laurie (Melonie Diaz), Dito still can’t wait to get away from home — from the noise and violence of the streets, and from the cramped chaos of the house where he lives with his irascible father, Monte (Chazz Palminteri), and his gentle, weary mother, Flaurie (Dianne Wiest).  Monte’s response to Dito’s desires is dismissive but also anxious. When he says, “You’re not going anywhere,” he really means, in part, “Please don’t leave me.”  The failure of communication between father and son is one of the painful elements in “A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints,” which arrives in theaters today after winning several awards at the Sundance festival earlier this year. We know that Dito will eventually   leave because the movie, in addition to chronicling the events leading up to his departure, also observes his return, nearly 20 years later. (When he comes back, Mr. LaBeouf has grown into Robert Downey Jr., and the casting of these two itchy, inventive actors in a single role is nothing short of revelatory. Ms. Diaz, for her part, is replaced by Rosario Dawson, who takes possession of the movie for the few minutes that she’s in it.) We also know that the real Dito Montiel grew up to be the author of a memoir and the director of this film.  Though autobiographical, “A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints” is also a coming-of-age story set against a tough urban background, in which the protagonist’s emerging sense of his own individuality cuts against his loyalty to friends and kin. What sets the film apart, and makes it one of the more remarkable American directing debuts in recent years, is Mr. Montiel’s passionate, almost reckless engagement with the possibilities of the medium. Adapting his impressionistic, often rambling memoir for the screen, he demonstrates an autodidact’s exuberant self-confidence and the eye of a born filmmaker. Working with a large, mostly young cast, he has made a picture so full of life and feeling that the screen can hardly contain it.  There is certainly a lot of screaming and yelling and fighting. Monte has a temper, but he is less a domestic martinet than an anxious, timid man hoping, against evidence and reason, that things will work out.    “Those kids are all right, they’re all right,” he says to Flaurie, speaking of Dito and his friends and trying to reassure himself. But Dito’s pals, whom Flaurie likens to “a pack of wolves,” are not all right. A simmering, racially-tinged feud with a gang from another neighborhood threatens to explode into serious violence.  The boisterous, antisocial behavior of the young men Dito hangs around with walks a fine line between annoying and menacing. Antonio (Channing Tatum), the alpha dog in this crew, is regularly beaten up by his father and compensates for the hurt and humiliation with bluster and brutality. Mr. Tatum, who has the bullish physicality of a young Brando, is an electrifying actor, and I suspect we’ll be seeing a lot more of him after this breakout performance.  Busy as the film is, it also pauses for reflective, intimate moments in which the camera’s movements and the texture of the sound design mirror the wide-eyed, confused state of Dito’s youthful consciousness. Mr. LaBeouf has a watchful, excited demeanor, and his character, miserable as he sometimes is, is also curious and adventurous, savoring the funny, strange and beautiful things the world throws in front of him. He and Mike ride the subway to Manhattan, where they work for a flamboyant and somewhat unstable dog walker (Anthony De Sando).  The closing credits roll over the sounds of Kiss performing “New York Groove,” and that silly, glammy Kiss anthem has never sounded more apt. Mr. Montiel’s nostalgia for the New York of his younger days is unabashed, but it is also unclouded by illusions and tempered by a ragged kind of wisdom.  Terrible things happen in “A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints.” Mr. Downey warns at the beginning that some of the people we meet in the movie will die before it’s over, and the nostrum that time heals all wounds is shown to be a lie. But though the picture is wrenching, at times devastating, it leaves you with that buoyant feeling of having encountered a raw, authentic work of art. All those howls of pain are its way of telling you that it is madly, defiantly, uncontrollably alive.  “A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian); there is violence, obscene language and nudity.</text>
      <date>September 29, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>