<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>When the eye of the married man wanders in Yvan Attal's breezy, skin-deep sex comedy, "Happily Ever After," the object of desire could be any of the thousands of shapely dream girls teeming through the streets and bars of Paris. And as the movie's opening scene suggests, many of those women can be even more forthright about acting on their desires than the beady-eyed hound dogs  who harangue them with the same  old lines. That's how Vincent (Mr. Attal), a mildly rakish car dealer with a wife and young son, embarks on an affair with an unidentified masseuse (Angie David), a cool ash-blond beauty and epitome of Parisian delectability. With barely a word exchanged, she snatches him up in a bar after rejecting the bumbling come-on spewed by the man standing next to him. Minutes later, she and Vincent are clawing off each other's clothes in the elevator speeding to her apartment. For a man who has created a nearly perfect life for himself, what harm could there be if he discreetly indulges in a little something on the side? That's the sort of thinking that landed Sherman McCoy, the  protagonist of "The Bonfire of the Vanities," in  trouble. But Paris is not New York. And if Vincent's exploits don't upend the City of Light, they are not without consequences. The movie's message may be terribly familiar, but it still bears repeating. Sexual combustibility is powerful stuff, and to extend a quick  encounter into a supposedly casual affair is to infuse fantasy with reality; the more ecstasy, the more attachment, the more attachment, the more expectation. Vincent and his beautiful, devoted wife, Gabrielle (Charlotte Gainsbourg), a real estate agent, have reached the point in their marriage when the passion has cooled to a simmer that requires novelty for the heat to be turned up. When they unleash their pent-up frustrations in a domestic food fight, that fire momentarily flares. But you can't keep a marriage spicy by emptying the entire contents of the refrigerator over each other's heads every day. Vincent finally succumbs to temptation after having absorbed one too many tales of conquest by his smarmy co-worker Fred (Alain Cohen). A smug, preening bachelor so ordinary looking he wouldn't turn a head, Fred is an unlikely Don Juan who succeeds on sheer nerve. In front of his friends, he schedules multiple liaisons on a constantly jingling cellphone. He  chastises Vincent and his ilk for living on the fairy tales they learned as boys. Vincent and Fred belong to a triumvirate of soccer-and-poker-playing pals of whom the third, Georges (Alain Chabat), is an unconvincing modern update of the henpecked husband. For him and his blond, pregnant wife, Nathalie (Emmanuelle Seigner), a sexy but abrasive 70's-style feminist, marriage is a blood sport fought over such sexually loaded issues as her giving their son a girl's toy or his impulsive purchase of a flashy sports car. As they go at each other tooth and nail, these two are more like Punch and Judy than Edward Albee's George and Martha. A fourth, entirely cardboard pair, briefly seen, are an Indian couple who seem to have it all after 20 years: hot sex and perfect devotion. Nobody does adultery in movies with more style and zest than the French, especially when the mode is frivolous. And anyone who watches "Happily Ever After" can identify with the grass-is-always-greener daydreams that haunt its characters. By introducing three different couples, the director and screenwriter tries halfheartedly to turn "Happily Ever After" into a treatise on marriage, but Vincent and Gabrielle's story is the only one that matters. Gabrielle is so in tune with Vincent that she instantly senses his infidelity but decides not to confront him, despite the pain. The film's more contemplative scenes observe her own responses to the temptations thrown in her path. One possibility involves a handsome stranger (Johnny Depp) standing beside her at a record store listening booth. The two don't speak or touch, but one move in the charged atmosphere might change everything.</text>
      <date>April 8, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>