<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>There may be a story hidden amid the attractive bits and pieces that make up the film "Happy Here and Now," but goodness knows, I can't find it. Set in New Orleans, this collection of loosely connected set pieces was written and directed by Michael Almereyda, who is perhaps best known for his 2000 iteration of "Hamlet," an inspired reconsideration of the classic text in which the moody Dane poses his famous question while strolling the aisles of a video store. That scene suggests Mr. Almereyda has a conflicted relationship with mainstream narrative; in both "Hamlet" and films like "Nadja," that conflict greatly works to the director's dreamy advantage. Alas, here it does not. Shot several years ago in the pre-ravaged Crescent City, the film takes place in what is meant to look like tomorrow but, because of the lag time between production and distribution, looks an awful lot like last year. In a page torn from the William Gibson playbook, characters in the film communicate with one another using some kind of Internet hookup, electrodes stuck to their heads and avatars that allow them to assume other identities. These avatars permit  a buggy exterminator like Eddie (David Arquette) to assume a rather more seductive form when he cruises the Internet, dropping pickup lines on babes like Muriel (Shalom Harlow), the woman who gives the film a smidgen of mystery by disappearing. The title "Happy Here and Now" may be ironic; perhaps not. Certainly no one in the film seems especially happy to be in the here and the now except a little girl named Josephine (Josephine Martin), who strums an electric guitar under the casual care of her mother (and Muriel's aunt), Lois (Ally Sheedy). Shortly after Muriel disappears without trace or explanation, her sister Amelia (the Canadian actress Liane Balaban) shows up at Lois's house and begins a lackadaisical search that mostly entails moping around picturesque locales that bring her face to face with various picturesque locals, including a bluesman by the name of Ernie K-Doe, Lois's friend Bill (Clarence Williams III) and a handful of squatters only slightly more believable than the Hollywood habitués in "Rent." In time, we also meet the most engaging member of this self-conscious menagerie, Eddie's firefighter brother, Tom (the Irish actor Karl Geary). Nothing much happens with this character, however, who like a seeing-impaired widow, Hannah (Gloria Reuben), disappears in a fog of intellectual allusions, goofy sight gags and  body-and-soul stirring rhythm and blues. Like some other contemporary films that try to stitch together a small army of characters into a community of sorts, "Happy Here and Now" feels like a symptom in search of a cure. The utopian impulse that seems to drive these films is hard to knock, but it can be less than persuasive when the characters seem little more than avatars for the people behind the camera, as they are here (and now). There is one other character worth mentioning in "Happy Here and Now": Eddie Mars. Devotees of Turner Classic Movies will recognize  the name of the gambler Humphrey Bogart goes up against in "The Big Sleep." In the Howard Hawks film of the Raymond Chandler novel, Eddie Mars tells Philip Marlowe, "Your story didn't sound quite right." With screwball timing, Marlowe says, "Oh, that's too bad - you got a better one?" Eddie Mars shoots back, "Maybe I can find one." In between the tough-guy patter, Chandler writes that it doesn't matter where we lie: we all sleep the big sleep. What matters, as we know from both the book and the film, are the stories we tell. The lyrically minded Mr. Almereyda clearly knows this; it's just that here his story doesn't sound quite right, either. "Happy Here and Now" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). There is some swearing, but nothing you haven't heard before. </text>
      <date>December 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>