<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It's possible that Maggie Gyllenhaal will never become a major star, but there isn't an American actress in movies today who holds the screen with as much deep-seated soul. In Don Roos's slyly subversive "Happy Endings," a drama disguised as a wisp of a comedy, Ms. Gyllenhaal plays Jude, a heartbreaker whose throaty voice was made for torch songs and drama. Adrift in a melancholic haze, with pixie hair and long, loose limbs, her eyes rimmed with liner and worry, Jude looks a lot like a doll, one that knows she is fated to be forgotten.  An ensemble piece about a miscellany of Angelenos bumping against one another with love and in anger, "Happy Endings" centers on two complementary characters: Jude and Mamie, an older woman played by Lisa Kudrow. Just south of 40, with no life partner or children, Mamie works as a counselor in an abortion clinic. She's distracted and disengaged even at home, where she wanders through rooms that have all the warmth and personality of a Hyatt. It's a measure of her profound disconnection that when she receives a massage from a smoothie named Javier (Bobby Cannavale), who also turns out to be her lover, she flinches under his touch. For her, the land of the living is dangerous territory.  Mamie and Jude meet only once, near the end, but their lives form parallel lines from almost the start of the story. The film opens with a literal bang as a woman we will soon know as Mamie, breathless and convulsively weeping, runs smack into an oncoming car. Mr. Roos, who wrote as well as directed the film, quickly assures us with some printed text that this is not the promised happy ending of the title and that the bloodied woman isn't dead: "No one dies in this movie, not on screen. It's a comedy, sort of." This annotation, which takes the shape of white-lettered words set against a slab of black, both diffuses the tension (Lisa Kudrow lives!) and underscores the filmmaker's personal stake in the story. He may be off-screen but he is never less than acutely present.  Mr. Roos, whose previous films include the nimble ensemble comedy "The Opposite of Sex" and, less happily, a romantic misfire called "Bounce," does well with a crowded canvas. If it takes a while to figure out that this new film is as much about Jude as Mamie, it's partly because there are other juicy characters jostling for attention. Among the most central are Mamie's  brother, Charley (Steve Coogan), who comes equipped with a lover, Gil (David Sutcliffe), and two friends, Pam and Diane (Laura Dern and Sarah Clarke), lesbians with a 2-year-old son on whom everyone dotes. At one time, Gil had been in the running to become the child's father, a road not taken that he and Charley peer down with uneasy wistfulness.  Sons and fathers, sisters and brothers, friends and lovers, gay and straight, adopted and sperm-banked - "Happy Endings" is a road map to the way we live now. Mamie and Charley are actually  step-sister and -brother, but they share a history that goes deeper than family ties. The absolute depth of their connection emerges after Mamie is approached by a would-be documentary filmmaker, Nicky (Jesse Bradford), who wants to force her into an on-camera reunion with the son she gave up at birth. (Nicky thinks the reunion will be his ticket to film school.) Years earlier, in a spasm of teenage lust, Mamie had laid the foundation for her life: she had given birth to a child whose absence would become the hole in her heart.  Mr. Roos has a screwball director's sense of timing and a writer's love for the well-turned phrase. Smartly, he lets the director hold sway over the writer, a bent  that is most obvious in the economic way he keeps his characters in rotation. The filmmaker moves the narrative center of gravity seamlessly from Mamie and Charley to Charley and Gil to, ever so briefly, Charley and an eager pup named Otis (Jason Ritter). A rhythmically challenged musician who works at Charley's restaurant, Otis becomes the bridge to Jude, whom he meets at work while she's singing karaoke. Rootless, Jude follows Otis home, where she soon becomes involved with his wealthy  widower father, Frank (a wonderfully poignant Tom Arnold), and ushers the story into surprising depths.  Ensembles this large tend to be unwieldy or overly schematic, often both, but Mr. Roos is enough of a craftsman (and a mainstream filmmaker) that he never lets the seams show. It's worth noting that although ensemble movies take place in different geographies, multilinear stories like this one seem particularly attractive to filmmakers working in the sprawling, decentered cities of Los Angeles and London. There are probably all sorts of reasons for this, including the vagaries of fashion (and Robert Altman's long shadow). But one obvious advantage of bringing characters together in this fashion is that it allows filmmakers to create microcosms of the world. It also allows some filmmakers to indulge in the fantasy of "community," surely one of the most denuded words in the contemporary American lexicon.  Mr. Roos doesn't pretend that a collection of spiky, selfish, self-serving individuals, even a group as white and comfortably situated as the one he has concocted, necessarily makes a community. In a lot of ensemble films, the moral of the story is that everyone is lonely, but at the end of the day and those empty nights, no one is alone. Mr. Roos doesn't peddle such off-the-rack comfort. In "Happy Endings," everyone is always alone, whether in the arms of lovers or curling into solitude. That makes the filmmaker sound somewhat of an art-house existentialist. But Mr. Roos is more radical than that stereotype because, against the tide of independent fiction film, he remains alert to the truth that the personal is the political.  It would be difficult to explain just how Mr. Roos raises that tattered old feminist flag without giving everything away, and it's possible that even the mention of this particular F-word may do more harm than good to this movie. Suffice it to say that when Mr. Roos shows Jude exercising one of her constitutionally protected rights, he is not indulging in melodramatic excess. He is making a statement about how our choices define who we are, for better and worse. In that respect, it's never clear if Mamie ever understands the mistakes she made. But it's a mark of Mr. Roos's generosity that this fretful, difficult loner is as much the heroine of this story as Jude, a woman whose ending may not be happy, but whose self-determination is.  "Happy Endings" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film has some strong language, adult themes and a little recreational pot smoking.</text>
      <date>July 15, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>