<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  The feet in the title of George Miller’s new film shuffle and stomp with glorious syncopation, but it would be a stretch to call them happy. Small and webbed and clawed, the appendages belong to an animated emperor penguin named Mumble (Elijah Wood) who, through the wizardry of computer animation, gets his terpsichorean moves from the brilliant tap-dancer Savion Glover. Like Mr. Glover and Eleanor Powell, Mumble was born to dance. There’s a song in his heart if not in his diaphragm, but, strangely, a lot of his tippity tappiting has the urgent pulse of an S O S.  Much like Mr. Miller’s excellent “Babe: Pig in the City” and his dystopian “Mad Max” trilogy, “Happy Feet” presents a vision of the world seen through a glass darkly. One of the most underrated  films of the 1990s, “Pig in the City” was a terrible commercial disappointment, an animal-farm noir that hewed closer in apocalyptic tone and feel to the “Mad Max” films than to its sunnier, much-beloved predecessor, “Babe.” “Happy Feet” is Mr. Miller’s first film in eight long years, and while compromised by the uplift and affirmation that mainstream animation regurgitates like a mommy penguin, it also shows a remarkable persistence of vision. Even in a story about singing-and-dancing fat and feather, Mr. Miller can’t help but go dark and deep.  It takes him a while to get there. First, he must unleash Robin Williams, who gives wacky, at times uneasy voice to several characters, including that of a charming Adélie penguin named Ramon,  who sounds more East Los Angeles than Anywhere Antarctica. Having been shunned by the other emperor penguins because he can’t sing, Mumble joins a flock of smaller, stubbier Adélie penguins who,  when not collecting pebbles, do stand-up. Mr. Williams, who these days is better heard than seen, also pours on the molasses as an Rockhopper penguin called Lovelace, who sounds a lot like the singer Barry White, which means he’s one of the few so-called black voices in a world that sounds otherwise white as deep winter.  That doesn’t mean that Mr. Williams isn’t funny, only that it’s discomfiting that so many children’s films depend on voices that are funny only because they exploit ethnic and racial stereotypes. Because penguins look pretty much alike, most of the principals deliver distinctive vocal performances. Nicole Kidman recycles her baby-breathy Marilyn Monroe shtick for Mumble’s mother, Norma Jean, while Hugo Weaving sticks a Scottish burr in his throat to play an elder penguin named Noah. For Mumble’s father, Memphis, Hugh Jackman throws his voice into the deep-fryer and comes up with something that’s a little bit country, a little bit rock ’n’ roll. Everyone sounds pretty white except when they’re lip-synching (beak-synching?) the funk and R&amp;B standards on the film’s playlist.  “Happy Feet” is far from the only animated film to lean on stereotype for its comedy: “Over the Hedge” and “Cars” do the same, among many other animated features, as does, of course, “Borat.”  I bring this up only because Mr. Miller brings an unusual depth of feeling to his work as well as a distinct moral worldview. “Happy Feet” is a familiar story about a wee outsider forced to struggle against the usual odds and misguided adults to discover his inner penguin. Yet tucked inside this nominally feel-good jukebox musical with its crooning and swooning critters is a piercingly sad story about the devastation being visited on the natural world. The tapping we hear, as it turns out, is drilling holes in our hearts.  For the most part, the screenplay — written by Mr. Miller, Warren Coleman, John Collee and Judy Morris — traces a familiar arc. Not long after he happens upon the flock of Adélie penguins, Mumble discovers that alien creatures (guess who?) are scooping all the fish out of the ocean. Determined to right this wrong, he and three others set off on a voyage that includes sweeping images of mountains that recall Mr. Wood’s high-altitude trekking in “The Lord of the Rings” and brings the travelers face to face with elephant seals with astonishing photorealistic tusklike protuberances. What makes the seals especially beautiful isn’t the almost tactile detail of their crinkles and grooves; it’s that, unlike Mumble and his vaguely anthropomorphized face, they look insistently and gloriously like animals.  Beauty announces itself quietly in “Happy Feet,” whether in the discreetly shifting shades of white that seem to turn the snow into a living, breathing organism, or in the articulated lines of penguin chicks that make each ball of downy fluff a very specific ball of downy fluff. All this beauty makes it easy to understand why Mumble might want to tap his feet with joy. It also explains why Mr. Miller, after doing an extremely credible approximation of the wonderful world of Walt Disney, plunges his hapless hero into a nightmare worthy of Samuel Fuller’s “Shock Corridor.” As politically pointed as it is disturbing, it is a view of hell as seen through the eyes and ears of creatures we foolishly, tragically call dumb.  “Happy Feet” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). There are a few scenes of peril that might frighten young children, but it’s the adults who will probably need the hankies.</text>
      <date>November 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>