<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> If you think the last seven years have been one long, dumb, dirty joke — or maybe if, sometimes, you just wish you could believe as much — then “Harold &amp; Kumar Escape From Guantanamo Bay,” written and directed by Jon Hurwitz and Hayden Schlossberg, just might be the perfect movie for you. That it is, quite unapologetically, far from perfect in every respect almost doesn’t matter. The simple fact that a movie exists with the title “Harold &amp; Kumar Escape From Guantanamo Bay” is cause for hope. Or maybe for alarm. In any case, for a few laughs.  Be warned that some of these are fairly cheap and crude, involving the standard motifs of R-rated male comedy: excrement, leering sexual aggression, hysterical sexual insecurity and drug use. Not much new ground is broken in this department, which doesn’t mean that the jokes themselves aren’t funny.  The idea of gay sex induces panic; the sight of unclothed female flesh causes jaws to go slack; and in a crisis someone is sure to whip out a joint. (I won’t spoil any surprises by saying just who.) At one point the movie’s titular heroes drop in on a friend who’s having a “bottomless” party at which there seem to be only female guests, and the movie loses some credibility when it declines to show the full extent of its stars’ eventual participation in the festivities. Dudes, if the dude in “Forgetting Sarah Marshall” could put his business up on the screen, then so can you. It’s a whole new world.  But in other, more significant ways, the “Harold &amp; Kumar” movies, of which this is the second (after the immortal “Harold &amp; Kumar Go to White Castle”) and I hope not the last, go further than most stoner raunch comedies in acknowledging certain realities of contemporary American life.  The simplest innovation, but also in a way the most radical, lies in Harold and Kumar themselves. Played by John Cho (he’s Harold Lee, the Korean-American investment banker) and Kal Penn (he’s Kumar Patel, the Indian-American would-be medical student), they are a postcollegiate multicultural odd couple in a world where ignorance and prejudice do battle with hypersensitivity and political correctness. They are at once nerdy achievers caught in the gears of meritocracy and stoner rebels against the machine. In their exasperated, half-baked (or, in the reefer-mad Kumar’s case, fully baked) way, these representative men mock all sides.  And just about everything else too. Their first adventure, four years ago, was simple and aspirational: they had the munchies and they wanted some burgers. But now times have changed, even though it is only a few days later in screen time. Paranoia is no longer an occasional, bong-induced side effect, but rather standard operating procedure at the highest levels of government.  Well, sort of. When Kumar is asked to step aside for a random security check at the airport, he blusters about ethnic profiling, which it turns out is less a matter of righteous outrage than an attempt to distract the security agents from finding the marijuana in his underwear. He and Harold are going to Amsterdam to find Maria (Paula Garces), the new love in Harold’s life, but rather than wait until they land in that paradise of legal vice, Kumar tries to fire up the pipe in the lavatory at 30,000 feet.  To their fellow passengers Kumar’s bong looks like a bomb, and to a zealous Homeland Security bureaucrat (Rob Corddry), its discovery exposes a terrorist conspiracy between Al Qaeda and North Korea. And so into United States custody, and then, post-escape, on another stoner road trip, to Texas, where Kumar’s college sweetheart, Vanessa (Danneel Harris), is about to marry a well-connected prepster named Colton (Eric Winter). On the way they meet people who challenge some stereotypes and confirm others, and they also, in a sublime pop-cultural in-joke carried over from the trip to White Castle, hook up with the great Neil Patrick Harris.  “Harold &amp; Kumar Escape From Guantanamo Bay” offers a shambling series of hit-and-miss goofs, rather than incisive satire directed at Bush-era America. That is the job of Mr. Corddry’s erstwhile “Daily Show” colleagues Jon Stewart and Stephen Colbert. Mr. Hurwitz and Mr. Schlossberg (who wrote but did not direct “White Castle”) instead rely on a general sense of good-humored exasperation that never reaches the boiling point of political indignation.  But precisely because their attitudes are so bluntly hedonistic and apolitical, Harold and Kumar manage to be fairly persuasive when they get around to criticizing the status quo, which the movie has the wit to acknowledge itself as part of.  “It’s people like you who make the rest of the world think Americans are stupid. But we’re not stupid, and we’re not going to take this anymore.” These lines are  spoken by an exasperated government official, and they could, I suppose, be directed at the makers and stars of “Harold &amp; Kumar Escape From Guantanamo Bay.” But they’re not stupid, and to the extent that the movie is, its idiocy serves the cause of good sense and intelligence. And no, I’m not smoking anything.  “Harold &amp; Kumar Escape From Guantanamo Bay” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has foul language, drug use and gratuitous nudity.</text>
      <date>April 25, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>