<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Not every book receives the film adaptation it deserves, but such is certainly the case with the collection of short stories "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things." Published in 2001 under the name JT LeRoy, this assemblage of extravagant horror purports to tell the autobiographical ordeals of a cross-dressing, H.I.V.-positive, underage former prostitute from West Virginia who from the age of 4 had been subjected to various evils by his whore of a mother and her cretin boyfriends and Bible-thumping parents. Dennis Cooper was a JT LeRoy booster, as was Dave Eggers, who vowed that both  "The Heart Is Deceitful"  and the similarly themed LeRoy novel "Sarah" would "prove to be among the most influential American books of the last 10 years." Somewhere, probably hell, William S. Burroughs laughed.  Now, it seems to appear that JT LeRoy never existed, and the books and articles carrying his name were actually written by a clever Brooklyn-born, San Francisco-based woman named Laura Albert. The hipster set, in other words, has its own James Frey. It's only a matter of time (here's hoping) before Ms. Albert grovels for forgiveness before Mr. Cooper, as Mr. Frey did before Oprah Winfrey, though given the readership and rough-trade trappings, HBO would make a more suitable confession booth than network television. In any event, until then the foolish and the masochistic can ease their curiosity about this teapot tempest with the screen adaptation of "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things." Viewer discretion is advised, if only because it's well-nigh unwatchable.  Directed by Asia Argento, who wrote the script with Alessandro Magania, the screen version of "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things" traces the tribulations of a young boy, Jeremiah (played first by Jimmy Bennett, then Cole and Dylan Sprouse), from the moment his birth mother, Sarah (Ms. Argento), reclaims him from his foster parents. Speaking in Italian-accented English (a detail explained with a throwaway about a boarding school), Sarah soon proves herself a supremely unfit mother. Then again, this chick has trouble standing up. Maybe it's those high heels and itty-bitty skirts she sometimes wears, which tend to force her to bend at the waist and flash the camera. Or maybe it's all the drugs that Sarah likes to take. Or maybe Ms. Argento is proud of her body. It's a nice body.  Since this isn't much of a film, there is nothing much else to say, other than that "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things" was, unaccountably, badly shot in crummy-looking Super 16 film by Eric Edwards, who has done great work on films like "My Own Private Idaho." As she proved with her tackily entertaining feature debut, "Scarlet Diva," Ms. Argento doesn't know how to move the camera or her actors, but at least in that film she mostly subjected herself to abuse. Here, she puts three young actors into some squirmingly uncomfortable setups that would be no big deal if they were adults. But that's the thing about underage actors: they're also children, which is why a scene of child rape (a JT  LeRoy specialty) isn't just ghastly, it's also grotesque.  Such exploitation, of course, is what puts books like "Sarah" and "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things" on best-seller lists. Given publishing's seemingly endless appetite for memoirs filled with sexual sob stories and kinks, a JT  LeRoy was inevitable. Sexual confession is hot, after all, both economically and otherwise, and here was an author who hit all the hottest buttons. That the prose is as tedious as the stories are outrageous mattered not at all,  compared with such lovingly rendered degradation. For her part, Ms. Argento had something loftier in mind when she took on the book. In an interview after the film wrapped in 2003, she said she felt bound to tell this story "because I know how hard it is, especially in America, to be a single mother."  Some stuff you can't make up.  "The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes child rape, intimations of incest and brutal language.</text>
      <date>March 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>