<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Jean-Paul Sartre famously wrote that "hell is other people." It is not a well-known fact that the people he was specifically referring to are the men and women in the film "Heights." Directed by the newcomer Chris Terrio, who wrote the film with Amy Fox, basing the screenplay on Ms. Fox's one-act play of the same title, this programmatic fiction tracks five New York characters who, over the course of 24 hours, search for direction, a sense of purpose, a life. Like the film, the characters mean well and look good. But they're so deeply immersed in their own heads that they can't see the world for their needs.  Front and center is Isabel (Elizabeth Banks), the delicately pretty, emotionally thwarted daughter of a famous actress of stage and screen, Diana (Glenn Close). Isabel is engaged to the even prettier Jonathan (James Marsden), behind whose cagey, darting eyes lies a groaningly obvious secret. Shortly after the story opens, Jonathan is dodging calls from Peter (John Light), a journalist writing a profile about a fine-arts photographer whose provocative male nudes are probably meant to evoke the sensational work of Robert Mapplethorpe but look closer to the glossy fashion snaps of Herb Ritts. Hovering nearby is Alec (Jesse Bradford), a hungry young actor who lives upstairs from Isabel and Jonathan, and just that day will audition before his idol, Diana.  In its aspirations, design and worldview, "Heights" resembles a number of other films about cozily connected souls. These films, like "Love Actually," constitute a soap-operatic subgenre that might be called We Are the World. Sincere to a fault, they are built on the bedrock of decency or, more accurately, a set of shared assumptions. In these films, married characters occasionally stray, but no one ever smacks the kid, kicks the dog or burns with true, blood-boiling hate. (Todd Solondz makes We Are the World movies, too, but no one hates as passionately in his movies as he does.) Everybody hurts, as Michael Stipe likes to sing, but people in "Heights" seem to hurt more or at least spend a lot of time nursing that hurt in brooding silence and noisy confrontation.  In the film's geometry of longing, women yearn for men who yearn for someone else. A daughter tentatively reaches out to a mother cocooned in narcissism; a mother boldly reaches out to a would-be lover who, as his cellphone murmurs suggest, will never return the compliment. Meanwhile, as the characters and their desire crisscross, an iconic image of Diana as a Lady Macbeth stares from  every bus and phone booth, the way Carrie Bradshaw's image haunted "Sex and the City." It's unclear what the film's director, Mr. Terrio, wants to convey with this image of Shakespeare's bloody queen, but good parenting is doubtless not part of the equation. Boring progeny, alas, are.  And so, while mommie dearest smiles her murderous smile on the Midtown bus, Isabel drifts through her day, transfixed by ennui or maybe just psychotropic drugs. Ms. Banks is a nice-looking blonde, with an angled face that recalls Parker Posey's, but here she seems too frail a vessel to carry the weight of all this cumbersome drama.  She and the film perk up when, during one of her mother's soirees, she meets a roguish Welsh artist who simultaneously hits on her and calls her out for being a New York cliché, thereby allowing the film to have its cake and eat it,  too. All's well that ends well, ad nauseam. Still, there is something unaccountably entertaining about the moment when, during that same soiree, Diana purrs to a startled man, "Do you merengue?"  "Heights" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has nudity and the usual adult language.</text>
      <date>June 17, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>