<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> With characters named Esperanza, Dawn and Patience that signal Deeper Meaning, “Henry Poole Is Here” traffics in the kind of inspirational kitsch that only a true believer could swallow. Those convinced that faith can literally move mountains may welcome a film whose characters discuss spiritual issues, although there are no grand tectonic shifts in the landscape. In the film, directed by Mark Pellington (“Arlington Road”) from a screenplay by Albert Torres, the miracles wrought by feeling a mystical connection with a mysterious reddish stain on the side of a stucco house are less earthshaking and have to do with physical and mental health.  That house is purchased by Henry Poole (Luke Wilson), a brooding American Everyman diagnosed with an unidentified terminal illness whose only visible symptoms are episodes of blotchy skin. Henry has returned to the Los Angeles neighborhood in which he grew up determined to die in slovenly solitude. While glumly waiting for the end, he comforts himself with vodka and Krispy Kreme doughnuts.  To his annoyance, his pesky neighbors refuse to leave him alone. The most persistent is the garrulous Mexican-American widow who lives next door, Esperanza (Adriana Barraza). She is the first to notice the stain, which contains a spot from which a bloodlike substance slowly drips. Certain that she has seen the face of God, she summons her pastor, Father Salazar (George Lopez), to inspect it, and as word gets around, visitors begin arriving to worship at the supposedly holy site.  Millie (Morgan Lily), an  8-year-old neighbor who hasn’t said a word since the breakup of her parents’ marriage, is also mysteriously drawn to the stain and miraculously begins talking again. Her beautiful, cookie-baking mother, Dawn (Radha Mitchell), just happens to be a perfect mate for Henry should he be roused from his morbid funk.  As Henry engages in furious verbal skirmishes with the true believers, Mr. Wilson offers a credible portrait of an angry, despairing man fending off a cult. But the film’s spiritual deck is stacked. In the mawkish tradition of movies like “Simon Birch,” “Wide Awake,” “August Rush” and “Hearts in Atlantis,” “Henry Poole Is Here” is insufferable hokum that takes itself very, very seriously.  “Henry Poole Is Here” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>August 15, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>