<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>"Taking pictures means holding your breath with all your faculties concentrated on capturing a fleeting reality," declares the pioneering photojournalist Henri Cartier-Bresson near the end of Heinz Butler's austere documentary portrait, "Henri Cartier-Bresson: The Impassioned Eye." In the small but stately film, completed a year before Cartier-Bresson's death at 95 in August 2004, he slowly leafs through volumes of his black-and-white photographs, shows some of his later drawings and muses on his art to the severe, prickly strains of Bach piano music. Even when viewed secondhand in a movie, these photographs are something to see. Their formal elegance is balanced by an intense, pulsing humanity. In all his photographs, Cartier-Bresson says, "geometry is the foundation." The documentary, which subscribes to the Great Man school of reverential portraiture, is not a biography but an interview (in French, simultaneously translated into English) conceived as a master class on art appreciation, with guest commentators augmenting Cartier-Bresson's own sparsely chosen words. A recurrent presence is the French actress Isabelle Huppert, who points to a portrait he took of her and says that it reveals a side of her personality she had never seen before. His pictures, she says, capture the "deep, mysterious bond between people and the things around them." But since the pictures speak so eloquently for themselves, her words are redundant. The keys to taking a good portrait, insists Cartier-Bresson, are making people forget they're in front of a camera and seizing the moment of truth as it passes. Portraits of Leonard Bernstein conducting, Isaac Stern playing the violin, Coco Chanel cracking a rare smile and Alexander Calder and Igor Stravinsky relaxing capture such unguarded moments. What sentimentality accrues to his famous subjects resides in the palpable aura of grandeur surrounding them. Arthur Miller shows off a picture of Marilyn Monroe, taken by Cartier-Bresson on the set of "The Misfits" while she was lost in thought, and says that it reveals her as she really was. The playwright's and the photographer's simpatico went far beyond a connection to the actress. Some of Cartier-Bresson's most emotionally charged pictures were taken in the United States in the 1930's and 40's and evoke the same raw-boned social realism that surges through Miller's greatest plays. "America is a place of great extremes, and if you choose to look at the extremes, it can be very tragic," Miller says. An intrepid world traveler, Cartier-Bresson had the instinct to be present at many of the flashpoints of modern history. He was in India when Gandhi  died and in China for the Communist takeover. He also expresses a special nostalgia for Mexico and its "passion." In his most vehement statement, he declares his revulsion to colonialism. But he still insists that he doesn't have a message and is not trying to prove anything. The pictures suggest otherwise. They show a complex and emotionally engaged observer who is innately, even fiercely political in his recognition of inequality and injustice. "Henri Cartier-Bresson: The Impassioned Eye" is not rated.</text>
      <date>January 13, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>