<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “He Was a Quiet Man,” a surreal creep show with a scatological sense of humor, tosses out ideas about vigilante justice, sanity and madness,  personal redemption and corporate duplicity with the abandon of a crazed juggler tossing pins too high to catch. Such is the bravado of the movie, written and directed by Frank Cappello, that your initial impulse is to assume that it must know what it’s doing. But by the time it reaches a weak, ambiguous conclusion, the movie has gone everywhere and nowhere, much like its psychotic main character, Bob Maconel (Christian Slater).  Bob is a worm, though not literally, of course. A cowering, glowering office worker who brings out the sadist in everyone, he is often seen in close-up through a fish-eye lens. Bent over in a reflexive cringe, wearing oversize aviator glasses and a little red mustache, he is a creature you want to step on and squash.  If Bob seems the antithesis of the Mephistophelean rebels Mr. Slater portrayed with such glee in his younger days, beneath the surface of this milquetoast is the seething rage of a man who has had the stuffing kicked out of him. In the movie’s opening voice-over monologue, Bob mutters paranoid idiocy about the erosion of manhood and the decline of heroism in the age of feminism. Alone in his suburban home, he is taunted by his goldfish. He has a fetishistic attachment to a figurine of a hula girl in a lei and a grass skirt.  At work in A.D.D., the wittily named Fortune 500 company where he does something undefined with sheets of numbers, Bob keeps a gun, which he surreptitiously loads and unloads while fantasizing about the half-dozen people he intends to kill. In his briefcase he also keeps a black box with a red detonator. On his lunch hour he visits a bluff opposite his office tower, opens the briefcase and imagines blowing up the building.  One afternoon, while contemplating mass murder in his cubicle, he accidentally drops a round. Crawling  under his desk to retrieve it, he hears shots and discovers that   his office neighbor has pre-empted him and is  killing people. Bob, pulling his gun, shoots him, then saves the life of Venessa  Parks (Elisha Cuthbert), a seriously wounded fellow worker.  Suddenly the pariah is a hero, cheered by one and all. Befriended by his younger, bullying boss (Jamison Jones), he is promoted by A.D.D.’s slimy corporate kingpin Gene Shelby (William H. Macy) to vice president of creative thinking, given an office on a higher floor, with a window, and the use of a car; in reality he is Shelby’s gofer.  But Bob receives a rude shock when he visits the beautiful woman whose life he saved, who is now  a quadriplegic from a bullet in her spine. Summoning him to her hospital bed, she spits in his face and curses him for not letting her die. When he returns the next day, she apologizes, then begs him to finish the job. Refusing at the last minute, he begins to discover his humanity, and the movie envisions a weird, romantic co-dependency developing between them.  That’s just the setup of a film whose outrageous misanthropy is indistinguishable from that of its main character.    Though he wildly overacts, Mr. Slater at least humanizes Bob enough to make you pity him, though not enough to eliminate the lingering impulse to crush him under your foot.</text>
      <date>November 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>