<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>n the downbeat, sufficiently unsettling "Hide and Seek," Robert De Niro rises to a formidable challenge: he holds his own against a scene-swiping 10-year-old. As a bereft widower, David Callaway, Mr. De Niro turns out to be more than well matched by Dakota Fanning, who plays his young and only child, Emily. One of the most actively employed child actors in the movie business and one of the most gifted, Miss Fanning has both chops and a preternaturally intense screen presence. Even when you don't believe the setup, you tend to buy what she is selling. That's a good thing when it comes to a film like "Hide and Seek," which needs all the help it can get from its actors. The movie begins as if in a dream. A New York City shrink, David is married to Alison (Amy Irving), a somnolent type whose obvious affection for her daughter can't disguise her restless unhappiness. Soon after the story starts, violence descends on the Callaway family, splintering it into pieces, and David and Emily move to the country for some healing. Once there, things go from lousy to worse as Emily starts staring blankly into the surrounding woods and palling around with a sinister invisible friend called Charlie. Blood drips into the story as if from a leaky faucet; then, it pours. Under the spell of Stanley Kubrick at his most audience-friendly and "The Sixth Sense," though without the delights these influences promise, the director, John Polson, keeps the underwritten screenplay by Ari Schlossberg moving at a steady, deliberate clip. In short order it becomes clear that all is not right in this depopulated country corner, where David and Emily's next-door neighbors (Robert John Burke and Melissa Leo) always seem to be lurking with anxious, guilty eyes. Among the story's other, more approachable passers-by are David's former student (Famke Janssen) and a friendly local (Elisabeth Shue) who wears big smiles and low-cut dresses that please David but not his increasingly moody daughter. Less attractive but no less welcome is Dylan Baker as the town's somewhat vinegary sheriff. "Hide and Seek" hinges on a creepily unpleasant last-minute twist, which attentive students of the horror-thriller hybrid will probably see long in advance. Mr. Polson, whose last directorial outing was the laughably overripe high school-horror movie "Swimfan," delivers the genre goods well enough in this new movie but is not in possession of a discernable style; for the most part, he just keeps the lights down and stays out of the way of his actors. The low illumination is meant to suggest all manner of subterranean terrors, though less unhappily it also suggests some budgetary restrictions. That Mr. De Niro and especially Miss Fanning manage to register through all this murk is a testament to their talent, which however squandered does nonetheless shine. "Hide and Seek" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film contains scenes of  bloody violence, including an incident involving a pet, and intense family dynamics.</text>
      <date>January 28, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>