<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Americans are a bloodthirsty lot, at least on the big screen. The recent Hollywood rage for redoing the best and often worst from the annals of horror has wrought remakes of "The Texas Chain Saw Massacre," "Dawn of the Dead," "The Amityville Horror" and various and sundry Asian films. Oozing into a theater near you soon will be remakes of "The Evil Dead," "The Wicker Man" and Wes Craven's "Hills Have Eyes," an atrocity exhibition (family + cannibals = trouble) that is being directed by the 26-year-old French filmmaker Alexandre Aja. We may not need another iteration of a story about psychos chowing down on human viscera, but need has nothing to do with what we want, and it's clear from box-office tallies that what we really want is to be scared - to throw our hands over our eyes, peek through our latticed fingers and whimper like dogs.  And because the original "Hills Have Eyes" is freaking creepy,  and because Mr. Aja has clearly made a dissertation-level study of classic American horror, specifically 1970's-era slasher flicks, it seems likely that he will keep audiences jumping with his remake. Meanwhile, you can test your reflexes by taking in his second feature, "High Tension," a horror movie he wrote with Grégory Levasseur that was released in France in 2003. By turns unnerving and numbing, "High Tension" opens with two young women, Marie (Cécile de France, who looks a bit like one of the acting Arquettes) and Alex (Maïwenn, who can look rather remarkably like Steven Tyler), driving on an emptied-out highway. On a study break from college, the women are somewhere in France en route to the farmhouse home of Alex's parents. Right from the get-go, something feels off, partly because it appears that a neutron bomb has done away with the rest of the world, partly because the women's lips don't match the audio. Having decided that horror fans don't pay much mind to, you know, words, the company releasing the film in the United States decided to use subtitles sparingly and dub most of the dialogue. Until the blood starts flowing, the dubbing creates an unfortunate distraction. The English dialogue has that slightly hollow sound you get with dubbed films, and after you notice the disconnect between sight and sound, you watch the women's mouths like a lip-reader. But once Marie and Alex drive down a road that cuts through a cornfield, you relax. Because outside of "Oklahoma!," cornfields herald very bad things, whether in that hair-raising "Twilight Zone" episode with Billy Mumy, or in the movies "Children of the Corn" and "Jeepers Creepers 2," and it isn't long before something wicked this way comes. Sure enough, doors are soon squeaking, and a stranger (Philippe Nahon, the slab of beef from the French cult films "I Stand Alone" and "Irréversible") is frolicking with a decapitated head next to the cornfields. What follows is a protracted, enthusiastically gory variation of cat-and-mouse in which a villain with a ravenous appetite for destruction plucks off one victim after another. One unfortunate is decapitated with a chest of drawers (don't ask); another is all but beheaded with a straight-edge razor. Mr. Aja presents these deaths with heart-thumping, gruesome verisimilitude; unfortunately, he also stages the shotgun murder of a small child, a decadent and unnecessary flourish. To an extent, the return to such extreme horror is a natural consequence of  the "Scream" movies, which turned decades of genre clichés into self-conscious irony, and of that franchise's parodies. After coaxing out so many laughs, both nervous and mocking, horror had to repackage itself if it was going to remain commercially and creatively viable. For those horror movies that don't recycle Asian material, the repackaging has often involved a return to the 1970's and early 80's, if not always to the actual era, then certainly in vibe and instrumentality. Like the fairly recent "Cabin Fever" and like earlier slasher films of that grisly ilk, "High Tension" takes a fairly straightforward approach to its essential reason for being, namely the stagecraft of death. There are all sorts of reasons we love horror films, including the fact that they get into our bodies - these are movies that literally move us. But watching Marie and Alex go through their paces in "High Tension" is to be reminded once more that at the heart of  horror is the spectacle of pain, and that the pleasure we take in that spectacle is often more unsettling than anything in the actual movie, this one included. "High Tension" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It features extreme violence via furniture, a razor, an ax, a chain saw, a knife and something that looks a lot like a corkscrew.</text>
      <date>June 10, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>