<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The current of intellectual energy snapping through “The History Boys,” the ferociously engaging screen adaptation of Alan Bennett’s Tony Award-winning play, set in a  boys’ school in northern England in 1983, feels like electrical brain stimulation. As two teachers jockey for the hearts and minds of eight teenage schoolboys preparing to apply to Oxford and Cambridge, their epigrams send up small jolts of pleasure and excitement. How to teach and interpret history is the question.  One view is represented by Irwin (Stephen Campbell Moore), a hotshot young tutor and symbol of Thatcher-era go-getter mentality,  hired by the school to scrape away the rust of received opinion from the students’ thinking so that their answers to test questions will have more “edge.” On the other side is Hector (Richard Griffiths), the poetry-spouting, eccentric teacher of general studies. An obese, 50-something school fixture (imagine a squishier, teary-eyed Charles Laughton or Peter Ustinov), Hector cares deeply about how knowledge is applied to life. A married homosexual, he might be described as Mr. Chips With Kinks.  His pure idealism is measured by his response to a student during a discussion of the Holocaust. When the boy reels off a quote from Wittgenstein  —  “Whereof one cannot speak, thereof one must be silent”  —  Hector scolds him for glibness and for treating the words as “a dinky formula.” A true believer in the humanizing power of education, Hector subscribes to the academic credo of A. E. Housman: “All human knowledge is precious whether or not it serves the slightest human use.”  Most of the best lines, of course, go to Irwin, a cynic who is also gay and who wouldn’t dream of scolding anyone for glibness. “History nowadays is not a matter of conviction,” he declares. “It’s a performance. It’s entertainment.”  “Truth,” he insists, “is no more at issue in an examination than thirst at a wine-tasting or fashion at a striptease.”  Hector lands in trouble when he is caught  touching a student on the back of his motorcycle and is reported.  When the school’s ambitious, stiff-backed headmaster (Clive Merrison) confronts him with his behavior, Hector ruefully replies, “The transmission of knowledge is in itself an erotic act.”  “The History Boys” sympathizes with Hector, whom Mr. Griffith plays not as a predator but as a lonely dreamer whose ineffectual gropes are not much different from pats on the back. These whip-smart 17- and 18-year-old students not only tolerate his fumbling advances but also accept them with good humor as expressions of devotion.  The movie is a streamlined adaptation of the  National Theater production in London, which was heaped with praise when it arrived on Broadway in April for a limited engagement. Although minor characters have been added (including a religious gym teacher) and scenes excised, the film retains the play’s quicksilver pace along with an airiness and cheek that vaguely recall the ’60s films of Richard Lester.  The film was created by the same hands who made the play, including Mr. Bennett, who adapted the script, and the director Nicholas Hytner. The actors playing the eight students are the same ones who originated the roles in London, then brought them to New York. If they seem a little old for the parts, they make a seamless ensemble.  Transferred to the screen with its language intact, “The History Boys” inevitably feels less like a movie than like an academic vaudeville show. In one scene the students converse comically in French. Interwoven with the serious monologues are vintage popular songs (“Bewitched, Bothered and Bewildered”) and scenes from old movies (“Now, Voyager” and “Brief Encounter”) performed by the students with a deadpan playfulness. If these songs and re-enacted film bits seem anachronistic choices for a movie set in the 1980s (the soundtrack includes period rock by the Clash and other groups), without its breezy horseplay “The History Boys” would come across as a drier, English answer to “Dead Poets Society.”  The acting is wonderful. Mr. Moore’s avid Irwin and Mr. Griffiths’s shambling Hector are matched by the extraordinary Frances de la Tour as Dorothy Lintott, the droopy, horse-faced history teacher with a baritone voice who is the wisest and most balanced member of an academic triumvirate. Dorothy belatedly has her say when she observes with an amused exasperation: “History is a commentary on the various and continuing incapabilities of men. History is women following behind with the bucket.”  All this verbal dexterity should awaken in viewers a wistful Anglophilic envy. How often do the most articulate characters in American films express themselves with such finesse?  Here is another of Irwin’s best. “There’s no better way of forgetting something than by commemorating it,” he says, commenting on the British inability to assume more responsibility for World War I.  Of the eight students, cocky, seductive Dakin (Dominic Cooper), his eyes hotly glued on the headmaster’s secretary, Fiona (Georgia Taylor), is the most charismatic. Applying the history of World War I to his potential conquest, he compares her to the Western Front. Madly in love with Dakin is his gay, Jewish fellow student Posner (Samuel Barnett), who suggests a younger, nerdier Irwin. These two spend the most time under the movie’s microscope.  Next on the list are the overweight, clownish Timms (James Corden);  the dumb jock Rudge (Russell Tovey);  and Scripps (Jamie Parker), a voluble Christian. The others, who include a black and a Muslim student, barely register except as voices and faces in the ensemble.  For all its delights, “The History Boys” is not a world-changing work of art. It is exactly what Irwin calls history: entertainment, a scintillating contrivance that is only as good as its epigrams. Below the surface lies a gooey custard filling.  “The History Boys’’ is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for strong language and sexually explicit dialogue.</text>
      <date>November 21, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>