<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A masterpiece of indirection and pure visceral thrills, David Cronenberg's latest mindblower, "A History of Violence," is the feel-good, feel-bad movie of the year. The story of a seemingly average American family almost undone by cataclysmic violence, the film takes place in a surreal and mercilessly brutal land, Anytown, U.S.A., that has been repeatedly soaked in blood only to be repeatedly washed clean. The great kick of the movie - or rather, its great kick in the gut - comes from Mr. Cronenberg's refusal to let us indulge in movie violence without paying a price. The man wants to make us suffer, exquisitely.  Mr. Cronenberg also wants us to have a good time, and it's this tension between cinematic pain and pleasure that helps make "A History of Violence" such a sensational moviegoing experience. The film, which hinges on an upstanding citizen and reluctant mystery man, Tom Stall (brilliantly played by Viggo Mortensen), takes it as an article of faith that we, the multiplex allegiant, have been long-reared on the ways and means, giddyups and brutalizing downs of the action movie. Decades of mainlining blockbusters have, for better or perhaps for worse, inured us to the image of bullet-chewed bodies and the pop-pop-pop of phony weapon fire. For the contemporary movie connoisseur, film death is now as cheap as it is familiar. To which Mr. Cronenberg quietly says, "Oh, yeah?"  Loosely adapted by Josh Olson from the 1997 graphic novel by John Wagner and Vince Locke, the film opens with two men exiting a motel room. The younger man (Greg Bryk) is dressed in a T-shirt and jeans; the older (Stephen McHattie) wears the black suit of a funeral director and a Beelzebub Vandyke. Although it's day, probably morning, each also wears the scowls and sagging expressions of men who have long been hard at work. And back to work they go: the older man heads to the motel office to check out while the younger drives their late-model convertible a few dusty yards. When the older man returns, he sends the younger one to fetch water. They're almost ready to hit the road, but, first, there is killing to do.  There is a lot of killing in "A History of Violence," none more troubling than the first murder, which takes place inside that motel office turned charnel house. In its outrageous brutality, this inauguration into the spectacle  - and entertainment  - of death signals that Mr. Cronenberg's film isn't the usual bloody cinematic joy ride. There is, it soon emerges, nothing usual or routine about "A History of Violence," which at first plays like a stock genre picture (or an outtake from "Pulp Fiction"), only to grow progressively freakier and hair-raisingly nasty. A master of conflicting, contradictory moods, Mr. Cronenberg has a history of turning genre, particularly horror, inside out and upside down, and he applies his cool intelligence and prodigious craft to the action movie like a French deconstructionist moonlighting as John Woo.  The killers ultimately get theirs, as monsters almost always do in Hollywood movies, receiving their villainous comeuppance from a figure of outwardly impeccable rectitude and gentleness: Tom Stall. Happily married with a sexy, adoring wife, Edie (Maria Bello), and two charming children, the teenage Jack (Ashton Holmes) and a towheaded pipsqueak named Sarah (Heidi Hayes), Tom runs a diner straight off the yellowing cover of a  Saturday Evening Post in a town as cozy and sleepy as one perched on an old studio back lot. Here, the townsfolk greet one another with a smile and a wave, and youngsters share ice cream sodas like Mickey and Judy. There isn't a Wal-Mart or McDonald's in sight  - no boarded-up storefronts, no toxic waste dumps, no despair, no bums, no bad men.  Although the sign above the front door of Stall's promises "friendly service," these villains receive something altogether different when they enter the diner early one evening. In a furiously paced scene that tears a hole in both the character and the town's pacific facades, Mr. Cronenberg establishes that he can outgun Mr. Woo and then some with a sensationally choreographed shootout. The encounter leaves both desperados dead  - Mr. Cronenberg lingers on one man's ripped away face for a few squirmingly uncomfortable seconds  -  and Tom is declared an "American hero." The media descends in short order as do three men (including Ed Harris) whose sunglasses, black town car and tough-guy accents suggest we're not in Kansas (or Hollywood) anymore, but somewhere north of David Lynch's "Mulholland Drive" and far west of Lars von Trier's "Dogville."  Like both those films, "A History of Violence" explores the myth and meaning of America (or at least a representative facsimile) through its dreams, nightmares and compulsive frenzies. But where Mr. Lynch invariably imbues the violence in his films with eroticism, mixing in lipstick with the blood, and Mr. von Trier has recently let didacticism get the better of his ideas, Mr. Cronenberg plays it cool. He knows that movie violence turns us on: we kiss to the bang-bang. There's something undeniably exciting about Tom's heroic actions, so much so that they effectively produce a veritable contact high, first spurring his son to stand up to a bully and, a while later, inspiring some intensely rough sex that will leave his wife covered in abrasions. But there is something irredeemable and soul-killing here, too.  "A History of Violence" might have easily been called "A History of America," but it would sell both Mr. Cronenberg's art and his purpose short to reduce this film to an ideology. While transparently set in small-town America (Ontario passing for Indiana), the sheer unreality of the hamlet initially makes it clear that this story is not taking place in the here and the now, but in a copy of the world that looks  - wouldn't you know it  - a lot like a movie. Mr. Cronenberg, a Canadian,  is taking aim at this country, to be sure. But he is also taking aim at our violence-addicted cinema, those seductive, self-heroicizing self-justifications we sell to the world. Perversely, though, the more violent this film becomes  - in time, the blood flows all the way to Philadelphia  - the more real Tom and his family seem. He kills, therefore they are.  That sounds far grimmer or at least more relentlessly grim than this shrewd, agile, often bitingly funny film plays. Ornamented with ghoulish comedy (a "live bait" sign posted at a murder site) and superbly acted by all the principals, including, in a nice surprise, William Hurt, who delivers a beautiful showboat of a performance late in the film, "A History of Violence" finds Mr. Cronenberg at the top of his form. Few directors working today know more about the erotics of screen violence than this filmmaker, who can make your head spin and your pulse quicken with a single edit. Fewer directors still bother to acknowledge that the canard "it's only a movie" is not only an article of bad faith, but also a deceptively comforting one. Movies, Mr. Cronenberg understands, make meaning: they entertain, therefore we are.  "A History of Violence" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has several  intense and bloody fight sequences, some adult sex scenes and strong language.</text>
      <date>September 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>