<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> How is this for loving postcoital pillow talk? “For a moment you sounded like a 12-year-old cheerleader.”  That kind of snidely witty remark characterizes the way everybody speaks in Rosser Goodman’s sour little film, “Holding Trevor.” It suggests that the budding relationship between Trevor (Brent Gorski), who works for an answering service in Los Angeles, and Ephram (Eli Kranski), a hospital intern, faces some hurdles.  Mr. Gorski, who wrote the screenplay, resembles a much younger Steve Buscemi. His pretentious voice-over narration wanders off into nowhere. The digital camera scours the actors’ blank faces (including Mr. Gorski’s) in extreme close-up, as though searching for substance that is nowhere to be found.  At least “Holding Trevor” has a story to tell. No sooner has Trevor’s heroin-addicted boyfriend Darrell (Christopher Wyllie) returned from rehab than he is caught using again. Fed up, Trevor ends the relationship, with tragic consequences, and begins dating Ephram, who admitted Darrell to the hospital after his last overdose. During their first extended conversation, Ephram invites Trevor to play a game in which they gaze at the city lights and invent imaginary lives for people behind the windows.  Trevor shares an apartment with Andie (Melissa Searing), a morose alcoholic who passes out during a party and awakes to discover she had sex with a stranger she can’t remember. Together Trevor; his promiscuous best friend, Jake (Jay Brannan); and Andie get tested for H.I.V. One comes back positive.  This portrait of 20-something gay men and their straight friends is a joyless exploration of middle-class deadbeats (with the exception of Ephram) lost in a torpid funk of low self-regard. Because they’re not rich, there is no sleazy zing of “Less Than Zero”-worthy glamor.  Within their circle their rudeness to one another may seem vaguely hip, but it makes you want to avoid their company at all cost.</text>
      <date>July 4, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>