<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A POSTER for the period drama “Hollywoodland” says that “dying in Hollywood can make you a legend.” George Reeves would have been flattered. A two-bit talent who is the film’s nominal reason for being, Mr. Reeves is best remembered, if at all, for two things: playing Superman on TV, and a bullet in the head. In 1959 someone blew his brains out in a house tucked between Sunset Boulevard and Mulholland Drive. The death was ruled a suicide, but the movies love a tasty murder, which is why Ben Affleck has packed on the pounds, slipped on some tights and given this exasperating film far more than it gives in return.  “Hollywoodland” tells several stories, one of them reasonably well. Before he became a cautionary tale about making it in the movies, Mr. Reeves was a smoothie with brilliantine hair as slick as his pickup lines. In the early 1950’s he was hustling hard, hitting auditions while the sun was up and cruising the nightclub scene after dark. He was trying to build on his decent roles in forgettable films and negligible parts in memorable ones, including a bit as an eager young caller who worships at Scarlett O’Hara’s feet in “Gone With the Wind.” Even now, if you didn’t know Mr. Reeves from “The Adventures of Superman” you might not notice him next to Vivien Leigh and David O. Selznick’s expensive sets, which of course was the problem.  Mr. Reeves didn’t have the requisite acting skills that might have led to steady work, much less marquee billing: he was a would-be star in a town full of extras with superior luck, looks and talent. In the late 1930’s, when he appeared in “Gone With the Wind,” he was pretty, if not pretty enough to break ranks. As the years passed, and the pounds and disappointment mounted, the prettiness disappeared as did the opportunities.  By the early 1950’s what remained was a puffy face that was quick to smile but, at least on “Superman,” could seem impatient, almost irritable. As it happens, all those times Clark Kent took Jimmy Olsen to task, it might have been Mr. Reeves who was expressing his own discontent. That, at any rate, is how the world turns in “Hollywoodland.”  In 1951 Mr. Reeves met the older, far richer Toni Mannix (Diane Lane), a Hollywood wife made vulnerable, if not yet humble, by age. A former actress of no note, she was married to the MGM executive Edward J. Mannix, played by Bob Hoskins, perhaps accurately, as a thug in a front-office suit. Mr. and Mrs. Hollywood, with his-and-her paramours to go with the other servants, the couple was powerful enough to take their playmates out on a double date. Pets yukking it up with their masters at the dinner table is an ideal setup for the director Allen Coulter, who until now has only worked on a small canvas directing for television.  Mr. Coulter and the screenwriter Paul Bernbaum want to bend Mr. Reeves’s biography as an actor-cum-gigolo into a tragedy, and Mr. Affleck is more than up to the task. When the actor first eases up to Toni, sweet and softly talking, he makes you see what a woman like her might see in him besides a good time. Buzzing with life, he has yet to fall prey to self-pity, and Toni draws on his youth and his optimism as if from a deep well. Later, as defeat takes its grinding toll, Mr. Affleck lets weariness creep into his face, pulling his features down until it becomes difficult smile. Mr. Reeves’s career shrinks, his silhouette bloats; the pounds turn his body into dough, and then into lead.  George Reeves was a sad case, but not every sob story or even every suicide has the makings of a tragedy. Even the filmmakers don’t seem especially convinced on this count, since half of “Hollywoodland” involves a dead-end pseudo-noir about another hustler, a private eye named Louis Simo, whom Adrien Brody fails to shape into a character of interest despite much aggressive eyebrow raising. Hired to investigate the Reeves death, Simo subsequently enters on a journey that distractingly toggles between his life and that of the dead man, and involves feeling and healing, fathers and sons and an occasional knuckle sandwich. In time Simo learns about facing the life you have rather than the life you want, which may be grand advice in therapy but doesn’t make for involving drama.  Hollywood history is filled with stories as bleak as that of the man who was Superman, if only on TV,  object lessons about hungry hopefuls who went looking for fame and found nothing, or maybe just a little something.  Mr. Reeves might have been disappointed by life whether he became a doctor or a soda jerk at Schwab’s. To amp the pathos, though, the film implies that he was edited out of “From Here to Eternity” because audiences were distracted by Superman trading lines with the star Burt Lancaster. Yet Mr. Reeves is still in the picture, and he’s fine. As a gossipy off-duty soldier in a Hawaiian shirt, he gets the job done. And then he ambles off, leaving the rest of the film to those who could manage it better.  “Hollywoodland” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Salty language, partial nudity, gun violence.</text>
      <date>September 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>