<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The wits behind the controlled chaos that is “Hot Fuzz,” a parody of Hollywood-style action flicks, wield a somewhat heavier comic cudgel than they did in their last big-screen outing, the zombie caper “Shaun of the Dead.” This time, as they say in the blow-up business, it’s personal, or at least somewhat personalized, since the more obvious targets here include high-octane producer-auteurs like Jerry Bruckheimer and Joel Silver, who, with their fat budgets and armies of heavily armed bad boys, have helped define the modern action spectacular, reshaping the old kiss-kiss, bang-bang movie experience into the cinema of lock-and-load.  Simon Pegg, the snub-nosed, cricket-bat-swinging blond avenger of “Shaun of the Dead,” plays Nicholas Angel, a crack London police officer who’s bounced to a small town by his inferior superiors (Bill Nighy, Steve Coogan,  Martin Freeman, smirking and smiling) for being just too damn good at his job. Banished to the sticks, where a missing snow-colored swan initially proves the only investigative distraction, he finds himself desperate for action. He rousts some teenagers from the local pub, but outside of fielding smutty insults from the precinct’s layabout detectives (Paddy Considine and Rafe Spall, as matching and mustachioed as a Tom of Finland cartoon), there’s little to do but water his lily plant and nurse his cranberry juice nightcap.  There are few girls allowed inside the Bruckheimer and Silver clubhouses, and so it is here. Although the homosocial worlds of Messrs. Bruckheimer and Silver on occasion make room for a Venus in leather like Carrie-Anne Moss or, more routinely, a neonatal-size waif like Keira Knightley, these are testosterone-fueled domains, largely defined by bulging muscles and exploding guns, both symbolic and actual. It’s a world that Mr. Pegg and the film’s director, Edgar Wright, who together wrote the awfully funny screenplay, know intimately and recreate with admirable fealty, from the hard-crashing edits to the soft, tender looks exchanged by Angel and his slavishly attentive sidekick, Danny Butterman (Nick Frost). It’s a world in which boys will be boys at every available opportunity.  For the most part these are fine boys indeed, and in the wonderful, weird case of Timothy Dalton, an unctuous toff with a menacing twinkle in his eye, even better than that. (Look for the director Peter Jackson in an eye-blink cameo.) Mr. Pegg and Mr. Frost, who played best buddies in “Shaun of the Dead,” have an easy, believable rapport that, once it gets cooking, opens up a pocket of sweetness in a film that is otherwise played cool and for laughs. Mr. Pegg’s performance here, befitting his uptight, upright character, is somewhat one-note, if otherwise likable, with little of the Everyman depths that were finally tapped in “Shaun.” The emotional intimacy of Mr. Pegg and Mr. Frost’s onscreen relationship suggests that there’s more to these performers than parody.  A wee bit of plot tucked amid a fusillade of film-geek jokes and charming nonsense, bang-bang, hee-hee, “Hot Fuzz” trots out the predictable verbal and visual allusions to modern Hollywood action movies great and forgettable, hitting the highs (“Point Break”) right along with the lows (“Bad Boys II”). The meta-movie silliness works well enough for the crisp setup. But since Mr. Wright and Mr. Pegg are essentially parodying self-parodies (see “Con Air” ad infinitum), they have also smartly kinked up their conceit by setting most of the film in a sleepy village that might as well be called Ye Old English Towne, thereby wedding one of the most irritating British exports (see “Calendar Girls” ad nauseam) to one of the most absurd American ones.  Think of it as “The Full Monty” blown to smithereens.  “Hot Fuzz” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Big bangs, hard oaths.</text>
      <date>April 20, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>