<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Hot Rod” might be called the poor man’s “Eagle vs. Shark” if “Eagle vs. Shark” were not already the poor man’s “Napoleon Dynamite.” It certainly lacks the conceptual purity and aesthetic integrity of the “Jackass” movies. In any case poor certainly describes the quality of the filmmaking. Directed by Akiva Schaffer from an improvisation-enhanced script by Pam Brady, “Hot Rod” is unapologetically, almost proudly crummy looking, as though paying tribute with its sloppy framing and clumsy editing to the goofy, half-baked quality of its hero’s stunts.  “Hot Rod” is primarily a vehicle meant to propel Andy Samberg from “Saturday Night Live” and YouTube celebrity into the stratosphere of comic-movie stardom. As such it is a bit like the rickety moped that Mr. Samberg’s character, Rod Kimble, uses for his not-quite-death-defying stunts. In one of these he tries to leap a municipal swimming pool and lands in the water.  Similarly “Hot Rod” sets itself modest, pointless goals and then falls short of them. Mr. Samberg is as much a movie star as Rod is a daredevil stunt man, and “Hot Rod” is less of a movie than Mr. Samberg’s “SNL” digital shorts, which are a lot of fun on the laptop.  Mr. Samberg’s wide smile and eager manner are engaging, but he labors under the misapprehension that he is automatically, innately funny. There is a difference between finding humor in laziness and self-delusion and lazily deluding yourself that anything you do will bring big laughs. The laughs to be found in “Hot Rod” are small and easy. Mr. Samberg falls down, or collides with a blunt object (a washing machine suspended from a tree by a rope, for instance), or utters lame, self-conscious catchphrases.  Rod is the latest version of what is fast becoming a cliché: the guy who thinks he’s cool but is actually, objectively a loser. You are meant to laugh knowingly at the discrepancy between his self-image and the reality he cluelessly inhabits, and then, to excuse the cruelty latent in this laughter, to sympathize with the sincerity and nobility of his dreams and root for their fulfillment. Rod, who lives with his mother (Sissy Spacek, if you can believe it) and stepfather, Frank (Ian McShane), dreams of living up to the legend of his deceased father and also of winning Frank’s respect.  Styling himself after Evel Knievel — since no movie of this kind can survive without a wink at the endlessly parodied pop culture of the 1970s — Rod is assisted by a crew of nerds and misfits, including his half-brother Kevin (played Mr. Samberg’s longtime pal and sometime creative partner Jorma Taccone). Rod also has a crush on his next-door neighbor, Denise (Isla Fisher), who has a jerky rich boyfriend (Will Arnett) and an endlessly sweet disposition. Ms. Fisher, an actress who showed herself to be a nimble comic performer in “Wedding Crashers,” is not allowed to be funny in this infantile comic universe. Funny is apparently a guy thing.  “Hot Rod” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some drug and sexual references.</text>
      <date>August 3, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>