<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The turbulent reality of young love is something most of us would probably prefer not to remember too clearly. It’s easier to graze vicariously on movie fantasies of shapely young bodies swooning in rapturous lip-locks than to dwell on uncomfortable memories of needy, unformed adults in erotic collision.  Ethan Hawke’s earnest, talky film “The Hottest State,” which he adapted from his own semi-autobiographical 1997 novel, doggedly peels away the gloss to dive into the emotional swamp where two young people get lost in each other. As it follows the coupling and uncoupling of William Harding (Mark Webber), an aspiring young actor from Texas, and Sara Garcia (the Colombian actress Catalina Sandino Moreno), a Latina pop singer from Connecticut who lives in downtown Manhattan, you feel their growing pains much more acutely than their fleeting happiness.  Nearly two hours long, with a tenuous narrative continuity, “The Hottest State,” whose title refers both to passion and to Texas, is far more coherent than Mr. Hawke’s 2001 directorial debut, “Chelsea Walls.” At around the halfway point, however, its characters’ haranguing voices begin to grate on you. People in their early 20s, even pretty people, lose their appeal when they dwell this obsessively on their own inchoate turmoil.  Sara’s frequent insistence that she is not as interesting as William imagines is sadly accurate. A singer with a strong physical resemblance to Norah Jones (Ms. Jones is heard on the soundtrack, composed by Jesse Harris, who has written hits for her), Sara might be described as a drip. Although attractive enough, she exhibits little of the dignity and determination of Ms. Moreno’s title character in “Maria Full of Grace,” and the actress’s lingering discomfort with the English language doesn’t help matters. (In the novel her character was an American from Seattle.) The issue bedeviling Sara is whether to surrender herself to a consuming relationship or resist; she makes the sensible decision to back off.  If William is an even bigger handful than the ambivalent Sara, Mr. Webber’s emotionally risky, wide-open performance makes this infinitely self-dramatizing youth considerably more charming. Not long after he and Sara meet, they spend six days in Mexico, where he is about to appear in a film of Tennessee Williams’s “Camino Real.” Following this de facto honeymoon, during which they briefly contemplate marriage, Sara returns to New York. When he comes back after finishing the movie, he discovers that in his absence she has decided she doesn’t want a boyfriend.  Unwilling to accept her withdrawal, William turns into a stalker who delivers soliloquies from “Romeo and Juliet” under her apartment window and compulsively harasses her on the telephone. For any rejected lover who has succumbed to such desperation, these scenes are excruciatingly real, and Mr. Hawke deserves credit for exploring a place visited by many more men than would care to admit it.  “The Hottest State” also feels dated. William and Sara are a lot more like ’60s bohemians playing grown-up in downtown Manhattan than the sleek serial daters on MTV game shows pursuing hot-  and cold-blooded hookups. One of the most original things about the film is its recognition that there are many different ages of young love. What seems like a half a lifetime can separate being 21 from being 27.  The movie, viewed entirely through William’s eyes, awkwardly throws in some family psychology. His distant, macho father from Fort Worth is a stoic noncommunicator who might have dropped out of a Sam Shepard drama and is played by Mr. Hawke as though he were impersonating Mr. Shepard. William’s embittered mother, Jesse (Laura Linney), hammers him with the kind of hardheaded advice no fervent romantic wants to hear. People aren’t going to love you back and you’re going to die anyway, so get over yourself, she tells him.  When you’re 21 and madly in love, words like that fall on deaf ears.  “The Hottest State” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has intense sexual situations and strong language. </text>
      <date>August 24, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>