<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Save for the scandalized sound bites that surrounded its initial unveiling at last year’s Sundance Film Festival, “Hounddog” might have fizzled quietly on the fringes of movieland leaving few traces beyond  Dakota Fanning’s astonishing performance.  Instead, this overripe tale of innocence lost has become one of notoriety found. Set in rural Alabama in the 1950s, the movie clings protectively to Lewellen (Ms. Fanning), a gangly preteenager  whose only family is an abusive Daddy (David Morse) and a Bible-spouting Grammie (Piper Laurie). To ease her loneliness Lewellen dreams of singing with Elvis. She warbles “Hound Dog” to all and sundry  — quite well, as it happens — and wriggles her skinny body in imitation of her idol.  Daddy, of course, loves it, but despite the script’s intimations of incest and Lewellen’s guilelessly provocative squirming, “Hounddog” never comes close to being salacious. The much-maligned deflowering, when it finally occurs, is probably the film’s most accomplished scene, composed of thoughtful cutaways and relying for resonance on a single, lingering shot of the girl’s traumatized expression.  The only exploitation here is that of skilled actors lending their gifts to a less than worthy project. Though the lovely Robin Wright Penn, playing Daddy’s fragile girlfriend (and perhaps sister), juggles a black eye and a preposterous monologue with aplomb, Mr. Morse has little to do except hang around looking gormless. Ms. Laurie, for her part, simply recycles the God-fearing, liquor-loving harridan she perfected in “Carrie,” ranting against “devil music” and Lewellen’s twitching hips.  Most abused of all is Afemo Omilami as a gentle black neighbor who appears, genielike, whenever a white character requires spiritual guidance or a jolt of folksy wisdom. “You got to fill all those empty, hollow places,” he advises Lewellen, patiently milking the venom from rattlers and humans alike. The empty places in the script (by Deborah Kampmeier, who also directs), however, remain stubbornly vacant: cicadas chirp, chickens squawk and rutting men grunt, but nothing can salvage a narrative that’s all symbol and no substance, every rain shower and batch of homemade jelly loaded with mythic significance.  As snakes dangle in the trees, slither in the river and nestle in Lewellen’s crotch, the audience is left to speculate on whether her attacker will be good-for-nothing Daddy, his brain now stir-fried by God’s lightning bolt, or the aw-shucks milkman, leering beneath a devilish dose of acne. Yet compared with, say, the kicky, visceral pulp of Craig Brewer’s “Black Snake Moan” — an aria of Southern excess — “Hounddog” is never more than a sluggish dawdle from shack to swimmin’ hole and back again.  Like many a Deep South saga before it, the movie believes in the curative role of the blues, the symbolic role of reptiles and the strictly supportive role of African-Americans. If anyone were going to be scandalized, it shouldn’t have been the Catholic League and child protection advocates.   It should have been the Humane Society and the N.A.A.C.P.  “Hounddog” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has booze, buttocks, bruises and bad words.</text>
      <date>September 19, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>