<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ouse of Wax," the latest high-end frightener to be released by Warner Brothers under the Dark Castle label, begins with a creepy flashback to 1974. The date is fitting, because even though this movie is a loose remake - a "reimagining," in the words of its publicity material - of a 1953 horror classic starring Vincent Price, its more immediate sources of inspiration are the cheap, grisly and highly effective scare pictures of the 70's, a decade that saw the birth of the "Halloween" and "Texas Chainsaw Massacre" franchises. As in those movies, this updated "House of Wax" features a group of randy, quarreling young people who wander off the main road only to be dispatched one by one by a ruthless maniac. The set design is fairly elaborate by the standards of the genre, and the victims don't die in precisely the order you might expect, but everything else goes pretty much according to formula, including a last-minute plot twist that opens the creaky door to a sequel. In another slight departure from convention, there are apparently two maniacs (twin brothers), but even so it takes them nearly an hour of screen time to claim their first victim, which may make you wonder if the filmmakers mislaid their horror-movie instruction manual. Not to worry. After a few too many teasing false scares, and some obligatory ogling of Paris Hilton and Elisha Cuthbert, the screenwriters (Chad Hayes and Carey W. Hayes), the director (Jaume Collet-Serra) and the maniacs (both played by Brian Van Holt) settle down to their sadistic business. There is some pretty bloody stuff - decapitation, a severed finger, lips stuck together with high-powered glue, a snipped Achilles tendon - all of which is a prelude to an exquisitely icky method of murder. The victims, sometimes before they are dead, are covered in hot wax and then carefully made over into uncanny, motionless reproductions of themselves. The perpetrators of this horror - whose motives are hinted at in that opening flashback, and then spelled out at some length later on - deserve credit for ghoulish creativity, as does Jason Baird, who created the film's wax figures, though mainly out of silicone and fiberglass. The statues populate the town of Ambrose, a Louisiana hamlet that seems lost in time. There is an Art Deco movie house playing "Whatever Happened to Baby Jane?," a gas station where regular sells for $1.19 a gallon, and a church where a funeral is always in progress. Somehow, even though none of the telephones work, and a Cadillac's G.P.S.  navigation can't locate the town, cellphone reception is crystal clear. The six hapless young folk stumble into Ambrose on their way to a football game, and in the midst of their own petty melodramas. Ms. Hilton is Paige, who is keeping a secret from her boyfriend, Blake (Robert Ri'chard). Ms. Cuthbert is Carly, the subject of a three-way rivalry among her dreamboat boyfriend, Wade (Jared Padalecki); a dispensable doofus in a baseball cap named Dalton (Jon Abrahams); and her twin brother, Nick (Chad Michael Murray), who has just finished a spell in jail for auto theft. Carly and Nick's contrasting temperaments - he sardonically refers to himself as "the evil twin" - mirror the sibling dynamic of the killers, providing "House of Wax" with at least the hint of a psychological subtext. Mostly, though, it's the usual scary stuff - the sudden noises on the soundtrack, the shock cuts and camera tricks that never seem to grow old. You know exactly when you're going to be jolted, but you jump anyway and view the spurts of phony blood through the spaces between your fingers. What humor there is comes mainly at Ms. Hilton's expense; the movie sends up her two most famous roles so far, on the fish-out-of-water reality show "The Simple Life" and in that notorious Internet sex tape. A certain portion of the audience will no doubt buy tickets hoping to see her meet a gruesome end, which is a little mean spirited, given that she seems, in this movie at least, to be a pretty good sport, if not exactly a good actress. It would be a little too scary if she were. "House of Wax" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has blood, gore, teasing sexual references and strong language.</text>
      <date>May 6, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>