<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>A good scolding and a toke on a joint: that’s all it takes to turn the curmudgeonly old folks in “How About You” into goofy pussycats frolicking on the lawn of their comfy retirement home. Would that it were so easy to transform those angry, embittered elders  into a happy family. But as Vanessa Redgrave, Joss Ackland, Brenda Fricker and Imelda Staunton chew up the scenery, you may be half-convinced that such miracles can occur. When portrayed by fine actors, Ebenezer Scrooge can metamorphose into Bob Cratchit and the Wicked Witch of the West into Glinda  the Good Witch. The movie, set in Ireland at Christmastime, takes its title from the 1941 Burton Lane-Ralph Freed standard that begins, “I like New York in June.”  Heard over the opening credits in a mediocre, bowdlerized version by Bobby Darin and repeated incessantly,  it’s the favorite ditty of Georgia Platts (Ms. Redgrave), a former showgirl who wears a turban and gives imperious directions on how to fix the martinis to which she is avidly addicted. The song, which eventually becomes a jolly singalong in an Irish pub, also helps thaw the frozen souls of Donald Vanston (Mr. Ackland), a widower and retired judge who demands his breakfast be served at 5:30, two and a half hours ahead of schedule; and Heather and Hazel Nightingale (Ms. Fricker and Ms. Staunton), bickering spinster sisters who are continually at each other’s throats as they recycle old family grievances. These  four are the only residents of Woodlands,  a residential home, who have not vacated the premises for the Christmas holidays.  While Kate (Orla Brady), the strict owner, is away, it is up to her younger sister Ellie (Hayley Atwell), a wild Irish rose, to keep order.  The four are holy terrors whose bad behavior has driven away so many lodgers that Woodlands’ very existence is threatened. The achievement of peace and harmony depends on the success of a proposed Christmas dinner that becomes a modest British answer to “Babette’s Feast.” “How About You,” directed by Anthony Byrne from Jean Pasley’s screen adaptation of a short story by Maeve Binchy, belongs to the sentimental genre of post-Terence Rattigan white-glove British dramas like “Mrs. Palfrey at the Claremont” and “Ladies in Lavender.” If those two predecessors have a little more substance than “How About You,” all three appeal to the delicate  palates  of an audience that craves the movie equivalent of tea and biscuits:  stiff upper lips conceal hearts of gold, and all psychological conflicts are resolved with tearful confessions of vulnerability. To that audience, which has little stomach for barbarity, this genre is a godsend, because it offers the consolations of civilized conversation in complete sentences and cultural name-dropping. The retired judge, a recovering alcoholic whose greatest regret is not having sobered up while he was married, plays Satie on the piano and hums a theme from “Die Fledermaus.” There is a half-baked subplot involving Ellie’s unseen boyfriend that appears to have been mostly left on the cutting-room floor. When a resident regales Ellie with tales of her happy days smoking hashish in Morocco, Ellie immediately bakes some hash-laced cookies, but Kate finds them and throws them away. When that Bobby Darin recording is first heard on the soundtrack, with its references to Kennedy and “a Bernstein tune,” you are misled into thinking the movie is a period piece set in the 1960s. But  if there is just enough modern technology to set the movie’s time as now, on a deeper level, the era it depicts is really then.</text>
      <date>November 14, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>