<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> THE worms go in, the worms go out, but mostly what they do in the children’s film “How to Eat Fried Worms” is end up battered, splattered, pureed, deep fried and nuked (in a microwave).  The story, based on the popular book by Thomas Rockwell, first published in 1973, involves the new kid on the block who, in a spasm of nutty, if age- and gender-appropriate braggadocio, agrees to a wormy dare under pressure from the school bully. Nicely directed, the film version proves refreshingly free of the customary blights that affect most modern children’s movies, notably adult condescension. But, man, is it mean.  It could hardly be otherwise. As the title says, “How to Eat Fried Worms” is, at least in part, about how to eat fried worms.  Recently transplanted to a new town, 11-year-old Billy (Luke Benward) has barely climbed off his bicycle when he becomes a target of scorn and abuse. Led by a pint-size terror named Joe Guire (Adam Hicks), the boys in Billy’s fifth-grade class immediately give him the freeze and then stuff a handful of worms in his lunch thermos.  Initially appalled, Billy retaliates with some big talk and a fearsome gesture that wins him the approval of some of the other school outcasts: he tosses one of the worms in Joe’s face, turning his carrot-topped tormentor’s freckles a darker shade of red.  Joe exacts his revenge of course, which is how Billy, strong of heart but weak of stomach, ends up eating and sometimes slurping one creepy crawler after another over the course of one Saturday afternoon.  For Billy — whose predictably useless if warmly loving parents (played by Tom Cavanagh and Kimberly Williams-Paisley) can offer him no help, largely because he doesn’t tell them what’s going on — the crucible of the worms has the potential glory, certain agony and epic dimension of a knight’s quest. If he succeeds in completing his gastronomic journey, he earns his freedom and more; if he fails, it will be an exceedingly long school year. For as the worms and his stomach turn, so does his life.  If “How to Eat Fried Worms” sounds like Iron John for peewees, that’s more or less how it plays out, though with more intentional laughs than provided by Robert Bly. The questing young males in the film don’t bang drums to satisfy their mythopoetic needs; they just throw another worm on the barbie.  As important to their strange rite of passage and to the film’s plangent realism, the boys also join forces whenever a grown-up (including the great Andrea Martin as their teacher) comes snooping. The secret worlds that children make for themselves are delightfully realized in a scene in which Billy’s father asks the boys, enemies and friends alike, what they are up to and receives a collective “having fun” in response.  Directed by Bob Dolman, who also wrote the fine adaptation, “How to Eat Fried Worms” is an easygoing entertainment in which a sensible message about growing up also rationalizes the abuse of power. However lightly played, this is, after all, a film in which children learn to stand up for themselves, and for one another, by killing animals.  Yeah, yeah, we’re talking worms, sure. But the lesson remains the same, whether it’s an invertebrate squirming on the grill or a puppy. On the page Mr. Rockwell’s humor produces hoots. (“Tomorrow I’ll roll the crawler in cornmeal and fry it. Like a trout.”) But transposed to the big screen, yuck! No worms may have been harmed in the making of this film, but it’s unlikely the under-age audience will care.  “How to Eat Fried Worms” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). There is some talk about poop and lots of cooked worms.</text>
      <date>August 25, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>