<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> How lovely the American high school experience might be if it offered even a smidgen of the euphoria that spirals “High School Musical 3: Senior Year,” into a candy-colored never-never land that Peter Pan might envy.  In making the leap from  Disney Channel to the big screen, the third chapter of the phenomenally popular franchise crystallizes a moment in movie-musical history that is probably as evanescent as it is triumphant. If you recall all that hyperbolic talk in the ’80s about music videos spurring a full-scale revival of the movie musical  —  a revival that fizzled after “Footloose” and “Flashdance”  —  here it is (without  frantic MTV-style  editing). Or was. “High School Musical 4” has already been announced. But whether the franchise can continue after the major characters graduate is open to question. Quirky new characters are introduced. But are they stars?  Much of the success of the “High School Musicals” owes to the shrewd mixing and matching of proven formulas, augmented  by the charisma of Zac Efron and Vanessa Hudgens as  the dewy-eyed puppy lovers Troy Bolton and Gabriella Montez. Mr. Efron’s athletic grace is Astaire-like in its casual authority. Ms. Hudgens’s blissful smiles melt the screen.  The taken-for-granted ethnic diversity of the students at East High in Albuquerque,  the franchise’s unlikely setting, comes from “Fame.” So does the craving for show business glory expressed in “I Want It All,” belted by the movie’s resident  not-so-nasty mean girl,  Sharpay (Ashley Tisdale),   a teenager  so ambitious she would steal the scene off your back.  Most of the 10  songs in “High School Musical 3” belong to a boy-band tradition that runs from New Kids on the Block through the Backstreet Boys to the Jonas Brothers. The best of the score’s several songwriters are the team of Matthew Gerrard and Robbie Nevil, whose auto junkyard anthem, “The Boys Are Back,” echoes Thin Lizzy’s 1976 hit “The Boys Are Back in Town” filtered through Michael Jackson’s “Beat It,” and is frenziedly performed by a male chorus executing post-break-dance acrobatics on the hoods of rusted cars. The genre, which might be described as sugarcoated bubblegum hip-hop, may be disposable, but it is extremely catchy and rhythmically elastic.  The all-purpose choreography by  the director Kenny Ortega and his collaborators mixes up Rockettes-like kick lines, angular writhing in the style   of “Cats,” break dancing and accelerated ballroom moves. (Mr. Efron does an impeccably suave waltz.) In one number, Mr. Ortega even quotes his own choreography from Madonna’s “Material Girl” video. My favorite dance number is the triumphal title song, performed on a playing field where the lines of dancers ripple like a human roller coaster.  All very sweet, you say. But what does it all mean?  To which I would reply:  Does it have to mean anything beyond the pleasure of entering a dream of high school harmony?  So what if these wholesome singing-and-dancing characters include no teenagers you or I will ever meet? If you dropped the term “friends with benefits” to any of these absurdly idealized youth who appear to have descended from the same planet that produced “The Brady Bunch,” you may rest assured they wouldn’t know what you were talking about. The only things on their minds besides basketball and musical comedy are choosing a prom date and a college to attend. There are wistful moments, but no sulky ones. The one lingering kiss is delicate.  The movie’s cleverest notion is its portrayal of sports and musical comedy as interchangeable. In the sensational opening number, “Now or Never,” East High’s Wildcats trounce their rivals to hip-hop beats and semi-rapped chants shouted by the cheerleaders and players alike.  Whether to choose sports or musical comedy,  that is the burning question facing Troy, who has been planning to accompany his best friend,   Chad Danforth (Corbin Bleu),  to “U. of A.,” as it is  called, and play basketball. But when the school’s fluty-voiced drama teacher, Ms. Darbus (Alyson Reed), announces to Troy’s shock that he is one of four students being considered for a scholarship to Juilliard, he is  thrown into a quandary. As he ponders his future, the movie slips in an argument for musical theater as a more-than-O.K. activity for all-American guys; after all, it is another sport.  The other small conflicts in Peter Barsocchini’s story (the weakest of his three “High School Musical” plots) are hardly worth mentioning. But in a movie determined to keep reality at a safe distance, would you want it any other way? As its wholesome perpetual-motion machines leap, tumble and whipsaw  through the halls and playgrounds of East High, you want to leave the world behind and be one of them now and forever.</text>
      <date>October 24, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>