<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “The Hunting Party,” a misfired, misguided would-be satire set in postwar Bosnia, Richard Gere plays one of those Fourth Estate burnouts who periodically lurch into the movies. There’s the regulation flask, a week’s worth of whiskers and the pouched eyes that have seen a world of sorrows, and even more closing times. Marinating in booze and his own sour juices, he is meant to look worn out and nearly used up, punch-drunk on man’s inhumanity to man (and to woman and child and dog). He probably had a Humphrey Bogart poster on his dorm-room wall and a Hunter S. Thompson paperback in his back pocket.  Bogie didn’t have to work at tired; those eyes were weary in utero. For all his beard growth and effort, the appealing Mr. Gere looks like a manicured star whose expensive flesh is regularly anointed in oil and receives plenty of B12 and exercise. He doesn’t look as if he keeps company with misery, though that’s precisely what his character, Simon Hunt, does. A onetime star television reporter who suffered an on-camera meltdown while reporting from Bosnia in the mid-1990s, Simon now roams the globe’s really big horror shows and tries to sell the bad news freelance. He’s a stumblebum in the big geopolitical ring, though mostly he’s just a reassuring cliché, the good guy gone only superficially south.  “The Hunting Party” was written and directed by Richard Shepard (“The Matador”), and owes its gonzo setup to a 2000 Esquire article by Scott Anderson. In brief, Mr. Anderson and four other journalist pals, all of whom had covered the Bosnian war, popped into Sarajevo for a reunion on their way to some R &amp; R on the Adriatic coast. One improbability led to another, and before long the five (including Sebastian Junger) were mistaken for a C.I.A. hit squad on the hunt for the fugitive Bosnian Serb leader Radovan Karadzic. Toward the end of their escapade an American military officer turned to them and declared that it “would make a helluva movie,” which apparently set light bulbs to glowing above some producer’s head.  The article isn’t really funny; it’s dark, glib and knowing and, weighing in at a little over 6,300 words, a fast read. There’s no sign of anyone who remotely sounds or behaves like Simon Hunt, no doubt because a working journalist who gets the job done like Mr. Junger isn’t as sexy sounding as a wreck of a reporter who has been ennobled both by personal tragedy (cue the gauzy flashback) and by his contempt for mainstream journalism.  Much like those renegade cops who always work outside the very system that produced them (a system that, natch, finally does bow to the righteousness of the renegade), the only good movie journalist is one who tells off the guys wearing ties cosseted safely back in the newsroom.  Of course Simon really does want back in the good graces of the suits (the pay’s better), which explains why he sweet-talks his former cameraman, Duck (the great Terrence Howard, wasted), into a Balkan misadventure. Together with a network executive’s son (Jesse Eisenberg, a graduate of the Woody Allen institute of hand wringing), the three go looking for a Serbian villain (Ljubomir Kerekes), a sneering smoothie with the carefully coiffed hair of a French intellectual.  Mr. Shepard tilts the camera, freezes the action and unleashes a veritable carnival sideshow — potato ladies, a mustachioed functionary, oily thugs, even a midget towing a giant — which adds noise, certainly. The tone lurches from maudlin to arch to frantic. Every so often a corpse pops up on screen as a reminder of just how unfunny this whole thing is.  “The Hunting Party” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Some bloody violence and a whole lot of cussing.</text>
      <date>September 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>