<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is a lot of heart in "Hustle &amp; Flow," Craig Brewer's first feature film, and a lot of nonsense as well. Perhaps this is only fitting, since the movie's hero, a Memphis pimp named DJay (Terrence Howard) who dreams of becoming a rap star, is both cunning and earnest, a scam artist who claims to want nothing more than to speak his mind and lay bare his soul.  This tension is summed up in the movie's title, which refers to the  language that defines DJay's conflicting professional ambitions. The pimp's mode is the hustle, a smooth, manipulative patter designed to separate johns from their money and keep hookers in line. But the rapper lives and dies by the integrity of his flow, which is praiseworthy insofar as it is "live" and "real."  And the movie, which scored an audience award and a big-money distribution deal at Sundance, is a volatile mixture of slickness and sincerity, hard-edged naturalism and sheer show-business hokum. It's certainly live, with fine performances and a strong soundtrack, including music from the Memphis rappers Al Kapone and Three 6 Mafia, but never quite real. A rough, sticky sense of place - you can almost smell the sweat of Memphis coming off the screen - dresses up a story so conventional that it sometimes verges on self-parody. Mr. Brewer's attempt to fuse hip-hop street credibility, art-house cachet and follow-your-dream, triumph-of-the-underdog Hollywood uplift is canny but clumsy.  The film, which he wrote and directed, feels both naïve and cynical, which may turn out to be the key to its success. It's hard to hate a movie that falls so completely for its own hustle. Perhaps more than it intends to, "Hustle &amp; Flow" illustrates the contradictions and distortions that define contemporary popular culture. It depicts - and inhabits - a world in which the only sure determinants of value are money and fame, but that still holds onto sentimental notions of authenticity and regionalism.  The film's embodiment of this paradox is not only DJay, but also Skinny Black (played by the real-life rapper Ludacris, a k a Chris Bridges), who has risen from peddling homemade tapes at the local drive-in to music-video ubiquity and platinum-selling albums. (Ludacris is not the only musical figure to show up in the movie. Isaac Hayes's cameo as a bar owner pays tribute to his place both in Memphis musical history and in the tradition of blaxploitation cinema from which Mr. Brewer takes some stylistic cues.)  DJay, hearing that Skinny is coming back home for the Fourth of July and convincing himself that they knew each other in the old days, decides that his one shot at fame lies in getting a demo tape of his own material into Skinny's hands. He enlists the help of a high school friend, a hard-working family man named Key (Anthony Anderson) who once dreamed of being a producer with his own record label. Key recruits Shelby (DJ Qualls), a white musician, to lay down the beats, and the three of them hole up in a makeshift backroom studio. Their interactions give the movie a rough, boyish humor that undercuts some of the melodrama, and the music they come up with sounds pretty good. In the end, though, it all depends on Skinny. Surely he will remember where he came from, and give a fellow striver the leg up he needs. Or, as DJay more pragmatically puts it, "If I can pimp $20 ho's out the back of my Chevy, I can pimp Skinny."  But as every old-school hip-hop fan knows, pimping ain't easy. It sure is fascinating, though, to rappers and to filmmakers, both black (like the Hughes brothers, who made the wide-eyed documentary "American Pimp") and white (like Mr. Brewer). Not that DJay's life is especially glamorous. He conducts business out of an old Caprice Classic and lives in a run-down, un-air-conditioned house with three prostitutes: Shug (Taraji P. Henson), who is pregnant and weepy; Lexus (Paula Jai Parker), a belligerent stripper; and Nola (Taryn Manning), a skinny young white woman to whom DJay confides his hopes and fears as they wait in the front seat of the Chevy for clients.  The complexity - one might less charitably say the incoherence - of DJay's character requires a lot from an actor, and Mr. Brewer's good fortune in casting Mr. Howard can hardly be overstated. The actor's heavy eyes and downturned mouth convey weariness and worry, but he tries not to presume too heavily on the audience's sympathy. DJay, who sheds a tear when he hears a hymn in church, is also capable of cruelty and selfishness, and the braggadocio of his raps is more often than not tinged with self-pity. "It's hard out here for a pimp," goes the chorus to one of his songs (sung by the honey-voiced Shug), updating a point first made by Big Daddy Kane and noting that one of the problems facing a man in this business is "a lot of bitches jumping ship."  But hold on a minute. What really happens is that DJay throws one of his "bitches" out on the street, along with her toddler, when she dares to question his management skills. A pimp might be forgiven for failing to see his own misogyny - pimping is not a profession usually associated with feminism - but the movie can't just slide off the hook along with its hero. Indeed, the outlaw charisma - the lower-depths soulfulness - that Mr. Brewer lovingly bestows on DJay arises precisely from his ability to keep women in their place. Lexus, after all, is an uncouth loudmouth who won't give the man a moment's peace. Shug, on the other hand, is a picture of weepy, simple-minded maternity. Nola, who hates the life she is living, is nonetheless loyal and smart enough to become the junior partner (or "principal investor") in DJay's rap enterprise. She also has the job of turning off the fan when DJay and his real partners are recording.  Key's wife, Yevette (Elise Neal), meanwhile, who is made to look like a shrew when she talks too much at the dinner table, overcomes her churchly distaste for pimps and prostitutes and shows up at the studio with a plate of sandwiches. By the end, everyone is singing along with a hook that goes "Whoop that trick." The original lyrics, rejected by Key in the interests of radio airplay, were "Beat that bitch."  Not that the movie exactly endorses such behavior; it just can't establish enough distance from its hero. "Everybody gotta have a dream" is the movie's hopeful tag line, which DJay's sideman Shelby glosses as "every man has the right to contribute his own verse." His gender-specific version is truer to the spirit of "Hustle &amp; Flow," where women, if they behave themselves, are allowed to sing backup. This disdain for women is not incidental to the film; it is integral to the fantasy Mr. Brewer is selling, which is that pimping is not as hard as it looks.  "Hustle &amp; Flow" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has brief nudity, sexual situations, obscenity, drug use and violence.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>