<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The joint doesn’t jump in the musical “Idlewild”; it just twitches and stumbles. As much a missed opportunity as a terrible tease, the film stars André Benjamin and Antwan A. Patton, better known as André 3000 and Big Boi of the hip-hop group OutKast, playing lifelong friends living and sometimes singing in Depression-era Georgia.  Their characters, Percival (Mr. Benjamin) and Rooster (Mr. Patton), have reached adulthood by going down radically different roads, an approach that will be familiar to fans of OutKast, well accustomed to its creative dissonance.  A great or even good version of “Idlewild” sounds heavenly. The shy and retiring and very single Percival works for his father, a gruff, unsmiling mortician played by a persuasively vinegary Ben Vereen. Rooster, meanwhile, married with a half-dozen children, earns his comfortable keep as a singer down at the local juke joint, called Church. Rooster is all crow and plenty of show, and the first time he takes the stage in “Idlewild,” he enters wearing a fur coat that looks like a skinned yeti and surrounded by a chorus of beauties in bubble-gum pink ostrich feathers. Like most of the songs in the film, what he sings isn’t especially memorable, but he delivers this disappointing news with style.  The rest of the news is equally bad, alas. The writer and director, Bryan Barber, a music-video auteur with loads of credits, seems to have riffled through the Warner Brothers film catalog to compile enough chestnuts to take him and his crew through several Christmases. Without any ironic inflection, he recycles ideas and tropes that were stale when Edward G. Robinson was chewing cigars and scenery in the 1931 film “Little Caesar.” When a wife in  “Idlewild” pleads with her wayward husband by imploring him to remember the way it “used to be,” his only response is to call her baby and ask for her trust. And when someone gives the same man a Bible, you know that good book will save him, body and soul.  There are more clichés, including a beautiful singer, Angel (Paula Patton), who strolls into  Church one day and tries to steal the show. Ms. Patton is a lovely woman with a serviceable voice, but when the fabulous Macy Gray is in the house, as a loud canary named Taffy, Angel can’t help but seem beside the point. (It’s disconcerting that Ms. Patton, by far the most glamorized female lead, also has the palest skin.) Like clockwork, Angel hooks up with Percival, who tends to otherwise mope about idly tickling piano keys. A Jelly Roll Hamlet in search of a reason for being or maybe just for leaving the small town of Idlewild, Percival has talent and apparent depth, which Mr. Benjamin conveys principally by looking downcast.  Neither star is well served by his  director, but Mr. Benjamin is  particularly let down because he has, in the past, dazzled whenever a camera has been pointed at him. Given both his interest in film acting and the limited role historically assigned to black entertainers, you can understand why he doesn’t want to smile for his first big film role. But there’s a difference between being a serious actor and being a wet blanket, and Mr. Benjamin and his director have neither the experience nor the instincts to make sure that Percival has sufficient emotional shading. If Mr. Patton fares better it’s largely because Rooster, with his lust for life and outsize personality, has been drawn with broad strokes that make sense for the real-life singer and his fictional self.  In an interview this summer, Mr. Barber expressed a long-held desire to direct what he called a “1930’s musical”; he might have done well to actually watch a couple before he started shooting. Busby Berkeley, the brilliant choreographer of 30’s musicals like “42nd Street,” could have taught Mr. Barber something about moving bodies and cameras through space. A close study of one of Mr. Barber’s professed touchstones, Vincente Minnelli’s 1943 all-black musical “Cabin in the Sky,” would have been similarly instructive. Mr. Barber loads his visually incoherent film with poor camera choices that make it difficult to ground yourself in a scene and that, with the grievous overediting, make it hard to appreciate the actual talent on screen.  On the rare occasions when the camera sits still long enough for you to get a sense of space and place, the editing invariably reduces the image to confetti-size bits. That’s a shame because the choreographer, production designer and costume designer have done nice work, even if the women’s nails tend to look more Beverly Hills contemporary than Southern period. Still, the real trouble isn’t  the rapidity of the edits; it’s that the editing choices generally lack rhyme and narrative reason. This kind of overediting can murder a mood and undercut a performance, turning what should have been an intimate love scene with Percival and Angel, for instance, into a jumble of shots, some only as long as one or two seconds.  The narrative compression that works so well for Mr. Barber in his music videos for OutKast, particularly in pastiches like “Hey Ya!” and “Roses,” damages “Idlewild” beyond repair. Instead of letting a scene play out to the natural ebb and flow of conversation, Mr. Barber rushes in, moving the camera here and there, and seemingly running from a fine cast that also includes Terrence Howard, Cicely Tyson and Ving Rhames. Like too many young directors, Mr. Barber seems in the grip of a kind of creative attention-deficit disorder, caused less by the digital tools at his disposal than the lack of good guidance. Too bad Arthur Freed, who produced a number of musical masterpieces for MGM, wasn’t around to show him how it’s done and say, “Once more, from the top....”  “Idlewild” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film has female nudity, adult language, hooch and suspicious-looking clouds of “cigarette” smoke.</text>
      <date>August 25, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>