<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  For binge-drinking frat-boy types and the women who love them “I Hope They Serve Beer in Hell,” Tucker Max’s best-selling comic journal of his true adventures boozing, vomiting and fornicating, is a gleeful primer on the New Coarseness. Its far less pungent film adaptation is something else: a mediocre gross-out movie that barely pushes the envelope.  An early scene follows the author (Matt Czuchry) and his buddies Drew (Jesse Bradford) and Dan (Geoff Stults) into a bar where Tucker, the threesome’s leader and provocateur, initiates flirtatious verbal warfare. After he rudely assesses the physical attributes of the women within earshot, insults and epithets begin to fly. Except for one plain goody-two-shoes,  who is offended by Tucker’s fondness for sexist trash talk, the women fight back.  But the New Coarseness is really just the Old Coarseness with steroids and breast implants. The etiquette that prevails in the kind of pick-up joints and strip clubs that are Mr. Max’s hunting grounds of choice has always been crude. The language may have gotten rougher, but inside the clubhouse words that would offend beyond its walls are the accepted weapons of choice; they may sting, but they don’t wound. Skillfully wielded, they even turn into mating calls.  If the uproarious behavior chronicled in “I Hope They Serve Beer in Hell” has been compared to Hunter S. Thompson’s antics in “Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas,” Mr. Max’s book is no gonzo classic. What marginally holds your attention is the narrator’s swaggering attitude, not his language. The shoehorning of his anecdotes into comic situations in the movie blurs their edges. Now and then the book suggests an ’80s monologue by Eric Bogosian, but lacking the social insight and political consciousness. Still, “I Hope They Serve Beer in Hell” would have had more vitality as a filmed stand-up routine augmented with skits than a conventional comedy.  Directed by Bob Gosse from a screenplay by Mr. Max and Nils Parker, it is no better than a dozen other Hollywood guy movies like “The Hangover.” Mr. Czuchry is also less of a jock than the author, judging by Mr. Max’s YouTube appearances. A tarnished towheaded angel with a maniacal grin, Mr. Czuchry comes across as a potty-mouthed little boy.  The most developed character, the misanthropic Drew, has a heart of gold beneath a sour, suspicious attitude acquired after his traumatic discovery of a girlfriend giving oral sex to a rapper. In the scenes following his hook-up (after an extended verbal skirmish) with Lara (Marika Dominczyk), a stripper and single mother of an adorable tot, the movie turns as squishy sweet as a Disney Christmas film.  The screenplay consists largely of bits and pieces of Mr. Max’s book, many borrowed from the Austin Road Trip section, slapped onto the chronicle of Dan’s disastrous bachelor party, arranged by Tucker, in a strip club. While a badly battered Dan lands in jail, his marital future in question, Tucker finds himself dashing naked through a hotel lobby with a case of explosive diarrhea from a can of beer laced with a laxative by a vengeful woman. Need I say more?  “I Hope They Serve Beer in Hell” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has scatological jokes, sexual situations and strong language.</text>
      <date>September 25, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>