<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> For those in the mood for a story about same-sex lovers up against the odds, their histories and the world around them, may I suggest an evening on Brokeback Mountain. And for those searching for a distaff variation on the same general idea while scanning the shelves of their local video store, where the enervating trifle "Imagine Me &amp; You" will soon be gathering dust, may I instead suggest a night in with "Mädchen in Uniform," "Go Fish," "The Incredibly True Adventure of Two Girls in Love" or even that disreputable classic of vampire fangs and gauze, "The Hunger."  Written and directed by Ol Parker, a British screenwriter making his lackluster directorial debut, "Imagine Me &amp; You" tells the story of Rachel (Piper Perabo), who's fast-tracking down the straight and narrow when the florist-next-door, Luce (Lena Headey), unintentionally throws up a roadblock. The women meet cute at Rachel's wedding, during which the bride exchanges vows with her longtime beau, Heck (Matthew Goode, angling to become the new Hugh Grant), shortly after swapping long looks with Luce, who's provided the flowers for the ceremony along with the story's jumping-off point. Mr. Parker's aspirations to the light tone and touch of Richard Curtis, the screenwriter and sometimes director of romantic comedies like "Love Actually," are thwarted by a pronounced absence of cinematic imagination.  One thing leads very slowly to another as Rachel tries to come to terms with her attraction to Luce, and her newfound object of desire tries not to muck up a young marriage. En route to the obvious clinch there are long walks, awkward pauses, family dysfunction and fireworks, though not from the visibly uncomfortable leads, and coy bits of business with the supporting cast. Ms. Perabo, who starred in the howler "Coyote Ugly" a few years back and is currently appearing in "Cheaper by the Dozen 2," manages a credible British accent, if not the requisite feeling, while the fetching Ms. Headey tries her hardest to appear interested in  her costar and the material. In this she has only intermittent success.  "Imagine Me &amp; You" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian), mainly for adult language.</text>
      <date>January 27, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>