<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the most wrenching scene from Luis Mandoki's film "Innocent Voices," Salvadoran army troops storm into a  school in the heart of an impoverished rural village, bark out a list of names and forcibly conscript any boy over 12 into the military. As the dazed, terrified children are herded into the back of a truck and carted away, their stricken parents look on in horrified silence; to interfere would be to risk being shot to death.  This scene is one of several in the film, set in the 1980's during El Salvador's 12-year  civil war, that break your heart. During those years, the Farabundo Martí National Liberation Front, or the F.M.L.N.,  waged an armed struggle against the right-wing government, which responded by attacking villages and massacring inhabitants suspected of sympathizing with the left-wing guerrillas. The United States, fearing a Communist takeover of the country, backed the government and dispatched American soldiers to train the government troops, who eventually prevailed.  These events are viewed through the eyes of Chava (Carlos Padilla), a spirited 11-year-old boy and the oldest of three children who live with their mother, Kella (Leonor Varela), a seamstress struggling to provide for her family. Chava's father has left El Salvador for the United States, and there is no word as to his whereabouts.  Because this is history  viewed through the eyes of a child, "Innocent Voices" gives you feelings and impressions, but few facts. The only people  seen in the village are women, children, the elderly and the disabled cowering in fear and uncertainty. In one brief scene, American soldiers are shown handing out chewing gum to children whose parents warn them that the kindly soldiers are really their enemies. In another, Chava witnesses the kidnapping off the street of two girls who are dragged away to be raped; the heroic local priest (Daniel Giménez Cacho), the film's most eloquent voice, refuses to tell the boy what will happen to them.  The film is based on the real-life childhood experiences of Oscar Torres, who co-wrote the screenplay with the Mexican director Mr. Mandoki. It is set mostly in the year between Chava's 11th and 12th birthdays, as the war worsens and his conscription looms.  Between attacks, life in the village goes on. Chava, an enterprising child, talks a local bus driver into giving him a job collecting fares and announcing the stops. He pursues an innocent flirtation with Cristina Maria (Xuna Primus), the daughter of a local teacher. One day, an uncle (José María Yazpik), an F.M.L.N. member, sneaks back into town for a visit. He brings a guitar and calms the household during a raid by quietly singing and playing a banned folk song. Later he takes the boy to visit his camp in the mountains, gives him a portable radio, shows him a forbidden station on the dial and warns him never to play it in public. Chava is so delighted by his toy that he naïvely struts through the streets, blaring it under the noses of the soldiers until the priest intercedes.  But the familiar world shatters the instant a military vehicle wheels around a corner, scattering the panicked villagers, who huddle on the floors of their shacks, clutching mattresses against the bullets that rake through the cardboard-thin walls.  If these  horrific scenes are well directed, they belong to a movie that has no qualms about pressing your emotional buttons. The mother-child bond and Chava's puppy love are stroked by the same heavy directorial hand that applied extra layers of sentimental varnish to Hollywood movies like "When a Man Loves a Woman" and "Message in a Bottle."  Early in the story, Kella named Chava "the man of the house." When the war worsens, and mother and son are separated, her search for him and their eventual reunion are squeezed for a last teardrop long after the well has been depleted. "Innocent Voices" is a movie in which there are only heroes and villains, the persecutors and the persecuted.  It is understandable and maybe even necessary that a movie with a humanitarian agenda should bluntly manipulate the emotions. But how far should it go? As an outcry against the forcible conscription of children into armies around the world, "Innocent Voices," is an honorable film. But as a balanced portrait of a tragic civil war, it is simplistic and opaque. A movie like "Hotel Rwanda," which also indulged in sentimental excess to dramatize mass slaughter, at least provided some background and shading to the events it portrayed. "Innocent Voices" offers neither.  "Innocent Voices" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has harrowing scenes of war.</text>
      <date>October 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>