<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Claire Denis's magnificent enigma of a film, "The Intruder," explores the troubled soul of Louis Trebor (Michel Subor), a brooding loner with a heart condition who lives with two large white dogs in a forest near the French-Swiss border. As this rugged, ailing 68-year-old outdoorsman travels halfway around the world to begin a new life, his past, present and future, real and imagined, blend into a visually spellbinding depiction of a selfish sensualist's quest for a longer life with a redemptive final chapter.  In an early scene, Louis, while swimming in a lake near his cabin one idyllic afternoon, suffers a mild heart attack, his dogs at his side. With the help of a mysterious Russian woman (Katia Golubeva) who stalks him for the remainder of the film like a guilty conscience and a portent of mortality, he buys a new heart on the black market with cash stashed in a Swiss bank account.  Then he travels  to South Korea, where he buys a boat and sails it to his former home, a dilapidated shack on a remote island south of Tahiti. His dream is to find the son he sired decades earlier when he lived there. But once he is settled, his body begins to reject the alien heart.  Ms. Denis, a fearless aesthetic adventurer who lived in Africa until she was 14, has always been fascinated by stories and images of cultural imposition, exile, alienation and the contemplation of the Other. She is also one of the world's most sensual filmmakers. Working with her brilliant cinematographer Agnès Godard, she spills onto the screen images of man  and  nature with an  attunement to light, shadow, color, texture and mood that approaches the surreal.  That sensuality is metaphysical as well as tactile. "The Intruder," like her 1999 masterpiece, "Beau Travail," a variation of "Billy Budd" re-imagined in Africa among a regiment of the French Foreign Legion, conveys a spiritual reverence for the beauty of the human form along with a visceral fascination with the animal essence beneath that radiant surface. Her notorious film "Trouble Every Day" went so far as to portray love as cannibalism, literally and metaphorically.  As Louis exchanges his sylvan paradise in the Jura Mountains for a tropical one in the South Seas, the movie's portrayal of the natural world is ravishing, but ominous in its recognition of a fierce natural order beyond mankind's  control. The most breathtaking image in this film of few words and many revelatory flashes is a long-held shot of cloud-draped mountains viewed from a boat plowing through the heaving gray water of the South Pacific. The shot is so permeated with awe, dread and mystery that you wish the camera would never turn away.  At the least, "The Intruder" is a rich travelogue in which Louis's journey from one hemisphere to another describes, in the words of Ms. Denis's director's statement, "a loop, the curve of Earth as I imagine it." But these images have a conceptual dimension. The movie, true to its title, is filled with images of intrusion, of physical and cultural boundaries being traversed. Once transplanted, Louis's new heart, which he insists must come from a young man, is an alien presence in his body. Hikers, hunters and drug smugglers intrude on his forest, in which  the pastoral atmosphere is punctuated by gunshots and dogs barking. The movie's most astounding image, plucked from Louis's unconscious, shows a human heart dropped into the snow and sniffed at by dogs.  Cold-eyed and determined with a streak of violence, Louis is himself emotionally heartless. His estranged son, Sidney (Grégoire Colin),  lives in a village near the cabin with his wife (Florence Loiret-Caille), a border guard, and two young children to whom he shows a tenderness that Louis never exhibits. Louis is also having an affair with the local pharmacist (Bambou) who brings him his heart medication, and he nurses an attraction to a beautiful, feral local dog breeder (Béatrice Dalle), dubbed Queen of the Northern Hemisphere, who doesn't return his interest and thinks he's crazy.  Once in the South Seas, Louis finds himself an intruder in a primitive, seafaring culture whose tribal council, informed that he is looking for his long-lost son, holds auditions for young men in the village to fill the role and receive the large inheritance Louis has promised. We even see the young Louis in a brief excerpt from Paul Gegauff's obscure 1965 film, "Le Reflux," in which Mr. Subor appeared.  One way to view a film that will frustrate those seeking crisp narrative structure and a linear story is to see "The Intruder" as a collagelike stream of allusive cinematic poetry assembled from various sources to evoke an idea. An acknowledged inspiration is "L'Intrus," a short memoir  by the French philosopher Jean-Luc Nancy about his heart transplant.  But Louis's futile search for a better paradise also evokes the literature and journals of Robert Louis Stevenson and Paul Gauguin, as well as F. W. Murnau's classic 1931 film "Tabu." The best way to enjoy "The Intruder" is to surrender to its poetry without demanding cut-and-dried explanations.  The score for "The Intruder," composed by Stuart Staples of the British group Tindersticks, is a repeated loop of clattering percussion, plucked guitar and wailing trumpet. This seductive musical fragment complements the movie's dream of a paradise that beckons and remains as elusive as a mirage.</text>
      <date>December 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>