<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Introducing the Dwights,” directed by Cherie Nowlan from a script by Keith Thompson, is a funny-sad, icky-sweet comedy of family dysfunction  — a genre that seems to flourish in Australia, this film’s country of origin. The monstrous, needy matriarch of the Dwight clan, Jean, may be British, but she has assimilated, however miserably, into a familiar lower-middle-class Down Under milieu of dreamers and eccentrics.  Jean was once a semifamous nightclub comedian, and she fans the sputtering flame of her career at C-list nightclubs, where she is introduced as “clubland’s raunchiest homemaker” and tells broad, bad jokes about the uselessness of men. (“Having sex with a big bloke is like having a wardrobe fall on you in the middle of the night,” she observes.)  There is nothing particularly subtle about Jean’s material, but then again, she is played by Brenda Blethyn, a woman who can overact brushing her teeth or frying an egg, and who conveys her character’s emotional state by mugging, winking and occasionally shrieking. You know, early on, that Jean’s volatility is heading for a Big Scene, and it arrives punctually in the last act, a scheduled train wreck complete with booze, loud music and wanton blubbering.  After which everything is more or less O.K. And “Introducing the Dwights,” in spite of Ms. Blethyn’s excesses, is also more or less O.K. Her absences come as a relief to the audience, much as Jean’s do to her younger son, Tim (Khan Chittenden).  He and his older brother, Mark (Richard Wilson), who has a disability resulting from brain damage suffered at birth, live with their mom and cater to her fragile, voracious ego. (Dad, a country crooner played by Frankie J. Holden, makes ends meet working as a supermarket security guard.) When Tim, who has a one-man moving company, meets Jill (Emma Booth), Jean’s fierce jealousy is activated, and she embarks on a campaign of bullying, guilt-tripping and spiteful manipulation.  It takes Jill awhile to understand that Jean is the source of her new boyfriend’s skittishness, and she at first mistakes his sexual timidity for lack of desire. Ms. Booth and Mr. Chittenden are both attractive young actors with a knack for easygoing understatement, and the best parts of “Introducing the Dwights” observe the flowering of their tentative, tender relationship. When Jean enters the picture, though, the melodramatic volume is cranked to a level beyond what the movie’s modest scale can sustain.  Her narcissistic awfulness does increase your sympathy for Tim and Mark — how could it not? — but it also makes the cute, sentimental aspects of the story seem forced and implausible. The film seems pulled between conflicting impulses — toward a dimension of psychological gothic almost worthy of Tennessee Williams and toward a tidy, quirky sitcom — and the filmmakers can’t find a tone that would manage both.  “Introducing the Dwights” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for sex, nudity and language.</text>
      <date>July 4, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>