<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The latest and lamest version of Don Siegel’s 1956 pulp classic “Invasion of the Body Snatchers” (from the Jack Finney novel) might have been an accidental camp classic if its politics weren’t so abhorrent and the movie didn’t try to hide its ineptitude behind a veil of pomposity. A miscast Nicole Kidman stars as a Washington-area shrink who’s so deep in her own little world she doesn’t initially notice that everyone else appears to be mainlining antidepressants. Maybe they’re former patients. Or maybe all those tight skirts she wears have cut off her circulation. That certainly must explain why she barely notices Daniel Craig, wasted here as her best friend.  Whatever the case, “The Invasion” lurches and drags and teeters on the brink of death from scene to scene; it plays as if it had been made by someone in a trance, though not a cool one. The glaring technical glitches are just the beginning. The film looks murky and at times blurred (the cinematographer has done fine work elsewhere), and it’s been badly overedited in a transparent bid to goose the action, to create a suggestion of narrative tension. But nonsensical jump-cuts and incoherent flash-forwards can’t raise the dead. That said, the vomiting does look great. (The aliens spread their evil ways by hurling like booze-soaked frat boys, a gesture that takes on increasingly symbolic weight as the movie plays and peters out.)  The producer Joel Silver has said that “The Invasion” was partly redone by the Wachowski brothers (the credited screenwriter is David Kajganich) and that, at some point during production, the directing chores were handed over to their sometime collaborator, James McTeigue, who performed the same duties on the almost equally moribund “V for Vendetta.” (The original director here, Oliver Hirschbiegel, retains credit.)  The Wachowskis’ bludgeoning touch can be felt in some laughable dinnertime chitchat during which Ms. Kidman’s character grandly announces that she’s a “postmodern feminist” to a guy with a cartoon Russian accent. Rather less amusing is the creepy ideology that seeps into the movie and informs its denouement, one suggesting that to be human is to be purely and violently self-interested — a pod person of a kind, but with a gun.  “The Invasion” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Violence and vomit.</text>
      <date>August 17, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>