<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Irina Palm” may be the work of a German-born Belgian director, but it belongs to a sturdy and very British genre: the naughty-granny comedy, in which an older woman is liberated and rejuvenated by an excursion into vice. In this case the iffy activity is sex for hire, which may give the film a jolt of topicality for New York audiences. The workaday London sex shop where parts of “Irina Palm” take place is decidedly down-market compared with the Emperor’s Club V.I.P., but it also may be less tawdry. In this kind of movie, sleaze and salaciousness are quickly banished in favor of sentimental good cheer.  Still, “Irina Palm,” directed by Sam Garbarski from a screenplay by Philippe Blasband and Martin Herron, does rise slightly above the silly clichés embedded in its story. This is mostly because of Marianne Faithfull, who plays Maggie, a middle-class suburban widow preparing to settle into a meek and marginal old age. Maggie has a few friends, but her great love is for her grandson, Olly, whose life is threatened by an illness that can be cured only by an experimental treatment available in Australia that his family can’t afford. This fact efficiently disarms any prudish objections to Maggie’s behavior, since the life of an innocent child is at stake.  And so she finds her way to London, where she innocently answers a want ad and finds herself ensconced in the cozy, comical demimonde of prostitution. To minimize implausibility and avoid making the audience uncomfortable, the filmmakers contrive to give Maggie a specialty that does not involve penetration or face-to-face contact with clients. Instead she sits alone in a room with a hole in the wall and provides a form of satisfaction suggested by her professional pseudonym, which is also the movie’s title. And she’s so skilled that men are soon lining up and insisting on her special services.  Her warmth and sensible good humor also endear Maggie to her boss and some of her co-workers, and before long she is glowing with renewed confidence and self-esteem. Of course predictable dangers and complications loom on the horizon. But the rather shopworn plot of “Irina Palm” is buoyed by Mr. Garbarski’s sense of realism — he manages to make the movie look and feel as if it were a slice-of-life drama rather than a preposterous fable — and above all by Ms. Faithfull.  Without showiness or actorly straining — but with a faint aura of rock ’n’ roll sexual glamour still hovering around her — Ms. Faithfull explores a full and fascinating range of emotion. Maggie is weary and timid at first, bruised by grief and by a sense of diminished prospects. To see her recover her toughness and humor is moving and satisfying despite the dubious narrative machinery that enables her rebirth. “Irina Palm” is, for the most part, a phony trifle, but at its heart, somehow, is a real and fascinating person.</text>
      <date>March 21, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>