<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "The Island" is the kind of movie almost entirely devoted to the explanation of its own premise. This takes some time, because the premise is complicated. But since the explainer is Michael Bay, the exposition is carried out on the run, and you have a lot of flashy images to look at while you're connecting the dots.  Really, the picture consists of two semi-familiar science-fiction conceits nestled one inside the other. At first, after Ewan McGregor wakes up from a Calvin Klein perfume commercial of a dream in a sterile white room full of talking gadgetry, you might take this for a dystopian, "Brave New World"-inspired vision of a totalitarian future. It sure looks that way, like an update of "THX 1138," with product placements for Puma sneakers and Aquafina bottled water. Everyone wears white and travels through a hushed, shopping-mall environment, where every mood and movement is monitored and regulated. For their own good, of course. These people are survivors of an environmental catastrophe and are quarantined until they are chosen, one by one in a lottery, for a trip to the island, which is the only uncontaminated spot left on the planet.  Lincoln Six Echo (Mr. McGregor)  starts to ask some questions and, with the help of McCord (Steve Buscemi), a large moth and his own curiosity, discovers that he is not in a post-apocalyptic totalitarian science-fiction fantasy at all but in another kind altogether.  "There is no island," he breathlessly tells his friend Jordan Two Delta (Scarlett Johansson), as they prepare to flee. "Trust me."  And what choice do we have? We've paid our money to see a picture called "The Island" (which begins with a picture of a really nice-looking island), and now they tell us that there is no island. So we trust Mr. Bay and his several screenwriters to tell us what, exactly, there is.  I don't want to give too much away - at least no more than the trailers already have, which is most of it - but the science-fiction movie our hero and heroine turn out to be in has to do with unbridled technology and corporate irresponsibility. Their controlled, tranquil environment is not a refuge but a factory - or perhaps a warehouse - and they, along with their white-jumpsuit-wearing friends, are the products. They are the unknowing clones of rich people, having been bred by a greedy, ambitious scientist named Merrick (Sean Bean) to be harvested for spare parts. The lottery that pretends to select them for the island is actually their appointment for slaughter.  These days, every self-respecting summer blockbuster must also be an allegory, usually with a vague connection to President Bush and 9/11. "The Island" sends its symbolic feelers out in a different and perhaps even more contentious direction. The issues raised by the possibility of human cloning are vexed in themselves, and they are also connected to more immediate debates about abortion, stem cells and euthanasia. These debates are quite pointedly invoked - in ways that cut sharply against the assumption that Hollywood is a liberal propaganda factory - whenever the question of Lincoln and Jordan's humanity is raised. According to Merrick, they cannot be human since they exist as the result of a purely utilitarian process and "have no souls."  Yes, but they do have the most beguiling matched set of blue eyes. And Mr. Bay, in any case, is not exactly what you would call a humanist. Death on a large scale - whether in "Pearl Harbor" or "Armageddon" - does not really trouble him, as long as there are some spectacular explosions and whiplash-inducing car chases. Which there certainly are in "The Island," once it busts out of the clone tank to zoom across the Arizona desert into the streets of futuristic downtown Los Angeles (played, curiously enough, by the special-effects-enhanced present-day city of Detroit).  Along the way, as Lincoln and Jordan flee a heavily armed bounty hunter (Djimon Hounsou) and his minions, Mr. Bay treats us to some of his signature set pieces, including a freeway chase in which giant metal train wheels roll from the back of a fast-moving truck into speeding traffic. (He did something like this in "Bad Boys II," but with embalmed corpses instead of train wheels. By the way, it turns out that in the future, rail travel on Amtrak will enjoy something of a renaissance, and L.A. will have a high-speed, skyscraper-level public transit system.) Apart from the explanatory cross-talk and the occasional flight of philosophical speculation, the dialogue is mostly breathless imperatives. "Run!" "Watch out!" "Go!"  And by all means do, if you're in the mood for glossy, witty eye candy with some moderately chewy stuff in the middle. This lavish, exhaustingly kinetic film is smarter than you might expect, and at the same time dumber than it could be. It's an impressive product: a triumph of cloning that almost convinces you that it possesses a soul.  "The Island" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has intense action sequences, some of them bloody, and a few sexual situations.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>