<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “I Think I Love My Wife” Chris Rock, who also directed and wrote the script (with his frequent collaborator Louis C. K.), plays Richard Cooper, an investment banker whose life is as bland as his name. Richard, in his voice-over narration, is the first to admit that his situation is enviable in many ways: He has a lovely wife named Brenda (Gina Torres), two cute small children, a spiffy house in the suburbs and a flourishing career at a reputable Manhattan firm.  The problem, as you may be able to intuit from this checklist of bourgeois amenities, is that he’s bored. He has reached a point at which existence settles into a series of pleasant routines and minor frustrations. In Richard’s case one of these frustrations —  the sexual cooling of his marriage —  becomes the source of some potentially major trouble.  “My marriage is frozen solid,” he declares. He means to say that it’s strong, but the metaphor sneaks up and traps him in an uncomfortable admission. To make matters worse, he delivers this diagnosis to Nikki Tru (Kerry Washington), a human blowtorch —  even without the cigarettes, she’d still be smoking —  aimed at the facade of Richard’s comfortable, complacent life.  Nikki, the ex-girlfriend of an old friend, shows up at Richard’s office one afternoon, supposedly seeking a letter of recommendation. By caprice or design she ensnares him in a long, volatile flirtation, a relationship that, while not technically adulterous, is nonetheless tinged with furtiveness and guilty exhilaration.  If the premise sounds familiar, that is in part because “I Think I Love My Wife” is a remake, at once free-handed and faithful, of “Chloe in the Afternoon” (1972), the sixth and last of Eric Rohmer’s “Moral Tales.” Mr. Rock’s affection for this source is evident in his careful restaging of some of its shots and scenes, even though Mr. Rohmer’s wry, ironical temperament could not be further from Mr. Rock’s candid, confrontational stand-up style.  In attempting to synthesize the later French New Wave of the late 1960s and early ’70s with the upscale African-American romantic comedies that flourished in Hollywood in the late 1990s, Mr. Rock has not only done his best work as a director and screenwriter but has also made an unusually insightful and funny mainstream American movie about the predicaments of modern marriage.  There are some raucous set pieces and a lot of frank, jokey talk about sex, but “I Think I Love My Wife” is not after crude or easy hilarity, and Mr. Rock works hard to hold his aggressive, irrepressible comic personality in check. Though he has made great strides as a filmmaker —  his previous effort, “Head of State,” was a better idea for a movie than an actual movie —  he is still, unfortunately, not much of an actor.  He is able, just barely, to impersonate a buttoned-up suburban professional, looking perfectly respectable in his suits but never quite conveying the inner life of the man inside them. Mr. Rock has a bit of a Woody Allen problem, in that any character he plays will always seem to be a transparent alter ego, and in the case of Richard Cooper this causes blurriness and confusion. Is this guy supposed to be Chris Rock or not? And if not, who is he supposed to be?  Richard’s everyman qualities, in other words, clash with Mr. Rock’s irreverent individuality. But the movie still works, in part because the observational sharpness that characterizes this comedian’s best performance work is sprinkled through the script. Without making race into a Big Theme, Mr. Rock and Louis C. K. nonetheless pepper the film with sharp insights into the black middle class, taking note of how the consciousness of race remains lodged in the fine grain of daily life. In front of her young daughter Brenda insists on spelling the words “white” and “black” instead of saying them, and Nikki, examining Richard’s iPod, offers a piquant diagnosis of his monochromatic musical tastes.  The key to the movie, in many ways, is Ms. Washington, whose flighty, needy, unpredictable character might have been better suited to Paris in 1972 than to present-day Manhattan. Nikki is a bit of a male fantasy, a dangerous temptress whose motives and feelings are as mysterious as they are intense, and whose attention is like oxygen to the sputtering vanity of a successful, sexually unfulfilled man.  Luckily, Ms. Washington is as quick-witted and subtle as she is lovely, and she makes Nikki not just seductive but interesting, a quality that is crucial to the story’s credibility. (Steve Buscemi, as Richard’s wise, philandering colleague, similarly rounds out what might have been a flat, obvious role.)  In short, “I Think I Love My Wife” is  smart and likable, which is lavish praise in a season whose comic offerings have included “Music and Lyrics” and “Because I Said So.” The success of this movie also suggests, refreshingly enough, that not every Hollywood remake of a French movie is necessarily a crime against taste. I look forward to seeing the boxed set of Chris Rock’s “Moral Tales” on my shelf, in alphabetical order right between Richard Pryor and Eric Rohmer.  “I Think I Love My Wife” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has some very frank and grown-up discussions of sex, though not much explicit depiction of it.</text>
      <date>March 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>