<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is surely no shortage of aspiring rock bands, logging lonely hours of rehearsal and traipsing from one club date to the next in search of the big break. Not many of them, however, have famous actors serving as their tour managers, roadies and record-label bosses. That Rocco DeLuca and the Burden are attached, in these ways and more, to Kiefer Sutherland — son of Donald and star of “24” — may not be their only claim to distinction, but it is the only discernible reason for the existence of “I Trust You to Kill Me,” Manu Boyer’s inconsequential documentary about the band’s brief first tour of Europe.  Mr. DeLuca, whose wailing voice and anguished songwriting drives the Burden, is an intense, skinny 28-year-old who takes himself very seriously as an artist. His music is a bit droning and sludgy for my taste, but his own taste in music —  John Lee Hooker, Johnny Cash, Appalachian murder ballads —  can hardly be argued with.  Mr. Sutherland, in any case, believes mightily in his protégé and lends his time and celebrity to the cause of promoting Mr. DeLuca. Mr. Sutherland unloads equipment outside a London nightclub on a freezing-cold day and hands out free tickets on the streets of Dublin (and inside a few of the city’s pubs). “Are you somebody famous?” one Dubliner asks. “Well, I’m working as an actor now,” he coyly replies.  As it follows the band from one city to another, “I Trust You to Kill Me” becomes less about Mr. DeLuca and more about his sponsor. Chronicling the ups and downs of the band gives way to charting Mr. Sutherland’s vaguely defined personal journey, one that involves tattooing the song lyric that gives the film its title onto his forearm in Icelandic runes.  Mr. Boyer shows up in the actor’s hotel room from time to time asking nosy questions, and Mr. Sutherland stays up late drinking and carousing, at one point flinging himself into a Christmas tree in the lobby of a London hotel. At the end we learn that the Burden later relieved him of his duties as tour manager, sending him back to his day job of pretending to save the world from terrorism.</text>
      <date>September 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>