<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A sign of the season, as reliable as the first frost or the turning foliage, is the proliferation of dead, abused or endangered children on movie screens. It sometimes seems that you can’t make a serious film these days without one. Nothing cranks up the dramatic intensity quite as effectively as a child in peril — see Clint Eastwood’s “Changeling,” opening Friday (review on Page C1), for the latest evidence of this Hollywood axiom — and nothing seems to make ambitious actors happier than parental grief.  At least three movies this fall explore the durability of such grief, tracing the long shadow that a child’s death can cast over a family’s subsequent efforts at happiness. In “Rachel Getting Married,” Jonathan Demme’s ebulliently therapeutic domestic drama, the title character’s wedding is haunted by memories of the accident, some years in the past, that took the life of her younger brother. The specter of a lost boy, killed by a rare genetic disorder, also complicates the lives of his parents and surviving siblings in Arnaud Desplechin’s “Christmas Tale,” which opens next month. And “I’ve Loved You So Long,” a new French film written and directed by Philippe Claudel, is dominated by the murder, more than a decade in the past, of a 6-year-old boy.  That killing, shocking in itself, is made unimaginably more so because the murderer was the boy’s mother, Juliette, played with terrifying, heartbreaking poise by Kristin Scott Thomas. Released from prison after a 15-year sentence, Juliette moves in with her younger sister, Léa (Elsa Zylberstein), a college literature instructor with a loving husband named Luc (Serge Hazanavicius) and two adorable adopted daughters. Juliette,  affectless, chain-smoking, wrapped in a bulky overcoat, drifts through her sister’s house in the French city of Nancy like a restless ghost, unsettling the inhabitants as she struggles to emerge from a state of moral and spiritual limbo.  Mr. Claudel’s practice of fading slowly to black between scenes, and the spidery tones of Jean-Louis Aubert’s score, create an atmosphere of mystery and dread that is both appropriate to the story and a little misleading. If “I’ve Loved You So Long” is not exactly a horror movie, it is nonetheless filled with fear and foreboding. What Juliette did is hidden from her nieces and also from Luc and Léa’s social circle, into which she makes a few tentative steps. And the particulars of Juliette’s crime are left unspoken, even as Léa (like the audience) can barely contain her curiosity. Is her sister a penitent, a madwoman or a monster? Does her quiet, decorous, depressive manner represent a longing for peace or the sublimated threat of further violence? Why did she do it?  Luc, not unreasonably, is terrified — fearful for the safety of his own children and also perhaps somewhat superstitious about giving evil a place in his home. And Ms. Scott Thomas does not rush to dispel the possibility that Juliette, polite and pretty as she is, might also be a person of irreducible depravity.  Out of either pride or abjection  (the artistry of Ms. Scott Thomas’s performance lies in confounding such distinctions), she refuses to solicit sympathy, or to offer reciprocal, reassuring warmth when it comes her way. But as Juliette makes her way from one day to the next  — picking up a stranger for sex, looking for a job, forming tentative bonds with her nieces and with Luc’s father, figuring out how to be friends with her needy, nervous sister  — it becomes clear that the film is, at bottom, a story of rehabilitation and healing.  This kind of narrative is familiar enough, and so are the risks of sentimental talk-show piety associated with it. Luckily, Ms. Scott Thomas’s furious honesty rules out easy, unearned redemption, as does the film’s tough-minded resistance to the temptations of melodrama. A first-time director with a literary background (like Léa he teaches in Nancy, and he has published several novels), Mr. Claudel is gratifyingly absorbed in details of setting and character. And even though the unfathomable horror in Juliette’s past dominates everything else, the small felicities and absurdities of real life manage to peek through the gloom.  Juliette is alive, whether or not she wants to be, and the project she finds herself involved in, half-heartedly at first, is one of rehumanization. This is accomplished through contact with other people (including a colleague of Léa’s, played by Laurent Grevill) and also through activities like reading, looking at paintings and going to the cinema. In an entirely believable and matter-of-fact way, Mr. Claudel’s film makes a case for the psychological and ethical necessity of art.  He also includes a warning against overstating the case, in a remarkable scene involving Léa and her students, in which she berates them for treating fiction (in this case Dostoyevsky’s “Crime and Punishment”) as an exalted reflection of life. Her fury arises in part from her own inability to make sense of Juliette, or of the tangle of contradictory feelings her sister inspires.  The film, in the end, turns away from the Dostoyevskian implications of Juliette’s crime and its expiation. A revelation comes near the end that is both tremendously moving and a bit disappointing, in the way that the solutions to great mysteries frequently are. This turn   does not diminish the accomplishment of Ms. Scott Thomas’s deep, subtle and altogether stunning performance, but it does alter the scale of the movie, turning it into a more manageable, less existentially unsettling drama. Which is a relief, I suppose, but also a bit of a letdown.  “I’ve Loved You So Long” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has extremely upsetting themes and references and a lot of cigarette smoking.</text>
      <date>October 24, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>