<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Jane Austen Book Club” is such a well-acted, literate adaptation of Karen Joy Fowler’s 2004 best seller that your impulse is to forgive it for being the formulaic, feel-good chick flick that it is.  After all, aren’t novels that fall under that noxiously condescending rubric contrived to reassure readers by offering them secondhand problem-solving advice? Like it or not, Jane Austen is a rock on which the genre was founded. So why shouldn’t a novel and the movie adapted from it acknowledge the connection in a way that is smart and amusing as well as comforting?  A tightly knit ensemble piece directed and written by Robin Swicord, the film adroitly shuffles nine characters (five women and four men) and throws in a too-brief cameo by Lynn Redgrave as one woman’s dissipated, post-hippie mother.  You can question the story’s conceit that the novels of Austen are an ideal guidebook to personal fulfillment for the modern American woman. But as the members of a Jane Austen reading group, who live in Sacramento, analyze the behavior of the characters in her novels, the movie is also a savvy course on how to read a novel of manners. If that novel has any depth, the characters’ motives are open to interpretation. Is a knight in shining armor really Mr. Right? Does a happy ending really augur happily ever after? What are so-and-so’s real motivations?  For these likable women and the one man who joins their group, which meets monthly to discuss a different Austen novel at each session, Austen’s books serve as mirrors and Rorschach tests in which the members recognize themselves and their romantic peccadilloes. The discussions in these  group-therapy sessions lead them toward solutions to their problems. The screenplay includes just enough references to characters and plot developments in Austen novels to whet your appetite for reading or rereading them, but not so many that it alienates the uninitiated.  The movie gets foolishly carried away only once, when it suggests that a clueless macho boor, pressured to read Austen by his neglected wife, is magically transformed into a cuddly enlightened tomcat purring with empathy. I didn’t believe it for a minute. But I like the idea of a great British author from another century casting such a spell. If Shakespeare can do it, why not Austen?  The movie glamorizes Ms. Fowler’s characters in ways large and small. Several are a decade younger in the film than in the book, and all are attractive. Grigg (Hugh Dancy), the lone man, has been transformed from a temp in a university linguistics department in his 40s into a cute-as-a-button Silicon Valley techie and possible genius in his early 30s. Having grown up with three older sisters, this puppyish man-child and science-fiction fanatic who compares an Austen novel to “The Empire Strikes Back” is charmingly feminized without being effeminate.  The rest of the lineup is as follows: Bernadette (Kathy Baker), the group’s founder, is a six-times-married dynamo in her mid-50s who is both free-spirited and maternal. Her close friend Jocelyn (Maria Bello), a control freak and dog fancier who breeds Rhodesian Ridgebacks, fancies herself above the human mating game.  Sylvia (Amy Brenneman), happily married for 25 years, imagines she has it all, then falls apart when her husband, Daniel (Jimmy Smits), breaks the news that he is having an affair with a woman in his law firm and wants to end their marriage. The couple’s lesbian 20-ish daughter, Allegra (Maggie Grace), who has an active love life and a secret addiction to extreme sports like skydiving,  moves back home to keep Sylvia company.  Prudie (Emily Blunt), drawn into the group after meeting Bernadette in line at an Austen film festival, is a beautiful, prim, married high school French teacher. To her recently acquired husband, Dean (Marc Blucas), an uncommunicative sports nut, the author’s name only conjures the capital of Texas. As their marriage falters, she is pursued by Trey (Kevin Zegers), a handsome senior. One of the movie’s few surreal touches is a traffic sign that flashes “What would Jane do?” as Prudie contemplates meeting him in a motel.  The main plot involves Grigg’s unrequited passion for Jocelyn, who invites him into the group as a potential boyfriend for Sylvia and keeps trying to throw them together, never realizing that she herself is the one he wants. Her unlikely naïveté and his unlikely shyness gives the movie an Austen-like narrative gloss.  “The Jane Austen Book Club” isn’t any better or worse than the recent “Becoming Jane,” a fantasy of Austen’s youthful love life. Like the other movies and television projects in a Jane Austen boom that continues to gather momentum, it is an entertaining, carefully assembled piece of clockwork that imposes order on ever more complicated gender warfare.  “The Jane Austen Book Club” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It contains some strong language and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>September 21, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>