<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Are we ever going to get to kill anyone?" asks a young marine toward the end of "Jarhead." It may be a strange question to hear in a war movie, but "Jarhead," about an unusual war, the first gulf war,  is a curious example of the genre.  Adapted from Anthony Swofford's best-selling memoir of the same title - a profane, scabrous prose poem alive with wit and anger - the film tries to convey not only the terror and thrill of military life, but also the frustration and tedium. This is something of a challenge: how to evoke a jittery, anxious state of boredom without inducing it in the audience.  And "Jarhead," directed by Sam Mendes from a screenplay by William Broyles Jr., half succeeds. It has moments that capture the peculiar mixture of stress, fatigue and impatience evoked in Mr. Swofford's reminiscences of his time in the United States Marine Corps. There are scenes full of surreal, desperate comic energy, like a football game played, for the benefit of visiting journalists, in gas masks and protective suits in 112-degree desert heat; and a feverish Christmas party fueled by contraband booze and hip-hop that ends in accidental fireworks.  The daily routines - basically rifle-cleaning, arguing, hydration and masturbation - are efficiently evoked. The Arabian landscape (or rather its California stand-in) is shot in harsh, desaturated tones by Roger Deakins, whose camerawork produces some haunting images. In this empty space, almost entirely devoid of greenery or topographical variation, people seem like abstractions - lonely, clumsy ciphers at once solitary and stripped of individuality.  But the movie, in spite of occasional concessions to melodrama, never produces much insight into or sympathetic connection with its characters. Mr. Swofford's memoir, which has a churning, abrasive immediacy, has been subjected to the aloof aestheticism that is Mr. Mendes's hallmark. The rough language and rough manners have been retained, but the story has been tamed and prettified. While it is not another lacquered, overpriced collectible in the manner of Mr. Mendes's "American Beauty" and "Road to Perdition," "Jarhead" is, in the end, similarly empty. It is a movie that walks up to some of the most urgent and painful issues of our present circumstance, clears its throat loudly and, with occasional flourishes of impressive rhetoric, says nothing.  Mr. Swofford  - "Swoff" to his buddies - is played by Jake Gyllenhaal as a smart, watchful young man who can't quite keep the smirk off his face. He reads Camus on the toilet and tells his first drill sergeant that he's in the Marine Corps because he "got lost on the way to college." (The officer responds by smashing Swoff's head into a blackboard.) The Swofford family history is declared off limits to us (a series of symbolic doors are slammed in our faces), and all we know is that Swoff's father and uncle were  marines in Vietnam and that his sister has been hospitalized.  He also has a girlfriend named Kristina (Brianne Davis), whose half-naked pictures provide him with both comfort and torment. Recruited by a staff sergeant named Sykes (Jamie Foxx) into an elite sniper unit, Swoff eventually finds himself on the border between Saudi Arabia and Iraq, as Desert Shield slowly segues into Desert Storm.  At one point, Sykes relays the news that Saddam Hussein has promised "the mother of all battles," and the movie gestures back to a time before that phrase was the mother of all clichés. The first gulf war is obviously an event that impinges directly on the current situation, and yet at the same time it seems curiously remote. Its post-cold-war, pre-9/11 context is in some ways blurrier than more distant times. The war itself happened fast and left a confused legacy. As the last line of the movie's voice-over narration notes, "We're still in the desert."  No kidding. And what are we doing there? Nobody wants to talk about that. Early on, one of the characters interrupts a fellow marine's ranting to say, "No politics - we're here." Mr. Broyles (whose previous scripts include "Cast Away" and "Apollo 13") and Mr. Mendes obey this injunction, which I suppose is fair enough. There is a long tradition, literary as well as cinematic, of focusing on the ground-level experiences of combatants rather than on policy and strategy.  The operative question is not why we fight, but how, and "Jarhead,"  on screen and on the page, is thick with detail. There is the "wall of shame," where pictures of unfaithful wives and girlfriends are posted; the hazing rituals; the rules and procedures; the special language marines use to refer to everything around them. Devoted to war movies, they whoop and holler and sing along with Wagner while watching the "napalm in the morning" sequence from "Apocalypse Now." (Coincidentally or not, the editor of "Jarhead," Walter Murch, also worked on "Apocalypse Now.") All of this, along with the wildly obscene dialogue, holds your interest, but you can also feel the movie straining for an authenticity it lacks either the will or the means to achieve.  Swoff's comrades are basically stock platoon-movie figures retrofitted for postmodern warfare. There is an irresponsible prankster (Evan Jones), a trash-talking Texan (Lucas Black), a shy, nerdy guy (Brian Geraghty) and a Latino family man (Jacob Vargas) who shows off pictures of his pregnant wife. Sergeant Sykes is the in-your-face, tough-talking leader who shows his tenderness and wisdom at just the right moment as the flames of burning oil wells illuminate his features.  The filmmakers treat these men - and also Troy (Peter Sarsgaard), a tightly wound Michigander who becomes Swoff's shooting partner and closest friend - like pistachio nuts, splitting their hard shells to reveal morsels of emotion. Now and again there are scenes of rage or weeping, but these reveal little more than the movie's occasional need for a shift in tone. Mr. Sarsgaard's performance is, as usual, a model of intelligence and control, but his considerable skill is devoted to compensating for the vagueness and incoherence of his character, and of "Jarhead" as a whole. The movie is full of intensity with almost no real visceral impact.  Mr. Swofford's book has earned a place alongside the classics of military literature, but Mr. Mendes's film is more like a footnote - a minor movie about a minor war, and a film that feels, at the moment, remarkably irrelevant.  "Jarhead" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has pervasive profanity and some strong sexual content.</text>
      <date>November 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>