<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Steven Seagal is cutting off his ponytail. This bit of news — apocryphal, perhaps — has great significance for Jean-Claude Van Damme, the star, protagonist and leading ontological conundrum of “JCVD,” as well as a one-time rival of Mr. Seagal’s for the title of world’s second-best second-rate action hero. Mr. Seagal’s supposed sacrifice, a source of astonishment to this elfin Belgian muscleman, suggests a possible answer to the question posed in and by this odd, almost-clever film: what does an aging action-movie superstar have to do to keep himself in the game?  The real-world choices are limited. Keep going, oblivious to the ravages of time, in the pathologically stoical manner of Sylvester Stallone. Embrace self-parody and character roles in indie films, as Bruce Willis has so brilliantly done. Maybe become the governor of a large state or, failing that, a tough-talking cheerleader for Mike Huckabee.  You could always go back to Belgium — an option that works only if you came from there. This is what JCVD (as we’ll call the character, to distinguish him from the actor, Mr. Van Damme) decides to do, fleeing Hollywood in the wake of an ugly custody battle with his ex-wife and landing in his blue-collar, red-brick hometown outside Brussels. He may be seeking a simpler, more authentic way of life, but Mabrouk El Mechri, the director (and, with Frédéric Bénudis and Christophe Turpin, the writer) of “JCVD,” has other plans. A botched bank robbery traps poor  JCVD in a tense hostage drama, caught between a motley, semi-incompetent gaggle of crooks and the cops who think  he’s one of the bad guys.  Will this lurching, small-scale thriller blossom into a full-blown action picture, with Mr. Van Damme’s fists, feet and elbows enacting righteous payback on the villains? The possibility is teased whenever the tension starts to flag, but “JCVD” more often aims for a knowing, cerebral mood, allowing its hero moments of moody contemplation, during which he reflects on the strange, lonely life of a middle-aged, globally known martial artist.  Some of this is affecting, some of it tedious, and the film’s inconsistencies of tone are made more glaring by its peculiar look. Everything seems to be shot through a gold filter, making Mr. Van Damme look like an Oscar  statuette in a jaundice ward. The metallic visual texture is not only obtrusive but also baffling, since it undercuts the pseudo-documentary touches that are central to the conceit of pretending to show a “real” JCVD in his real homeland. If he had  wandered into a movie by Jean-Pierre and Luc Dardenne, Belgium’s masters of no-frills proletarian realism and hand-held camerawork, now that might have been something to see.  Still, as a foray into self-mocking, self-aggrandizing career rehabilitation, “JCVD” shows some promise and holds some interest. It would hold more if Mr. Van Damme were not so fundamentally lackluster a celebrity, with a string of negligible movies to his name. While the filmmakers — and the star himself — gamely make fun of this legacy of mediocrity, they cannot quite escape it. This may well be the most memorable Jean-Claude Van Damme movie ever, but I’m afraid that’s not saying much.  “JCVD” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language and some violence.</text>
      <date>November 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>