<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>iminy Glick in Lalawood," a frantic comic hodgepodge built around Martin Short's popular Comedy Central character, Jiminy Glick, is an intermittently funny free-for-all that tries desperately to flesh out a television sketch into a feature-length movie. Jiminy, whom Mr. Short introduced six years ago, is the most star-struck, grandiose and inept interviewer ever to apply his tongue to the sole of a celebrity shoe. Double-chinned and bewigged, quacking and waddling around in a fat suit, his eyes aglitter with salacious curiosity, Jiminy originated as a caricature of Skip E. Lowe, a real-life cable-access interviewer whose gushy interrogations of C- and D-list celebrities are phenomena unto themselves. Mr. Short is unable to improve on Mr. Lowe, but at least he has succeeded in lugging him bodily into the comedy mainstream as a parody. The movie yanks Jiminy out of his interviewer's chair and gives him a back story that doesn't really jibe with his flamingly effeminate persona. The Hollywood reporter for a television station in Butte, Mont., Jiminy has a roly-poly wife, Dixie (Jan Hooks), whose mind is addled by Thorazine, and idiotic twin sons (Matthew and Modine), who suggest a 21st-century Tweedledum and Tweedledee. This ramshackle comedy suggests three movies carelessly slapped together into a chaotic whole. In the funniest segments, Jiminy is his familiar ebullient self, springing into action as a hysterical bug-eyed interviewer grilling every celebrity who crosses his path at the 2002 Toronto International Film Festival, where some of the movie was made. Jiminy blithely confuses the real life Whoopi Goldberg with Oprah Winfrey and accosts Forest Whitaker, whom he hails as "the wonderful Forrest Gump." Longer, zany conversations are conducted in a studio with Kurt Russell and a twinkling Steve Martin. These sequences find Mr. Short and the actors near the top of their improvisatory form. The second (moderately funny) movie is a spoof of the Toronto Film Festival itself. We watch excerpts from "Growing Up Gandhi," an atrocious vanity project by a spoiled young filmmaker that immediately puts Jiminy to sleep. That doesn't prevent him from interviewing the sullen director (Corey Pearson) and heaping praise on a project every other critic has savaged. The third movie (a dud) is a satire of David Lynch films. Mr. Short, in full prosthetic makeup, impersonates Mr. Lynch, the director of "Mulholland Drive" and "Lost Highway," for a re-examination of the 1958 Lana Turner-Johnny Stompanato scandal, in a Lynchian spoof of an "Unsolved Mysteries" episode. Jiminy (like Mr. Lowe) is stuck in a late-50's scandal-mongering mind-set. After a drunken night on the town, he dreams he murdered Miranda Coolidge (Elizabeth Perkins), an alcoholic star visiting Toronto to promote her newest film, "The Queens of Africa," a lesbian-themed remake of "The African Queen." The dream is so vivid that Jiminy is convinced a murder might have been committed, and he becomes a bumbling sleuth tracking down the story. Directed by Vadim Jean, "Jiminy Glick in Lalawood" tries to twist its threads into a knot, but it unravels at every turn. The movie comes at you as a frenzied jangle of noise, activity and clever half-digested notions flung into the improvisatory stew pot. If the movie has intelligence to spare, it also suffers from attention-deficit disorder. "Jiminy Glick in Lalawood" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes abundant, harsh profanity.</text>
      <date>May 6, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>