<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  The scariest thing about “Jonestown: The Life and Death of Peoples Temple” is that so many of the followers of Jim Jones, the demented demagogue who led them to commit mass suicide, appear to have been intelligent, idealistic, life-loving people. On Nov. 18, 1978, more than 900 of them died after drinking poisoned Kool-Aid in what this documentary, directed by Stanley Nelson, calls “the largest mass suicide in modern history.”  Two of the five Jonestown residents who resisted Mr. Jones’s call and escaped into the jungles of Guyana after their loved ones died in their arms offer moment-by-moment accounts of this orgy of self-annihilation. The movie includes an audiotape of Mr. Jones urging them to “die with a degree of dignity” rather than “lie down in tears and agony.”  Death, he argued, was not that big a deal; it was just crossing a line. He heralded communal self-destruction as “an act of revolutionary suicide protesting the conditions of an inhumane world.”  This is a movie to make you shudder. How many of us are so desperate for a charismatic leader claiming to have the answers that we will surrender our basic instincts for survival, along with our reason? This film paints a portrait of Mr. Jones, who died with his flock in Guyana, as a man with two faces. The appealing one was that of a trained Pentecostal minister, an idealist with polished oratorical skills. Growing up poor in Indiana, Mr. Jones was sensitive to the plight of African-Americans, and preached racial equality. His son Jim Jones Jr., who appears in the film, boasts of being the first black child adopted by a Caucasian in the state of Indiana.  Especially for Mr. Jones’s poor black followers, the interracial, self-sufficient community he established in Guyana, and before that in San Francisco and in the Redwood Valley of Northern California in the mid-1960’s, promised utopia. In exchange for their life savings, church members happy to work 20 hours a day for the cause were provided comfortable accommodations and given allowances. The documentary has clips of euphoric Peoples Temple celebrations in all three locations.  The other Jim Jones wears the scowl of a paranoid sadist. As a child, this Jim Jones (whose father was an unemployed alcoholic) conducted funerals for dead animals. A social outcast among whites, he found community in the Pentecostal church and preached on the revival circuit. Years later, he performed bogus faith healings.  Declaring that everyone in the community except himself was homosexual, he verbally coerced men and women into having sex with him and afterward told them he did it for them. At the same time, he discouraged liaisons among Temple members, asserting that sexual relationships were selfish and took away from the focus of the church.  One New Year’s Eve in California, he rehearsed the coming mass suicide by passing out punch to 126 people, then telling them they had just drunk poison and would die together as one. When nothing happened, he said it was a loyalty test.  After the church moved from the Redwood Valley to San Francisco, Mr. Jones became a political force whose support helped elect George Moscone the city’s mayor in 1975. But as the church grew in numbers and influence, Mr. Jones’s paranoia deepened. The night in 1977 that New West magazine went to press with an exposé of Peoples Temple based on defectors’ accounts, Mr. Jones fled for Jonestown, which was already under construction.  Some embraced it as a heaven on earth. But Mr. Jones also set up a speaker system through which he broadcast his paranoid ravings 24 hours a day. Before long, anyone who expressed a wish to leave was considered a traitor.  The end came suddenly, right after Leo Ryan, a California congressman, arrived in Jonestown on Nov. 17, 1978, to investigate complaints from constituents whose relatives had moved there. When Mr. Jones learned that several residents wanted to return with him to the United States, chaos erupted. As Representative Ryan’s plane was about to leave, he was one of five people who were killed on the airstrip. The mass suicide followed on the same day.  In hindsight, it may be convenient to view Jonestown as the most tragic manifestation of 1960’s utopianism run amok, and to imagine that in today’s tougher, more cynical social climate, it couldn’t happen. But as this powerful, minutely documented film reveals, the tragedy wasn’t caused by the failure of the Peoples Temple to realize its goals. In many ways, it was succeeding as a self-sufficient community.  Rather, the horror of Jonestown was caused by people’s willingness to surrender their reason to a madman who was also a charismatic manipulator. And that can happen anytime and anywhere.</text>
      <date>October 20, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>