<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Just Friends" hangs its crude, clobbering sense of humor on a dubious theory. Once a boy and a girl have entered the "friend zone" in a relationship, there's no turning it into sweet romance. Translated into the movie's loutish high school mentality, that means no  you-know-what.  The idiot who spouts this theory is Chris Brander (Ryan Reynolds in a fat suit, prosthetic makeup, frizzy wig and a slimy retainer that he pops in and out of his mouth more than once). A New Jersey high school senior, Chris is besotted with his best friend, Jamie Palamino (Amy Smart), a blond cheerleader to whom he has devoted a whole wall of tribute in his suburban bedroom. Chris's private tête-à-têtes with this best friend are exercises in torture, in which Jamie sprawls all over him,  oblivious to his agonized frustration, which, when you think about it, is not really very friendly of her.  Chris's awful moment of truth arrives at a graduation party during which his abject confession of love to Jamie, scrawled in a high school yearbook, is read aloud to screaming derision from the assembled guests. He stumbles out of the party vowing to show them.  That was in 1995. The movie jumps ahead 10 years. Chris is now a slimmed-down, slick-haired Hollywood smoothie operating in the music-video world; compliant models drip off his arm. The movie, directed by Roger Kumble from a screenplay by Adam Tex Davis, wants us to think that Chris has lost his soul in Hollywood. But Mr. Reynolds is not an actor who oozes either sensitivity or intelligence.  In its one stroke of originality, "Just Friends" gives Chris a nightmarish sidekick in the person of Samantha James (Anna Faris), a ferociously possessive, psychotically self-centered, nymphomaniacal music-video star who attaches herself to him like a creeping fungus. Think of all the worst characteristics of Britney, Madonna and Courtney magnified by a hundred and rolled into a poisonous package resembling  the young Joey Heatherton. When Samantha serenades Chris during a flight to Europe with her new song, "Forgiveness," in a cat-scratching yowl, his pained response, "Oh, God," is taken as a sign of approval.  Chris gets his chance to show them when a fire aboard the jet causes the flight to be grounded near Trenton, and, with Samantha clawing at his arm and jabbing his groin, he makes a 10th-anniversary reappearance in his hometown. Jamie, as beautiful as ever, and single, still lives there.  Although "Just Friends" belongs to the same genre as "Wedding Crashers" and "The 40-Year-Old Virgin," it has only about half their wit and stamina. But it is somewhat better than "Waiting," the nadir of the style, which also starred Mr. Reynolds. "Just Friends" overcompensates for its sloppiness with loud,  knockabout farce, much of it involving Chris's violent love-hate relationship with his younger brother, Mike (Christopher Marquette), on whom he tries to palm off Samantha while he pursues Jamie.  He has a challenger for her affection in Dusty Dinkleman (Chris Klein), another high school frog turned into a prince. Dusty, who appears at the beginning of the movie as a pimply geek so adoring of Jamie that he becomes tongue-tied in her presence, is now a pseudo-sensitive, guitar-strumming seducer wielding a New Age shtick. His last name, however, indicates how despicable he really is.  "Just Friends" knows its audience and their points of reference. There is a gross-out toothpaste scene that echoes the hair-gel sequence in "There's Something About Mary," and accidental vandalism to rival the destruction of a suburban yard in "Meet the Parents." The movie would like us to believe that Chris, eventually reduced by a series of mishaps into wearing another retainer, gets back his lost soul. Don't believe it. There was never one there to begin with.  "Just Friends" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual content.</text>
      <date>November 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>