<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Keane" was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Manohla Dargis's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 13, 2004. The R-rated film opens today in Manhattan at Landmark's Sunshine Cinema, 139-143 East Houston Street, East Village.  Lodge Kerrigan keeps such a tight watch on the title character in "Keane" that at times you think the camera is going to crawl in the man's ear to take a look inside. The film opens with Keane, played by Damian Lewis, frantically searching for his daughter amid the rush-hour throngs at the Port Authority Bus Terminal. As he tugs at passers-by and grills ticket agents, Keane comes across as a man possessed, a father engulfed by tragedy, the linchpin in some evolving thriller. That he may be all three things at once is what gives this discomforting film its torque as well as a jolt of deep feeling.  In "Keane," Mr. Kerrigan both gives us a life at the edge of the abyss and pulls off a deft narrative sleight of hand. It doesn't take long to realize that the searcher, who's been keeping up a running conversation with himself while raging through the terminal, may be suffering from something other than worry. As he rips through the crowds, nervously peering from behind corners, Keane seems less like a man freaked out by his child's disappearance and more like a man in a perpetual freak-out. When at last he returns to his squalid hotel room and gulps down a beer in a single guzzle, it's as if he were a furloughed prisoner gratefully returned to his cell.  Keane ventures into the world again, though he never does leave the prison house of his mind. The question of whether he was forced inside this prison by the loss of his daughter (much less if the child even exists) gives the film the aspect of a psychological mystery, one that takes a disquieting turn when Keane meets a young woman, Lynn (Amy Ryan), and her 7-year-old daughter, Kira (Abigail Breslin). Initially, Lynn rebuffs Keane's friendly overtures, though not his offer of cash. The money eases her doubts or maybe it just reminds her of how lonely she is, and she soon invites Keane to dinner.  Suddenly, as the adults share small talk, and Keane smiles tenderly at Kira, the foundation of the story begins to shake violently. All the film's unanswered questions about this man, with his incessant chatter about a missing, perhaps phantom child, even his apparent lack of family and friends, start to surface and swirl, filling the cramped room like a poison gas. In an instant, Keane flips from a figure of tentative compassion to one of full-blown suspicion. Mr. Kerrigan isn't just playing with our sympathies; he's also playing with our assumptions. That keeps the tension going, of course, even as it also makes a strong case for even the most ostensibly unsympathetic and wretched among us. </text>
      <date>September 9, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>