<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The dark British comedy “Keeping Mum” exudes the comfy familiarity of a vintage episode of “Alfred Hitchcock Presents” stretched into a feature-length film. All that’s missing is a mordant epilogue by the master of suspense himself reassuring us with lofty comic hauteur that justice will eventually be visited upon the guilty. This particular story trafficks in the same black humor as the episode in which a mischievous murderess (played by Barbara Bel Geddes, if I remember correctly) ends up serving the murder weapon (a leg of lamb) to the police.  In “Keeping Mum,” Maggie Smith, her tongue digging a hole in her cheek, is Grace Hawkins, a seemingly angelic old lady who materializes almost Mary Poppins-like in the English village of Little Wallop, population 57. No sooner has she begun working as a housekeeper for the local vicar’s troubled family than she sets about solving their problems, large and small.  The stuffy vicar, Walter Goodfellow (Rowan Atkinson), has grown too pious by half, and his marriage to his beautiful wife, Gloria (Kristin Scott Thomas), is withering from lack of attention. Sexually frustrated, she is considering an invitation from her sleazy American golf teacher, Lance (Patrick Swayze), to run away with him to Australia. Meanwhile the couple’s boy-crazy daughter, Holly (Tamsin Egerton), is on the verge of running wild, and their adolescent son, Petey (Toby Parkes), is the target of school bullies.  The first indication that a miracle worker has arrived in the Goodfellow household is the sudden disappearance of a dog in the next yard that has been keeping Gloria awake at night. Other blessings quickly follow. Grace invites Petey to watch what happens when his tormentors pursue him on bicycles after school one afternoon. When the gang members appear, pedaling furiously, and try to stop, their brakes fail. Earlier we have seen Grace wielding shears and wearing a secret smile.  Grace revitalizes the Goodfellows’ marriage by visiting Walter in church and reacquainting him with the Song of Solomon, which sets his juices flowing. Suddenly Walter and Gloria are all over each other. Grace also introduces Walter to an ecclesiastical joke that leads him to pepper his sermons with religious humor gleaned from an Internet site, and his jokes make him the star of a clerical convention.  None of this is at all surprising. In the movie’s opening scene, set four decades earlier, the young Grace (Emilia Fox) is shown aboard a train on which her enormous trunk begins leaking blood in the baggage compartment. Approached by the police, she proudly confesses to having killed and chopped up the bodies of her unfaithful husband and his mistress and is sent to a prison for the criminally insane. Newly discharged after four decades, she appears in Little Wallop toting the same trunk.  It’s refreshing to see Dame Maggie in a lighter mode than usual. The role of a genteel psychopath is a piece of lemon tea cake she consumes in one delicate bite. Ms. Scott Thomas matches her in the ease with which she carries off the latest variation of her stereotype: the chilly English beauty with a volcanic libido. Mr. Atkinson embellishes the vicar’s ludicrous overnight metamorphosis from prune to plum with amusing comic touches.  “Keeping Mum,” directed by Niall Johnson, doesn’t pretend to have anything to do with reality. Except for the glaringly overwrought performance of Mr. Swayze, it is as determinedly British and old-fashioned as an Agatha Christie mystery consumed with cucumber sandwiches and a spot of tea.  “Keeping Mum” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>September 15, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>