<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The rollicking bar mitzvah comedy "Keeping Up With the Steins" should cinch Jeremy Piven's status as the go-to guy for scuffling, type-A wheeler-dealers in hip-hop-era Hollywood. (Goodbye, Kevin Spacey.) His character, Adam Fiedler, an insanely competitive talent agent, is virtually identical to Ari Gold, the rat-eyed attack dog he portrays with such bloodthirsty bonhomie on the HBO series "Entourage."  Mr. Piven's beasts, for all their ferocity, are warmblooded creatures cherished by their masters for their devotion and tenacity. Once they latch on to your trouser leg, they will never let go. Depending on who you are, they'll either kill you or kill for you.  "Keeping Up With the Steins" begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the movie becomes a family comedy oozing good vibes, generational reconciliation and (far-fetched as it may seem) a spirit of humility.  Humility is nowhere to be found, however, in the opening bar mitzvah sequence. This half-million-dollar "Titanic"-theme bash given by Adam's former business partner and archrival, Arnie Stein (Larry Miller), and his new wife Raylene, (Sandra Taylor) — whom Arnie salvaged from a wet T-shirt contest — gets Adam's competitive juices boiling.  The party, honoring the passage into manhood of Arnie's 13-year-old son, Zachary (Carter Jenkins), involves a miniature Titanic plastered with the salutation "Mazel Tov, Zachary!" Moments later the boy makes a grand entrance proclaiming, "I'm King of the Torah." As a thumping rap version of "Hava Nagila," performed by the guest star DJ Quik, announces, "Hava nagila, beer and tequila," the camera lingers on the tables of piggy children stuffing ice cream into their pudgy mugs.  Adam vows then and there to give his son, Benjamin (Daryl Sabara), an even splashier bar mitzvah. When Benjamin, a timid butterball of a boy still several inches short of five feet, is pressed to come up with a theme, he hurriedly replies, "Baseball." Adam immediately begins making plans to rent Dodger Stadium, serve pizzas shaped like baseball mitts (catered by Wolfgang Puck) and leave each guest a personal Dodger uniform. Neil Diamond himself must sing "Hava Nagila."  Satire is probably the wrong word to describe this hilarious first half-hour. In certain obscenely wealthy circles, this is how it really is.  "Keeping Up With the Steins," directed by Scott Marshall from a screenplay by Mark Zakarin, spends the rest of its brisk 84 minutes amiably retreating into niceness. Behind the camera as well as on the screen, the film, Mr. Marshall's directorial debut, is a family affair. The role of Adam's father, Irwin, a superannuated hippie who abandoned the family when Adam was a boy, is played by Mr. Marshall's father, the director Garry Marshall ("Pretty Woman").  As the guest list is being compiled, Benjamin, secretly and against his father's wishes, invites Irwin, whom he has never met. His grandfather shows up two weeks ahead of time in a camper, accompanied by his much younger girlfriend, Sandy Frost (Daryl Hannah), a k a Sacred Feather, an enthusiastic vegan who works on a Navajo reservation. The scenes in which this preposterous couple frolic naked in the Fiedlers' pool provide the movie's final laugh-out-loud moments before the whole thing turns to mush.  As in countless Hollywood movies where embattled families discover the true meaning of Christmas, Benjamin, with a lot of help from his benign granddad, learns the true meaning of bar mitzvahs. Mr. Piven's lovability quotient is essential to making this turnabout pay off. But as hard as he pushes it, Mr. Piven can get only so far in making the inevitable reconciliation between Adam and Irwin even faintly believable.  Irwin may be saintly now, but the fact remains that he walked out on his family 26 years earlier, and his feeble explanations don't wash. It's the kind of transgression not easily (if ever) forgiven. The movie's method of solving problems is to rush forward and gloss over the chasms of credibility. "Keeping Up With the Steins" would have been a much better film if it had waited twice as long before retracting its fangs.  "Keeping Up With the Steins" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language, flashes of nudity and sexual innuendo.</text>
      <date>May 12, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>