<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The mountains that rise from the Tibetan plateau make a suitably dramatic backdrop for this story about the murderous cost we humans exact on the natural world. Based on depressingly true events, "Mountain Patrol: Kekexili" tracks the heroic efforts of a small group of Tibetans   struggling to keep the Tibetan antelope, or chiru, from extinction. Although hunting the antelope was made illegal in the 1970's — you need to kill the animal to harvest its wool, which is turned into a rare commodity  called shahtoosh — the population dwindled precariously,  beginning in  the late 1980's and early 90's, because enough wealthy consumers had no qualms about hitting the boldface scene with shahtoosh on their shoulders and blood on their hands.  If that sounds like a recipe for piety and sob stories about cute critters, think again. Written and directed by Lu Chuan, whose first feature was  the well-received  "Missing Gun," "Mountain Patrol" is as tough and unsparing as its backdrop, a blood-boiling environmental thriller with a dash of Sergio Leone. Although the traffic in endangered wildlife gives the film its headline hook — you need to kill three to five antelopes to make one shahtoosh shawl — the story that briskly unfolds has as much to do with man's inhumanity to man as to his fellow creatures. Which is why, given China's historic and violent aggression against the Tibetan people, it's hard not to read the film on several levels at once.  The way into this unlikely nail-biter is through a young Beijing photojournalist, Ga Yu (Zhang Lei), who lands in this otherworldly  region in 1996,   armed with a camera and a well of idealism. His quarry is a mountain patrol, led by a former soldier, Ri Tai (Duo Bujie), that tracks poachers who, with their automatic weapons and hired skinners, leave thousands of antelope carcasses across the plateau. More action-oriented than expository-minded, Mr. Lu never explains why a Chinese journalist would find this story especially newsworthy. Ga Yu simply shows up, slips into his new environs (it helps that he is part Tibetan) and proves himself a quick study, whether learning the proper way to cut meat — draw the knife toward your body, away from your companions — or hopping a ride with the patrol.  Mr. Lu has an appreciable sense of narrative economy,  and it isn't long before the photographer is on the desolate road with the patrol in Kekexili, a region in the northwestern part of the plateau. Filled with astonishing vistas and a minimum of chatter,  this is the kind of film that invites you in with beauty, only to surprise and even shock you with a sudden burst of violence. The images of the men driving their trucks and dwarfed against the mountains recall, however fleetingly, the sweeping sight of pioneers framed against a different range in John Ford's "Wagon Master." Mr. Lu, a graduate of the Beijing Film Academy, has clearly watched his share of westerns, which is why still other scenes evoke Leone and, when two men, gasping for oxygen and spitting blood, chase each other until they drop, even Erich von Stroheim.  Despite the sporadic film-school allusions, "Mountain Patrol" has its own very specific take on things. Films about environmental catastrophes tend to wax preachy, putting pedagogy and scolding above art.  This one, for all its sorrow and the throb of righteous anger it provokes (only about 50,000 antelopes remain),  is more than anything a work of creative imagination. Filled with strange and horrible visions, it draws you in again and again, not with characters, who all  remain at a psychological remove, but with set pieces that distill the story's life-and-death struggle to its essence. The extraordinary scene of one  man  sinking into quicksand is characteristically potent, a reminder of the fragility of human life and the unblinking power of the world we dominate, to our peril.</text>
      <date>April 14, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>