<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>According to the paltry biographical information provided with the music documentary "Kill Your Idols," its director, cameraman and editor, S.  A. Crary, was born in Hawaii where he "learned how to march before he learned how to dance" and "held a gun before he held a girl's hand." That's cute, but perhaps more telling is that the video maker was born in 1978, just around the time that aficionados of orchestrated mayhem were paying homage to Lydia Lunch, then radiating spit and dark energy across downtown New York in her role as the lead singer cum banshee for the No Wave band Teenage Jesus and the Jerks. Ms. Lunch appears all too briefly in "Kill Your Idols," cropping up both in abused black-and-white film clips shot by East Village anti-auteurs like Richard Kern and Nick Zedd and in a rather more sedate recent color video interview shot by Mr. Crary. With her trademark sneer somewhat tempered and her familiar peekaboo décolletage in full bosomy bloom, Ms. Lunch makes for a resplendent, predictably entertaining witness to the whole No Wave scene  — an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave  — when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial),  the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand) and the only rich people trolling Avenue B were looking to cop a nickel bag, not nibble a $60 sashimi sampler. You don't get much of the old downtown trip or much of anything interesting in "Kill Your Idols," though it is nice to amble briefly  along memory lane with the jowly, dryly funny Glenn Branca (founder of Theoretical Girls), the perennially boyish Thurston Moore (Sonic Youth) and Arto Lindsay (DNA), who still looks as if he should be wearing a pocket protector and a "Hello, Ask Me About Our Specials!" ID tag, only grayer. Missing in action, well, there are too many to mention, though among the most notable is James Chance, who after leaving Teenage Jesus went on to create one of the bigger and more danceable No Wave songs, "Contort Yourself," two words that nicely describe the moment and its anarchic pleasures. That moment flickered out not long after it ignited, extinguished by success or (mostly) the lack thereof, along with the usual personal miseries and the seismic socioeconomic shifts that eventually transformed all of downtown, stripping away the dirt and the danger and making it safe for lifestyle lofts and those sashimi samplers.  But that's another story, one conspicuously and ridiculously missing in "Kill Your Idols." Despite his access to both No Wave luminaries and atmospherically battered footage of various bands wreaking  havoc at various venues, Mr. Crary never figures out what story he wants to tell. And so, after checking in with the oldsters, he checks out newbies like the Yeah Yeah Yeahs, whose connection to once-upon-a-downtown-time remains as elusive here as Mr. Crary's entire enterprise.</text>
      <date>July 7, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>