<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The kingdom that the central character in "The King" wants to inherit may be here on earth but not anyplace that is always recognizable. A dark vision of contemporary America stitched together from both clichés and some lived-in emotions and atmosphere, this fitfully engaging, finally exasperating film involves a young Mexican-American whose search for his patrimony leads him into the bosom of a deeply religious Texas family and, in time, a world of inexplicable suffering. Much like David Cronenberg's superior "A History of Violence," and Lars Von Trier's "Dogville," the point appears to be the return of the (politically) repressed, American style, though here it's unclear to what end.  We first meet Elvis Valderez (the young Mexican actor Gael García Bernal) on board the United States Navy ship he is about to leave for good. Having been honorably discharged, he packs up his few belongings, including a rifle that brings to mind Chekhov's adage that a gun introduced in the first act must be fired by the last. From there it's a short hop to Corpus Christi, where he casually tools about, checks into some fleabag digs and cruises a dewy young churchgoer, Malerie (Pell James), who turns out to be the teenage daughter of a Baptist preacher, David Sandow (William Hurt). The pastor, in turn, happens to be Elvis's long-estranged father. With a smile, the son approaches this man of God, his nominal king, searching for a place at his side.  Rebuffed by David, who waves away his son and the past ("that was before I became a Christian"), Elvis starts sniffing around Malerie. The girl, sheltered by family and faith, is as unprepared for his attentions as she is receptive to them, having no idea that her suitor is also her half-brother. One thing leads to another, as might be expected when a man as pretty as Mr. Bernal starts romancing a 16-year-old virgin with a domineering father, and behind the wheel of a 1969 Cougar no less. Unlike most teenagers, or, for that matter, Oedipus, Elvis knows precisely what he's doing, incest being only his first transgression. The intentions of the film's British director, James Marsh, who wrote the script with Milo Addica, remain more opaque.  Mr. Marsh, whose previous films include a documentary about Elvis Presley's appalling eating habits, "The Burger and the King," and a fiction-nonfiction hybrid, "Wisconsin Death Trip," about people driven to violent acts appears to have a taste for American Gothic. (In Mr. Addica, one of the writers on "Monster's Ball" and "Birth," he appears to have found a kindred spirit.) The Sandows are the sort of true believers that American filmmakers often condemn or lampoon (see "Saved!"), and generally fail to get a real bead on. Although the cavernous, antiseptic church in which David preaches and in which his other son, Paul (Paul Dano), performs with his rock band, initially suggests that the filmmakers are similarly inclined toward derision, the Sandows emerge as surprisingly sympathetic, largely because of the actors.  They have their work cut out for them. Unafraid of stating the symbolically obvious, Mr. Marsh and Mr. Addica lard their story with the kind of touches — David gives Paul the present of a monstrous S.U.V., and the two bow-hunt a deer — that seem designed to raise the suspicions and even antipathy of the film's presumptively non-Baptist, art-house audience. Yet while the appealing Mr. Bernal can do little with the cruel task he has been given, the rest of the cast, particularly Mr. Hurt and Mr. Dano, invest their characters with real feeling. They make you care about men whose fundamentalism and contradictions never get in the way of their humanity, which is a triumph of a kind for a filmmaker who evinces too little of the same.  "The King" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It contains incestuous scenes and murder most foul.</text>
      <date>May 19, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>