<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ear the end of "Kingdom of Heaven," a plaintive period epic from Ridley Scott about the bloody orgies of piety known as the Crusades, the camera pulls back from the tumult of battle. Perched on high, as if assuming the view of a passing bird or some divine being, the camera looks down on a medieval scene that condenses the barbarism that has consumed the previous two hours of screen time - the impaled flesh, the crushed bone, the hollow and inflamed invocations of faith. From this great height, the Christian crusaders and Muslim warriors below no longer look like men, like warring armies of God, but bacteria under a microscope. Outside of a couple of sneering papal emissaries, this high-flown image of men at war comes about as close to real commentary on the Crusades as Mr. Scott gets in his curiously disengaged film about the Christian incursion into the Holy Land. Written by a newcomer, William Monahan, "Kingdom of Heaven" is an ostensibly fair-minded, even-handed account of one of the least fair-minded, even-handed chapters in human history, during which European Christians descended on the Middle East for more than 200 years.  Given the presumed lofty price tag of the film, its global reach and the current state of world affairs, with warriors of different faiths and ideologies battling one another in the name of God and terrorism, this vision of the Crusades is not that surprising. Paint a majority  religion with too damning   a brush and you just may lose out on a nice chunk of the international movie market. The historian Robert  Wolff has called the Crusades a "long chronicle of greed, stupidity, treachery, duplicity and incompetence." Mr. Scott begins his chronicle in France, sometime before the Third Crusade, circa the late 12th century, with a grieving blacksmith, Balian, played by the young English actor Orlando Bloom, reuniting with a father he never knew, Godfrey of Ibelin (Liam Neeson). En route to Jerusalem, where he has long done his part for the holy war, Godfrey pauses to give his son both legitimacy and a title. Initially reluctant, Balian acquiesces partly because his wife's recent death has left him unmoored, partly because the law is hot on his heels, a story element that gives Mr. Scott license to very quickly - to borrow a memorable phrase from the director's last epic endeavor, "Gladiator" - "unleash hell." Mr. Scott is a virtuoso of movie violence and he does not disappoint on that count here. "Kingdom of Heaven" is filled with scene after scene of choreographed mayhem. Soon after Balian and Godfrey join forces, accompanied by crusaders whose numbers include a sword-swinging, rough-riding monk (a characteristically fine David Thewlis), they are beset by soldiers intent on bringing the blacksmith to justice. (Earlier, Balian both crosses the law and proves his crusader mettle by tossing a man in an open fire.) Amid a storm of very fast cuts and whiplash camera moves, sprays of blood and flying dirt, men meet one another without mercy. One crusader tugs at an arrow buried deep in his torso while another kneels, stunned in the dirt, gurgling blood with an arrow speared straight through his neck. After starting with a bang, Mr. Scott tries to keep us in his storytelling grip with many more visceral, frenetically violent scenes. Soon after they meet, Balian and Godfrey part ways and the son ends up sailing for the Middle East without his father. What follows is a shipwreck and a desert fight to the death (there are neither safe landings nor safe harbors in this part of the world), followed by a lull during which Balian grapples with a crisis in faith. The death of his wife has made Balian question his belief in God, a crisis that serves the character but robs the story of both narrative thrust and purpose, since it means that "Kingdom of Heaven" is effectively a Crusades movie without a convincing crusader. Both believers and nonbelievers joined the Crusades, driven into the Middle East from Europe by a variety of spiritual and political rationales. (One historian has called crusading "an act of love.") Whether the Crusades were offensive or defensive campaigns remains a matter of predictable dispute, though a dispute that seems - at least from this angle - beside the point given the ghastly death toll. Whatever the case, Mr. Scott carefully stacks his films with the righteous and the tolerant, keeping the real villains far and few between. In this context, Balian initially comes across as a kind of ecumenical Hamlet, pondering not death but belief, and then, when forced to protect Jerusalem against Muslim troops, a proto Henry V who rallies the faithful with yet another iteration of the St. Crispin Day's speech. Mr. Bloom delivers this unpersuasive speech amid a climactic battle during which the Muslim leader, Saladin, tries to wrest Jerusalem from Christian control. As played by the Syrian film actor Ghassan Massoud, Saladin looks as cool as a long drink of water. (That may explain online rumors that some Christians are up in metaphoric arms about the film, though this Crusade couldn't be better timed if it had been dreamed up by studio publicists.) With his creased cheeks and wind-snapped black robes, Mr. Massoud quietly commands his scenes with a hushed intensity that serves as a relief to Mr. Bloom's droopy sensitivity and much of the rest of the cast's gnashing and bellowing. Only an entertaining Jeremy Irons, in the role of the Jerusalem king's closest adviser, has a role juicy enough to withstand such furious scenery chewing. How it all comes down will be familiar to students of religion and cinematic spectacles alike. Mr. Scott and Mr. Monahan play fast and loose with facts and figures, but here the chief difference between history and Hollywood is that there are few bad guys outside of Guy de Lusignan (Marton Csokas), a baron whose dastardliness is immediately signaled by his French accent. "Give me a war," he growls to his henchman, played by Brendan Gleeson like some holy evil fool, complete with rolling eyeballs and a very strange dye job. Mr. Gleeson and the unfortunately cast Eva Green, as Balian's hot-to-trot illicit love interest, a desperate housewife who appears to live in some kind of fabulous day spa, bring "Kingdom of Heaven" perilously close to camp, which is depressing for a filmmaker of Mr. Scott's gifts. Equally at home in the future and the past, Mr. Scott seems born to direct epics. His ravishing visual style, characterized by a fetishistic attention to surface detail and unrelenting beauty, can work wonders with big subjects, but this is also a director who needs actors powerful enough to shoulder narrative and emotional extremes. One of the reasons that "Gladiator" worked as well as it did is that its star, Russell Crowe, could credibly put across one of Mr. Scott's typically anguished and existentially lonely heroes while wearing a skirt and gargling some very unfortunate lines. It takes an actor as self-serious as Mr. Crowe to carry the weight of Mr. Scott's ambitions; it also takes a story Mr. Scott himself can really believe in for the filmmaker to do the same. "Kingdom of Heaven" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film contains a great deal of bloody violence with lots of impaled flesh and a few decapitations, among other outrages. It also features some discreet lovemaking.</text>
      <date>May 6, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>