<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Arriving in theaters buffered by a built-in audience of upscale female tweens, “Kit Kittredge: An American Girl” appears poised to incite the kind of box-office frenzy more commonly associated with characters named Hannah and Harry.  Over the last 20-odd years American Girl — the savvy purveyor of magazines, books, dolls and television movies — has gradually won the approval of parents seeking an alternative to the vanity of Barbie and the sexiness of the Bratz. Its commitment to down-home values, meticulously researched back stories and be-all-you-can-be girl power has a seductive wholesomeness: alongside the flagship line of historical dolls (excuse me, “characters”), your daughter can play in a past where low-rise jeans are as unthinkable as high-rise apartments.  Written by Ann Peacock and based on Valerie Tripp’s stories for the doll of the same name, “Kit Kittredge” takes place during the Great Depression in Cincinnati (earnestly played by Toronto), where the jobless are in the streets and the middle classes are in denial. To 9-year-old Kit (little miss Abigail Breslin), however, the shambling hobos who haunt her affluent neighborhood have an untapped utility: as subjects for the article she’s determined to have published in The Cincinnati Register.  Kit’s Amanpour aspirations are briefly sidelined when her beloved father (Chris O’Donnell) loses his car dealership and heads to Chicago to look for work. Desperate, her saintly mother (a lovely Julia Ormond) opens their home to a motley collection of boarders, who provide the film with a lively core of adult performances and punch lines. Stanley Tucci is especially delightful as a smooth-tongued, secretive magician, while Joan Cusack, always more comfortable in vinegar than sugar, struggles a bit as a librarian whose personality leans more toward batty than tart.  Finding friendship  — and more than a little farce —  in deprivation, “Kit Kittredge” is a movie of missing men and lonely women. In Kit’s world the absent father (a familiar theme from girls’ novels including “Little Women” and “A Little Princess”) is an epidemic, and the picture makes this the impetus for children’s resourcefulness and emotional development.  Endlessly curious and cheerfully pushy, Kit pursues amateur sleuthing and hobo rescue with equal vigor, locking Ms. Breslin into a relentlessly spunky performance that restricts her considerable range. Less wearing are her closest sidekicks: a very sweet Madison Davenport as Kit’s best friend, Ruthie, and Zach Mills as Stirling, a delicate, jug-eared darling who’s sure to be breaking hearts before he breaks his teens.  A study in tolerance wrapped in a Nancy Drew mystery, “Kit Kittredge,” with its all-American ideals and old-fashioned rhythms, seems an odd choice for the Canadian director Patricia Rozema. Best known for her sharply modern and feminist take on Jane Austen’s “Mansfield Park,” this director does what she can to showcase female resilience in the context of a story unavoidably more invested in Kit’s color-coordinated, ’30s outfits than in the harsh realities of extreme poverty.  Nonetheless this classy, heart-on-its-sleeve movie is packed with laudable life lessons and Depression-era trivia, including the fact that the hobo sign of fish bones means really good garbage (particularly useful on the Upper East Side). But when you consider that a Kit doll, complete with book and accessories, will currently run you $105, the movie’s insistence on the nobility of the indigent might be a tad more difficult to stomach. </text>
      <date>June 20, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>