<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>imrod Antal's "Kontroll," filmed entirely in the Budapest subway system, one of the oldest in the world, begins with a disclaimer of sorts, delivered by a public transit official reading from a clipboard. Mr. Antal's request for access to the tunnels and stations underneath the city, this man says, were at first greeted with some apprehension, and he admits that the finished movie might not create a favorable impression of the subway or its employees. Still, he thinks it will be clear enough that the filmmaker's intentions were "symbolic." "Symbolic of what?" you may ask yourself, and chances are that by the time you surface from this nerve-jangling underground journey the question will still linger in the air. Like many modern allegories, "Kontroll," a tour de force of grime, fluorescence and destinationless velocity, is more concerned with atmosphere than meaning. Still, the chaotic world it surveys - a lawless realm that makes the title sound like a grim joke - is not entirely obscure or unfamiliar. The movie throws in its lot with a group of soulful, slovenly ticket inspectors, known as controllers, working stiffs whose function seems to be to serve as receptacles for the contempt of their fellow citizens. Identified by red-and-black armbands, they are not so much guardians of public order as embodiments of social absurdity. They look like bums, think of themselves as heroes and make their living where the sun doesn't shine. In place of a straightforward narrative, Mr. Antal cooks up a stew of genre conventions. Like intersecting subway lines, various plots trail off into the darkness. At times, when it examines the workaday routines of one particularly hapless group of inspectors - including a cynical, chainsmoking veteran; a gangly, unkempt narcoleptic; and an excitable rookie - "Kontroll" resembles a platoon picture or a police procedural. When its leader, a handsome fellow named Bulcsu (Sandor Csanyi), who left behind a promising aboveground career of some kind, meets a pretty young woman in a fuzzy bear costume, a whimsical romantic comedy seems to be blossoming amid the dirt and noise. But a sinister figure hurling passengers in front of oncoming trains suggests a serial killer movie, with Bulcsu in the dual role of chief detective and prime suspect. "Kontroll," which opens Friday after being shown today (at the Walter Reade Theater) and tomorrow (at the Museum of Modern Art) as part of the New Directors/New Films series, is both more and less than the sum of these parts. Mr. Antal is an exuberant stylist with a cranky sense of humor, but his aesthetic demonstrates more punk-rock bravura than postmodern glibness. Self-conscious as it is, "Kontroll," his first feature, also has a throb of raw, genuine life that distinguishes it from other recent examples of international provocateur cinema. The film noir and horror movie set pieces in "Kontroll" feel a bit perfunctory next to the loose, extended scenes of the inspectors trundling through train cars trying to cajole and bully reluctant riders into proving that they have paid the required fare. A ragged, hectic foot chase suggests that Mr. Antal may have a future making action movies, which would be fine as long as he doesn't clean up his act too much. In the end, in spite of Mr. Csanyi's hangdog charisma and the inspired clowning of his crew, the star of "Kontroll" is the Budapest subway itself, which comes to seem, if not exactly enchanted, then at least possessed of a scruffy, durable magic. It may be a symbol after all, of the ways that creaky, battered cities, by their simple day-to-day persistence, can become strange, mythic places, turning their scruffiest inhabitants into heroes. 'Kontroll' Written (in Hungarian, with English subtitles) and directed by Nimrod Antal; director of photography, Gyula Pados; edited by Istvan Kiraly; music by NEO; production designer, Balazs Hujber; produced by Tamas Hutlassa; released by ThinkFilm. Running time: 106 minutes. This film is rated R. Shown tonight at 6 and 8:45 p.m. at the Walter Reade Theater at Lincoln Center, and tomorrow at the MoMA Roy and Niuta  Titus 1 Theater, 11 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, as part of the 34th New Directors/New Films series of the Film Society of Lincoln Center and the department of film and media of the Museum of Modern Art.</text>
      <date>March 30, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>