<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>he recent popularity of Chinese-language action movies has been a curiously highbrow phenomenon, as filmmakers of lofty reputation, like Ang Lee and Zhang Yimou, have discovered the pleasures (and the profits) of swordplay and wire work. Their forays into action romance - "Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,"  "Hero" and "House of Flying Daggers" - are full of swooping choreography and thrilling combat, but they are also marked by a stately, almost reverent tone. Luckily, Stephen Chow, the writer, director and star of "Kung Fu Hustle" (and the earlier "Shaolin Soccer"), is around to knock the genre off its high horse, and to remind American audiences, as Jackie Chan did before him, that clowning is as much a part of this cinematic tradition as nobility and sacrifice. Though it features a number of stars from the Hong Kong martial arts firmament - including Yuen Wah, Leung Siu Lung and Yuen Qiu, who was also in the James Bond movie "The Man With the Golden Gun" - "Kung Fu Hustle" has a demented appeal not limited to specialists or aficionados. Hectic and eclectic, the movie snatches tasty morsels of international pop culture, ranging from Looney Tunes to Sergio Leone to "Airplane!," and tosses them into a fast-moving blender. After 90 minutes, you will be dizzy and perhaps a little annoyed, but those aftereffects, like the queasiness that follows an amusement park ride on a stomach full of junk food, serve as proof that you have been thoroughly and mercilessly entertained. A thrill ride like this hardly requires a plot summary, and in any case the story is deliberately cobbled together out of time-worn conventions, which it both obeys and mocks. In a vaguely defined "time of social unrest," with sets and costumes meant to evoke China in the brief interval between World War II and the Communist revolution, a pair of hapless lowlifes (Mr. Chow and Lam Tze Chung), pretending to be members of the dreaded Axe  Gang, arrive in a dusty slum known as Pig Sty. Their failed attempt to terrorize the residents, who are much tougher than they appear, attracts the attention of the real Axe Gang, setting up a climactic series of battles among legendary kung fu warriors. These include Pig Sty's stumbling-drunk Landlord (Yuen Wah) and his wife (Yuen Qiu), a foulmouthed harridan in a housedress and curlers, whose chain-smoking does not seem to have weakened her lungs much. The showstopping fight sequences are choreographed by the legendary Yuen Wo Ping (whose credits include "Crouching Tiger," the "Matrix" movies and "Kill Bill") and given an extra jolt of nutty inventiveness by some cheerfully crude digital effects. Mr. Chow and his special-effects team use computer-generated imagery the way  Chuck Jones and Tex Avery used pen and ink - as a form of anarchic protest against the laws of physics and the limitations of physiology. Eyes pop, feet spin and fists leave dents and divots on their targets. All that's missing is an Acme delivery truck and a ready supply of anvils. Although its blend of mayhem and spoofery seems ideally suited to 12-year-old boys, "Kung Fu Hustle," unlike the version of "Shaolin Soccer" released in the United States, is sufficiently bloody and profane to warrant an R rating. Mr. Chow, true to his roots, sometimes carries slapstick to the point of gruesome brutality, which shows a certain integrity: this stuff may be fun, but you can really get hurt doing it. He also, again in accordance with tradition, slides from the hard-boiled to the softly sentimental, with flashbacks to his character's childhood that set up a swoony romance with a mute, delicately featured ice cream vendor (Huang Sheng Yi). Her silence gives the picture its few moments of peace, while the Landlady's mugging and ranting supply a raucous comic vigor that makes the fight choreography and the special effects almost redundant. Yuen Qiu, a Hong Kong star of the 70's, has not appeared in a movie in nearly 30 years, and "Kung Fu Hustle" suggests that, in that time, world cinema has been deprived of a great comedienne. She is said to have gained 30 pounds to give the Landlady some necessary heft, but she seems to burn it all off on screen, as she tears through a performance that is equal parts Lucille Ball, Thelma Ritter and the Tasmanian Devil. The film itself displays a similarly manic energy, spinning around like a high-tech windup toy designed to wear out its users and keep going. There will probably be sequels, but to some extent they will be redundant, since "Kung Fu Hustle" can be watched again and again. This is only partly a compliment: for all its punches, kicks, whacks and thumps, the movie does not have much impact, and for all its affectionate nostalgia, it produces a strange kind of amnesia. It knocks the sense right out of your head, and its own as well. "Kung Fu Hustle" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and stylized but intense violence.</text>
      <date>April 8, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>