<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Far too many literary adaptations wear the fancy dress of high culture prestige or bind themselves into corsets of reverence. Pascale Ferran’s “Lady Chatterley” is different, and not just because it is a costume drama whose main characters frequently appear unclothed. It is hardly a canonical or faithful rendering of D. H. Lawrence’s once-scandalous novel —  Ms. Ferran based her film on an earlier, less notorious version of the book and made Lawrence’s earthy English lovers profess their amours en français — but who needs that anyway? This “Lady Chatterley,” winner of five César awards in France, feels bracingly fresh, vital and modern.  It is easy to forget just how modern Lawrence was, and remains. Even books that were daring in their day have a way of becoming respectable with the passage of time, as they are folded into the educational curriculum and the other machinery of middlebrow culture. Ms. Ferran restores Lawrence to the present partly by placing his themes in the service of her own sensibility.  A learned friend of mine, after seeing the film, remarked that it was not very Lawrentian, an objection that is not so much inaccurate as irrelevant. Lawrence’s quasimystical notions about sex and nature have been revised and to some degree refined. His eros of dirt and sweat and animal impulses — less pronounced in the version Ms. Ferran chose than in its better-known successor — are replaced by the sensuality of sunshine, wildflowers and fresh air.  Which is not to suggest that there is anything soft or overly pretty about “Lady Chatterley,” which is candid, unsentimental and, in spite of a nearly three-hour running time, remarkably brisk. It tells a disarmingly simple story. Constance Chatterley (Marina Hands) is a young wife not so much oppressed by convention as bored with her marriage and detached from her own feelings. Her husband, Clifford (Hippollyte Girardot), crippled by a war wound, has moved them to his family’s estate, Wragby (try saying it in French), where there is not much for Constance to do. Until, that is, she meets Oliver Parkin (Jean-Louis Coulloc’h), Wragby’s taciturn gamekeeper, with his taurine physique and sad boxer’s face.  Lawrence was one of the first writers to insist that sexuality was a powerful, transformative realm of experience that deserved to be considered on its own terms, outside of traditional moral and religious considerations. His three versions of “Lady Chatterley” (Ms. Ferran’s source is the second) push this view beyond what seemed, to Lawrence and several generations of British censors, to be the limits of acceptable discourse.  Of course what once seemed transgressive is by now old news. But if novels and movies about sex have lost their salutary shock value, many of Lawrence’s essential insights about human nature remain true. What Ms. Ferran shows, with exemplary clarity and subtlety, is the way sexual attraction, and the connection it creates, alter both Constance’s and Parkin’s perceptions of themselves, each other and the world around them.  This is not an easy change to convey, in part because the lovers lack words to explain what is happening to them. But the actors’ faces and bodies prove to be impressively eloquent, as is Julien Hirsch’s verdant, summery cinematography. The film’s sex scenes (there are six in all) chart the progress of desire from curiosity to intimacy and convey how sexual chemistry can turn into love.  The first time Parkin and Lady Chatterley make love, it is in haste, fully clothed, on the floor of Parkin’s cottage. Afterward the camera lingers on Ms. Hands’s face — her loveliness is more sweet than smoldering — as if pausing to interpret the enigmatic smile that plays over her features. It is a look of pleasure certainly (though not exactly of sexual rapture, given how quick and clumsy Parkin was), but also of surprise, apprehension and insight. Something unexpected has happened to Constance, and she appears intrigued by the prospect of figuring out what it was. And of doing it again.  Ms. Hands, still in the early stages of her film career, has a beguiling mixture of poise and naturalness. Her Lady Chatterley is both decorous and straightforward, a woman whose easy friendliness helps to bridge the differences of background and status between her and Parkin. Class, at least as much a preoccupation for Lawrence as sex, figures less prominently in this film than it might have. This is partly because the actors, speaking French while pretending to be English, don’t have the accents that would mark their place in the British social hierarchy.  But the contrast between Parkin and Lady Chatterley is not just a matter of privilege, and Mr. Coulloc’h and Ms. Hands complicate the stereotypes to which their characters might be vulnerable. He is timid and kind as well as rough, and she seems to be as comfortable in the woods as in her drawing room.  In stripping “Lady Chatterley” of some of its mystique, Ms. Ferran has rediscovered both the novel’s originality and the source of its durable appeal, which is not salaciousness but candor. She has made a love story that stands on its own, a film whose imaginative freedom perfectly matches the liberation experienced by its heroine.</text>
      <date>June 22, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>