<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> IT was just around the time when the giant eagle swooped out of the greater Philadelphia night to rescue a creature called a narf, shivering and nearly naked next to a swimming pool shaped like a collapsed heart, that I realized M. Night Shyamalan had lost his creative marbles. Since Mr. Shyamalan’s marbles are bigger than those of most people, or so it would seem from the evidence of a new book titled “The Man Who Heard Voices” (and how!), this loss might have been a calamity, save for the fact that “Lady in the Water” is one of the more watchable films of the summer. A folly, true, but watchable.  A bedtime story that plays like a stab at a modern myth, “Lady in the Water” follows Mr. Shyamalan’s sensationally entertaining breakout (“The Sixth Sense”), a pair of misfires (“Unbreakable” and “Signs”) and a raging bore (“The Village”). As before, this film involves characters who, when faced with the inexplicable, behave less like real people than idealized movie audiences: they believe.  Mr. Shyamalan is big on faith. He wants us to believe. In him. In film. In his films. To be swept away by that transporting swell of feeling that comes with love, sex, gods, the great outdoors and sometimes, though not often enough, the movies. Mr. Shyamalan wants to carry us away. He wants to be Steven Spielberg.  Of course even Mr. Spielberg is not Mr. Spielberg anymore (see “Munich”), meaning the former boy wonder of Hollywood is no longer content to tuck us into the basket on Elliott’s bicycle in “E.T.” and pedal off to Neverland. Even when he is gleefully blowing the planet to smithereens, as he does in “War of the Worlds,” Mr. Spielberg takes on the important issues now, leaving the easy kids’ stuff to manqués like Mr. Shyamalan. This can happen when someone matures, or at least goes gray. Though in Hollywood — which is something of an enormous incubator, where embryonic personalities curl up in their own goo, kind of like Neo before he unplugs from the Matrix — growing up is sometimes awfully hard to do.  That’s too bad, because Mr. Shyamalan has a nice way with actors, a fine eye and an actual vision of the world (scary but hopeful). Like Jerry Bruckheimer, he also knows how to buy great screen talent, no doubt at bargain rates. For this new film, he has tapped the excellent Paul Giamatti, who plays Mr. Shyamalan’s hero, a building manager with the torturous name of Cleveland Heep, and, in smaller roles, the fine character actors Jared Harris and Jeffrey Wright. Also along for the strange ride are other familiar indie-film types like Bob Balaban, Sarita Choudhury and Bill Irwin — who, having recently gone up against Martha on Broadway in “Who’s Afraid of Virginia Woolf?,” seems content to sit in the dark here doing precious little.  Mr. Irwin won’t be the only one in the dark, storywise and otherwise. For all its exposition — and, as a screenwriter, Mr. Shyamalan is certainly one Chatty Cathy — this film could have easily been called “Lady in the Dark.” It’s obscure in more ways than one. Shot by the cinematographer Christopher Doyle, best known for his superb work for Wong Kar-wai, “Lady in the Water” appears to have been lighted with a book of matches and a dying flashlight. The murky results are generally unlovely if occasionally striking, though, like Mr. Shyamalan’s decision to have most of the actors deliver most of their lines in a hush, as if they were courtiers tendering precious gifts, the low illumination does help create an air of claustrophobic intimacy.  Mr. Shyamalan has said “Lady in the Water” began as a bedtime story he told his daughters, to whom he has dedicated the film. There are all kinds of bedtime stories, those that lull you to sleep and those that keep you anxiously perched at the edge of the bed. This film, which involves Cleveland’s  attempt to save a water nymph, or what Mr. Shyamalan distractingly calls a narf (Bryce Dallas Howard), has the baggy, meandering structure of a parental yarn invented on the fly. And because Mr. Shyamalan works hard to be original, the story zigs and zags into unexpected corners, like the apartment where five of Cleveland’s neighbors sit rapping in a cloud of smoke, or under the pool, where a secret world lies in wait.  There are moments of charm in “Lady in the Water,” along with funny bits, some intentional, others not, and a satisfyingly big “boo!” It’s always pleasant to spend time with Mr. Giamatti, who does most of the heavy lifting as a battered soul in need of healing, though Cleveland’s haunted eyes suggest it isn’t emotional succor he’s desperately in need of.  Unfortunately, while Ms. Howard’s character, the regrettably  named Story, spends a lot of the film wet, she’s one of those juiceless virginal fantasies who inspire pure thoughts, noble deeds and stifled yawns. Disney’s Little Mermaid comes off like a tramp by comparison, which suggests that Mr. Shyamalan needs to add a fairy-tale revisionist like Angela Carter to his bedtime reading.  That seems unlikely, since he appears insistent on clinging to myths, particularly about innocence and faith, that serve the myth of his own genius. In “Lady in the Water,” an unseen narrator (David Ogden Stiers)  explains that while man once listened to “those in the water,” he no longer does, which is why we have gone to hell in a handbasket or words to that effect. Apparently those who live in the water now roam the earth trying to make us listen, though initially it’s rather foggy as to what precisely we are supposed to hear — the crash of the waves, the songs of the sirens, the voice of God — until we realize that of course we’re meant to cup our ear to an even higher power: Mr. Shyamalan.  That doesn’t make him any different from any other bubble boy with a fat paycheck and the slavish attention of a media that mocks his narcissism by publishing articles about his narcissism. Before movies could talk, the great director Erich von Stroheim stuck a von in his name and a monocle over an eye and strutted around Hollywood until the producer Irving Thalberg slapped him down to size. (Guess who Hollywood named an Academy Award for?) In “You’ll Never Eat Lunch in This Town Again,” Julia Phillips writes that Martin Scorsese greeted a news report about Sara Jane Moore’s attempt on Gerald Ford’s life with the line “You think this’ll hurt the picture?”  He was worried about “Taxi Driver.” It didn’t hurt, thank goodness.  Mr. Shyamalan isn’t an artist on the level of Mr. Scorsese; he’s just another film director who, having made a lot of money for a lot of people, was crowned an auteur at an age when he should have been deemed promising. The curse of the auteur fells a lot of filmmakers, in and out of the studio system. And paradoxically, the weakest link in Mr. Shyamalan’s new film is its story, which is filled with strenuously overworked bits and locutions like scrunt (kind of like a devil dog) and the tartutic (monkeylike creatures that descend from the trees). Mr. Shyamalan has yet to realize that one Giamatti in the hand is worth two scrunts in the bush, but maybe one day, after he’s recovered all those  misplaced marbles, he will.  “Lady in the Water” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). The violence is bloodless and rarely intense.</text>
      <date>July 21, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>