<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Lakeview Terrace,” directed by Neil LaBute from a script by David Loughery and Howard Korder, belongs to a reasonably familiar subgenre: the suburban psycho-neighbor noir. At the beginning, little suspecting what horrors lie ahead, an attractive young married couple, Lisa and Chris Mattson (Kerry Washington and Patrick Wilson), move into a lovely new house on a quiet cul-de-sac amid the hills and canyons of Los Angeles County. There is no lake to be seen, but the property does afford a nice view of metaphorical wildfires   in the distance.  Next to Chris and Lisa lives Abel Turner, single dad and Los Angeles cop, whose behavior rapidly escalates from odd to creepy to menacing to murderous. Abel disapproves of the rap music Chris listens to and the cigarettes he smokes, and holds opinions  that make his Prius-driving, liberal-minded new neighbors a little uncomfortable. He’s a law-and-order conservative who doesn’t believe in global warming, and his views on interracial romance would not be out of place in Jim Crow-era Mississippi.  The twist in this tired scenario — a variation that allows Mr. LaBute, not for the first time, to assume the posture of social provocateur — is that Abel is not your average white bigot but rather a righteously angry, or at least seriously crazy, black one, played by (who else?) Samuel L. Jackson. Abel finds various pretexts for abusing and humiliating Chris, but it’s clear from the start that this white man’s marriage to a black woman is the main source of his   animus.  His fury might be interesting if it were rooted in anything more than the filmmakers’ glib desire to play with the audience’s assumptions. The hostility of a middle-age, middle-class African-American man toward a younger, more privileged, racially mixed couple is a potentially interesting subject, fraught with bitter history and complicated sexual politics. But Bernie Mac did more with the topic in a few throwaway moments of the lamebrain comedy “Guess Who” than Mr. Jackson manages in all of “Lakeview Terrace.” Abel’s resentment of Chris and Lisa exists in a political and cultural vacuum, and turns out in any case to be explained by an episode from Abel’s past that will make your jaw drop (or ache from laughter) when it is revealed.  Mr. Jackson’s glowering, bellowing performance is so close to self-parody that I had to check the end credits to make sure I hadn’t been watching Dave Chappelle doing an extended version of his Comedy Central impersonation. But no, it was indeed Mr. Jackson, who is nothing if not enterprising. Whether he’s chasing snakes on a plane, chaining a wayward young lady to a radiator or persecuting newlyweds in the suburbs, Mr. Jackson can always find a new application for the snarling, sarcastic fury that has come to define his range as an actor.  In the past Mr. LaBute’s filmmaking has occasionally  risen above the level of minimal competence (and sometimes, as in “The Wicker Man,” dropped far below it). Considered purely as a formal exercise, “Lakeview Terrace” is a passable piece of hackwork, with some adequately suspenseful passages and a few mild shocks near the end. But the psychological dimensions of the story are so risible, and its supposed insights into race and class so wrongheaded and ugly, that irritation trumps enjoyment.  Mr. Wilson and Ms. Washington do what they can to bring life to an onscreen marriage that has been arranged solely to annoy Mr. Jackson’s character. The script fails to explore how their relationship might crack under the pressure of Abel’s harassment, preferring to complicate matters with a bit of left-field spousal deception. I won’t disclose the nature of the lie — you may  as well be surprised by something, since you won’t be surprised by how bad this movie is — but it may reassure what fans remain of Mr. LaBute’s rote misanthropy. Your neighbor may be a raging, racist nut case, but the person who’s really out to get you is the one you’re married to.  “Lakeview Terrace” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some sex, violence and strong language.</text>
      <date>September 19, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>