<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Nothing is better than a big, juicy steak" goes the double-edged slogan repeated incessantly through the last half of Robert Edwards's satirical allegory, "Land of the Blind." First mouthed by Thorne (Donald Sutherland), a shaggy leftist dictator who suggests a Maoist John the Baptist, the words are meant literally, since starvation is morally superior to consumption in the unidentified nation he rips to pieces with iron-clawed ideology.  As the fable goes along, that nation swings from extreme right to extreme left; yet at the end all signs point toward a spasmodic reversal of the pendulum. In its fascist phase (the movie's first half), this troubled Everycountry suggests Nazi Germany overlain with a banana republic in a multicentury, intercontinental time warp that alludes to everything from Iran under the Shah to prerevolutionary France. Its despotic ruler, Maximilian II, a k a Junior (Tom Hollander), is a demented little Caligula (or Napoleon) who has christened himself "president for life." Besides tormenting his incompetent toadies, his consuming passion is running the movie industry, for which he pumps out homemade action-adventure trash like his latest, "Out for Vengeance 4."  Junior eventually gets his comeuppance when his imperial bedroom is raided by Thorne while he and his tarot-card reading kook of a wife, Josephine (Lara Flynn Boyle), are playing a kinky sex game involving diapers and a ball gag. Thorne — a dissident playwright and guerrilla leader of the revolutionary Citizens for Justice and Democracy, who has been released from prison and made a member of Parliament in an effort to undermine his populist mystique — shoots the president and first lady and seizes power.  Under Thorne's autocratic rule, Everycountry becomes a pastiche of Communist China, North Korea, Cambodia under Pol Pot and Iran since the Islamic Revolution. Frightened women huddle under burqas, book burnings commence and the professional class is purged in grim re-education camps. Thorne even insists the traffic signals be reversed so that red means go.  "Land of the Blind" is narrated by Joe (Ralph Fiennes), the Everycountry's Everyman, who begins the film as Thorne's jailer and becomes his accomplice in Junior's assassination and, finally, an enemy of the people for refusing to sign a loyalty oath. As the screenplay's sour wisecracks fizzle around them, Mr. Fiennes and Mr. Sutherland play their characters without a smidgen of irony or facetious humor, and their performances in impossible roles lend "Land of the Blind" a frisson of gravitas.  But don't be deceived. Character is a misleading word to describe either of these stick figures, whose changes of attitude make no psychological or political sense. Why does Thorne, who won Joe's sympathy by spouting eloquent quotations from Shakespeare, Yeats and Eliot, become an enemy of literature? Did he undergo a brain transplant?  And why does the suave, chameleonic Joe turn into a priggish masochist willing to endure torture, beatings and solitary confinement, along with years of separation from his wife and daughter, merely for refusing to sign a piece of paper? Isn't he the same duplicitous guy who, during Junior's reign of terror, worked against the system from within?  Mr. Edwards, who wrote and directed "Land of the Blind" (it's his debut film), might counter that the movie is a Brechtian comedy that's not supposed to make literal sense: the big picture is what matters.  But the big picture is a mess. And Brecht at least created coherent mouthpieces. The movie is so clotted with references from here and there, now and then, that watching it is like poring over a quadruple exposure. Scattered around are some cute visual wisecracks, as when Thorne, his time having run out, is slain in a trompe l'oeil reference to  David's "Death of Marat," but such moments are few and far between.  And what's with the elephant herd periodically observed in black-and-white film clips? Might it  symbolize the herd of clichés stampeding through this dramatically inert film, which shamelessly borrows ideas from Orwell's "1984," then tramples them into the dust? Absolute power corrupts absolutely; fascism and Communism are two sides of the same coin; yada yada yada.  "Land of the Blind" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and scenes of torture and defecation.</text>
      <date>June 16, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>