<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Writing about American theater in 1957, the  British critic Kenneth Tynan sounded a familiar note. Modern American drama, he had discovered, is a family affair. Always there is the “confused adolescent boy, just awakening to the eternal mysteries of stud poker.” There’s “a strange,  stammering poetry” to this boy,  who is  right on track for “an emotional upheaval.”  There is also “comic relief” in the form of friends and neighbors, though in time we learn that “their lives too are founded on pain and insecurity and lack of togetherness.”  Tynan could have been describing modern American independent cinema in the main; throw in more comic relief and you have “Lars and the Real Girl” in the specific. An indie wolf in old-studio sheep’s clothing, the film is about a sensitive young loner (“sensitive as a snail’s horn,” to steal another stinger from Tynan) who heaves hurt by the bucket, but finally burrows into the warm, welcoming embrace of his community. It’s part comedy, part tragedy and 100 percent pure calculation,  designed to wring fat tears and coax big laughs and leave us drying our damp, smiling faces as we savor the touching vision of American magnanimity. It holds a flattering mirror up to us that erases every distortion.  Hollywood used to turn out these visions on a weekly basis; it still does on occasion, often by way of sports flicks, though no one sold this type of canned hokum like the old-school professionals. “Lars and the Real Girl” is an independently financed enterprise, which mainly means that it stars Ryan Gosling as Lars, has been padded out with actors whose faces will be more familiar than their names, and was produced with an eye for thrift with modest sets and Ontario locations. It was written by Nancy Oliver, who  regularly contributed to the HBO series “Six Feet Under,” and directed by the relative newcomer Craig Gillespie, whose only other official credit is the recently released big-studio comedy with Billy Bob Thornton called “Mr. Woodcock.”  Before  “Six Feet Under”  succumbed to the familiar serious-television malady and became as mired in suds as any daytime soap, with the usual complement of pathologies and predicaments,   it created a recognizable, lived-in world that balanced individual concerns against larger social issues. The specific flowed into the general and back out again. In “Lars and the Real Girl,” the general has been banished, as it too often is in American independent cinema. The film is set in an anonymous Midwestern town with pretty  clapboard houses, a busy church, bustling stores and even a hopping bowling alley that’s so removed from the larger world, from Iraq, Hillary, Rush and Britney, it might as well be  in deep space. It’s America, shrink-wrapped.  No one seems to pay heed to the nightly news here, but at least one of Lars’s co-workers surfs through the Internet’s racier offerings. This is how Lars comes to buy Bianca, a life-size doll with a ready mouth and monumental bust. The doll has something hiding under her skirt, but we never see Lars playing peekaboo because this is a story about innocence, not sad sacks having their weird way with artificial vaginas. More pointedly, the film means to be about  the generous spirit of everyday folks who, when their 27-year-old neighborhood loner with a funny grin begins lugging around a plastic sex doll, open their hearts and minds to them both — never mind the previous years of neglect that probably helped make Lars a little loony.  American self-nostalgia is a dependable racket, and if the filmmakers had pushed  into the realm of nervous truth, had   given Lars and the town folk sustained shadows, not just cute tics and teary moments, it might have worked. Instead the film is palatable audience bait of average accomplishment that superficially recalls the plain style of Alexander Payne, but without any of the lacerating edges or moral ambiguity. Lars’s anguish has nothing to do with the loneliness of small towns or alienation in the modern world or even real pain; unlike the characters in Mr. Payne’s films, he suffers without disquieting fuss or messy fluids. His infatuation with Bianca inspires clucks of sympathy and a little confusion, but the priest smiles indulgently, as do the old ladies.  It is a well-played con, particularly by Paul Schneider and Emily Mortimer as Lars’s brother and sister-in-law. Mr. Gosling fares less happily. With the exception of a delicate moment when Lars sways in a darkened room, his eyes squeezed shut in private reverie, the performance is a rare miscalculation in a mostly brilliant career. Lars is a difficult, maybe impossible character, a holy fool and a martyr in waiting, a subject of mockery and a  means of redemption. With his awkward manner and solitary habits, he comes across as more stunted than damaged, soft rather than hurt. Mr. Gosling smiles his goofy smile and begs for attention, but he never fills this conceit with life. Lars too is a doll, as pliable as Bianca and just as phony.  “Lars and the Real Girl” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). No man-and-doll sex, just courtship.</text>
      <date>October 12, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>