<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Queen Latifah has a beautiful smile and the sort of relaxed screen presence that can take some performers decades to hone, but even this superflack for Wal-Mart can't gold-plate junk. Based on the 1950 British film of the same title with Alec Guinness, from a screenplay by J. B. Priestley, this story of a gentle soul who learns to live only after learning of  her imminent death has been reconfigured as one of those generic wish-fulfillment flicks in which the soul in question actualizes her goals through perseverance and pluck. Real-life obstacles are immaterial; so too, at least here, is competent filmmaking.  The man credited with directing this lackluster vehicle is Wayne Wang, a promising figure in the American independent film scene of the 1980's, best remembered for "Chan Is Missing" and a raucous entertainment called "Life Is Cheap ... but Toilet Paper Is Expensive." Mr. Wang subsequently went Big Hollywood with nutrition-free trifles like "The Joy Luck Club," with an occasional detour into strenuously independent fare like "The Center of the World," about a man and the woman he hires for sex. Last year, Mr. Wang directed the cute-kid, cuter-dog film "Because of Winn-Dixie," which, in conjunction with "Last Holiday," offers further proof that the classical studio system, with its enforced professionalism, served most directors and audiences better than today's marketplace free-for-all.  The reconfigured screenplay by Jeffrey Price and Peter S. Seaman, whose credits include "Who Framed Roger Rabbit?," is as witless as it is formulaic. After receiving her deadly diagnosis, Ms. Latifah's Georgia sheds her church-lady reserve and swans into a European sugar-plum palace amid the rich and the craven. Armed with her savings and a newfound joie de vivre, she shops à la Julia Roberts in "Pretty Woman" and crosses wits with a nasty white guy, much as she did in "Beauty Shop," which feels like Lubitsch next to this sluggishly paced trial.  Lessons are tendered and absorbed, artery-clogging banquets are cooked and consumed, and Gérard Depardieu briefly stops in, as does Emeril Lagasse. Eventually LL Cool J hauls the happily-ever-after into the proceedings, and not a minute too soon.</text>
      <date>January 13, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>