<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Something wicked this way comes in the nifty horror film “The Last Winter,” crawling through the hallways and howling into the dread night. Set in the blinding white beauty of the Alaskan wilderness (though mostly shot in Iceland), the story brings us close to a small research team scouting the crude commercial possibilities for a large oil concern. Under the corporate rubric of “energy independence,” the company hopes to drill through the permafrost, a scheme that promises shivers that have nothing to do with the cold. Ah, but the ice is melting, melting, which makes the truth as inconvenient as it is deadly.  It’s amazing what you can do with a low budget, an expansive imagination and a smooth-moving camera. (A fine cast helps.)  An heir to the Val Lewton school of elegantly restrained horror, wherein an atmosphere of dread counts far more than a bucket of blood and some slippery entrails, the director Larry Fessenden is among the most thoughtful Americans working on the lower-budget end of this oft-abused and mindlessly corrupted genre.  Apocalyptic in title and tone, “The Last Winter,” written by Robert Leaver and Mr. Fessenden, breathes fresh air into a stale setup (an isolated group gone stir crazy or something) by insisting that our everyday horrors aren’t a matter of arid news reports but of feverishly real, terrifying life.  And death, of course: for the wind-battered and sunburned team running the outpost, debased life will soon beget anguished death, drop by bloody drop. But first there are signs and visions, cawing black birds and mysteriously thundering hooves.  During the day the team’s lead science researcher, Hoffman (James Le Gros), stares into the surrounding wild whiteness like a writer searching for words, for anything, in front of a never-ending and terrifyingly empty sheet of paper. At night he slips into the obliterating darkness with a company true believer, Abby (Connie Britton), who once offered shelter to the team’s boisterous leader, Pollack (Ron Perlman), a comic-strip villain with a cigar and a mouthful of gravel and nonsense.  There are others wandering the corridors, oiling the machinery, filling in the blanks and ably hitting their marks: a mechanic named Motor (the reliable Kevin Corrigan); another scientist, Elliot (a very fine Jamie Harrold); a stray lamb, Maxwell (Zach Gilford); a smiling cook, Dawn (Joanne Shenandoah); and a mystery man with piercing eyes, Lee (Pato Hoffmann), who seems to know more than anyone else but doesn’t ask and never tells.  Each adds another part of the story with a laugh, a gesture or even louder silences. Twisting his lips and adjusting his glasses, Elliot puts Hoffman into an even more eccentric light than he might otherwise appear, undermining our faith in the very character (the lead, perhaps the hero) toward whom the film seems to be nudging us.  The question of Hoffman’s role, as well as of his trustworthiness, hovers over the story, leaking into the camp hallways like a gas. With his soft, youthful face glazed red-brick and partly obscured by his beard, Mr. Le Gros invests the character with sympathy without making him especially likable. There’s something closed off about this man, despite his nocturnal visits and talks with Abby, as if he’d already surrendered part of himself to some other force. He’s the first to sound the alarm, though it isn’t initially clear if his early warnings, delivered with mad-prophet quiet and ominously scribbled research notebooks, mean that he’s the canary in the coal mine or the cat in the birdhouse. Our desire for a hero is as unsettling as it is instructive.  Against the vast white of “The Last Winter,” every man and woman eventually looks like a blot on the landscape, like a mistake. Working with the Icelandic cinematographer G. Magni Agustsson, Mr. Fessenden makes great expressive use of his natural canvas and its negative space, playing with the depth of field so that the whiteness either seems to stretch on forever or suddenly flatten, at times turning these fully dimensional human figures into silhouetted cutouts.  This metaphorically resonant visual trick works beautifully for Mr. Fessenden’s genre and political purposes, adding pathos and urgency to the creeping unease. Here, when someone’s nose begins to bleed, it isn’t long before that drip turns into a gusher.</text>
      <date>September 19, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>