<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At the end of Gus Van Sant's mesmerizing dream of a film, "Last Days," the director adds a cautionary note. Although "inspired" by the last days of Kurt Cobain, the film ends with a disclaimer stating that "it is a work of fiction and the characters and events portrayed in the film are also fictional." A similar disclaimer could have been fixed to Cobain himself. By the time he put a shotgun to his head in April 1994, it had become hard to tell which Cobain was real and which was fiction - tortured genius, reluctant rocker, henpecked husband, depressive, addict or martyr - a mystery that only deepened after he was nailed to the cross.  Putting a gun to your head seems a poignantly symbolic act of violence for a star as uncomfortable with celebrity as Cobain claimed to be. This gruesome detail isn't in "Last Days," the 11th feature directed by Mr. Van Sant and one of this year's indisputably great films. The filmmaker freely borrows from Cobain's sad story, but "Last Days" is neither a straight biography nor one of those forensic narratives so beloved by television producers. An impressionistic portrait, "Last Days" is, in many ways, less about the death of Kurt Cobain than the resurrection of Gus Van Sant, even as it is also about the mystery of human consciousness, the ecstasy of creation and about how sorrow sometimes goes hand in hand with the sublime.  Set in and around a sprawling stone mansion situated amid a lushly green countryside (shot in upstate New York), the film tracks the comings and goings of a young musician named Blake (Michael Pitt) in the weeks, days or perhaps hours before his death. Blake lives in this house with its peeling paint and expensively distressed charm with a quartet of stragglers - played by Lukas Haas, Asia Argento, Scott Green and Nicole Vicius - none of whom pay him much mind. Blake spends most of his time wandering the grounds and trying to stay upright; during the film he also takes a swim, builds a fire, digs a hole and plays guitar. He lives and then he dies, without drama, weeping violins or explanation.  Beautifully shot by the cinematographer Harris Savides and edited by Mr. Van Sant, "Last Days" appears built out of everyday scenes with no apparent rhyme or reason, and at first the whole thing seems disjointed, almost randomly organized. The film opens with Blake walking through densely forested woods and mumbling. When he reaches a small lake, he peels off his clothes, jumps in and swims to the other side, where he stands on a rock with his bony back to the camera and urinates. Eventually, he arrives at the house where, sometime later (days? hours?), he prepares macaroni and cheese, an undertaking that doesn't lead to anything other than undercooked pasta and a bit of comedy when, after the packet of cheese falls out of the box, Blake mumbles something about "a prize."  Like Jim Jarmusch, Mr. Van Sant belongs to a generation of filmmakers that was independent long before Sundance was a gleam in the collective eye of Hollywood. In the mid-1980's, while living in Portland, Ore., he made "Mala Noche," a rough-cut jewel of a first feature about a gay dishwasher smitten with an illegal immigrant. As the 1980's gave way to the 1990's, and Mr. Van Sant took on increasingly commercial projects, the rhythms and colors of his filmmaking voice, as well as an interest in outsiders so touchingly expressed in films like "My Own Private Idaho," were muted by louder imperatives. His adventures in commercial moviemaking reached a nadir with "Finding Forrester," a film he directed without any evident commitment to the material or his vision.  If there is a single theme that unites his films, even the most commercial, it is the figure of the outsider, from the druggies in "Drugstore Cowboy" to the gay drifters in "My Own Private Idaho" and Matt Damon's working-class genius in "Good Will Hunting." For the most part, these stories are classically shaped narratives with defined beginnings, middles and ends, outsider stories told from deep inside the confines and safety of conventional narrative filmmaking. With the 2002 film "Gerry," a formally austere work in which two men travel through desert landscapes during an unspecified number of days, Mr. Van Sant began to separate story from its usual time-and-space coordinates. Things happen in "Gerry," but as in "Elephant," released in 2003, and "Last Days," it is never clear when or why; they just happen.  In hindsight, "Gerry" appears to be less of a radical break from Mr. Van Sant's past than an attempt to find a form, a way of telling his outsider stories, that makes you feel as dislocated as the characters. "Gerry" unfolds linearly, but in "Elephant," which presents a shooting at a high school, Mr. Van Sant repeats scenes from different points of view, playing with time as if it were elastic. In "Last Days," day follows night follows dusk follows day, and scenes are, again, shown from contrasting angles. Blake doesn't live according to the usual workaday rhythms of rise and shine. He is out of time, out of step and in the wilderness, a dislocation underscored by the stop-and-go rhythm of his routine: he walks, he nods off, he walks, he nods off.  One danger with this sort of strategy is that impatient (or unpracticed) viewers might be tempted into nodding off as well; like beauty, boredom is also in the eye of the beholder. But for all of this film's leisurely interludes, the images of Blake shuffling and sleeping, "Last Days" makes for hypnotic viewing. There are shivers of pleasure to be had watching an artist like Mr. Van Sant working at the top of his   powers, and shivers, too, from the actual, physical act of watching a film that arouses both the mind and the emotions. The voluptuous beauty of the images, the tenderness of the storytelling, the cruelty of situation, the carelessness of Blake's houseguests - taken together, these elements create an extraordinary experience.  Mr. Van Sant met Cobain in 1991 and has said he was unfamiliar with the musician's work at the time. Perhaps as a consequence, there isn't much about rock 'n' roll in "Last Days" or, for that matter, Nirvana and grunge. No Courtney-Love-like figure makes an on-camera appearance, though there is a blisteringly funny reference to a woman that one houseguest solemnly and somewhat fearfully refers to as "Herself." Still, while some of the details of the story are borrowed from Cobain's life, including the greenhouse where Blake occasionally hides from the world and the Tom Moore cigar box presumably containing drugs that he digs out of the ground, Mr. Van Sant never suggests that these details constitute any kind of psychological evidence, a way into the dead man and his thinking.  Mr. Van Sant's refusal to root around in Cobain's consciousness, to try to explain why and how he created, suffered and died, is a radical gesture, both in aesthetic and in moral terms. In one of the most powerful scenes in "Last Days," Mr. Van Sant plants the camera outside one of the house's picture windows. Inside, Blake moves about a room, playing guitar and then drums before moving on to a new instrument. The music continues even as he shifts instruments, with the drone of the guitar merging with the beat of the drums and the haunting sound of the singer's voice rising and falling. Slowly, Mr. Van Sant pulls the camera away from the window as if to acknowledge the mystery of artistic creation and everything that remains unknowable in other people's souls.  "Last Days" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film has adult language, some discreet nudity and a little sexual romping.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>