<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>he rangy British actor Daniel Craig slices through a room like a shark cutting through water. Mr. Craig, who is a few years shy of 40 and rumored to be in the running for Sean Connery's old gig as 007, has given the charismatically challenged British cinema a much-needed jolt in recent years. Even when his movies are far from perfect, Mr. Craig grabs your attention by the raw force of his physical presence. In the underrated "Sylvia," he turned the poet Ted Hughes into a bohemian pinup, a man whose internal fires made him seem hot to the touch; as the rake in "The Mother," he eased from sexy to repellent without dropping a beat. Mr. Craig smolders nicely and, as it also happens, he looks good slipping out of his shirt, which he does in the entertaining gangster flick "Layer Cake." It's a measure of Mr. Craig's allure that when he takes it off, he easily upstages the young actress Sienna Miller, a new It Girl who barely registers on-screen despite wearing little more than lacey filaments that make her look like a gift meant to be unwrapped very quickly. For Mr. Craig's character, a drug dealer hoping to cash out after a proverbial last job, Christmas seems to have come early. Alas, a knock on his hotel door doesn't bring Champagne, compliments of the house, but thugs who roughly deliver Mr. Craig's nameless character to his next plot point. Directed by Matthew Vaughn, making a smoothly assured debut, and written by J. J. Connolly from his book of the same title, "Layer Cake" is the newest in British gangland entertainment and the tastiest in years. Despite films like "Gangster No.  1" and the success of novelists like Mr. Connolly and Jake Arnott, author of the excellent "Long Firm," about a gay East End hoodlum  in the 1960's, the British gangster movie looked as if it might have suffered irreparable brain damage after the success of Guy Ritchie's idiotic combination punch, "Lock, Stock and Two Smoking Barrels" and "Snatch." Mr. Vaughn produced both those films, but nonetheless learned a few lessons along the way, particularly about pacing and directing actors. In each case, he keeps the human factor pre-eminent. As its title suggests, "Layer Cake" has a notably vertical architecture: it stacks layers upon layers, much as "The Usual Suspects" piled on the kinks, though with a surer, more intelligible sense of story. Mr. Craig's character, who, for the sake of ease will here be called the narrator, opens the proceedings by explaining his trade (coke dealer), his rules (don't cheat) and his world (criminal). The narrator works for Jimmy Price (Kenneth Cranham), a thug with posh tastes and no conscience who would as happily wine and dine the help as blow out their brains. Set to retire with a hefty nest egg, the narrator lands in trouble after Jimmy asks him to track down the missing daughter of a more powerful villain, Eddie Temple (the reliably excellent Michael Gambon). Of course there are myriad complications, including a stash of Ecstasy, Serbian gangsters, a two-bit gangster (Jamie Foreman) with a trigger-happy moll, and Colm Meaney and George Harris as a nicely matched pair of muscles-for-hire. The narrator navigates through good and evil, along with fate and happenstance, trying to reach his destination without too many bruises and nicks. There is murder, intrigue and an array of nasty behavior, including an unnecessarily brutal beating in a restaurant that soon loses any point or plot relevance amid so many vicious body blows. The blood in "Layer Cake" runs copiously, but with few exceptions it tends to run warm, as if still connected to the body that spilled it. Mr. Vaughn is unquestionably in the entertainment business, but he doesn't come across as overly amused by death. "Layer Cake" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film has a sizable amount of bloody violence, including gunplay and one off-screen decapitation.</text>
      <date>May 13, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>