<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the good old days, around 1925, according to “Leatherheads,” professional football was a lot more fun, a rough, ragged enterprise, untrammeled by corporate influence and unconstrained by rules and regulations. And in the slightly more recent old days — the ’30s and ’40s, more or less — movies were also more fun. They had zip, pep, moxie, trains, hats and double-entendres.  “Leatherheads” makes the second case as strongly as it does the first, but mainly by showcasing its own dullness and timidity. The picture labors so strenuously to approximate some of the old screwball spirit that it winds up in traction. The actors, writers and directors who made those old studio whirligigs spin — Clark Gable and Carole Lombard; William Powell and Myrna Loy; Preston Sturges and Frank Capra and all the rest — made it look easy. By contrast “Leatherheads,” the third and by a wide margin the weakest movie directed by George Clooney, looks to have been nearly as hard to make as it is to watch.  Mr. Clooney, mugging and flexing his eyebrows and lingering needlessly in the frame when he should be taking care of business behind the camera, plays Dodge Connolly, aging star of a Duluth, Minn.,  football squad on the verge of bankruptcy. The professional game is a marginal, low-rent undertaking played in front of sparse crowds in cow fields. The glamour is all at the collegiate level, where lantern-jawed scholars in smart uniforms fill vast stadiums with ardent fans.  Dodge, a smooth-talking sharpie on and off the gridiron, persuades Princeton’s star player, Carter Rutherford (John Krasinski), to join the Duluth team. Carter and his oily manager, C. C. Frazier (Jonathan Pryce), agree. A while later Mr. Clooney and Mr. Krasinski punch each other in the face.  But in the meantime they and we make the acquaintance of Lexie Littleton (Renée Zellweger), a fast-talking, ambitious lady reporter for The Chicago Tribune who admires the sound of her own voice and the sight of her own legs just in case no one else will. They all do, of course, because the script (by Duncan Brantley and Rick Reilly) requires them to. It also stuffs Ms. Zellweger’s mouth with hard-boiled witticisms that have all the intoxicating fizz of Diet Coke.  But since it’s Prohibition, everyone drinks whiskey until the cops raid the speak-easies. The music, by Randy Newman, gooses the action along in a desperate effort to create an atmosphere of madcap Jazz Age insouciance, and the screenplay multiplies subplots in the same doomed cause. Before he was a football hero, Carter was a war hero, and Lexie aims to use her womanly wiles and her journalistic smarts to debunk his claims of battlefield glory.  This sets up a botched farcical climax that will require several viewings of Sturges’s “Hail the Conquering Hero” to chase from your mind.  Lexie, at least, has a clear goal in mind, which is more than can be said for “Leatherheads.” Mr. Clooney is known to be high-spirited as well as high-minded, and it’s perfectly reasonable that he would follow the earnest moral inquiry of “Good Night, and Good Luck” with a lighter, looser excursion into the American past. It is also interesting to note that all three of the movies he has directed (“Confessions of a Dangerous Mind” was the first) share a passing concern with the ethical problems of journalism and the conundrums of celebrity culture at various points in 20th-century history.  What is harder to comprehend is how Mr. Clooney turned out such a sloppy, haphazard and tonally incoherent piece of work. “Leatherheads” lurches hectically between Coen brothers-style pastiche and John Saylesian didacticism, while Mr. Clooney works his brow and his jaw and waits in vain for his charm to kick in and save the day. Unless he’s just vamping until the director shows up and gives him some clear instructions.  “Leatherheads” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual innuendo and comic violence. </text>
      <date>April 4, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>