<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The trouble with sequels is that most are obliged to outperform their forerunners in the most obvious ways. Bigger, faster and more spectacular is usually the rule. Strenuously applied to "The Legend of Zorro," the sequel to the 1998 blockbuster "The Mask of Zorro," that rule translates into busier, sloppier, less coherent and more frantic. Subtlety is out the window.  This fitfully entertaining mess of a movie was directed by Martin Campbell from a screenplay by Roberto Orci and Alex Kurtzman. Especially in its jampacked final 45 minutes, it leaps off the precipice like the rider who jumps (Zorro himself) from a ledge onto a speeding train that disperses a crowd as it races toward a tunnel. It's all accomplished by brazen cut-away editing. Beyond the breakneck velocity  of that editing, which generates its own momentum, little suspense is sustained; speed rules, but the pace is hectic and haranguing. All the while, James Horner's stampeding pseudo-Spanish score huffs and puffs, working overtime to conjure a bullfighters' marathon.  "The Legend of Zorro" brings back Antonio Banderas, looking considerably older and in some shots haggard and flabby, as Don Alejandro de la Vega and his alter ego, Zorro, the original caped crusader, invented by Johnston McCulley in a 1919 novel. The voluptuous Catherine Zeta-Jones returns as his buxom wife, Elena, a 21st-century Hedy Lamarr, who smolders even in repose.  In this sequel-ready episode, the fun couple come apart at the beginning of the story, then reconnect just in time to save the still-expanding United States of America from falling into the hands of Confederate villains armed with a new secret weapon, nitroglycerin disguised as soap; California's statehood also hangs in the balance.  This fantasy of American history, of course, is utterly bogus in the same way that the history trotted out in a movie like "National Treasure" is fiction. But, hey! This is just a rootin'-tootin' daydream of the Old West, a heck of a yarn whose relationship to reality is at best tangential.  "The Legend of Zorro" could be dubbed the family edition of the myth, since the fun couple have spawned a son, Joaquin (Adrian Alonso), who at 10 is already a fearless action hero who affects the course of American history. The unfortunate actor playing Joaquin has mouthfuls of cutesy pseudo-tough-guy dialogue that comes out sounding strained and affected. Look out, however, for Mr. Alonso, or for some other soon-to-be adolescent, to take over the franchise if it is to be picked up for further episodes, which is probably not a good idea.  Like "National Treasure,"  "The Legend of Zorro" throws in a large pinch of the occult. It imagines that in 1850, when California was just becoming the 31st state of the Union, a mysterious secret Spanish fraternity, the knights of Aragon, was scheming to rule the world through its agent, the evil Count Armand (Rufus Sewell), a school friend of Elena's. To Don Alejandro's chagrin, Elena seems willing to become Armand's new trophy wife.  Early in the story, the count celebrates the opening of a fancy winery that doubles as a front for his assembly line of explosives. Not even in the ritziest corners of Napa wine country have you seen a crowd as delirious or pyrotechnics as excessive as the fireworks bursting around Armand's mansion like explosive frosting on a wedding cake.  Unlike most his-and-hers action teams, Mr. Banderas and Ms. Zeta-Jones enjoy combustible chemistry; in a couple of backbending clinches they munch hungrily on each other's mouths, and Ms. Zeta-Jones seems genuinely dazed with desire when she comes up for air. Their chemistry notwithstanding, neither star is required to act beyond putting on a few stock grimaces. All Mr. Banderas has to do is to direct thunderous scowls in the direction of this or that villain. Ms. Zeta-Jones's principal task (particularly when wearing pearls) is to embody fleshy sultriness and to express mild indignation when vexed.  This is a hiss-the-villain, cheer-the-hero kind of movie. The slimiest of several bad guys is Armand's election-stealing, land-grabbing, cackling henchman, Jacob McGivens (Nick Chinlund), a grinning fiend with removable brown teeth and a hideous scar. His comically exaggerated caricature of evil embodies the collapse of the franchise that originally embraced and sent up clichés with a knowing sense of humor and a hint of subtlety. No longer.  "The Legend of Zorro" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has comic violence and some strong language.</text>
      <date>October 28, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>