<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Alain and Bénédicte Getty (Laurent Lucas and Charlotte Gainsbourg) are a sweet young couple living in a pleasant suburban neighborhood in the South of France. Alain has an exciting job designing computer gadgets — notably a remote-controlled Webcam — and one night he invites his boss (André Dussollier) over for dinner.  At that point in "Lemming," a new thriller directed by Dominik Moll ("With a Friend Like Harry"), things start to go wrong. The kitchen sink is blocked, and the dinner party is marred by the strange behavior of the boss's wife, Alice (Charlotte Rampling), who doesn't remove her sunglasses and throws a glass of wine in her husband's face.  The plumbing obstruction turns out to be a small rodent — the lemming of the title — which somehow found its way from Scandinavia into the Gettys' pipes. And Alice's outburst foreshadows more trouble to come: inappropriate sexual advances, a fatal gunshot and some vexing supernatural occurrences. All of this turns Alain's tranquil domestic life into a nightmare, something out of Alfred Hitchcock or Claude Chabrol.  Well, not quite. Mr. Moll is clever, and for the first half of "Lemming" he manages to imbue ordinary goings-on with inklings of strangeness that are at once sinister and quietly comical. But there is, in the end, less to this film than meets the eye.  The director (who wrote the screenplay with Gilles Marchand) flirts with silliness and gets lucky. Like other youngish French filmmakers — François Ozon, for example, who has also made use of Ms. Rampling's chilly, enigmatic charm — Mr. Moll likes to tease the boundary between the ghost story and the psychological thriller and to throw the viewer's sense of reality off balance. Is the lemming an omen? A metaphor? A hamster? Is Alice who she appears to be? Is Bénédicte?  Unfortunately the answers to these questions turn out to be not all that interesting, and the picture takes too long in answering them. Mr. Lucas, a likable, easygoing actor (who also appeared in "With a Friend Like Harry"), is too bland and transparent here to give full resonance to Alain's discomfort.  Ms. Gainsbourg is a more mysterious and unpredictable performer, but Bénédicte too is ultimately a cipher. The second half of the movie squanders suspense and momentum, solving its riddles by deflating them.</text>
      <date>May 19, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>