<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Career Politicians, the Fourth Estate and Disaffected Youth all earn a stern knuckle rapping in “Lions for Lambs,” Robert Redford’s big-screen lecture about civic responsibility and its absence in the Age of Iraq. Those who remain shocked, shocked that elected officials, certain journalists and cosseted college students sat idly by, huffing Hummer fumes and nodding out on 24/7 infotainment (all Britney, all the time), while the administration led the charge, first into Afghanistan and then into Iraq, may find much to embrace here. Everyone else will continue to nod out or resume banging their heads against the wall in bloody frustration.  I suppose there’s something commendable about Mr. Redford fighting the good fight, or at least one civilized version of it. Movie critics often flog directors for not engaging with urgent contemporary matters, like the current wars, but when they do engage, as several have tried to this year (“In the Valley of Elah,” “Rendition”), we complain that they’re not saying much of anything. Consider “Lions for Lambs” exhibit R  in this open case: It names the wars, presents a handful of fictionalized main players from politicians to soldiers, and drops words like “the people” and “Al Qaeda” and “propaganda.” It flashes photographs of George W. Bush, Dick Cheney and Condoleezza Rice, if without overtly naming names.  What else do we learn from “Lions for Lambs”? That America is no longer only the land of the free, home of the brave, but also of the opportunistic and the compromised. Among the most conniving, or most true-believing of these new Americans are politicians like Jasper Irving (Tom Cruise), a Republican senator with his eye on the White House. Among the most compromised among us, or the most exhausted, or timorous — or something — are journalists like Janine Roth (Meryl Streep), whom Irving has summoned to his office so he can pitch her a shiny new war plan. Mistakes were made, he says, but that was then, this is now. From their framed photographs, President Bush, Mr. Cheney and Ms. Rice silently keep watch.  Nothing if not on party message, the senator has taken aim at Iran, which, he tells Roth, is allowing Iraqi terrorists to cross its borders on their way to Afghanistan, where they will fight alongside Al Qaeda. As Roth leans forward, you can almost see the thought bubble above her: Howzthatagain? But Roth is also vain; she’s a journalist, after all, and rubbing shoulders, and who knows what else, with movers and shakers has blunted her senses, clouded her vision. Power is an aphrodisiac, as well as addictive. And power begets power, as Mr. Redford reminds us when he shows Roth looking at a Time magazine cover story she wrote about Irving. She helped make the senator and he did much the same for her in turn.  It’s fun to watch this acting odd couple spar even in such a visually inert context. Mr. Cruise pours on his characteristic intensity and lights up the board with alternating flashes of charm, sincerity, gravity, indignation and outrage. Every mood feels phony, a total put-on, which works well for a character delivering a self-conscious, constructed performance. As his audience of one, Ms. Streep’s journalist must do a lot of listening, which the actress does with one of her vibrant, entertaining, gestural performances. Every twitch, blink, shrug, head bob and seat shift speaks softly at first and then with increasing volume, giving physical form to the inner voice we actually hear only later. Mr. Redford’s camera pays her close, appreciative heed, as do we.  Alas, there’s more — namely two other story threads, the dreariest of which involves yet another two speakers locked in one claustrophobic space: a history professor, Dr. Stephen Malley (Mr. Redford), who has summoned an apathetic student, Todd Hayes (Andrew Garfield), into his office for a metaphoric spanking. One of those bright young things who puts the “i” in Generation iPod, Todd has been dodging Malley’s class, opting to turn off and tune out even while agreeing to drop in for morning coffee. It’s not nearly as much fun to watch these two, largely because the screenwriter, Matthew Michael Carnahan, has stacked the deck so much in Malley’s favor you know the end of the conversation as soon as it gets going.  It’s a long conversation, more soporific than Socratic, and brimming with parental chiding, generational conflict and invocations of Vietnam. You see, back in the day, Malley fought in that war after being drafted. He didn’t want to fight, didn’t agree with its aims, but he did nonetheless, which leads to another story fragment and two more of his students: a Latino, Ernest Rodriguez (Michael Peña), and an African-American, Arian Finch (Derek Luke). After absorbing Malley’s lessons about responsibility, Ernest and Arian joined the army. These lion cubs don’t believe the current wars are righteous, but they believe they can effect change from the inside, which is how they land in an Afghan misadventure more unbelievable, both in thematic and visual terms, than Senator Irving’s military strategy.  In truth Ernest and Arian are less lions than sacrificial lambs that exist solely so the film can wave the flag (and race and poverty) along with index fingers. Malley regrets but respects the students’ decision to enlist, which echoes the prevailing wisdom that you should support the troops even if you don’t support the wars. The problem isn’t whether this assertion is true; the problem is the film reflexively embraces it, much as it does every single other cliché, without inquiry, challenge or a single ounce of real risk. It tells us everything most of us know already, including the fact that politicians lie, journalists fail and youth flounders. Mostly it tells us that Mr. Redford feels really bad about the state of things. Welcome to the club.  “Lions for Lambs” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Some bloody combat scenes, gun violence and tough language.</text>
      <date>November 9, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>