<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The 27-year-old protagonist of Steve Buscemi's deadpan comedy "Lonesome Jim" lives out the worst nightmare of every bushy-tailed go-getter who moves to New York to Be Somebody (in his case, a writer) and fails miserably. After eking out a living as a dog walker, Jim (Casey Affleck) skulks back to his parents' home in rural Indiana with no idea of what to do next. As Robert Frost observed, "Home is the place where, when you have to go there, they have to take you in."  In describing "Lonesome Jim," I use the term comedy advisedly, since the subject of the movie is depression, and the movie's sense of humor is only as broad as the Mona Lisa's smile. As for Indiana, the self-described "crossroads of America," I doubt there is a chamber of commerce in the entire Hoosier State that would endorse this portrait of it as the country's capital of boredom and despair.  "Lonesome Jim," written by James C. Strouse, is the third feature film directed by Mr. Buscemi, whose 1996 movie, "Trees Lounge," depicted a similar state of ennui gripping a town  in suburban Long Island. Mr. Buscemi also wrote and starred in that small gem of a movie, which had more psychological nuance than this emotionally cauterized slice of minimalist malaise.  While Jim's robotically perky mother, Sally (Mary Kay Place), makes a fuss over him, his father, Don (Seymour Cassel), greets him with a wary scowl. His deadbeat older brother,  Tim (Kevin Corrigan), a divorced father of two young girls who lives at home at 34, is so consumed by disappointment that he barely acknowledges Jim's return. When the brothers finally compare notes, Jim sweetly observes that he may be a mess but that Tim is a disaster.   Tim responds by deliberately  slamming his car into a tree and nearly dies.  Video: Movie Minutes Stephen Holden reviews Steve Buscemi's "Lonesome Jim," a deadpan comedy about a depressed writer who returns in defeat to his parents' home in rural Indiana.  Jim's father pressures him to work on the assembly line in  the family's ladder factory, and before long,  he gives in. There he meets Stacy, a k a Evil (Mark Boone Junior), a scruffy, motorcycle-driving drug dealer and the only character in the movie who hasn't fully succumbed to  lethargy.  Jim also hooks up with Anika (Liv Tyler, slightly more expressive than usual), a good-hearted nurse and the divorced mother of a smart young boy. Although their first sexual encounter is consummated in less than five seconds, Anika doesn't seem to mind much and returns for more.  "Lonesome Jim" would be a stronger movie if Mr. Affleck had the wherewithal to bare more of the passive-aggressive rage inside a character who contemplates the world with a hangdog, poker-faced stare and drones his dialogue in a neutral monotone.  That attitude  is  convincingly struck,   but a more resourceful actor would have used  this blank slate to scrawl a thousand telling details about the feelings percolating below the surface.  "Lonesome Jim" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and strong language.</text>
      <date>March 24, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>