<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>n "The Longest Yard," the crummy remake of the 1974 film of the same title, Adam Sandler stars as the former N.F.L. quarterback Paul Crewe, who years earlier was booted out of the league for shaving points. In the original film, directed with seriocomic facility by the great Robert Aldrich, Crewe was played by Burt Reynolds with effortless charm, tufts of visible chest hair and the tightest pants this side of Tony Orlando. Finding a perfect groove as the fallen hero, Mr. Reynolds didn't attempt to ingratiate himself with the audience or make nice; he knew that we would fall for him anyway. Mr. Reynolds is also on hand for the remake, and here's hoping he  snagged a nice fat paycheck for his trouble and ours. This time, the actor plays the role of a former college ballplayer, Nate Scarborough, who has been kicking around a dusty Texas prison yard for decades and wants to lend Mr. Sandler's character a helping coaching hand. As in the earlier movie, Crewe has landed in jail after violating parole and resisting arrest, among other infractions. He has also attracted the attention of Warden Hazen (James Cromwell), a cookie-cutter martinet who thinks he can use Crewe to improve his semi-pro team made up of guards and headed by Captain Knauer (William Fichtner, stuck playing a baddie once again). The new movie was written by Sheldon Turner, whose contribution to Tracy Keenan Wynn's original screenplay consists of the usual updating, including a lame bit about the television show "The View." It's uncertain, however, whether Mr. Turner or the director Peter Segal deserves the blame for the opportunistic use of Malcolm X's image in one scene. This iconic image pops up in a scene that, like much of the movie, plays a lot like the original, albeit with some instructive differences. In the scene, a couple of white prison guards try to bait a black member of Crewe's team, here named Megget and nicely played by the rapper Nelly. Megget smartly refuses to take the bait. But because the filmmakers want to make sure we don't think he's a coward, they toss in Malcolm X. Leaving aside the idea that the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. might have made  more sense in a scene hinged to passive resistance, this scene indicates just how little faith the filmmakers have in their audience and how much anxiety they have about what it means to be a man. Only with Malcolm X watching over him can Megget be forgiven for not talking back, for not getting his skull cracked, for not getting tossed off the team; only with Malcolm X serving as his symbolic guardian angel, it seems, can he be a real black man. One of the points that Aldrich makes in his movie is that the character is smart enough to bide his time. His courageous resistance inspires other black inmates to join forces with Crewe to fight what is, after all, a common enemy. Aldrich didn't haul out Malcolm X to pump up his football saga and curry favor with the audience, partly because the film's larger theme - the relentless pursuit of power - transcends racial lines. In the remake, Warden Hazen wants to use his football team as part of his strategy to assume the state governorship. The original  Hazen (played by Eddie Albert, doing a 180-degree turn from his affable role on the sitcom "Green Acres") simply covets power,  a rather more nihilistic take on what it means to live and to play ball. For Aldrich, football isn't just another Sunday night entertainment, it is emblematic of the human condition. The trappings of that entertainment - the cheerleaders, marching bands and cheering crowds - are secondary to the game's camaraderie, strategies and meaning. You play, therefore you are. The first "Longest Yard" doesn't represent Aldrich and 1970's American moviemaking at their finest, but it certainly moves better and skews smarter than the remake. Softer, louder and cleaner than the 1974 version, the new film sentimentalizes the prisoners and the game, filing down their sharpest edges so that winning becomes a matter of triumph rather than resistance. In this respect, it is worth noting that the new film contains more speaking parts for  black actors than the original. First  among these unequals is Chris Rock, who as Crewe's right-hand man, Caretaker, has assumed the humiliating job of playing second banana to a less-gifted comedic talent. But like the hip-hop-heavy soundtrack, these speaking roles are mere calculation, a crude ploy to lure in black audiences and to make white audiences feel cool by proxy. Unlike Mr. Reynolds, Mr. Sandler has never been cool. Mr. Sandler's talent, such as it is, has been his ability to embody a strain of everyday guyness characterized by an undercurrent of aggression and a thick overlay of smug. At his best (notably, the drag-down fight with Bob Barker in "Happy Gilmore"), Mr. Sandler brings the American primitive male to instantly recognizable, abrasive life. The director Paul Thomas Anderson tapped into that primitivism in his film "Punch-Drunk Love," but Mr. Sandler needs more off-center roles if he is going to transcend his rapidly aging frat-boy  persona. Both last year's "Spanglish," in which he played a family man, and "The Longest Yard" appear to be part of a strategy aimed at turning Mr. Sandler into an adult. But that can't happen with movies made by thumb-suckers for the delectation of other thumb-suckers. "The Longest Yard" is rated PG-13  (Parents strongly cautioned).  It features football violence, homophobic jokes and an intimation of gun violence.</text>
      <date>May 27, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>