<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Ritual. Pattern. Repetition.”  Those words are intoned in voice-over by Chris Pratt (Joseph Gordon-Levitt), a brain-damaged bank janitor who narrates the screenwriter Scott Frank’s directorial debut, the Midwestern crime drama “The Lookout.” They’re catch phrases learned in therapy, designed to help Chris regain the sense of chronology he lost in a car accident. But they also acknowledge that “The Lookout” is a new version of a very old story: A nobody falls in with scuzzball crooks who make him feel like somebody.  Scuzzball No. 1 is Gary Spargo (Matthew Goode), a former classmate who taps Chris to play lookout in a planned robbery of Chris’s suburban bank in Kansas City, Kan. No. 2 is Bone (Greg Dunham), a longhaired, trench-coated killer who looks like a “Matrix” character played by Sam Shepard. No. 3 is a former stripper who calls herself Luvlee Lemons (Isla Fisher). Is she more wholesome than her companions, or does it just seem that way because she puts on a frumpy nightgown before seducing Chris?  Mr. Frank’s screenplay for “The Lookout” was long considered one of Hollywood’s great unproduced scripts. The end product doesn’t justify that buildup. Some of the minor characters are thinly drawn (particularly Luvlee, who never manifests the femme fatale qualities her plot function seems to require). And Chris’s last-act conversion from sad-sack patsy to devious score-settler is not persuasive. Still, there’s a lot to like here, and the film’s bleak setting and empathetic tone add interest to what could have been a by-the-numbers affair.  Mr. Frank, who is best known for adapting the Elmore Leonard novel “Out of Sight” for Steven Soderbergh, has a clean, purposeful directing style, particularly in the quick-cut sequences that show Chris shambling through his daily routine. And he displays sincere interest in Chris’s roiling emotions, which are grasped only by his best friend and roommate, the blind ex-criminal Lewis (Jeff Daniels).  With its country music characterizations and its wintry panoramas (by the snow specialist Alar Kivilo, who also shot “A Simple Plan”) “The Lookout” feels less like a modern film noir than a social drama with noir trappings. Several major characters live with mental or physical afflictions (even Gary, who carries the go-to accessory of modern screen goons, an inhaler). The potential haul is pocket change compared to the amounts bandied about in Jerry Bruckheimer epics, and some of the participants seem as though they would back out if they sensed there was another quick way to improve their social station.  Even Chris falls into this category.  The son of a pompous rich man (Bruce McGill),  he is determined to make his own way despite handicaps that he refuses to see as handicaps. He would not have gotten involved with Gary if his condescending boss had allowed him to train as a teller; a rare encouraging statement by that same boss spurs his 11th-hour doubts.  The movie is worth seeing for its cast. Like Lee Marvin in his thug mode, Mr. Goode, with his mix of intelligence, cruelty and self-loathing, is both repugnant and fascinating. Mr. Daniels initially seems to overplay the blind man’s eccentric charisma until you realize that Lewis has fashioned himself into a “character” to mask his feelings of dependence.  Ms. Fisher’s tricky line readings suggest that Luvlee is not the plush waif she appears to be,  particularly in a scene in which Lewis reveals how he lost his sight, and she deadpans, “That is a sad story.  I’m sorry, if it’s true.”  Most impressive of all is Mr. Gordon-Levitt, who is convincing as one of cinema’s most difficult archetypes: the reactive protagonist whose complex emotions are visible to the viewer but invisible to his fellow characters. As he did in “Mysterious Skin,” Mr. Gordon-Levitt conveys damaged decency without special pleading; his average-guy introspection recalls Timothy Bottoms in “The Last Picture Show.” He’s a sweet stoic.  “The Lookout” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language, some violence and sexual content.</text>
      <date>March 30, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>