<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One of the running gags in "Looking for Comedy in the Muslim World" is that Albert Brooks - the director, screenwriter and star, as well as the main character - is best known around the world for his role in "Finding Nemo." Or as it is more frequently and humiliatingly put, for playing a talking fish in a cartoon.  Mr. Brooks likes to deprecate both himself and the work for hire he does in Hollywood, but the difference between "Nemo" and his own films may not be as great as he pretends. Whether or not they are named Albert Brooks, his anxious, baffled, passive-aggressive alter egos are always fish out of water, made perpetually uncomfortable by the ordinary business of the world.  Mr. Brooks has pursued this premise on the open road ("Lost in America"), in the hereafter ("Defending Your Life") and in his own backyard (in "Modern Romance," "Mother" and "The Muse"). "Looking for Comedy" ranges farther afield - all the way to India and Pakistan - and as a consequence is less introspective than those earlier pictures, though the character named "Albert Brooks" is no less self-involved. This film's humor is based on the obvious discrepancies of culture and temperament that are its subject, and it tiptoes across a minefield of political sensitivities on its way to a handful of pretty good jokes.  Unfortunately, there are not quite enough of those to carry an audience through 98 minutes. Like many movies of its kind, "Looking for Comedy" is front-loaded with inspired gags, and the first half-hour is both sneakily and explosively funny, raising expectations that are never quite met. Mr. Brooks generates a lot of momentum from a conceit that seems at once utterly ludicrous and strangely plausible, namely that an American comedian might be sent overseas by the State Department to see what tickles Islam's funny bone.  Fred Dalton Thompson, the lawyer-turned-actor-turned-senator-turned-actor (who regularly plays a lawyer), is in charge of the project, which arises from a candid acknowledgment that there are large swaths of the world's population that the American government just doesn't get. "The Africans, the Chinese," Mr. Thompson enumerates, "but most of all the Muslims." Mr. Brooks - not the administration's first choice, but good enough - is dispatched to Delhi with two bureaucratic sidekicks (John Carroll Lynch and Jon Tenney), one of them a devoted fan. The comedian's assignment - for which he is promised a Medal of Freedom - is to produce a 500-page report on what makes Muslims laugh. While he's at it, he might throw in something on the Hindus, too.  Once in India, he hires a perky, naïve young assistant named Maya (Sheetal Sheth) to help him with the document, but she is able to produce only a few pages of notes. "Looking for Comedy" experiences a similar shortfall, noodling and meandering through colorful settings and promising set-ups as its farcical vigor and satirical rigor drain inexorably away.  It turns out that Mr. Brooks's interest in the nature of comedy is less anthropological than philosophical. His approach to the contemporary clash of civilizations - surely a ripe subject for risky, queasy humor - is curiously timid, as well as lazy. Like the comedians surveyed in "The Aristocrats," Paul Provenza and Penn Jillette's documentary essay on the world's dirtiest joke, "Looking for Comedy in the Muslim World" is best understood as an inquiry into the theory and lore of professional comedy. But unlike "The Aristocrats," which managed to be both shocking and smart, this movie's abstract, cerebral quality becomes both puzzling and boring.  Mr. Brooks has never been one for obvious belly laughs or zany physical comedy; you have to work a bit to appreciate his humor, which is fine when the jokes themselves work. A meeting with Al Jazeera network executives (they want to pitch a sitcom idea) is funny enough in itself, and made appreciably more so by the fact that Mr. Brooks wears what he takes to be the local attire while his interlocutors are dressed in sober business suits. The real punch line comes when Mr. Brooks's fictional wife (Amy Ryan) wonders if he should be so quick to turn down television money.  But other situations sputter and falter, and plot lines - including one involving Maya's jealous Iranian boyfriend (Homie Doroodian) - never really gather momentum. Mr. Brooks's screen persona, while as worried and put-upon as ever, also seems strangely becalmed, and his self-absorption, which expanded movies like "Lost in America" and "Defending Your Life" into full-blown studies of cultural malaise, shrinks "Looking for Comedy" into a series of hit-or-miss riffs.  In one of these, Mr. Brooks, caught up in conversation, walks right past the Taj Mahal without noticing it. There is some resonance in the conceit of an American so wrapped up in himself that he misses the reality of the rest of the world even when right there, larger than life, all but staring him in the face. Still, making the joke at his own expense doesn't quite get Mr. Brooks off the hook. "Looking for Comedy in the Muslim World" is really about finding Albert Brooks wherever you look, and leaving the Muslim world to fend for - or laugh at - itself.  "Looking for Comedy in the Muslim World" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some naughty innuendoes and strong language.</text>
      <date>January 20, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>