<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ords of Dogtown," directed by Catherine Hardwicke from a script by Stacy Peralta, is about a minor pop-cultural earthquake made possible by the serendipitous convergence, in Los Angeles in 1975, of two otherwise unremarkable events. One was a drought that emptied the region's swimming pools, leaving their smooth, curving concrete interiors available for other uses, and the other was the arrival, in a Santa Monica surf shop, of a paper bag full of urethane wheels. Attached to a skateboard, these wheels enabled a skilled rider to execute hard turns; long, easy glides; and quick changes of direction. In an empty swimming pool or along a section of concrete pipe, skateboarding could at last realize its potential to become the land-based equivalent of surfing, with its own ethos, its own stars and its own marketing possibilities. Mr. Peralta, one of the founders of this legend-shrouded subculture (played in the film by John Robinson, a slender, pretty young actor introduced to movie audiences in Gus Van Sant's "Elephant"), has lately emerged as its leading cinematic historian. "Lords of Dogtown" represents both a dramatic expansion and a narrative compression of the story he told in "Dogtown and Z Boys," an energetic documentary released in 2002. This film follows the knot of teenage boys at the center of the Venice, Calif., skateboarding scene - Mr. Peralta, Tony Alva (Victor Rasuk), Jay Adams (Emile Hirsch) and Sid Gianetti (Michael Angarano) - as they grapple with rivalry, family problems and the consequences of sudden fame. They must also struggle with their shaggy mentor, Skip Engblom, owner of the Zephyr surfboard shop and a less than ideal role model. Played by Heath Ledger in what seems to be a demented tribute to Val Kilmer's performance in "The Doors," Skip is always volatile, frequently drunk and consistently the most entertaining figure in the movie. Which is saying something, since "Lords of Dogtown," from start to finish, is pretty much a blast. Ms. Hardwicke, whose previous film as a director was "Thirteen," shares with Mr. Peralta an enthusiastic interest in young people that is neither condescending nor exploitative. Drawing on her long experience as a production designer (and on the skills of her director of photography, Elliot Davis, who also shot "Thirteen"), she has given the movie an appropriately scruffy, unpolished look consistent with the resourceful, do-it-yourself aesthetic of the place and time it depicts. She and Mr. Peralta are more interested in evoking a milieu than in telling a story, and their scenes have both the loose, stop-and-start rhythms of a long summer day and the restless, competitive energy of young men in the heat of adolescence. What plot there is consists of a set of familiar signposts and crises - girl trouble, family trouble, emotional trouble, skateboard trouble - but the filmmakers nonchalantly weave through them, subordinating the predictability of narrative to the spontaneous pleasures of style. The acting is appealingly low-key, in keeping with the skaters' code of cool, watchful reserve, but the distinct and contrasting personalities of the main characters emerge all the same. Tony, with his caramel skin and curly blond mane, is vain and ambitious, eager for the stardom that awaits him and perhaps willing to betray his friends to achieve it. Jay, perhaps the most talented skater, is also the least able to cash in on his skills. Stacy, the straight arrow, is at first left off the Zephyr team because he is unwilling to let go of the responsibilities of job and school. Sid, a rich kid whose inner-ear troubles prevent him from doing much on the board, serves as an all-purpose sidekick. The main women in the story are Jay's sad, burnt-out mother (Rebecca De Mornay) and Tony's sister, Kathy (Nikki Reed), whom both Jay and Stacy have a thing for. And there is a louche promoter (Johnny Knoxville) who makes Skip look like a scoutmaster. What unites the younger characters, and what gives "Lords of Dogtown" its buoyant, rebellious kick is the combination of recklessness and discipline that defines their approach to skateboarding. Their lives are a complicated and perhaps typically Southern California blend of hedonism and striving. Apart from Sid, they have all grown up pretty hard: Kathy and Tony are the children of a tough, working-class Mexican-American father; Jay's mother, perpetually sunburned and a little unstable, works in a lamp factory and lives with her son in a tiny, cluttered apartment near the beach. But the climate and their own rambunctiousness combine to give these kids a sense of freedom and possibility that is at once antisocial - they throw punches, trash restaurants and break into suburban homes - and upwardly mobile. Not having been there, I can hardly vouch for the movie's accuracy, but there is something about it that feels right - the looseness of its construction, the eclectic welter of its soundtrack, the faces of its cast. Mr. Peralta, having sustained his youthful obsession into middle age (and turned it into a varied and lucrative career), looks back without nostalgia, and Ms. Hardwicke makes you feel as if it's all happening now. "Lords of Dogtown" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some bad language, sexual situations and mild violence.</text>
      <date>June 3, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>