<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In Julian Schnabel’s grimly majestic concert film “Lou Reed’s Berlin,” Mr. Reed wears the deadpan smirk of a Zen master who has endured unusually punishing Buddhist training. His look isn’t that of a blissed-out monk newly returned from mountaintop meditations. It is the grimly amused seen-it-all stare of a voyeuristic chronicler of drug-fueled sadomasochistic rituals in the grittier corners of cities that never sleep. This is the real world, Mr. Reed seems to signal, while strumming tough minimalist riffs on his guitar and singing in a quavering, gravelly monotone: Get used to it, boys and girls.  At the December 2006 concerts of Mr. Reed’s rock oratorio “Berlin” at St. Ann’s Warehouse in Brooklyn, where the movie was filmed, Mr. Reed performed with a 35-piece ensemble conducted by his fellow guitarist Steve Hunter, who played on the original 1973 “Berlin” album. The movie faithfully reproduces the sound of that record, which was a commercial disappointment when released.  A digressive 10-song suite, “Berlin” chronicles the disintegration of a couple’s relationship in West Berlin in the era before the wall dividing East and West was torn down. The wife (or lover), Caroline (filmed for a fragmentary silent movie within the movie by the director’s daughter Lola Schnabel  and played by Emmanuelle Seigner), is a speed and sex addict who sneers at her partner for being passive and unmanly, and binges on depravity until the authorities step in and take away their children. Caroline eventually commits suicide by slashing her wrists.  Her partner, Jim (Mr. Reed), narrates the story in the tone of a helpless bystander whose bottled rage sporadically leaks out, only to be swallowed as he resumes his attitude of stoic detachment. In the final number, “Sad Song,” Jim, still besotted with the memory of Caroline, confesses in Mr. Reed’s typical clipped verbiage: “I thought she was Mary, Queen of Scots/My castle kids and home/I tried so very hard/Shows just how wrong you can be.”  “Berlin” evokes Gail Sheehy’s exposé, “Speed Is of the Essence,” published in 1971, when the perils of methedrine addiction were just beginning to be recognized. The book’s centerpiece portrayed a desperate drug-addicted couple spiraling toward insanity.  Mr. Schnabel’s set design depicting Jim and Caroline’s seedy hotel room suggests a battered Chinese scroll. Projections flickering across it create a semi-abstract murk that reflects the ceaseless agitation described in the songs.  Those songs are some of the most melodic and tender of Mr. Reed’s career. The original record, produced by Bob Ezrin in the grand style of ’70s concept albums, is Mr. Reed’s most operatic. For the concert, in addition to basic rock instrumentation, intensely dramatic arrangements with four horn and reed players, two violas and a cello were used. In the more contemplative passages, the music seems to hover as though holding its breath until the last second before a storm breaks. When it does, the guitars swell to a howling crescendo that evokes the passing of a tornado.  Demons charge through this music, but so do angels. The voices of the Brooklyn Youth Chorus lend the score a thread of eerie sweetness. In the most evocative moment, the voices flutter downward like falling angels sighing in defeat.  The concert’s three encores, not from “Berlin,” include Mr. Reed’s ominously quiet “Rock Minuet,” from his 2000 album “Ecstasy”; “Candy Says,” a duet between Mr. Reed and the ethereal-voiced Antony (of Antony and the Johnsons) that evokes the same demonic-seraphic dichotomy found in “Berlin”; and his Velvet Underground classic, “Sweet Jane.”  In the film’s production notes, Mr. Schnabel describes “Berlin” as the soundtrack of his life. I hesitate to imagine what that means. As a cautionary tale “Lou Reed’s Berlin” is an 85-minute public-service announcement that preaches “Just say no.” The force of the music, however, lends this tawdry melodrama a tragic stature.  “Lou Reed’s Berlin” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). There are images of depravity and strong language.</text>
      <date>July 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>