<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Loverboy," a cautionary mother-child drama, starts out warm and fuzzy, then stealthily pulls out the rug until you suddenly find yourself standing on a cold stone floor, barefoot and shivering.  The movie, the shaky second feature directed by Kevin Bacon, is an artistic valentine to his wife, Kyra Sedgwick, who stars as Emily Stoll, a single mother whose possessive instinct runs amok. Its juicy list of reputable actors in small roles includes Blair Brown, Matt Dillon, Oliver Platt, Campbell Scott, Marisa Tomei, Melissa Errico and Sandra Bullock.  This small, earnest film might be taken as a companion piece to "The Woodsman," the 2004 movie directed by Nicole Kassell in which Ms. Sedgwick's character, Vicki, was another headstrong woman who takes a huge risk by entering into a relationship with a convicted pedophile (Mr. Bacon). If Ms. Sedgwick's performance in "Loverboy" is even sharper, the movie, whose tone wobbles between lyricism and farce, is much less sure-footed.  Hannah Shakespeare's screenplay, adapted from a novel by Victoria Redel, frantically bounces between the present and the early 1970's, when Emily was the glum, spoiled daughter of lovebirds so wrapped up in each other that she felt like a lonely bystander. Ms. Tomei and Mr. Bacon (disguised behind a mustache and large pink aviator glasses and grinning from ear to ear) play the loony parents, Sybil and Marty, as cheesily dressed old-time Las Vegas-style fools in love. Ms. Bullock periodically materializes in dreamy soft focus as the sympathetic next-door neighbor the young Emily wished had been her mother.  If the comic episodes have no stylistic connection to the rest of the film, a scene, in which 10-year-old Emily (Sosie Bacon) embarrasses her parents at a school talent show by singing a weird a cappella rendition of David Bowie's "Life on Mars?," is grotesquely funny.  The adult Emily, who narrates the story, readily admits to arrogance. And, in retrospect, her coldblooded quest for no-strings-attached single motherhood is an ominous sign. With her inherited money, she tours the country, engaging in a succession of zipless one-night stands with men she uses and discards without a second thought. But Emily is so articulate and sure of herself that your initial impulse is to suspend doubt and applaud her nervy independence.  Eventually (after a miscarriage), Emily becomes pregnant and has a beautiful baby she names Paul, after his father (Mr. Scott), who is never contacted. She vows to give her little darling all the love she never got. In the first symptom of her deepening instability, she freaks out when her baby suckles at another woman's breast.  The story leaps ahead several years to observe the idyll she shares with Paul (Dominic Scott Kay), whom she calls Loverboy. They sleep together in a tent strung with flowers in the backyard. During an off-season jaunt to the New England coast, Emily can hardly bear it when Mark (Mr. Dillon), a geologist who lives nearby, takes a fatherly interest in Paul.  If there is something irresistibly touching in the sight of an attractive mother in love with her perfect child, vicarious delight gives way to exasperation and eventually to alarm as Emily home schools her son and possessively prevents him from making friends his own age. When she reluctantly allows him to attend public school, she becomes pathologically suspicious of his teacher. Long after he has demanded she stop, she insists on calling him Loverboy.  Almost until the end, "Loverboy" maintains a shaky integrity. But in its final moments it caves in to convention with a mawkish epilogue to a story that ends with an appalling act of selfishness.  The movie is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations.</text>
      <date>June 16, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>