<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Until it erupts in tears, “Love Happens” dawdles along uncertainly as though debating exactly how to season its morose story with enough attempted witticisms to keep the audience from dozing off. Directed by Brandon Camp, from a screenplay he wrote with Mike Thompson, the movie stars Aaron Eckhart and Jennifer Aniston as a widowed self-help guru and the conveniently single Seattle woman who prods him into releasing his pent-up anguish.  Mr. Eckhart’s character, Burke Ryan, is a tepid pastiche of real-life powerhouses like Anthony Robbins, Werner Erhard and Dr. Phil. As the movie begins, Burke, the best-selling author of “A-OK! A Path Through Grief,” arrives in Seattle to conduct a seminar. A major multimedia deal is in the works to turn him into a brand.  Ms. Aniston’s character, Eloise Chandler, is a poker-faced floral designer he bumps into in a hotel corridor. The next time he sees her, she responds to his flirtatious overture in sign language. This gratuitous quotation from Mr. Eckhart’s breakthrough film, “In the Company of Men,” like many of the movie’s stabs at humor, is simply bizarre.  Burke’s best seller was inspired by the death of his wife three years earlier in a car crash that is recalled in several ponderous flashbacks. The ramshackle screenplay takes its time to signal that Burke, who pretends to have all the answers to emotional recovery after a loss, is clueless about his own blocked condition.  Mr. Eckhart was wonderful as a cynical, hot-wired shill of the tobacco industry in “Thank You for Smoking.” But as a self-help know-it-all who bullies people in his seminars into walking barefoot over hot coals, he is so devoid of charisma, and his character so lacking in insight, that you wonder why anyone would heed his advice. Ms. Aniston’s role is underwritten to the point that her character barely takes shape. Once again she inhabits the Hollywood stereotype of a lonely all-American gal waiting to be completed by a man. Here her super-normality isn’t simply bland; it is empty and lifeless; there is no gleam in her eye. When she and Mr. Eckhart tentatively lock lips, love doesn’t happen.  The movie’s only real feelings take place on its fringes. The truest moments belong to John Carroll Lynch, playing Walter, a rugged contractor whose life unraveled after the death of his young son. You applaud him, the rebel in Burke’s seminar,  for refusing to scamper over the hot coals. Martin Sheen also has a human moment as Burke’s tough-guy father-in-law who bares his soft side during the climactic deluge.  Otherwise the vital signs in “Love Happens,” a movie that feels likes a laboriously padded outline, are faint.  “Love Happens” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>September 18, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>