<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Cards on the table: I find it hard to dislike a movie that delivers songs by George Jones and Bruce Springsteen within the first five minutes or so. The rest of the music in “Lucky You” is of a similarly high, canonical quality (even when it’s Drew Barrymore rather than Mr. Jones singing “Cold Hard Truth”), but by the time the brand-new, specially commissioned Bob Dylan number plays over the end credits, it feels less like an apotheosis than like a consolation prize.  I still can’t entirely dismiss “Lucky You.” Even though it is sometimes dull and generally thin, there is something winning about the movie’s genial lack of ambition. It’s a nickel-ante fable of lessons learned and chances taken set in the world of high-stakes competitive poker. The sense of disappointment that lingers afterward may result from inflated expectations, since this is a small picture with some big names attached to it.  Like the main character, a Las Vegas poker player with the literary name of Huck Cheever (Eric Bana), “Lucky You” has a noble pedigree. It was directed by Curtis Hanson (“L.A. Confidential,” “Wonder Boys,” “8 Mile”), who wrote the script with Eric Roth (“Forrest Gump,” “Munich”). Mr. Hanson’s style is relaxed and observant; he is more interested in watching his characters than in hurrying them through the plot. This is just as well, since the story he has to tell is a pretty wheezy contraption, a slack assemblage of romantic-comedy and Oedipal-reckoning clichés.  Huck’s dad, a onetime English professor named L. C., is a two-time winner of the World Series of Poker and a raffish, self-possessed gambler of the old school. That he is played by Robert Duvall is one of the film’s great advantages; if I were as devoted to poker metaphors as Mr. Roth and Mr. Hanson seem to be, I’d say that Mr. Duvall was the ace in the hole.  With a neat mustache and a twinkle in his eye, he portrays a man in possession of more charm than scruple, and he attacks the role with his usual unpretentious gusto. Watching other people play cards is not necessarily riveting, and if the card table sequences in “Lucky You” turn out to be the best parts, it is largely thanks to Mr. Duvall, who could bring wit and excitement to a movie about the high-stakes world of competitive Sudoku or Crazy Eights.  The card-playing scenes — many  featuring real-life fixtures of the professional poker circuit — also offer some relief from the clumsy attempts by Mr. Bana and Ms. Barrymore to breath whimsy and longing into an unconvincing love story. Huck, who lives in an unfurnished house with an empty swimming pool, is not much for commitment. He is tempted to give up his rambling ways by Billie Offer, Ms. Barrymore’s character, an aspiring singer who has just arrived in Las Vegas from Bakersfield.  Billie’s most important attribute, as far as the filmmakers are concerned, is her complete ignorance of poker (and, it seems, of certain common American idioms that have nothing to do with gambling). This allows Huck to explain the basics of the game.  Billie, in turn, explains the finer points of Huck’s psychology. These are not mysterious. As L. C. puts it, his son plays cards the way he should live his life, and vice versa. In the casinos (lovingly recreated on a Hollywood studio soundstage), he is what’s known as a blaster, and in the course of “Lucky You” he repeatedly piles up big stacks of chips only to lose them on a rash bet. He steals money from Billie the morning after sleeping with her, and then feels convincingly remorseful. She, a bit less convincingly, decides to forgive him. Like money, her affection is something he wins and loses over and over again.  The crux of “Lucky You,” though, is the father-son drama between Huck and L. C., which has an oddly inert, tired feel about it. Part of the problem is that Mr. Bana, quick-witted and good-looking though he is, is an essentially passive, reactive screen presence. This served him well enough in “Munich,” in which he was the quiet, troubled soul at the mercy of external crises. But everything in “Lucky You” depends on Huck’s confused motives and feelings, and Mr. Bana’s diffidence is less intriguing than frustrating. His performance is so controlled that it becomes inscrutable.  There is not much heat between him and Ms. Barrymore, who is on hand mainly because the conventions of the genre require it. To be the girl in a gambling picture is a thankless task, though this movie deals out less heartbreak than some of its predecessors.  Compared with movies like “The Hustler,” “The Gambler” and “California Split,” “Lucky You” feels tidy and safe, more interested in kibitzing the action than in partaking of the existential rush that comes from taking big, mad risks. Strange to see a film about gambling that  wants only to break even.  “Lucky You” is rated PG-13. There’s a hint of sex, but this Las Vegas is smoke- swearing- and generally sin-free.</text>
      <date>May 4, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>