<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Lucky Ones,” a bittersweet comedy about three seemingly dissimilar American soldiers who embark on a road trip after their flights home are canceled, is the latest in a string of films inspired by the war in Iraq. But this one, written by Neil Burger and Dirk Wittenborn and directed by Mr. Burger, has little interest in making bold pro- or antiwar proclamations.  With a smooth, light touch (though not without bumps and awkward moments) it focuses instead on the idea that the present and the people who factor into it are all we really have. Aside from the opening, the only combat scenes to be found here are strictly domestic, and, in terms of its lead characters, internal.  At the end of his tour and after nearly two years overseas, Fred Cheever (a refreshingly restrained Tim Robbins) can’t wait to see his wife and son in St. Louis, but the reunion turns out to be teary for unforeseen reasons. Colee Dunn (Rachel McAdams, luminous as always), on a 30-day leave after being shot in the leg, is on her way to Las Vegas to pay an unannounced visit to her dead boyfriend’s parents. More than a few surprises await her as well, but nothing can beat down her determinedly sunny outlook on life. T. K. Poole (Michael Peña), also recently wounded and headed for Las Vegas, dreads informing his fiancée that a piece of shrapnel has left him impotent.  Their journey is jampacked  with misadventures and personal epiphanies, some touching, others laughably contrived (a sudden, completely phony-looking tornado being the most absurd). But because the lead actors work so well together, adding depth and levels of vulnerability to fairly underwritten roles, the emotional consequences of the sense of displacement these “lucky” characters — lucky to be alive, lucky to have met one another — must deal with always ring true.  “The Lucky Ones” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language, brief violence and sexual content.</text>
      <date>September 26, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>