<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The mad and the sane take a leisurely spin around the dance floor in the Czech filmmaker Jan Svankmajer’s “Lunacy.” With thematic nods to Edgar Allan Poe and the Marquis de Sade, this feature-length phantasmagoria relates the Mad Hatter adventures of a young man, Jean Berlot (Pavel Liska), who, on meeting an aristocrat simply called the Marquis (Jan Triska), tumbles down a very strange rabbit hole. But before this happens, the filmmaker appears, talking into the camera and cautioning (or, rather, taunting) us that what we are about to see is not art, but a horror film, with all the “degeneracy peculiar to that genre.”  Those seeking the usual charnel-house cheap thrills characteristic of so much modern horror will be disappointed; Mr. Svankmajer’s provocations skew toward the intellectual and the shivery rather than the pop and the visceral, and at his best, he doesn’t just get under your skin, but also deep in your head, too. Here, unfortunately, he does neither, despite some marvelous stop-motion animated sequences involving a literal moveable feast of severed animal tongues, loose eyeballs and errant brains. These peripatetic parts interrupt, though not often enough, the main event, which involves Jean playing horrified, seemingly captive witness to the Marquis’s elaborate follies, one of which is borrowed from Poe’s famous short story “The Premature Burial,” some of which are borrowed from Sade, though without the really nasty bits.  In the prologue Mr. Svankmajer states that “Lunacy” owes its “blasphemy and subversiveness” to Sade, by which he probably and principally means the scene in which the Marquis unleashes a harangue against God, while some half-dozen seminude actors execute a tame pantomime. Despite a little rough business with an effigy on a cross, this awkward tableau doesn’t seem all that blasphemous, particularly in view of artists like Andres Serrano, who have helped drain words like subversive of meaning. Luis Buñuel pulled off a better trick 40 years ago, and with more economy, by posing Catherine Deneuve as St. Sebastian and flinging mud at her in “Belle de Jour.” Though the reason Buñuel succeeded so brilliantly and enduringly is that he blasphemed a bigger modern god, that of celebrity.  To its advantage, “Lunacy” owes less to Sade and more to Poe, in particular the humorous story “The System of Doctor Tarr and Professor Fether.” Soon after making the acquaintance of the Marquis, Jean arrives at an asylum where the inmates and their keepers may have switched places, amid clouds of chicken feathers and lots of cackling (and clucking). Mr. Svankmajer hits his point too hard, though happily he also regularly sets loose those errant animal parts, which combine to create a shadow narrative that easily trumps the live-action sequences. As it happens, a pinch of Sade and a whiff of blasphemy are nothing compared with a cluster of brains crawling out of some tin cans like fugitives,  or a detached tongue creeping along a wall like an inchworm.</text>
      <date>August 9, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>