<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>he sight of a roomful of modern New York City fifth graders determinedly going through the paces of traditional ballroom dancing - the fox trot, the rumba, even the sultry tango - has a certain charming incongruity. The dances, with their old-style Astaire-and-Rogers urbanity, fit oddly with the unlithe bodies and dressed-down urban attitudes of today's American schoolchildren. Nonetheless, thanks to a program organized by the American Ballroom Theater, students in 60 New York elementary schools not only learn the steps and postures but also display them in an annual tournament. Their competition is the subject of "Mad Hot Ballroom," a slight, charming documentary directed by Marilyn Agrelo. The film was snapped up in January by Paramount Classics shortly after it made its debut at Slamdance (the scruffy stepchild of the Sundance Film Festival). It is the latest crowd-pleasing documentary to use a narrative device long relied upon by fictional sports movies: the road to the big game. Ms. Agrelo and her co-producer, Amy Sewell, first-time filmmakers, went to three public schools in different parts of New York and followed their students through the stages of competition leading to a final event at the World Financial Center. The prize was a trophy taller than most of the competitors, and also the kind of glory that fuels the dreams of many young people. Like the young orthographers in "Spellbound," these kids show tremendous pluck and discipline, as well as a sometimes overwhelming desire to win. Not all of them can, of course, which is one of the hard lessons competition teaches. And not every documentary on a beguiling subject is entirely successful. The built-in suspense of the road to the final tournament (and the serendipitous development that at least one of the three schools makes it  that far) gives "Mad Hot Ballroom" its shape. The young dancers - from TriBeCa, Washington Heights and Bensonhurst, Brooklyn - give it perkiness and personality, but it misses the chance to present them in their full individuality. The interviews with them are fascinating - in addition to dancing, they talk about school, the streets and the state of relations between girls and boys - but also superficial. Nonetheless, the dancing itself is fun to watch, both comical and genuinely touching, and any movie that captures some of the ineffable, magical process by which people learn is bound to be inspiring. There is also a glimpse at the ways class and ethnicity inform the lives of the city's children. The young sophisticates of TriBeCa seem not only materially better off than their counterparts uptown or in Brooklyn, but also confident of their superiority. In spite of their teacher's concerns about foisting too much competition on them, they expect to win. The children of Washington Heights, on the other hand - or at least their passionate, dynamic teacher - feel as if they need to win. Their school district is one of Manhattan's poorest, comprised largely of immigrants from the Dominican Republic, and the students' aspirations are shadowed by the realities of crime, poverty and broken families. The richness of the material makes "Mad Hot Ballroom" both fascinating and frustrating. There are subplots that seem buried in the hectic routines of practice and competition. We hear testimony, toward the end, about how participation in the program has changed some of the children's lives, but we are unable to witness, or even to intuit, the transformation. Ms. Agrelo and Ms. Sewell deserve praise for discovering and illuminating this delightful corner of an educational system that is often portrayed in the grimmest terms, but their execution falls a bit short. "Mad Hot Ballroom" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some mild references to violence and sexuality.</text>
      <date>May 13, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>