<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>t's not every day that a mechanic gets to be a movie hero. The last one may have been Joe Patroni (George Kennedy), who pulled a Boeing 707 out of the snow in "Airport" (1970). But Bruce Dern, as Harry Volpi, is a dashing figure, arriving to save the day in this sentimental film about hydroplane racing. "Madison," in the tradition of "Chicago," "Fargo" and "New York, New York," is a movie named for a city - in this case, Madison, Ind., population 13,000 or so, on the banks of the Ohio River. In 1971, Madison's economy, based on waterway shipping, is shot. All it has left is its tradition of hydroplane racing, and when it has the chance to play host to the Gold Cup race, there are four big questions: Can the town come up with the $50,000 prize money? Does Miss Madison, the community-owned boat whose crew is managed by Jim McCormick (Jim Caviezel), a heating and air-conditioning repairman, have any chance to win? What will Jim have to do? And how will it all affect his son, Mike (Jake Lloyd, a k a Anakin Skywalker of "Star Wars: Episode I - The Phantom Menace")? "Madison" wants to be both heartwarming and quirky but is sometimes just cutesy instead. A baby girl's first word is "Agnew." An elderly white man and an elderly black man argue about which racing day over the decades was best (1962? No, it rained). William Bindley, the director, who wrote the screenplay with his brother Scott Bindley, takes the position that big-city people disdain small towns just for being small. The racing teams from Budweiser and Atlas Van Lines and the television news people are portrayed as openly condescending. The peculiar thing, from an urban perspective, is that while the film, based on a true story, celebrates the peace, quiet and charm of small-town life, it also revels in the thrills of a super-noisy high-speed sport. Only moviegoers who care about nitrous-oxide injection systems or Madison itself are likely to appreciate it. "Madison" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It includes mild profanity and a couple of fatal explosions.</text>
      <date>April 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>