<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Mr. Magorium’s Wonder Emporium” is the only family film I can recall whose title character muses out loud about “King Lear” and the finality of death in language that wouldn’t be out of place in a college Shakespeare course.  What does King Lear have to do with Mr. Magorium (Dustin Hoffman), the 243-year-old proprietor of a magic toy store that opened its doors 114 years ago? You could describe them both as crazy sane. Mr. Magorium’s high-flown tangents suggest that the movie, a fantasy pitched mostly to 6-year-olds, also seeks to impress their 60-year-old grandparents with its zany erudition.  A benign, avuncular dreamer with mad-scientist hair who keeps a pet zebra, Mr. Magorium resembles a superannuated Pee-wee Herman with a deeper voice. Mr. Hoffman’s studied performance in this seriously weird movie refrains from Hermanesque extremes but is engaging nonetheless.  The storekeeper’s message to children is a variation of the old Peter Pan dictum that magic, if it is to exist, requires that you believe in it with all your heart. Stuffed with enough toys to fill several department stores, his shop suggests a surreal enlargement of Pee-wee’s Playhouse by way of “Charlie and the Chocolate Factory.” It is wonderful indeed, and you wish the movie had spent more time simply wallowing in it.  An embodiment of the unfettered imagination, it is a place where every item, from the adorable stuffed animals to the self-propelling tops, is alive and kicking, swooping, swirling and spinning. When a customer requests an item, a clerk consults a giant alphabetized book of inventory, and on the appropriate page, a whole little world pops out. One of the store’s most heartening qualities is its dearth of war toys and sexy dolls. Mr. Magorium’s signature plaything is a paper glider that, once deployed, keeps sailing around the room.  “Mr. Magorium’s Wonder Emporium” was written and directed by Zach Helm, whose previous major credit was the screenplay for the Will Ferrell comedy “Stranger Than Fiction,” which envisions a sophisticated adult version of the same kind of magic. But if the concept is ingenious, its execution is erratic. The story is arbitrarily divided into chapters of varying length that have no clear beginning, middle or end, and the movie’s narrative drive is sporadic.  The story finds Mr. Magorium planning to leave the world because he is down to his last pair of the shoes he has stockpiled for decades. He intends to leave the store to his devoted clerk and right-hand woman, Molly Mahoney (Natalie Portman), a once-promising classical pianist and composer who lost her inspiration. But when he announces the bequest, she balks, believing she lacks the power to keep the store alive. (One of the movie’s weaknesses is Ms. Portman’s attitude of disengagement. Even when magic is all around, the sparkle in her eyes is dim.)  Mr. Magorium engages an accountant, Henry Weston (Jason Bateman), whom he calls Mutant, to go through years of erratic bookkeeping, determine the store’s value and help arrange its passage into Molly’s hands. A prototypical uptight numbers cruncher, Henry seems like the last person in the world who would understand what the store is about. With the emporium’s future up in the air, its most devoted customer (and the movie’s narrator), Eric Applebaum (Zach Mills), a shy, lonely 9-year-old, makes a pitch for it.  In the most exciting scene the store, sensing its days are numbered, rebels and stages a full-scale temper tantrum. The toys turn on the customers (not violently, I hasten to add), and nothing works as it should. After the tantrum subsides, the magic rapidly dissipates. The brightly colored walls warp and turn black, and the place eventually resembles a charred ruin in which nothing stirs.  But not to worry. One tiny spark of faith is all it takes to revive a magic toy store.  MR.</text>
      <date>November 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>