<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In "The Man," a new action-buddy comedy directed by Les Mayfield, Eugene Levy plays Andy Fiddler, a nerdy dental-supply salesman who travels to Detroit for a convention. Before he leaves, Andy's wife warns him to be careful. "Detroit isn't Wisconsin," she says.  No, it isn't, and in any case, she's speaking in a rather obvious code. But it should be noted that this Detroit, apart from a few aerial skyline shots, is actually Toronto. However you describe it, the city is a hotbed of crime, especially the traffic in stolen firearms, in which Andy becomes unwittingly embroiled. This is because he is mistaken for Derrick Vann, a truculent federal agent played by Samuel L. Jackson, who is trying to crack a gun-running ring and also   dodge an internal-affairs investigation.  The idea that anyone would mistake Mr. Levy, the very embodiment of Caucasian dweebiness, for Mr. Jackson, the last angry black man of the American cinema, is just about the funniest thing in "The Man." And while nothing in the movie - least of all the two main performances - is especially fresh or original, it does have a few decent gags and amusing moments. Mostly, of course, Mr. Levy looks anxious and put upon, while Mr. Jackson curses and hits people - in particular, a petty hustler named Booty (Anthony Mackie), who gets a trash-can lid in the face, a phone book to the back of the head and a Coupe de Ville in the body part for which he is named.  It's a nice car, by the way, and unlike the movie, it may have really been made in Detroit. A lot of the film takes place in its front seat, where Andy rides shotgun, while Derrick drives and fulminates. Andy also suffers from a bout of flatulence, a bit of comic business so priceless that the filmmakers repeat it later in an elevator.  Otherwise, the two men explore the meaning of manhood, and argue about who might be said, and under what circumstances, to be the other one's bitch.  Andy learns to assert himself, and Derrick learns a bit of sensitivity as they chase down the bad guys (led by the eager, snarling Luke Goss) and evade the snoops from internal affairs (led by the reliably reptilian Miguel Ferrer). Also on hand are the "Saturday Night Live" big guy Horatio Sanz as an evidence-depot flunky and the "Curb Your Enthusiasm" termagant Susie Essman as Derrick's commanding officer. The whole thing is over in less than 90 minutes.  "The Man" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has profanity and violence.</text>
      <date>September 9, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>