<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> If hell is a place of soul-crushing boredom, the Kingman Motor Inn, the Arizona hostelry in which Stephen Belber’s off-kilter romantic comedy “Management” sputters to a start, is a gateway to damnation. This anonymous, sunbaked depot is where 38-year-old Mike Cranshaw (Steve Zahn) works as the night manager, repairing backed-up toilets and discharging other odd jobs under the watchful eyes of his parents, Jerry (Fred Ward) and Trish (Margo Martindale), who own the place.  Mike’s dead-end existence is unsettled by a sudden glimpse of heaven when an attractive guest, Sue Claussen (Jennifer Aniston),  who sells the kind of sterile corporate art found on motel walls, checks in for a short stay. With stalkerlike persistence, the pesky Mike courts her with a bottle of wine, “compliments of management,” which he insists they drink together, followed later by cheap champagne.  Worn down and impatient to be rid of him, Sue finally allows Mike to put his hand on her behind. A spark is struck, and just before returning to her home in Baltimore, she initiates an afternoon fling in the laundry room. Then she leaves Arizona without a second thought. Mike, of course, is besotted.  This absurdist comedy is about a not-so-young, not-so-glamorous man who forges a pathway out of hell after being struck by romantic lightning. Mike may be a bumbling sad sack, but Mr. Zahn gives him just enough spunky appeal to lend this unlikely fly-by-afternoon coupling  and its consequences a shred of credibility.  In pursuit of his dream girl, Mike spends his last dime on a one-way ticket to Baltimore. Sue has to pay his way back to Arizona. Eventually, however, his route to salvation carries him to Aberdeen, Wash., where Sue has gone to live with Jango, a former punk-rocker turned organic-yogurt mogul, played by  Woody Harrelson as a fire-breathing, wild-eyed maniac.  “Management” aspires to be a hybrid of that great-granddaddy of modern romantic comedies about uncomfortable male initiation, “The Graduate,” and smart American road-trip comedies like “Flirting With Disaster” and “Little Miss Sunshine.” If it isn’t half as good — or as funny — as its forerunners, it maintains its integrity as a small, sweet-natured comedy that refuses to obey the commercial dictates of Hollywood by allowing its characters to determine their own zany destinies.  In Aberdeen, Mike talks his way into a job in a Chinese restaurant where he meets his new best friend, Al (James Liao), a fellow employee whom he enlists in a vaguely creepy surveillance operation at Jango’s estate. Mike is so fixated on Sue that he skydives out of a plane into Jango’s swimming pool. Here is where “Management” turns into a screwball farce: it temporarily loses its bearings when it follows Mike into a Buddhist monastery for a period of reflection.  “Management” takes it on faith that there are exits from the cul-de-sacs of American life,  that  lives can have second and third acts, that losers can shake off defeat. Through his misadventures  Mike metamorphoses from superannuated boy into likable grown-up with his endearing childlike traits intact.  It takes an indie movie like “Management” or the 2002 film “The Good Girl” to reveal Ms. Aniston as an actor capable of uncovering darker elements within her usually bland persona of the grown-up girl next door. Underacting, she subtly conveys the loneliness and insecurity beneath Sue’s brusque, self-contained facade.  Sue first shows her humanitarian streak in a scene in which she hands out Burger King coupons to the homeless. Her real dream is to open a food kitchen for the poor. “Management” has a generosity of spirit that makes you believe that good people summoning a lot of pluck can make good things happen.  “Management” is rated  R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>May 15, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>