<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In Noah Baumbach’s “Margot at the Wedding,” a face is slapped, some punches and kicks are thrown and a gracious old shade tree is subjected to assault by chain saw. It all sounds pretty tame compared with what you might encounter on neighboring screens at the multiplex. This is, as my colleague Caryn James pointed out in a recent essay, a notably bloody season at the movies. So if you are interested in gore and gunplay, you can seek out “Saw IV” or “No Country for Old Men.” When it comes to emotional violence, however, “Margot at the Wedding” is hard to beat.  Mr. Baumbach’s characters exist in a state of highly civilized Hobbesian war: sister against sister, mother against son, neighbor against neighbor, lover against lover. And the combatants do love one another (except for the neighbors, who hurl garbage over the fence and scream obscenities on hiking paths). If they did not, they would be unable to inflict or suffer hurt the way they do, with well-aimed humiliation, cruelty disguised as solicitude and strategic displays of sensitivity and its opposite.  Their high degree of intellectual and cultural refinement — and the mixture of self-loathing and self-regard that is their most recognizable tribal feature — makes these people at once exquisitely vulnerable to pain and adept at causing it. Margot (Nicole Kidman) is a successful novelist from Manhattan. Jim (John Turturro), the husband she is planning to leave, is also some kind of writer, as is Dick (Ciaran Hinds), with whom she’s having an affair. Margot’s sister Pauline (Jennifer Jason Leigh), who didn’t speak to her sister for a long time,  does not have any evident profession, but she seems to have made a vocation out of insecurity and self-scrutiny. Her fiancé, Malcolm (Jack Black), whom she describes as “brilliant,” dabbles in music, painting and letters to the editor, though his main achievement is growing a mustache. “It’s meant to be funny,” he says.  And “Margot at the Wedding” is often mercilessly, squirm-inducingly funny. Mr. Baumbach, the child of literary parents, has an unfailing ear for the idioms of the intelligentsia and an acute sense of family politics. The alliances that form in the course of the film’s hectic story, which takes place over a few days in a rambling seaside house, are shifting and unstable.  Margot’s son Claude (Zane Pais)  bonds warily with Pauline’s daughter, Ingrid (Flora Cross). Margot awkwardly reaches out to Malcolm. Pauline turns her needy affection on whoever is in the room. But the occasional moment of kindness or sincerity is, more often than not, a pause in the hostilities, and a chance for the filmmaker to set up another painful comic explosion.  By the end, it all spins out of control in a pileup of exposed secrets, buried lies and moral failures expressed in a cacophony of screams, tears and furious whispers. To the extent that a narrative structure is discernible amid the chaos, “Margot at the Wedding” could be described as a farce. And for all the wild, at times aggressive originality of its literary and visual style, the film belongs to a familiar genre in which a filmmaker gathers a gaggle of kinfolk under one roof for a big event — though Pauline and Malcolm’s must be the most haphazardly organized wedding in film history — and watches the sparks fly, sprinkling gasoline on them when necessary.  This is a fairly shopworn conceit, but Mr. Baumbach’s resistance to cliché is nonetheless admirable. His last movie, “The Squid and the Whale,” was flecked with references to French filmmakers like Jean Eustache and Jean-Luc Godard, and his intention in “Margot at the Wedding” seems to have been to make a French movie with American characters.  This strikes me as, for the most part, a worthy ambition. The Gallic influence is evident not only in the quick, sometimes abrupt cuts between scenes and the intimate, breathless camera work, but also in the way the film is entirely absorbed in the particulars of its characters and their world. You are plunged into their lives rather suddenly — the first scene, riddled with jump cuts and bumpy tracking shots, takes place on a train — and you proceed through a thicket of idiosyncrasies, allusions and private jokes.  We never really find out, for example, why Margot and Pauline did not speak to each other for so many years, but the fact of their estrangement is as believable as their reluctance to rehash its origins for our benefit. The realism of “Margot at the Wedding” — the texture of unpredictable, lived experience that keeps both farce and melodrama in check — lies in its sense of sprawl and untidiness, in the feeling that the movie itself is snipped from an endless tangle of bad feelings and good intentions.  And the characters, unpleasant as they are, are depicted with bracing individuality. Ms. Leigh and Mr. Black have never been better — Pauline and Malcolm, for all their troubles, are at least trying to be honest and kind — and Mr. Pais more than holds his own in very intense company.  As for Ms. Kidman, the more complicated she is allowed to be, the better she is, and a whole school of psychoanalysis could be founded on a case study of Margot. The summary diagnosis might be that she’s just vain, selfish and mean — someone you would back away from slowly before running in the other direction. But if you were her son or her sister — or even her future brother-in-law — you might not have that option, and anyway “Margot at the Wedding,” despite its title and what she might think, is not all about Margot.  And that may be part of the problem with this frequently brilliant, finally baffling film. In the final third, the proliferating complications and dramatic revelations start to feel increasingly rushed and hysterical. There is a fine line between depicting emotional anarchy and succumbing to it, and Mr. Baumbach, eager to avoid anything that might seem obvious, stacks up appalling and improbable climactic incidents that finally undermine the logic of the story. The result is that the audience may tire of the characters too quickly. Yes, they’ve been dreadful from the start, but interesting enough that you at least wanted to stick around and see what they would do next. Which makes your relief at being rid of them (after only 93 minutes!) something of a disappointment as well.  “Margot at the Wedding” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has a lot of stuff in it that perceptive children already know, even if adults wish they didn’t.</text>
      <date>November 16, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>