<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Married Life,” a period comedy of manners merged with a suspenseful psychological thriller, aspires to be a hybrid of the sort that Alfred Hitchcock polished to perfection in the age of sexual subtext and subterfuge.  When to shudder and when to smirk: as you watch this sly marital fable of secrets, lies and homicidal intent, you’re never sure of what your reaction should be. Up to a point, the director, Ira Sachs (“Forty Shades of Blue”), who wrote the screenplay with Oren Moverman, clearly wants it that way.  Adapted from John Bingham’s book “Five Roundabouts to Heaven,” the movie, set in 1949, stars Chris Cooper and Patricia Clarkson as Harry and Pat Allen, a couple whose cozy marriage is suddenly endangered when Harry falls head over heels for Kay Nesbitt (Rachel McAdams), a beautiful, much younger war widow who returns his passion.  But Harry has convinced himself that his wife is so in love with him that she would be destroyed if he divorced her. To spare her the pain of abandonment, he decides that the most humane solution is to kill her. This is the sort of gallows humor that Hitchcock relished drawing out in cruelly amusing cat-and-mouse games, not to be taken too seriously. The same is true of “Married Life.” The murder plot is not to be taken any more literally than the lethal games of “Mr. and Mrs. Smith.”  The story is narrated by Harry’s best friend, Richard Langley (Pierce Brosnan), a suave lothario whose mouth begins to water the moment Harry introduces him to Kay. Harry foolishly insists that Richard visit his new lady love in Harry’s rustic country house to cheer her up while he is stuck in the city (presumably New York) or away on a business trip.  Mr. Brosnan is perfectly cast as a silver-tongued predator eyeing an irresistible morsel. Sixty years ago Ray Milland or James Mason (shown here in a love scene with Ava Gardner from “Pandora and the Flying Dutchman”) would have imbued him with the same serpentine charm.  Ms. McAdams’s Kay looks every inch the classic Hitchcock bottle blonde: a cherry-lipped, platinum-haired beauty cut from the Tippi Hedren-Kim Novak mold, who turns heads when she enters a room. But beyond a cheery vivacity, Ms. McAdams breathes no inner life into this luscious dish. Nor is there any chemistry between Ms. McAdams and Mr. Cooper, who looks almost old enough to be her grandfather.  Harry is a sharp deviation from Mr. Cooper’s brooding, granite-faced stoics. For all the layers he reveals of Harry, his performance feels like a slightly uncomfortable mismatch of actor and role. He is too much a man’s man to play a bumbling fool for love.  Ms. Clarkson’s Pat is a fascinating chameleon whose ability to feign a blind adoration that fools Harry into imagining that she can’t live without him is almost believable. She also shows the other side of Pat, a smoldering sensualist who believes that people marry for sex, not lovey-dovey companionship. With her throaty voice, which ripples with insinuation, and flashing glances,  which hint at treachery, she is as intriguingly enigmatic in “Married Life” as she was in “The Dying Gaul” and “Far From Heaven.”  In fact, “Married Life” could almost be taken as a prequel to “Far From Heaven,” Todd Haynes’s politically pointed deconstruction of a Douglas Sirk melodrama. But with Hitchcock replacing Sirk as muse, teasing comic mystery substitutes for sudsy melodrama. Beyond examining the age-old battle of the sexes within the confines of a long-term relationship, the movie is apolitical.  “Married Life” is as studious in its re-creation of late-’40s ambiance and décor as “Far From Heaven” was in its evocation of Eisenhower-era suburbia. A comparison of the two films suggests how rapidly American affluence advanced in half a decade, from shabby postwar gentility toward a sleek modernity. Together, the two movies and the television series “Mad Men,” set in 1960, can be looked at as a historical trilogy examining changing American design over a decade.  “Married Life” does not provide the shivery security of being manipulated by Hitchcock, a master trickster who calculated his every move. The sense of being guided through a story by a sure-handed Hollywood magician toward a delightful trick ending is missing. That insecurity, of course, is what makes “Married Life” contemporary. You can never really go back.  “Married Life” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for some thematic elements and a scene of sexuality.</text>
      <date>March 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>