<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Them that’s got shall get/Them that’s not shall lose.” That observation from Billie Holiday’s “God Bless the Child” sums up the cynical view of “Maxed Out,” James D. Scurlock’s documentary investigation of debt in America. This scattershot exposé of usurious banking practices examines why the most vulnerable segment of society is victimized by the lending industry and finds a simple answer: It’s obscenely profitable.  Although “Maxed Out” would like to be this year’s “Enron: The Smartest Guys in the Room,” it doesn’t measure up. “Enron” was a stronger film because its focus was specific, the personalities under its microscope were outsize, and its story had a beginning, middle and end. “Maxed Out,” which has no narrator, gathers facts, opinions and impressions and tosses them into a blender. And its story is still unfinished.  Because no spokesman for the lending industry would  be interviewed on camera, the closest the film comes to spearing financial sharks is in its bland clips of testimony from a short-lived 2005 Congressional inquiry into banking practices. The glib, well-heeled apologists for legal corporate loan sharking exude the same air of sanctimonious concern  bankers have always cultivated.  The most carnivorous fish in the movie’s net are the young hotshots  at a collection agency who gleefully describe pressuring debtors to pay up by threatening to alert their neighbors and relatives and to publish their names in the newspaper.  “Maxed Out” opens with scenes of a Las Vegas real estate agent showing off new mansions and describing the innovative ways in which they are financed. People purchasing these houses in upscale enclaves with pretentious Italian names, she says, expect to have their gated communities patrolled by guards.  The scene vividly establishes the notion that consumer debt in America is being driven by a grandiose national sense of material entitlement. Robin Leach muses unhelpfully that people would rather dream about lifestyles of the rich and famous than the poor and unknown. As the film drifts from one topic to the next, it throws in images of post-Katrina New Orleans, a televangelist soliciting donations and a yuppie pawnshop operator showing off his stash of Rolexes. Excerpts from an educational film in which a naïve couple are lectured on prudent borrowing by a solemn blowhard named Mr. Money adds a strain of deadpan humor.  The movie is hostile to President Bush, who is shown urging Americans in the wake of  Sept. 11 to do their patriotic duty and spend. Later it is suggested that a law signed by Mr. Bush in 2005 making it more difficult for Americans to apply for bankruptcy was written by MBNA, one of the largest credit companies in the country and a major Bush campaign contributor. Similarly provocative tidbits are scattered throughout the movie, but they remain disconnected.  For emotion the movie leans too heavily on the histories of despairing debtors, some facing foreclosure on their homes, others driven to suicide. We hear the story of one woman who drove her car into a river. The mothers of two  students who killed themselves describe their thwarted campaign to keep credit card companies from preying on  college freshmen.  For all its disorganization “Maxed Out” still  has an impact. The facts speak for themselves. Consumer debt in the United States amounts to more than $2.4 trillion; the debt carried by the median American household is $9,000. When people go into bankruptcy, about two-thirds of what they owe is in interest  and penalties, not principal. In its most provocative historical analogy the movie compares the lending industry’s predatory practices with sharecropping in the South after the Civil War.  There is little in “Maxed Out” that hasn’t been explored in greater depth and acuity on programs like “60 Minutes” and “Now.” Yet its gloomy message still resonates. It is as old as the republic whose Constitution enshrines the pursuit of happiness as an inalienable right: In a nation of financial snake oil salesmen, where the almighty dollar rules, greed usually trumps ethics.</text>
      <date>March 9, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>