<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Everything about being indie is tied to not being black,” says Micah (Wyatt Cenac), half of the accidental kind-of couple whose one-day romance is chronicled in “Medicine for Melancholy.” He is making an observation — and also registering a complaint — about the quasi-bohemian way of life he shares with Jo’ (Tracey Heggins), his temporary other half. It bothers Micah that their embrace of the folkways of urban hipsterism seems to require the suppression of their African-American identity.  But his words, which Jo’ doesn’t quite agree with, also suggest a degree of self-awareness, and self-questioning, on the part of Barry Jenkins, who wrote and directed this small, incisive film. Most recent movies about culturally savvy, affectless 20-somethings hooking up and being cool are very much tied to not being black. They are about diffident, underemployed white boys and the women who (sometimes inexplicably) go to bed with them.  It wouldn’t be entirely fair to say that Mr. Jenkins, a 29-year-old director whose immersion in movie history is both ardent and understated, is making a black version of a Joe Swanberg or Andrew Bujalski film, or even, to stretch the comparisons a bit further back, a mash-up of “Before Sunrise” and “She’s Gotta Have  It.” But it wouldn’t be entirely inaccurate, either, because the tricky questions that govern “Medicine for Melancholy” are how, why and to what extent race should matter in relationships between black men and women.  At one point Micah asks Jo’ if her live-in boyfriend (conveniently overseas on a business trip) is white. “Does it matter?” she asks him.  “Yes and no,” he says, and his ambivalence is both the theme of the movie and a crucial element of its curious, ruminative attitudes toward love, race and urban life.  We first meet Micah and Jo’ in a bed that belongs to neither of them, where they have awakened  together on the morning after a party. Both act shy and embarrassed, and Jo’ seems in a particular hurry to put this brief encounter behind her. Micah, though, proposes breakfast and a shared cab ride home, which Jo’ accepts more out of fatigue and some sense of post-coital decorum than out of genuine interest.  Micah tries to counter her aloofness with low-key humor, and when Jo’ leaves her wallet in the taxi,  he tracks her down, bicycling from his apartment in the  Tenderloin district of San Francisco to her place in the Marina.  “Medicine for Melancholy” is a two-hander, occupied entirely with the day Jo’ and Micah spend together, chatting, flirting, arguing and seeing the sights of San Francisco. But the city’s lovingly captured neighborhoods (shot by James Laxton in high-definition digital video from which all but the faintest hints of color have been drained) make the story as much a love triangle as a romance.  Micah, a native San Franciscan, is acutely aware of —  Jo’ might say obsessed with —  the demographic changes that have accompanied the city’s recent boom. He grieves over the attrition of the black population, which he says has shrunk to only 7 percent, and fears that gentrification will destroy his hometown’s free, democratic spirit. In a quietly illuminating documentary digression, he and Jo’ pause in their wandering to listen to a group of housing-rights activists.  Micah’s sense of politics and place, as much as the color of his skin, distinguishes  him from other mumblecore characters, who traipse through cool, scruffy parts of various cities indifferent to the history that surrounds them and the social contradictions that ensnare them. Mr. Jenkins’s spirit is exploratory rather than didactic. Micah is neither a saint nor a mouthpiece, but a young guy with sometimes confused motives and ideas. At first his race-conscious riffs sound, to Jo’ and the audience, like pick-up lines, as if he were trying to guilt-trip her back into bed with him.  And to some extent they might be. Mr. Cenac, a writer and fake reporter on “The Daily Show With Jon Stewart,” calibrates Micah’s vacillations between earnestness and guardedness perfectly. Ms. Heggins’s character is less developed. We know Jo’ is a cinephile, currently unemployed and a transplant to the Bay Area, but she never fully emerges as either a foil or a possible soul mate for Micah.  But that may be Jo’s choice as much as the filmmaker’s. There are no simple answers or obvious conclusions to be gleaned from this movie, which, like its soundtrack, is both sad and vibrant, meandering and formally sure-footed. It is an exciting debut, and a film that, without exaggeration or false modesty, finds interest and feeling in the world just as it is.</text>
      <date>January 30, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>