<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Is it too early for a movie about the short, charmed life and horrible death of Daniel Pearl? It’s a fair question, raised in echo of those voices that several years ago worried if it were too early for a movie about Sept. 11. Like all those who died that day, Mr. Pearl was a casualty of Islamist hatred of Western civilization. And, much as with those other terror victims, his murder has now inspired a mainstream movie meant  to entertain as much as to instruct and enlighten, a movie that will be seen by some as vulgar proof of that same civilization’s willingness to turn a buck on everything, including tragedy.  And make no mistake, despite its pseudo-documentary grit and the imprimatur of the midcult art-house director Michael Winterbottom, “A Mighty Heart” is a precision-tooled Hollywood machine. Based on the memoir by Mariane Pearl, it was bankrolled by a studio division and comes attached to two of the biggest stars in the world, Brad Pitt, who served as one of its producers, and his partner and the film’s heat-seeking star, Angelina Jolie. For some, these boldface names will be reason enough to snigger. But snigger too loudly and you may miss that “A Mighty Heart” is effectively fashioned, as jolting as it is polished, as well as a surprising, insistently political work of commercial art.  Ms. Jolie is clearly the glittering lure here, of course, as much a distraction as a pitifully easy target. That’s too bad, because fine as she is, what distinguishes “A Mighty Heart” is its assertion that politics and ideology play a part in poverty and terrorism, in the way some men exploit human misery in the name of God and righteousness.  It’s the movie’s insistence that politics are integrated into the warp and woof of life, rather than something you wear like a campaign button, which gives pause. Unlike “United 93” and “World Trade Center,” in which terrorism is only a criminal act —  without context, without history, without purpose —   “A Mighty Heart” underscores the idea that Daniel Pearl’s murder was as much an act of political theater as a personal catastrophe.  Personal politics were a driving force in Daniel and Mariane Pearl’s life together. Young, beautiful, in love and expecting  their first child (a boy, Adam), they landed in Karachi, a sprawling Pakistani port city on the coast of the Arabian Sea, on Sept. 12, 2001. They were  journalists: She mostly worked for public radio and television in her native France;  he filed for The Wall Street Journal. The year before, Mr. Pearl, 38, seen mostly in flashback and played by a serviceable Dan Futterman, had become the Journal’s South Asia bureau chief. Mr. Pearl liked to be in the thick of things (he covered Iran for years), but he was cautious too. For him, it appears, the great adventure was being in love.  That, at any rate, is the story that Ms. Pearl tells in her painful book, written with Sarah Crichton. Published the year after her husband was beheaded, after his body was cut into 10 pieces, buried and recovered, the memoir is a tenderly intimate portrait of two remarkable people. Adapted for the screen by John Orloff (“Band of Brothers”), the movie follows the arc of the memoir in sweep and faithful detail. The day before the Pearls were to leave Karachi, Danny  went off to interview an extremist cleric. Instead, he was kidnapped in a complex plot partly engineered by the British-born Ahmed Omar  Sheikh,  who had spent years in an Indian jail for taking foreigners hostage in a bid to free  imprisoned Kashmiri separatists.  Mariane, six months pregnant, waited for her husband. In a short time she was joined in her ordeal by an alphabet soup of Pakistani and American intelligence and counterterrorism types. Among the most important were Randall Bennett (Will Patton, perfect and perfectly creepy), an American security officer who worked at the United States consulate, and a Pakistani that Ms. Pearl calls the Captain (the great Indian actor Irrfan Khan), the chief of that country’s counterterrorism unit. Together with this swarm, Ms. Pearl and another Journal reporter, Asra Q. Nomani (Archie Panjabi), set up a war room in the house where the Pearls were staying with Ms. Nomani. They chased leads, pored through Danny’s  files  and waited some more.  Structured like a police procedural, the movie has the metabolism of a thriller (it’s quick, quick, quick), the bursting heart of a romance and the brains of, well, some very clever people. Just how clever is best evidenced by the way this star vehicle tries to pretend that it isn’t one. Mr. Winterbottom, a canny chameleon whose defining aesthetic signature as a director is that he doesn’t have one, makes a show of working around the gorgeous 800-pound gorilla parked in the center of his movie, mostly by the strategically spare use of close-ups. But even when he’s showing you the back of Ms. Jolie’s corkscrew-curly head, which he does repeatedly, you never forget whom you’re watching.  And, really, why should we? Some of us  may remember Daniel Pearl or at least his gruesome execution, but everyone knows Ms. Jolie:  That’s why stars were invented. Like all big movie stars, she  can’t disappear into her role for long; rather, she bobs to the surface of our consciousness, recedes, bobs to the surface, recedes. Her celebrity bequeaths the movie its capital “I” importance, but her wild stare also affectingly  suggests the tumult beneath Mariane’s preternatural calm. After she appears on CNN to plead for Danny’s  safe return, someone mutters that you wouldn’t know that this dry-eyed woman’s husband had been kidnapped. But why the American need for tears?  Ms. Pearl asks. She wasn’t sad; she was furious.  “A Mighty Heart” is wrenching, but it’s the buzzing undercurrent of anger that makes it most true to its source. Time and again, Mr. Winterbottom plunges his jittery camera into the chaos of Karachi, into the noisy streets crowded with men and notably absent many women. This was the disorienting, alien and often frightening world into which Mariane and Daniel Pearl, a French Buddhist and an American Jew, willingly and bravely jumped. Although Ms. Pearl insists that her husband was also a cautious man up until the day he was kidnapped, maybe they were a little reckless. But they were fired up by a shared belief that journalism could help make the world better, a chokingly poignant idea in these shockingly cynical times.  That may be naïve, but idealism is a form of resistance. And in its modest, at times awkward, way, this little movie with the big movie star tries to bring us into a conversation that, at least in this country, is often relegated to the bummer front pages of your daily paper or glimpsed on television in between diet tips and, yes, news about Brangelina. It’s a difficult conversation at times, and to its credit, the movie doesn’t shy away from just how difficult, specifically in a horrific scene that shows a man being tortured for information about Danny’s  whereabouts. Mr. Pearl would have probably been appalled that this outrage was committed on his behalf; the point is, we should be too.  “A Mighty Heart” is rated R. (Under 17 requires accompanying  parent or adult guardian.) The film contains verbal obscenities; Mr. Pearl’s death is not portrayed on screen.</text>
      <date>June 22, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>