<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>n idiot savant in crisis is an old cinematic saw, and "Milwaukee, Minnesota" presents Troy Garity as a Wisconsin man with cognitive impairments but enviable intuition, especially when it comes to finding fish in half-frozen lakes. A champion angler, Albert Burroughs feels some extrasensory kinship to those fish wriggling under icy surfaces. He squirms under his mother's control and grabs any lure that might present an escape. Many opportunists see Albert as a catch, given his winner's purse from past fishing tournaments and his eager-to-please disposition. When his mother is suddenly, violently out of the picture, the rivals descend. Albert is preyed upon by two father figures and a young harlot, who prizes him as a daft sugar daddy. Mr. Garity's big, sad eyes suggest early on that Albert will be another earth-inheriting meek guy. Rising above the predictable plot, Mr. Garity again proves his enormous talent; after all, he is the son of gifted attention-getters, Jane Fonda and Tom Hayden. Mr. Garity delivered superb performances in two films already - "Bandits" and "Soldier's Girl" - and here he dares to blend the twitches of Dustin Hoffman in "Rain Man" with the vulnerable good looks of Cliff Robertson's "Charly." Mr. Garity tidies up this messy, claustrophobic film as he squares off with the lumbering, unctuous grifter played by Randy Quaid and calms down the shrill Alison Folland, who plays Albert's seductress. Bruce Dern and Debra Monk excel as taciturn losers tiresomely at odds with each other over Albert's best interests, and Josh Brolin arrives in what look to be crotchless women's panties, driving the film's quirk factor ever higher. Directing his first feature film, Allan Mindel is too taken with a Midwestern strain of weirdos who flounder in ramshackle houses, no-tell hotels and depressing juke joints. The director gives in to dopey devices like the discovery of a photo that reveals old connections among the characters. Then, as Albert is busily amassing counterfeit currency in the beginning of the film, he is bound to play games with the stash by the end. "Milwaukee, Minnesota" is ultimately a showcase for Mr. Garity's skills as he reprises the kind of role that has garnered trophies for other actors. Not that he should clear off space on his mantel just yet: while Albert's generosity may compensate for his confusion, Mr. Garity's performance doesn't quite redeem this sorely lacking production. "Milwaukee, Minnesota" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes disturbing scenes of violence.</text>
      <date>June 3, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>