<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> IT would be a stretch to say that Tom Cruise needs a hit. What this guy needs is an intervention, someone who can help the star once known as Tom Terrific return to the glory days, when the only things most of us really knew about him came from the boilerplate continually recycled in glossy magazines, sealing him in a bubble of blandness and mystery. In those days, we didn't know that inside the world's biggest movie draw lurked a reckless couch-jumper and heartless amateur pharmacologist. All we saw was a billion-dollar smile and a performer who risked life and limb, everything but his own true self, for our movie-going pleasure.  Until the ascendancy of George Clooney, the multi-hyphenated sex bomb (he walks, he talks, he smiles and he thinks!), few stars seemed to work harder than Mr. Cruise. The embodiment of the 1990's extreme ethos, he could be counted on to hang tougher than anyone else, whether doing his own stunts, spending a couple of years in production with Stanley Kubrick, or, as he did on more than one occasion, rescuing a civilian. Recently, though, all that extremeness has seemed, well, too extreme. And you have to wonder if the real mission in his newest film isn't the search for the damsel in distress or the hunt for the supervillain, but the resurrection of a screen attraction who has, of late, seemed a bit of a freak.  Aptly named or not, "Mission: Impossible III" may emerge as Mr. Cruise's latest box-office triumph, but it won't do him any favors when it comes to his public persona, since it appears to have been explicitly tailored to reflect his personal life, or at least its outward face. As he has in the first two "Mission" films, Mr. Cruise plays Ethan Hunt, a member of a stealth government agency, the Impossible Mission Force, who circumnavigates the world, blowing stuff up to wage battle against all manner of wickedness. Again he racks up miles (Berlin, Rome, Shanghai) and lights a few fuses, including that of a humorously decadent arms dealer, Owen Davian (Philip Seymour Hoffman), but this time he also has a main squeeze, Julia (the welcome if badly used Michelle Monaghan).  The overlap between a star's private and public selves can add frisson to the screen, especially when the luminaries are Humphrey Bogart and Lauren Bacall, Brad Pitt and Angelina Jolie, but it can prove deleterious, especially when it reeks of public relations. "Mission: Impossible III" opens in medias res with a screaming match between Ethan, who's actually doing all the screaming, and Davian, who's holding a gun on a woman. "I am going to kill you!" Ethan shouts, limbs bound and tendons jumping. Alas, before that happens, the director J. J. Abrams, who wrote the script with Alex Kurtzman and Roberto Orci, backtracks to an engagement party, where, tendons at ease and smile blasting, Ethan is playing the aggressively jubilant fiancé, all but shrieking, "I am going to marry her!"  Viewer, he does. In between communiqués with his agency superiors (Billy Crudup, Laurence Fishburne), a rescue mission (hence, Keri Russell from "Felicity") and pyrotechnic larks with his newest team (Ving Rhames, Jonathan Rhys Meyers,  the decorative Hong Kong transplant Maggie Q), Ethan settles into domesticity, an endeavor interrupted when Julia is kidnapped by a malevolently aggrieved Davian. Mr. Hoffman isn't given all that much to do in the film, but what he does is choice. With a sneer in his voice and a lazy slouch that telegraphs world-weariness of the most misanthropic kind, he creates an ice-blooded creature who seems as if he would like nothing better than to destroy the earth, and with as much human suffering as possible. The too-few scenes of Mr. Hoffman going directly up against Mr. Cruise are particularly tasty.  Mr. Hoffman enlivens "Mission: Impossible III," which otherwise droops, done in both by the maudlin romance and by Mr. Abrams's inability to adapt his small-screen talent — evident in his capacity as the television auteur behind "Alias" and "Lost" — to a larger canvas. The action remains consistently lackluster despite the usual frantic editing and several stunts that should pop off the screen. Typical of Mr. Abrams's difficulty in getting a grip on big-screen action is an extravagant feat that finds Ethan BASE-jumping  from one high-rise to another, a stunt that, because it was filmed mostly in extreme long shot and at night, might as well have been executed by Spider-Man's computer-generated avatar. A daytime battle on a bridge works better, largely because you can see Mr. Cruise panting amid the bullets and mayhem.  Although he slams into stationary objects with his customary zeal, the usually dependable Mr. Cruise is off his game here, sabotaged by the misguided attempt to shade his character with gray. The domestication of Ethan Hunt may have seemed like a good idea, a humanizing touch, perhaps, but it only bogs down the action. Worse, it turns a perfectly good franchise into a seriously strange vanity project, as the simpering brunette is swept into a new world by a dashing operative for a clandestine organization. Much like the man playing him, Ethan works only if you don't know anything about what makes him tick. Once upon a Hollywood time, the studios carefully protected their stars from the press and the public. Now the impossible mission, it seems, is protecting them from themselves.  "Mission: Impossible III" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). There is fairly bloodless violence.</text>
      <date>May 5, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>