<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Until the director Frank Darabont decides that he’s saying something important instead of making a nifty horror movie, “The Mist” isn’t half bad. In fact,  until the monsters and the meaning start to emerge, this shivery story works your nerves far better than most recent horror does, largely because it knows that nothing scares moviegoers better than our own overactive, reactive imaginations. This is a film that knows how to make you jump in your seat simply by showing you next to nothing: It knows you’ll eagerly fill in the blanks all by your lonesome, genre-conditioned self.  Based on one of Stephen King’s more modest efforts, meaning under 500 pages and pounds, “The Mist” takes place in a small Maine town where everyone seems to know everyone else by name or by sight. Most of the action unfolds inside a supermarket where the townspeople have gathered to stock up on supplies in the wake of a large storm that hit the night before. Among the shoppers are David Drayton (Thomas Jane) and his young son, Billy (Nathan Gamble), who, along with the rest of the customers, stand by in shock when a bloodied man bursts in yelling murder and mayhem most foul. Something or someone seems to have snatched up another man, sucking this lost soul into the fast-creeping, swallowing mist.  The mist rolls into the town as a mystery at first, delicate and light gray and full of unknown possibility. It initially surges and billows and moves with unnerving quiet, by turns flowing like water and gathering mass, its smoky tendrils creeping like long fingers. In an early scene it hovers like a wary animal next to a metal gate at the back of the supermarket. A cluster of men, David among them, are trying to decide whether it’s safe to go outside and have slid the gate up just a little. They peer at the mist, and the mist seems to confront them in turn, though no one grasps its brooding, pulsing aliveness. Then a tentacle slithers into view and slimes across the floor.  The revelation of the monstrous drains much of the dread and menace from the story, leaving holes that Mr. Darabont fills with greater and greater heaps of portentous dialogue, some of which taps into ideas about the mass psychology of fascism and sounds straight out of a 1950s-style television talkfest. Among the most tiresomely yakky is an evangelical Christian, Mrs. Carmody (Marcia Gay Harden, in clover), whose observations about the End of Days first attract testy scorn and then an increasingly violent following inside the little supermarket community. This latter-day Aimee Semple McPherson turns out to be just as much a threat as the mist, though a considerably less pleasurable narrative conceit, and one that might have worked if Mr. Darabont hadn’t spent so much time preaching his own brand of scripture.  Much of that scripture sounds yawningly familiar and runs along the lines of all we have to fear is fear itself, and we have met the enemy, and he is us, and let him without sin cast the first stone. That’s too bad, because Mr. Darabont does some estimable work in “The Mist,” particularly when he moves away from the chattering mob and returns to the mist and its riddles, to its eerie, insectlike whirring and periodic elephantine trumpet blasts. In the haunting images of men and women cautiously venturing outside, their bodies melting into the mist, he offers a stronger, more palpable sense of what it means for human beings to be truly frightened than he does with any of the dialogue. He makes fear visible.  “The Mist” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Gory dismemberment, gun and monster violence and some adult language.</text>
      <date>November 21, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>