<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “I like creepy guys.” This is what Kate, a personnel manager at an Edinburgh hotel, says to a young co-worker after a few rounds of drinks one evening. As it happens, both of them are in luck. Hallam Foe, the co-worker in question, is even creepier than Kate suspects. He has been stalking her  since before she hired him, and his main extracurricular activities are peering across the rooftops into her windows and scrambling up to her skylight to spy on her as she sleeps, has sex and practices her kickboxing.  This young man — “Mister Foe” to American viewers of David Mackenzie’s new film, which was called “Hallam Foe” (the title of Peter Jinks’s novel) in Britain — is evidently troubled. Back home at his father’s estate, which he fled for the Scottish capital, Hallam was a seasoned  voyeur with a taste for dressing up in animal skins and lipstick. His treehouse served as a shrine to his dead mother. She drowned in the loch, and Hallam is increasingly certain that she was murdered by his stepmother (Claire Forlani). Kate (Sophia Myles) first caught his eye because of her uncanny resemblance to poor old Mum (also embodied by Ms. Myles, in photographs), and his fixation on her is both sexual and filial. Creepy indeed.  Hallam (played by the excellent Jamie Bell, who has gained some skill and shed a bit of cuteness since “Billy Elliot”) would no doubt benefit from some counseling, and  the melodramatic twists of the plot ultimately serve as a kind of substitute therapy. It’s certainly more entertaining to watch a confused young man work out his issues through kinky sex and daredevil wall-climbing than to be a fly on the wall as he talks things out with a shrink. And if the extremity of Hallam’s temperament tests the limits of our sympathy as well as our credulity, Mr. Bell’s ability to seem by turns sweet and scary prevents us from losing interest entirely.  So does Mr. Mackenzie’s success in translating Mr. Jinks’s prose into an atmosphere that is both gritty and picturesque. He infuses the examination of Hallam’s emotional disorder with enough macabre and comical touches to prevent “Mister Foe” from sliding into the clinical sensationalism of the case study. That is more or less what it turns out to be in the end, but the film is also a nimble, acrobatic tour of Edinburgh, traipsing through narrow alleyways, up drainpipes and across gables and gutters as it follows Hallam on his pathological  way.  And the object of his desperate, icky and fond attention is certainly well chosen. Like Emily Mortimer, who played Ewan McGregor’s dream woman in Mr. Mackenzie’s previous film, “Young Adam,” Ms. Myles has the task of turning a phantasm of adolescent desire into a real person.  Kate’s insistence, late in the movie, that she is just that is both superfluous and unconvincing. In her loneliness, her toughness, her perfect mix of maternal warmth and sexual adventurousness, she is at heart a literary conceit, an inhabitant of that realm of the male imagination where lust and sentimentality meet and mingle. But Ms. Myles inhabits the role with such crisp and understated wit that she manages to hold such doubts at bay. Common sense might suggest that a woman in Kate’s position should change her locks, call the police or move to another town when a guy like Hallam shows up, but somehow she never seems more sensible than when she does the opposite of what prudence might dictate.  The smaller performances are nearly as strong as Ms. Myles’s and Mr. Bell’s, even when the characters are a bit too broadly drawn, like Ms. Forlani’s gold-digger or a philandering brute played by Jamie Sives. Ciaran Hinds, a welcome presence wherever he goes — from “Munich” to “Miami Vice” to “Margot at the Wedding” — strikes the right notes of obliviousness and paternal worry as Hallam’s father, vexed and concerned about his son even as he is unable to see how much of the boy’s waywardness is his fault.  To the rest of us it’s pretty clear from the start. And the main problem with “Mister Foe” is that Hallam’s strangeness is a puzzle only to him and those around him. He’s more of a mystification than a mystery, and never quite creepy enough to risk our not liking him.</text>
      <date>September 5, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>