<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “More Than a Game,” a new documentary directed by Kristopher Belman, invites comparisons with “Hoop Dreams,” Steve James’s 1994 film about the lives of two young Chicago basketball players. That movie was an almost miraculous fusion of filmmaking art and real-life narrative full of twists and reversals. “More Than a Game,” which looks back on the achievements of a high school basketball team in Akron, Ohio, that happened to include the future N.B.A. superstar LeBron James, is halfway there. The art is lacking, but the material is remarkable enough to make up for pedestrian filmmaking.  The elements of the story are, at first glance, familiar: a group of players of varying ability, a coach who seems an unlikely candidate to lead them, various breakthroughs and setbacks on the way to the big game. The coach is Dru Joyce II, a former businessman whose interest in basketball came about because his son, Dru III, in spite of his small size, was crazy about the game. The elder Joyce coached a youth league team that included Sian Cotton, Willie McGee, James and his son, four friends who went on to become the nucleus of the Fighting Irish of St. Vincent-St. Mary High School.  After the coach who recruited those young men ascended to the college ranks, Joyce took over and led the Irish to state and national prominence. The tale of this journey, conveyed like the rest of “More Than a Game” through old video footage and recent interviews, is heartening but sometimes less than riveting. There is some interesting insight into the friendships among the players, the tensions between the coach and his son and the uneasy assimilation of a fifth player, Romeo Travis, into the close-knit nucleus of the team. But it’s mostly a whole bunch of games, many of them shot in low-grade home video.  Along the way, you catch glimpses of themes that might have been explored more thoroughly, as well as of some pretty good basketball. I found myself wanting to go further into Akron and its African-American neighborhoods and to spend more time with the players and their families. Still, there is enough personality and local flavor to create a context for the drama that takes shape in the film’s second half.  In 2002, while he was still a junior at St. Vincent-St. Mary, James was the subject of a Sports Illustrated cover story, and his sudden celebrity takes “More Than a Game” to a place that “Hoop Dreams” only dreamed of. Suddenly the modest celebration of a talented group of kids becomes something else: a half-critical, half-starry-eyed exploration of the money-mad, fame-besotted frenzy that is big-time sports in America. The value of the movie is that it keeps track of the impact that James’s rise had on his friends, his family and his team and reminds the audience that the superstars who so often seem otherworldly and unreal started out as ordinary kids.  It is moving to hear James, an executive producer of the film, talk about the poverty and displacement he experienced as a child and about his attachment to his mother, who was a teenager when he was born. And a lot of the archival video is pretty amazing. Mr. Belman, though, is too enamored of easy emotional payoffs cued by swelling music and manipulative editing, almost as if he did not quite trust the power of his story. And the story might have been richer in its characters and themes if its inspirational aspects were not pushed so hard. As it is, devoted fans of the game, and especially of LeBron James, will love “More Than a Game.” The skeptical and the curious may find themselves wanting more.  “More Than a Game” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has strong language.</text>
      <date>October 2, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>