<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Partly a family memoir, partly a historical essay and partly the record of an improbable feat of engineering, Godfrey Cheshire’s documentary “Moving Midway: A Southern Plantation in Transit” tells a fascinating and complicated story of regional identity. Mr. Cheshire, a longtime film critic (and as such an acquaintance of mine), connects his longstanding interest in American popular culture with the lore attached to his ancestral home, a North Carolina plantation called Midway. Midway, built in 1848 near Raleigh, belongs to the Hintons, ancestors of the Silvers, the family of Mr. Cheshire’s mother, Elizabeth, who appears in his film to offer tart opinions of her ancestors, Yankees and a good deal more. Elizabeth and other members of the family are concerned about the development that is rapidly changing the Southern landscape and encroaching on the gracious old mansion that is so central to who they are. As the strip malls and highways draw nearer, Mr. Cheshire’s cousin Charlie decides to move the house, a project that occupies the middle portion of the movie and turns it momentarily from an ambling first-person rumination into something like Werner Herzog’s “Fitzcarraldo.” Not that madness is what motivates Charlie to hoist an old wooden building onto steel beams and truck it across the backcountry. Like many white Southerners, the current generation of Hintons has a nostalgic, sentimental relationship to the past, and a wary, ambivalent attitude toward modernity. At the heart of “Moving Midway” is the desire to preserve that warm, respectful sense of tradition and continuity while at the same time looking clearly at the less noble realities of history and making some attempt to rectify them. “Moving Midway” includes an incisive tour of the “moonlight and magnolias” mythology of the Old South manufactured by Hollywood, which provides a useful context for Mr. Cheshire’s inquiries into the annals of Midway. He shares some fond reminiscences of the place, and an intriguing portrait of his great-great-aunt Mary (or Mimi), a dominant figure in the 20th-century history of Midway and a keen collector of Hinton genealogical information. Some of it, anyway. If the transportation of Midway provides one dramatic crux in Mr. Cheshire’s film, the other arrives with the discovery of an African-American branch of the Hinton family. The two narratives converge at the end, when, in the restored house, far from the rush of traffic and commerce, the descendants of masters and slaves come together for a party. It is a lovely, touching scene, but to his credit Mr. Cheshire does not oversell it as a moment of reconciliation. Having begun with William Faulkner’s famous observation that “the past isn’t dead; it isn’t even past,” he does not rush to forgive his ancestors their transgressions. Nor does he undertake his investigation alone. On his journeys back home, Mr. Cheshire is frequently accompanied by Robert Hinton, a professor of Africana studies at New York University, the film’s chief historian and associate producer as well as a descendant of slaves owned by the director’s family. The two men are not kin, but they do seem to be kindred spirits, thoughtful and courteous and also aware of the ambiguities of their shared project. “Moving Midway” may not advance any grand new thesis about the South and its history, but it turns an old house into a rich and strange repository of local knowledge.</text>
      <date>September 12, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>