<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In 1977 Nicky Barnes, by some accounts — his own, for sure — the most powerful drug dealer in Harlem, posed for the cover of The New York Times Magazine. The headline, “Mr. Untouchable,” is now the title of a flashy new documentary directed by Marc Levin that opens, conveniently, a week before “American Gangster,” Ridley Scott’s epic rendering of the career of one of Mr. Barnes’s rivals.  Dressing up for magazine photographers and flaunting his success at evading punishment was probably an unwise display of hubris on Mr. Barnes’s part. Once the New York Police Department, the Department of Justice and President Jimmy Carter saw the article, Mr. Barnes’s days as a free man were numbered, and before long he was in prison. But the nickname nonetheless remains apt, since Mr. Barnes, interviewed extensively for “Mr. Untouchable,” seems untouched by remorse, regret or second thoughts.  And Mr. Levin’s film, though it duly includes testimony from police officers, prosecutors and journalists who covered the crime beat in those bad old New York days — how filmmakers seem to miss them — takes a tolerant, even admiring view of its subject. Old photographs show him as a stylish, smiling fixture of the social scene. In the present-day interviews, his face is shadowed (he has been a protected government witness for many years), and he sits at a boardroom table like a corporate chief executive. The camera zooms in on his hands, noting the heavy gold watch and pinkie ring and observing as he fondles carefully selected props, including stacks of money and a single bullet.  Mr. Barnes comes across as thoughtful, well read (Machiavelli is a particular favorite) and utterly ruthless. His associates recall the glory days of the Harlem heroin syndicate, lauding his business acumen and his unsentimental, brutal manner of dealing with rivals and turncoats. There is some acknowledgment of the terrible effects of the drug trade on residents of Harlem and other poor New York neighborhoods, but for the most part “Mr. Untouchable” clings to the standard hip-hop mythology of the pusher as entrepreneur, rebel, celebrity and folk hero.  That narrative is complicated somewhat by the fact that Mr. Barnes was also a snitch, rolling over on his underlings, his partners and even the mother of his children once it became clear that he could no longer run his business from the penitentiary. The survivors express shock and betrayal — is there no honor among thieves? — but Mr. Barnes just laughs, the mirthless chuckle of a true capitalist hustler who will use anyone, criminal, lawyer or documentary filmmaker, to serve his own interests.  “Mr. Untouchable” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for pervasive drug content, strong language, some violent images and brief nudity.  MR.</text>
      <date>October 26, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>