<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The wonderful independent film “Mutual Appreciation” looks like something that just came out of a time capsule, but there’s nothing dusty about it. Shot on expressively grainy black-and-white celluloid, the film has the kind of artfully artless, low-fi vibe that brings to mind the French New Wave of the late 1950’s and the East Village film scene of the late 1970’s. It’s the sort of unassuming discovery that could get lost in a crowd or suffer from too much big love, and while it won’t save or change your life, it may make your heart swell. Its aim is modest and true.  The film was written and directed by the 29-year-old Andrew Bujalski, who, in keeping with the D.I.Y. ethos of classic independence, plays one of the film’s leads, a teaching assistant named Lawrence. He enters soon after the film opens, as another young man, Alan (Justin Rice), talks with a young woman, Ellie (Rachel Clift), on a bed plopped on the floor of a sparsely furnished apartment. The two are clothed, but from the easiness of their conversation and the way her arms move, almost as if they wanted to reach out across the bed, it feels as if maybe they wish they weren’t. The bed belongs to Lawrence, who, on entering this cozy setup, promptly wedges his body between his girlfriend and best friend.  Lawrence loves Ellie, and she says she loves him, but one year into the relationship she seems uneasy. Maybe it’s Lawrence or maybe it’s Alan: your boyfriend’s rock-musician best friend can do that to a girl, though Mr. Bujalski would never propose something so psychologically crude. His characters are self-conscious if not especially self-aware, and he isn’t about to let on that he’s more on the ball than they are. And, in a sense, they’re both still figuring it out. Mr. Bujalski earned some serious critical attention with his even more unassuming first feature, “Funny Ha Ha,” which was more knowing than its scruffy surfaces might suggest. The more openly ambitious “Mutual Appreciation” shows that the first film wasn’t a fluke and that Mr. Bujalski is beginning to appreciate visual beauty.  ‘“Mutual Appreciation” is what might be called character-driven, because not much happens. But Alan, Ellie and Lawrence don’t actually drive the film; they inhabit it, like people who took up residence long ago. So, what’s it about? Everything, nothing. Mostly, though, it’s about a group of young people trying to figure out where they fit into the world. And so they talk and talk and talk some more, circling and hedging and stammering “you know, umm.” Ellie teases Lawrence, who’s so deep in the relationship he can’t see her struggle. Hiding behind a killer smile, Alan repeats questions like a defense witness, as when Sara (Seung-Min Lee) asks if he has a girlfriend. “Do I have a girlfriend?” he echoes, as if wondering the same.  That scene with Alan and Sara is just about perfect. Alan, the only remaining member of a band called the Bumblebees, meets Sara at a radio station where she’s a D.J. They end up at her apartment, where he scrutinizes her books as if looking for clues. She offers him a beer and sits on her bed, apologizing that there are no chairs. (Never mind the sofa in the other room.) After she asks about a girlfriend and he repeats the question, Mr. Bujalski cuts from the two sitting together to Sara climbing onto Alan’s suddenly prone body. The cut underscores the scene’s painful comedy (it’s funny ha ha), but it also deepens the feeling because it reminds us of how bodies can speak more plaintively than words.  In writing about “Funny Ha Ha,” critics sometimes invoked John Cassavetes, the godhead of American independent cinema. Cassavetes too often serves as shorthand for anything that looks and sounds somewhat rough around the edges, authentic and seemingly unscripted (though what a burden that name can be, especially for young filmmakers). But what connects “Funny Ha Ha” and “Mutual Appreciation” to Cassavetes, or at least his legacy of willful independence, isn’t the handheld camera work or the persistent intimacy, which could have easily been learned from cinéma vérité. If Mr. Bujalski has learned anything from Cassavetes, it’s that films should be about life, not death, fashion or virtuosity, and that there are few more meaningful subjects for art and for personal expression than other people.  If “Mutual Appreciation” doesn’t look like any film out on screens today, it does boldly look back at Jean Eustache’s landmark of modern French cinema, “The Mother and the Whore.” Released in 1973, Eustache’s long generational bleat pivots on a handful of chatty young Parisians who are blotto with booze, sex and narcissism. The men and women in “Mutual Appreciation” often come across as being as inwardly directed as those in the Eustache; the crucial difference is that the shadow of 1968 that hangs over the French characters invests their self-absorption with an intimation of tragedy. Mr. Bujalski’s characters, by contrast, don’t even have generational failure on their side, an absence of history, of myth, alluded to by Alan’s drunken confession that all he wants out of life is “a good story.”  In a different film, that good story might mean a record deal and a surfeit of cool. But, like Ryan Fleck’s “Half Nelson” and Kelly Reichardt’s forthcoming “Old Joy,” two other hopeful signs of cinematic life from young American directors, “Mutual Appreciation” is a film that makes a strong, sincere case that we only get that good story with other people. It’s not for nothing that Alan is a man in search of a band. The need for mutual appreciation, as it were, is beautifully telegraphed by Mr. Bujalski in that scene when Sara abruptly tackles Alan. She tells him he seems nervous, not knowing that one of his hands is hovering above her back, trembling like a flag of surrender. “I just have, uh,” he stammers, “a congenital tremor.</text>
      <date>September 1, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>