<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>We've all met brash, loudmouthed go-getters like Brian Herzlinger, the garrulous fuzzball who narrates the personal documentary "My Date With Drew." When such people zero in on someone they want to know, they are often relentless in their pursuit. If they possess the charm to match their aggressiveness, chances are they will eventually wear down their prey. If they don't, pushiness can turn into intimidation and pursuit into stalking; then it's time to call the police. Fortunately, Mr. Herzlinger, who directed his home movie with Jon Gunn and Brett Winn, is a reasonably likable guy. His screen presence, however, takes some getting used to. For the first 45 minutes of a cinematic stunt in which he invites us to be witnesses as he tries to meet his childhood heartthrob, Drew Barrymore, his obnoxiousness outweighs his charm. But in the second half of the movie, when he finally collapses into an excitable grown-up baby, his charm wins out. His quest begins when he wins $1,100 on a game show pilot by giving the right answer, "Drew Barrymore," to a question posed in the final round and impulsively decides to squander the prize money by making a film documenting his campaign to meet this star. He gives himself a deadline of 30 days to succeed. Lacking the funds for a digital video camera, he uses a friend's credit card at Circuit City to buy one, which he plans to use and then return under the store's 30-day free trial policy. Early in the film, Mr. Herzlinger declares that he has had a crush on Ms. Barrymore since he was 6. He immediately begins trying to contact everyone who has had any kind of professional relationship with her and sends a 30-second trailer for his project to her production company. As his movie-in-progress goes along, his pursuit of a childhood dream looks increasingly like an excuse by a canny aspiring filmmaker to create a work sample. The facade of a brash, sad-sack clown that he presents to the camera seems as shrewdly calculated as Michael Moore's working-class everyman; it's shtick. Mr. Herzlinger holds a casting call for Drew Barrymore look-alikes and takes the winner on a trial date to a restaurant from which he scrounges a free meal. He pesters an old girlfriend over the phone for dating tips. He has his blackheads squeezed out by Ms. Barrymore's facialist and frets about his hirsute appearance. When her new movie, "Charlie's Angels: Full Throttle," has its Hollywood premiere, he has a friend design fake passes to the after-party. "My Date With Drew" is a revealing examination of the protective shell that surrounds Hollywood royalty. But as we become better acquainted with Mr. Herzlinger, it seems obvious that he and Hollywood are made for each other; a streak of shameless, go-for-broke exhibitionism is almost a job requirement. There would probably be no movie if Mr. Herzlinger didn't eventually realize his dream. America's sweetheart, when she finally appears, is in full command of her sweetly ditzy screen personality. She and Mr. Herzlinger are eternal children and kindred spirits, both under the spell of celluloid fairy dust; they really do understand each other. "My Date With Drew" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has strong language.</text>
      <date>August 5, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>