<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Just about everyone who has been the parent of a young child has a priceless collection of masterpieces: treasured drawings and paintings  taped to a closet door, stuck to the refrigerator with magnets or rolled up in a box somewhere in the basement. The value of these artifacts is personal and sentimental,  but they can also have an aesthetic power that goes beyond parental pride. The untaught sense of color and composition that children seem naturally to possess sometimes yields extraordinary results, and the combination of instinct and accident that governs their creative activity can  produce astonishing works of art.  Except that these magical finger-paint daubings and crayon scribblings aren’t really works of art in any coherent sense of the term, but rather the vital byproducts of play, part of the cognitive and sensory awakening that is the grand, universal vocation of childhood. The urge to commodify and display them is, primarily, an adult expression of appreciation and nostalgia. We love our children, and we long for the children we used to be. These feelings are, for the most part, perfectly benign. “My Kid Could Paint That,” a new documentary directed by Amir Bar-Lev, is troubling because it explores a case in which the grown-up fascination with a child’s art appears to have spun out of control.  The child is Marla Olmstead, who was born in 2000 and who found herself, a few years ago, at the center of a minor media frenzy. As far as anyone can tell, it all started innocently enough. Marla’s father, Mark, a factory manager in Binghamton, N.Y., was also an amateur painter who set his daughter up with brushes and canvases while she was still in diapers. On a whim, Mark and his wife, Laura, a dental assistant, exhibited some of Marla’s paintings in a friend’s coffee shop, where patrons expressed interest in buying them. A show at a Binghamton gallery owned by Anthony Brunelli followed, and a column in the local newspaper begat an article in this one. Soon Marla and her family were being interviewed on national television, and her paintings were fetching five-figure prices.  Mr. Bar-Lev assiduously traces Marla’s rise to fame, and also chronicles the backlash that followed when a “60 Minutes” report suggested that her father may have been helping her paint, or even presenting his work as hers. As “My Kid Could Paint That” unfolds, its emphasis shifts. A story that had seemed to raise philosophical questions about the nature of art after modernism — some of them posed by Michael Kimmelman, chief art critic for The New York Times — evolves into a queasy study of the culture of celebrity.  It is also an intimate, sometimes unsettling family drama. At the center is not really Marla, who has a sweet smile and a shy, delicate demeanor, but rather her parents. Throughout the film, Laura voices her apprehensions about subjecting Marla to so much public attention at so young an age. When asked if she’s having fun riding in limousines or appearing on talk shows, Laura tends to say no, and a quiet tension between her and her husband is evident in many scenes. Mark is more enthusiastic about Marla’s fame, so much so that his promotion of her career, like Mr. Brunelli’s, begins to seem opportunistic, even exploitative.  But both men are also caught up in a process beyond their control, trying to ride the beast of media celebrity without getting eaten by it. Elizabeth Cohen, the journalist at The Binghamton Press &amp; Sun-Bulletin who wrote the first article about Marla, serves as the film’s resident media critic and also as its (guilty) conscience, worrying about the corrupting, distorting effects of Marla’s success. There is something frightening about the breathless, overwrought excitement that greeted the first news of the child’s  paintings, and also about the ugly rage that followed the “60 Minutes” report. Ms. Cohen sensibly asks whether it might have been better for everyone if the Olmsteads had been left alone.  She quite properly directs this question — one that’s also clearly on Laura Olmstead’s mind — at Mr. Bar-Lev, who spends a bit of time worrying about his own motives and expressing ambivalence about his film. Mr. Kimmelman tells him, “Your documentary on some level is going to be a lie,” meaning that it will be a necessarily partial and constructed representation of the truth.  Of course. But there is, I think, a deeper dishonesty in “My Kid Could Paint That,” a bad faith that lies precisely in Mr. Bar-Lev’s studied displays of doubt and unease. Acknowledging that he as much as anyone else is guilty of exploiting Marla is an exemplary postmodern move, but it hardly lets him off the hook. He has made an excellent documentary, but it would have been better if he had not made it at all.    “My Kid Could Paint That” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some adult language.</text>
      <date>October 5, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>