<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the endearing but somewhat scatterbrained British film "Nanny McPhee," Emma Thompson creates an indelible character reminiscent of Mary Poppins as conceived by the author P. L. Travers and the illustrator Mary Shepard. Created in 1934, three decades before Disney and Julie Andrews got hold of her and dipped her in saccharine, the original Mary Poppins was a forbidding,  tight-lipped disciplinarian who dressed in black, rarely cracked a smile and wouldn't think of bursting into song.  The title character in "Nanny McPhee," loosely adapted from Christianna Brand's Nurse Matilda books (written in the 1960's), is a severe, unsmiling crone who wields a crooked walking stick that she raps hard on the floor to conjure magic. McPhee also has an alarming habit of materializing out of thin air while always insisting (in one of the movie's running jokes) that she knocked beforehand. Ominously reassuring, she promises she will be there "when you need me but don't want me."  Unlike Poppins, McPhee is a clownish figure with a bulbous nose, facial warts and a buck tooth that droops over her lower lip. As she shapes up a chaotic brood of seven children who have driven their widowed father, Mr. Brown (Colin Firth), to his wits' end, her physical flaws melt away, one by one.  The day she arrives on the doorstep out of the blue, Mr. Brown, who works in a funeral parlor, is facing imminent financial ruin and the breakup of his family, having run through 17 nannies, who all  were driven out of the house by his impossible brood. He has been put on notice by his  wife's wealthy, imperious Aunt Adelaide (Angela Lansbury), who has been supporting the family, that unless he remarries within a month, she will cut them off. The role of the dithery, harried dad is well off the beaten path for Mr. Firth, but he dispatches it with unassuming ease.  Just as she arrives, the children are gleefully destroying the kitchen and have tied up the family's good-hearted cook, Mrs. Blatherwick (Imelda Staunton). McPhee sets to work immediately: her strategy is to let the children have their way until she conjures a magical moment of reckoning. Once they've started making mischief, the children are unable to stop what they've started until they beg "please," and she calls a halt to the spell.  "Nanny McPhee," directed by Kirk Jones ("Waking Ned Devine") from a screenplay by Ms. Thompson, is a movie whose twisted visual imagination is more forceful than its wobbly, zigzagging narrative. The story goes off on tangents. After visiting the funeral parlor where Mr. Brown works with two assistants, Mr. Wheen (Derek Jacobi) and Mr. Jowls (Patrick Barlow), the movie largely forgets about them. And, under closer scrutiny, McPhee's techniques of behavior modification don't always make sense.  Against the magical goings-on, the movie awkwardly juxtaposes an undernourished love story about the secret crush shared by Mr. Brown and his sweet, shy scullery maid,  Evangeline (Kelly Macdonald), who is whisked away by Aunt Adelaide, taught elocution and  returned to the family speaking like a lady.  The movie's boldest stroke is its garish visual palette, which paints late-Victorian Britain in psychedelic Day-Glo hues. Much of the visual excess is heaped on the odious Mrs. Quickly (Celia Imrie), a snobbish, carnivorous widow to whom Mr. Brown, to meet the marriage deadline, becomes engaged. Outfitted in glaring fuchsia, she strolls around with two pet sheep, each dyed a different hideous color.  Delightful performances buoy the movie immensely. Ms. Lansbury's frosty Adelaide is as intimidating as any snobbish grande dame embodied by the mistress of hauteur, Dame Judi Dench. Ms. Macdonald blossoms like an English rose in the sunlight. Ms. Staunton's Mrs. Blatherwick is as spluttery and sentimental as Angela Baddeley's Mrs. Bridges from the television series "Upstairs, Downstairs." As Simon, the oldest and most diabolical of the holy terrors, Thomas Sangster wears the Mephistophelean grin of a pubescent Mick Jagger plotting mischief.  Richest of all is Ms. Thompson's McPhee, who conveys with a thousand subtle hints that just behind her affronted snaggletoothed glare lies a reservoir of affection and good will.  "Nanny McPhee"  is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested).  It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>January 27, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>