<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It’s best to think of “The Nativity Story” as a Hollywood version of the kind of Christmas production some of  the “Peanuts” kids put on in “A Charlie Brown Christmas.” This is not meant as a criticism. Quite the contrary.  Directed by Catherine Hardwicke from a script by Mike Rich, “The Nativity Story” sticks to the familiar details of the narrative and dramatizes them with sincerity and good taste. There are no flights of actorly or cinematic bravura — though  all of the performances are credible, and some better than that — and very few big, showy, epic gestures. Rather than trying to reinterpret or modernize a well-known, cherished story, the filmmakers have rendered it with a quiet, unassuming professionalism.  The challenge in producing a movie like this is to find enough conventional movie elements — suspense, realistic characters, convincing dialogue — without selling out the scriptural source. How do you make piety entertaining without seeming impious?  A certain degree of kitsch is inevitable, and perhaps even desirable.  The Bible supplies a ripe villain in the person of Herod, who is impersonated here, with a stagy frown and magnificent hair, by Ciaran Hinds.  The three wise men (Nadim Sawalha, Eriq Ebouaney and Stefan Kalipha) provide some comic relief along with the gold, frankincense and myrrh. They quarrel and kvetch their way across the desert like Hope and Crosby (or Moe, Larry and Curly) on the road to Morocco (which happens to be where much of “The Nativity Story” was filmed).  The movie has been cast with an eye toward authenticity rather than renown, which spares audiences the distraction of seeing familiar movie stars in robes and sandals. Instead  we have an impressive sampling of international actors; they come from Northern Ireland, Guatemala, Cameroon, Iran and even, aptly enough, Nazareth. Their accents sometimes clash — the ancient Israelites have apparently been instructed to sound like modern Israelis when they speak the English dialogue — but this could hardly have been avoided.  Several plots are threaded together, as the film synthesizes the plain, step-by-step storytelling of the Gospels according to modern screenwriting conventions. (It starts with the massacre of the innocents and then flashes back “one year earlier” to the story of  Zechariah and Elizabeth, parents of John the Baptist.) Political events — Herod’s paranoid cruelty and the brutality of the Roman occupation — are juxtaposed with the more intimate story of Mary and her family.    Keisha Castle-Hughes, the 16-year-old New Zealand actress (and the youngest-ever  best-actress Oscar nominee, for “Whale Rider” a few years ago), seems entirely unfazed by the demands of playing Mary. She has the poise and intelligence to play the character not as an icon of maternity, but rather as a headstrong, thoughtful adolescent transformed by an unimaginable responsibility. Mary’s stubbornness and her honesty make her entirely believable, and the film’s most subtle and lively dramatic thread concerns her maturation from an ordinary Nazareth teenager into a wife and expectant mother.  In “Thirteen” and “Lords of Dogtown,” Ms. Hardwicke’s previous films as a director — a role she took up after a long career as a production designer — she   showed an unusual sensitivity to the feelings and motives of young people growing up too fast, and a similar sympathy infuses her understanding of Mary. Without making the character into an anachronism, she and Mr. Rich try to imagine what Mary’s experience must have felt like. The daughter of loving, worried parents (Shaun Toub and Hiam Abbass), she must absorb first the shock of an arranged marriage (to Oscar Isaac’s Joseph) and then the startling attention of the Archangel Gabriel (Alexander Siddig).  One of the vivid memories of my earlier life as a movie-mad college student is of the protesters picketing a theater showing Jean-Luc Godard’s “Hail Mary,” a film whose retelling of the Nativity story was presumed, sight unseen, to be blasphemous. Ms. Hardwicke’s version, aimed at a global mass audience in the Christmas season, steers clear of both  Mr. Godard’s provocations and the confrontational style of Mel Gibson’s “Passion of the Christ.” At its best, though, “The Nativity Story” shares with “Hail Mary” an interest in finding a kernel of realism in the old story of a pregnant teenager in hard times. Buried in the pageantry, in other words, is an interesting movie.  “The Nativity Story” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). There is some violence, most of it implied rather than graphically shown.</text>
      <date>December 1, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>