<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the flat romantic comedy “New  in Town,” Renée Zellweger plays Lucy Hill, a shark in spike heels who wields pretentious corporate jargon like a machete. An aspiring master of the universe who works at the Miami headquarters of a food-processing giant, Lucy is dispatched to an underperforming branch in New Ulm, Minn.,   to oversee slash-and-burn operations. After a few minutes of listening to her running off at the mouth, you may never again want to hear “dialogue” used as a verb.  But the good citizens of New Ulm, including the hunky local union representative, Ted Mitchell (Harry Connick Jr.), will have none of her highfalutin double talk. In the movie, directed by Jonas Elmer from a screenplay by Kenneth Rance and C. Jay Cox, they thaw her frozen heart with tapioca, home baking and handmade valentines. As she warms to Ted, a bearded widower with a 13-year-old daughter, she even loses her contempt for men who drink beer.  The story contains the nub of a workable concept. What could be more pertinent than a yarn in which an arrogant, number-crunching city slicker regains her humanity when faced with decent, hard-working everyday folks in the provinces? But “New In Town” has no idea of  how to play its cards. From their regional accents to their cutesy-poo vocabulary (lots of okey-dokeys), the Minnesotans whom Lucy encounters are ludicrous parodies of the characters in “Fargo.”  You feel as if you are watching creatures more exotic than Snow White’s seven dwarfs.  In particular Lucy’s tapioca-obsessed secretary, Blanche Gunderson (Siobhan Fallon Hogan), acts as though she had been instructed to exponentially multiply the mannerisms of Frances McDormand’s police officer in “Fargo.”  Playing Stu Kopenhafer, the plant manager whom Lucy summarily fires, J. K. Simmons —  outfitted in what appears to be a modified fat suit —  struggles to maintain some dignity.  The calm, all-forgiving Ted, whom  Lucy has repeatedly insulted, comes to her rescue after she swerves into a snowdrift to avoid hitting a cow. During a crow-hunting expedition  she accidentally shoots him in the buttocks, and the next day the smirking workers show up  at the plant wearing targets on their backsides. That’s about as witty as “New  in Town” gets.  Lucy, for her part, brings a little Miami sophistication to New Ulm. She supervises a makeover for Ted’s daughter on the eve of a school dance. Just as the plant is about to be closed, she comes up with an emergency rescue plan that involves Blanche’s secret recipe for tapioca. The movie doesn’t bother to show how the plan is executed in record time.  Watching Ms. Zellweger’s joyless performance, you have to wonder what happened to this formerly charming actress who not so long ago seemed on the verge of becoming a softer, more vulnerable  Shirley MacLaine. As a corporate climber, her edge is all in her clacking heels, not in her bland performance. She is equally unconvincing as a cozy, born-again everyday person with a sense of community responsibility. And where is her most appealing mannerism, her dimpled smile? In a performance that operates as if on automatic pilot, it has faded away.  “New in Town” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>January 30, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>