<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Toward the end of Terrence Malick's elegiac film, "The New World," the young Indian princess known as Pocahontas - the "delight and darling" of her father, the king of the Powhatans of coastal Virginia - pauses in front of a gilt cage containing a live skunk. Brought from the New World to the Old in 1616, this morose creature, curled as tight as a fist, is being presented to the English court alongside a bald eagle, an Indian priest and Pocahontas herself. The princess, dressed in Jacobean costume, a ruff collar fluting around her throat, and played by the sublimely lovely newcomer Q'orianka Kilcher, looks both at ease and entirely foreign. When she sees this pitiful captive, does she see  any part of herself?  If that question is never answered in "The New World," it is because Mr. Malick, who wrote and directed the film, his fourth in three decades, never presumes to know the answer. For the filmmaker, who is more poet than historian, Pocahontas is clearly a metaphor (virgin land, as it were), but to see her as exclusively metaphor would only repeat history's error. What interests Mr. Malick is how and why enlightened free men, when presented with new realms of possibility, decided to remake this world in their own image: free men like Capt. John Smith (Colin Farrell), who marvels at the beauty of a place where "the blessings of the earth are bestowed on all" while Indians lie bound in his boat, and who claims to love, only to destroy.  Smith, whose histories provide much of what is known about Pocahontas, was part of a contingent of some 100 men charged with founding an American colony on behalf of the London-based Virginia Company. In April 1607, three of the company's ships dropped anchor off the Virginia coast and a group ventured ashore. What they found, one of the actual settlers wrote in a near-swoon, were "faire meddowes and goodly tall Trees, with such Fresh-waters running through the woods as I was almost ravished at the sight thereof." The colonists had entered a paradise, but they were looking for gold and a river route to the South Seas, not meadows and trees. They found Indians, too, though in Mr. Malick's description of this mutual encounter, it was not a happy discovery for either party.  The filmmaker opens "The New World" with images of rippling water, swimmers shot from beneath and the woman we will soon come to know as Pocahontas as she utters what sounds like a prayer ("sing the song of a land"). After a brief credit sequence, James Horner's score gives way to chirping birds, blowing wind and what might be the rumble of distant thunder or a cannon blast. This cacophony then melts into the opening notes of the prelude to Wagner's "Das Rheingold," the first opera in "Der Ring des Nibelungen." A haunting drone meant to suggest the rippling of the Rhine River, the prelude begins as a whisper that grows progressively louder until it reaches a crescendo, signaling the moment when the Rhinemaidens realize that the Nibelung dwarf Alberich has forsworn love for gold and power.  The musical chords ripple with escalating intensity as Indians run along the shore, excitedly pointing at the three ships. With a restless, searching camera that finds realms of beauty in a single leaf and the downy hair on a woman's forearm, Mr. Malick gives us a palpable sense of what this unspoiled place must have looked like to the English, what was found and soon would be lost. Like Smith, we come to this new world slowly, first in intoxicating glimpses, then in sweeping vistas. A soldier and an autodidact, Smith escaped captivity in Turkey and was said to have read Machiavelli; Mr. Farrell's captain doesn't look like much of a reader (or a greedy dwarf), but he does look like trouble.  Soon after they land, the colonists shut themselves in a fort and raise a towering cross. Smith, meanwhile, charged with finding fresh supplies, is imprisoned by Indians, brought before Pocahontas's father (called Powhatan and played by August Schellenberg) and either almost killed or just seriously frightened. The story of Smith's brush with death, which may have instead been an initiation ritual, remains under dispute. Mr. Malick stages the scene like a hallucination, a freak-out with shadows and smoke. Smith wrote that Pocahontas, then between 10 and 12 - though here she looks dangerously older - begged her father to spare  the colonist's life. The purported rescue inspired myths about a romance, which in turn fed lurid fantasies about natives and the forces of civilization and helped fuel justifications for the domination of a land and its people.  In a gutsy move, the filmmaker represents this romance between Pocahontas and Smith as real, but only to flip it on its head. In quiet, drifting scenes set amid surreally beautiful wilds (the Virginia locations are paradisiacal) the two slowly circle each other like dancers, their respective interior monologues filling in the silence between them. In the past, Mr. Malick's fondness for voice-over has sometimes seemed like a crutch, symptomatic of a weak screenplay, as in his last film, "The Thin Red Line," or as a misplaced bid at naïve consciousness. Here, though, you feel as if you are eavesdropping inside the characters' heads. While Pocahontas's voice-overs are filled with schoolgirlish yearning, Smith sounds dangerously lofty, as if he is rehearsing the dissembling that will shape his later histories.  If the affair seems strangely ethereal, as if it were taking place in another dimension, in a lovelier, more enchanted realm, it is because Mr. Malick is fashioning a countermythology in "The New World," one to replace, or at least challenge, a mythology already in place. In Mr. Malick's interpretation, Pocahontas is no longer  the simple girl of Smith's fanciful imaginings or the acquiescent native who bows to take the English yoke, thereby making way for all the colonies to come and all the catastrophes perpetuated against native peoples. Pocahontas is still irrefutably "other"; for a filmmaker living 400 years later in another world and different skin, there is no alternative. He is still putting words into her mouth, but with scrupulous tenderness.  The story of Pocahontas has inspired poems and portraits, histories and biographies and a 1995 Disney animated feature in which the cartoon princess wears what looks like a very full C-cup. "Captain Smith and Pocahontas," Peggy Lee sang, "had a very mad affair." Ripe for discovery and exploitation, she is uncharted territory and she has always sent temperatures rising. But Mr. Malick's Pocahontas, while impossibly young (the mature-looking Ms. Kilcher was 14 when the film was shot), is also the agent of her own destiny, never more so than after she and Smith are separated. The two are parted just as Mr. Farrell's moony reveries threaten to drown Pocahontas's voice. Once he is out of the picture, though, she secures her voice and then a husband (an excellent Christian Bale), and ushers the story toward its shattering close.  The real Pocahontas died in England in 1617, probably of tuberculosis or pneumonia, between the ages of 20 to 22, in the presence of  her first or second husband. By then she was Lady Rebecca and had met Ben Jonson. At one time, her life may have been her own, but with her death that was no longer true. Like those Indian princesses who have long been a favorite of Hollywood, the pop Pocahontas who later emerged in song and cartoons is a comfortable fiction, at least for a country eager to tell its story in the best possible light. In that telling, Pocahontas is the noble savage exalted by an impulse to self-sacrifice for a white man. In Mr. Malick's telling, Pocahontas is a woman whose story has the reach of myth and the tragic dimension of life.  "The New World" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). There is some intense, bloodless violence and the beautiful underage lead actress may cause cardiac arrest among some viewers.</text>
      <date>December 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>