<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> As thin as an iPod Nano, as full of adolescent self-display as a Facebook page, “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist” strives to capture, in meticulous detail, what it’s like to be young right now. Working from a popular novel by Rachel Cohn and David Levithan (and an idiomatically spot-on screenplay by Lorene Scafaria) the director, Peter Sollett, spins a shy, sweet romance around a carefully chosen soundtrack with music (and cameo appearances) by such emblems of up-to-the-minute hipster credibility as the singer-songwriter Devendra  Banhart and the band Bishop Allen, among others.  Nick and Norah, New Jersey high school students bouncing through the rock clubs of New York, are drawn together by their shared musical passions (in particular for an enigmatic band called Where’s Fluffy). The tunes that play alongside their nocturnal adventure express longing, sadness, anxiety and joy with more intensity than they can muster themselves. Nick, played by the wet-noodle heartthrob Michael Cera (“Juno,” “Superbad”) and Norah (Kat Dennings, who has a hint of Kate Winslet’s soft, smart loveliness in her face) are, like so many kids these days, most comfortable with diffidence, understatement and a deadpan style of address that collapses the distinction between irony and sincerity.  Norah’s wary, pouty manner and Nick’s odd mix of timidity and sarcasm are both strategies of self-protection. He has recently been dumped by Tris (Alex Dziena), a schoolmate of Norah’s and one of her social oppressors. She has a sometime boyfriend (Jay Baruchel) and, behind her mask of indifference, a lot of self-doubt. The daughter of a recording industry big shot, Norah is never sure if anyone likes her for herself. Nick, for his part, seems unsure about whether he likes himself at all.  But Nick and Norah are cool, and also nice. Which is cool for “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist,” and nice for them, but also somewhat limiting. Mr. Sollett shows an admirably low-key directorial temperament, resisting the temptations of melodrama and farce that hover around any teenage romantic comedy. Like “Raising Victor Vargas,” his earlier feature (also about lovestruck young people in Lower Manhattan, but set in a demographic universe far removed from Nick and Norah’s zone of suburban entitlement), “Infinite Playlist” regards its characters with affectionate detachment, and assures its audience that no great calamities or revelations are in store. Instead, there are a series of small crises and tiny epiphanies, all adding up to a story that courts triviality in its pursuit of charm.  The charm is there, not least in the film’s vision of New York as a happy playground for underage night owls. The city’s streets are so benign that Nick’s abandonment of a girl (not Norah) in a desolate spot on the West Side can seem like a forgivable failure of gallantry, rather than an act of passive-aggressive, potentially homicidal malice. Everyone has a cellphone, after all, and the criminals and crazies that used to haunt these neighborhoods are little more than flickering memories from older movies.  Partly because of its structure — it takes place in the course of a single night during which time races, dawdles, pauses and skips — “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist” may remind you of some older movies. It’s like Martin Scorsese’s “After Hours” filtered through the high school sensibility of John Hughes, or Richard Linklater’s “Before Sunrise” remade for Nickelodeon.  All of which I mean, mostly, as praise. Unlike run-of-the-mill teensploitation comedies that smirk at or condescend to the young, this film is smart about its audience, and respectful of it as well. The language and sexual activity are kept within PG-13 boundaries, but the script, like the book, is calmly candid about what adolescents do and say, sexually and otherwise, in the age of Too Much Information and Friends With Benefits. Neither prurient nor moralistic, “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist” surveys the varieties of teenage experience with tolerant sympathy, which is for the most part how the characters — gay and straight, reckless and cautious, drunk and sober — regard one another.  Indeed, the movie is so friendly that you may wish for a little more conflict: higher emotional stakes, riskier jokes, a touch of danger in the night air. But maybe those are age-inappropriate preoccupations. Just about everyone in “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist” seems to be having a good time, and most of them seem like good kids (though Norah’s friend Caroline, played by a scene-stealing Ari Graynor, is probably headed for a stint in rehab). Why begrudge them their fun, or wish premature heartache upon them? There will be plenty of time for the blues later on, which is all the more reason to savor the fleeting, teasing pop pleasures this movie celebrates and dispenses.  “Nick &amp; Norah’s Infinite Playlist” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has profanity, sexual references and situations, and underage drinking.</text>
      <date>October 3, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>