<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Hollywood used to know how to make a lady suffer. It might have thrown her around a little and smudged her mascara, but it also gave as much as it took, delivering the pleasurable goods along with the pain. The emotions were as phony as the tears, yet with the right director, star or script, all that weeping could send an arrow straight through your heart. The audience worshiped Our Lady of Masochism for her misery but also for her triumph, for the mink swaddling her shoulder pads, for the 100 sobbing violins, for the celestial halo circling her head. She was a glamorous sacrament, a delectable offering for the big-screen faithful.  It’s no wonder the faithful continue to forsake the movies, given junky embarrassments like “Nights in Rodanthe.” There’s no joy and not even much cruel laughter to be had from the spectacle of sympathetic actors — Richard Gere, Diane Lane,  Viola Davis, James Franco  — mouthing some of the most pitiful, platitudinous, risible dialogue in recent memory, particularly if you were suckered into  watching this movie specifically because of its performers. Even those with a high tolerance for melodramatic drivel, who have stuck by Sandra Bullock through thick, thin and her changing smile, or found themselves sniffling at “The Notebook” yet again because, well, Ryan Gosling and Rachel McAdams should be together, will find “Rodanthe” insulting, an assault on their already perilously weakened romantic hearts.  Adapted by Ann Peacock and John Romano  from the Nicholas Sparks novel and directed by George C. Wolfe (the former producer of the Public Theater, who fared better with his HBO movie “Lackawanna Blues”), “Nights in Rodanthe” revolves around the unhappily married Adrienne (Ms. Lane), who leaves her two nauseating children with her husband to baby-sit a North Carolina coastal inn owned by a friend (Ms. Davis), who has gone off for weekend sex with a muscled bit player. A hurricane is a-coming and so is Paul (Mr. Gere), one of those lonely Jaguar-driving geniuses of the operating room. The hurricane hits, and the shutters bang open and shut, which would be funnier if this film didn’t insist that the only road to a woman’s happiness runs up her legs.  You know the rest: trembling lips, delicate lovemaking, pop-song montage. Ms. Lane and Mr. Gere smile bravely and fumble like teenagers but are defeated by the scripted clichés and lack of focused direction. Mr. Wolfe seems as uncomfortable with the material as his leads are, though it’s impossible to know if he’s uninterested in this romance or whether his disjointed storytelling is a result of post-production triage.  Whatever the case, it’s a shame that beautiful movie suffering has gone the way of the durable hack, the kind of studio lifer who knew that action meant, you know, action, and came equipped with a cinematographer who could turn light and shadow and all those glistening tears into a night to remember.  “Nights in Rodanthe” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned).</text>
      <date>September 26, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>