<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> During the final vignette of "Nine Lives," Rodrigo García's extraordinarily rich and satisfying suite of fleeting but intense moments in the lives of nine women, Maria (Dakota Fanning), a girl visiting a cemetery with her mother, Maggie (Glenn Close), notices a cat wandering on the lawn and wonders out loud if cats really have nine lives; her mother answers that she doesn't think so.  Maggie has spread out a picnic blanket in front of a modest tombstone that marks the grave of her husband or a close relative (the inscription is never shown nor is a name mentioned). Later, she stands guard behind a tree while her daughter urinates. At another point, she remarks at how amazing it is that people make it through life carrying so much heavy baggage.  This is how the moments unfold in the movie and in life, like the shadows of clouds skittering  across the lawn. While Maggie converses with her daughter, there is a split second in which her grief suddenly wells up, but she catches herself and swallows it. And in one slow, breathtaking shot, the camera pans 360 degrees to observe the trees and grass and to drink in the quiet of an eternal resting ground.  Although the vignette is set in a cemetery, it doesn't offer the sort of weepy closure that people go to the movies expecting to find. Nor do any of the film's eight other vignettes end in snug little epiphanies. Together, however, they add up to a film that may be the closest movies have come  to the cinematic equivalent of a collection of Chekhov short stories.  The film's reward for intense concentration is a feeling of deep empathy and connection. For once, you don't harbor the uneasy suspicion of having been emotionally manipulated. Given our immersion in the ways of Hollywood, the absence of that feeling may frustrate some moviegoers accustomed to getting the message in a neatly tied package.  In each vignette, filmed in one continuous Steadicam shot, a 10-to-14-minute slice of a different woman's life passes before your eyes in real time. The nuances of body language and details in the setting tell as much about the people in these stories as what is actually said.  Working with many of the actors who have appeared in his earlier mosaics, "Things You Can Tell Just by Looking at Her" (five vignettes) and "Ten Tiny Love Stories" (10 monologues), Mr. García has made a film that could be described as radically realistic. "Nine Lives" is a quantum leap better than its forerunners. In its subtle, understated performances, the actors vanish into characters who behave like ordinary people observed through one-way glass.  The movie begins in prison where an inmate, Sandra (Elpidia Carrillo), is visited by her young daughter and has a meltdown when the telephone connecting them for their five-minute monthly conversation fails. Sandra's treatment by the guards suggests she is an unruly prisoner, and this chapter leaves you with a chill of foreboding about her future in or out of jail.  It would be stretching a metaphor to say that all nine of the stories' focal characters are in some way imprisoned, unless the concept of imprisonment is meant to imply the notion of life itself as a kind of confinement. But Mr. García, the son of the Colombian writer Gabriel García Márquez, is too discreet and subtle a storyteller to voice the theme in more than a murmur.  With a Chekhovian objectivity and compassion, he brings to his characters' struggles and pains an evenhanded awareness of how the ties that bind also inevitably chafe. Diana (Robin Wright Penn), the second story's focal character, is a married, very pregnant woman with trouble in her face who runs into an old lover (Jason Isaacs), also now married, while in a supermarket. Erotic sparks fly, and she is gripped by the familiar, scary feeling of disappearing in his presence.  Holly (Lisa Gay Hamilton), an enraged African-American woman in the third vignette, returns to her childhood home to confront her estranged stepfather over childhood wounds that may have involved sexual abuse. In the fourth story, Sonia (Holly Hunter) and her boyfriend (Stephen Dillane) have a revealing fight while visiting the elegant new apartment of their closest friends (Mr. Isaacs and Molly Parker). Samantha (Amanda Seyfried), the beautiful, bright, teenage protagonist of the fifth vignette, resists leaving her disabled father (Ian McShane) and long-suffering mother (Sissy Spacek), to attend an elite Eastern college, for to leave would mean forsaking her role as parental go-between in an undeclared war.  Ms. Spacek's character is one of several in the movie to appear in more than one vignette. In the episode "Ruth," she has a secret motel rendezvous with a Scotch-swilling boyfriend (Aidan Quinn) on the night of a full moon.  In one of the rawest vignettes, Lorna (Amy Brenneman) finds herself an uneasy guest at the funeral of her ex-husband's wife. When the widower, who is deaf and communicates mostly in sign language, drags her aside and confesses his lingering passion for her, she is forced to acknowledge her contribution to the wife's suicide.  Anyone who has ever faced surgery can identify with Camille (Kathy Baker), a woman awaiting a mastectomy, who expresses her terror of "no consciousness" while under anesthesia and her horror at being "at the mercy of others" to her patient husband (Joe Mantegna).  As "Nine Lives" winds it way from a prison to a cemetery with stops in many houses along the way, it walks a tightrope. Any glitch in a film this committed to a delicate, slightly heightened realism, risks throwing the whole thing off the track. You hold your breath waiting for that false moment to arrive, and you heave a sigh of amazement and relief when it doesn't.  "Nine Lives" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>October 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>