<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the three loosely related stories that make up “The Nines,” a philosophical mind teaser with satirical fangs that marks the directing debut of the screenwriter John August, the stressed-out psyches of jockeying Hollywood muckety-mucks are disturbed by strange metaphysical intimations. Think of it as a kind of “Twilight Zone 2007” in which the paranoia endemic to an industry that runs on illusion, hype and extravagant grandiosity comes home to roost.  For the Hollywood player with the right job description and available technology, isn’t it tempting to imagine being God? A video-game designer or a reality-television director, as omnipotent creator and manipulator of a discrete little world, may fancy himself possessor of the keys to the kingdom.  Even garden-variety stars are regarded as semicelestial beings. Feed them drugs, and the distinctions between heaven and earth begin to blur. As that wise old sage Leonard Cohen muses in his world-is-going-to-hell-in-a-hand-basket song of pseudoprophecy, “Everybody Knows”: “Everybody knows that you live forever when you’ve done a line or two.”  In “The Nines” the game designer, the television producer and the star are all played by Ryan Reynolds, a blond, handsome B-list actor who in this movie shows glimmerings of A-list talent. If Mr. August’s screenplay demonstrates some of the imagination of a Charlie Kaufman script (“Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind,” for instance), “The Nines” isn’t a neatly packaged mind game like Mr. Kaufman’s cleverest films. Instead it playfully tosses out ideas, then leaves it to the viewer to read the pieces like tea leaves.  Mr. August’s screenwriting credits include “Go” (another three-part film), “Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,” “Big Fish,” “Corpse Bride” and two “Charlie’s Angels” movies. In the production notes for “The Nines” he writes that the middle chapter, in which a television producer has the rug pulled out from under him, is largely autobiographical.  Each section is about a half-hour long and features the same three actors. In Part 1, “The Prisoner,” Mr. Reynolds’s character, Gary, is a distraught television star who in a fit of rage tosses his ex-girlfriend’s clothes on the backyard barbecue, sets them on fire and goes on a bender of crack cocaine and booze that ends in a car crash. He winds up living under house arrest, tended by his unflappably cheerful publicist and devoted fixer, Margaret (Melissa McCarthy), who installs him in the empty house of a producer.  Idle and impatient, Gary begins a flirtation with Sarah (Hope Davis), his enigmatic, sexually aggressive next-door neighbor, and has hallucinations in which the number nine appears almost everywhere he looks. What does it mean? Margaret, who knows more than she is letting on, drops some provocative clues.  In Part 2, “Reality Television,” Mr. Reynolds plays Gavin, the house’s owner, whose latest project, “Knowing,” is a supernatural drama created for his best friend, Ms. McCarthy (who plays herself).  He originally pitched it as “Rosemary’s Toddler.” A network is supposedly high on the show, whose development is being filmed by Gavin as a “Project Greenlight”-like reality series under the supervision of Susan (Ms. Davis), his closest ally at the network.  At the last minute Susan betrays him and takes the side of the network boss who suddenly insists on replacing Ms. McCarthy with another actress. It is up to Gavin to deliver the bad news. And the scene in which he lowers the boom on her is such an awkward, ugly and painful confrontation, it feels as though it might have taken place.  In Part 3, “Knowing,” Mr. Reynolds is Gabriel, a video-game designer hiking in the Hollywood Hills with his wife, Mary (Ms. McCarthy), and their mute young daughter (Elle Fanning). Returning to their car, they find its battery dead and their cellphone reception blocked. Leaving his wife and daughter in the car, Gabriel goes to seek help and on the road meets Sierra (Ms. Davis), a hiker who at first shuns him, then reappears offering assistance that soon turns sinister. This third story could be an episode of Gavin’s series “Knowing,” as it might have been directed before Ms. McCarthy’s firing.  What matters in “The Nines” is how these vignettes glance off one another. The fact that the same actors appear in all three chapters gives you the uneasy sense that they might be variations of the same story, set in overlapping universes, in which the female characters, especially those played by Ms. McCarthy, know all the answers, which they are not allowed to reveal.  “The Nines” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language, some drug content and sexuality.</text>
      <date>August 31, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>