<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At some point Randall Miller, who has directed one movie about ballroom dancing and another about the wine trade — apparently decided he wanted to become a tough guy, or at least flex his genre muscles. Thus “Nobel Son,” an aggressively noisy exercise in style over substance about nasty people doing nasty things to one another in (sigh) Southern California. Like many contemporary genre flicks, the new movie features a hyperactive visual style that owes its tricks and tics, smeared images and staccato cuts to art-house exploitation like “City of God” and latter-day Tony Scott, but without the commensurate technical finesse.  Alan Rickman plays Eli Michaelson, who shortly after the story chugs to a start has won the Nobel Prize in chemistry, a milestone that delights no one save for him. A world-class heel and adulterer, a lousy father (to Bryan Greenberg’s Barkley) and worse husband (to Mary Steenburgen’s Sarah), Eli, with his monstrous ego, would be enough for a lot of movies but turns out to be merely the warm-up act for a chaotic plot involving a violent kidnapping, a distant suicide, murky secrets and outright distortions. Mr. Greenberg, whose character is writing a dissertation about cannibalism (he appears to be pro), somehow crosses paths first with Eliza Dushku and then with Shawn Hatosy, both of whom are better than their material.  Mr. Miller is clearly slumming in “Nobel Son” (it was shot before his recently released “Bottle Shock”), which wouldn’t be a problem if he seemed to be interested in playing with genre rather than condescending to it, as he does here. But from story to casting, “Nobel Son” feels designed for mockery, from the stunt casting (Danny DeVito as a dim-bulb neighbor, Ted Danson as a bow-tied academic) to the lazy parodies of coffeehouse poetry readings to the treatment of poor Ms. Dushku, who, as a wild-eyed poet who sleeps with the nominal hero, not only has to play the crazy woman and a hack artist but also has to brandish her thong underwear. Isn’t being young and female in Hollywood punishment enough?  There’s a bit more, mostly a throbbing techno score and a showy, disappointing performance from the almost always welcome Mr. Rickman. (He and Bill Pullman, who has a small role in this film as the requisite rumpled cop, were the headliners in “Bottle Shock.”) As Eli, Mr. Rickman oozes from scene to scene doing a fair approximation of a lizard with a little Joan Crawford thrown in for good (or bad) measure. Although it’s amusing to watch him point his nose in the air while taking aim at the ostensibly nicer characters, all of whom are even more tedious than Eli, the performance grows thin fast. Even lizards and villains need a perch, something more solid than noise and smears from which they can do their slithering.  “Nobel Son” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). One scene features the very bloody, nonsurgical removal of a thumb.</text>
      <date>December 5, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>