<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The gnarly dead tree in front of the Rodriguez house in Humboldt Park, a working-class Latino neighborhood of Chicago, will not be processed into kindling. As the Rodriguez menfolk, gathered for Christmas, attack it with chain saws, their incompetence with power tools makes them look like fools. Even when they try to drag it out of the earth with ropes and chains attached to a car, it refuses to budge.  That old dead tree is an unwieldy metaphor for family solidarity in “Nothing Like the Holidays,” an efficient home-for-Christmas ensemble comedy trimmed with plastic teardrops. But the tree might also stand for a wooden holiday genre in which uplift follows tumult as surely as Christmas morning follows Christmas Eve. The only distinguishing characteristic of this mildly agreeable variation of a worn-out formula is that the boisterous family under examination is Puerto Rican, and the screenplay includes a smattering of Spanish.  In its early scenes the movie, which has as many underdeveloped subplots as characters, threatens to be another melodrama about a returning soldier.  The glum Jesse (Freddy  Rodriguez), home from Iraq, is picked up at the airport by his neighborhood pals; sunglasses cover deep scratches around one eye that suggest he has had a set-to with a riled-up house cat.  But “Nothing Like the Holidays,” directed by Alfredo de Villa (“Washington Heights”) from a screenplay by Alison Swan and Rick Najera, has neither the time nor the inclination to explore Jesse’s malaise in any depth. Although he harbors guilt about the death of a friend in combat, what really bugs him is that Marissa (Melonie Diaz), the girlfriend he dumped, has happily settled down with another man.  No sooner has the Rodriguez clan gathered around the dinner table than the mother, Anna (Elizabeth Peña, who is at least a decade too young for her role), announces she is divorcing Eddy (Alfred Molina), her husband of 36 years, who owns a bodega; he allegedly cheated. The notion that a family-loving matriarch would make such a surprise announcement (even Eddy is ambushed) at a festive holiday reunion is simply bizarre.  Dinner, of course, is ruined. The taciturn Eddy, who urges a reluctant Jesse, the younger of his two sons, to go into the family business, has his own secret torment. (Hint: It’s medical.)  Anna, as written, is a disagreeable piece of work.  She badgers her non-Hispanic daughter-in-law, Sarah (Debra Messing), a yuppie banker, to give her a grandchild and mutters nasty things about her in Spanish, which Sarah can’t understand. The movie appears to take Anna’s side. Sarah is married to Anna’s oldest son, Mauricio (an unconvincing John Leguizamo in expensive eyewear), a successful lawyer.  Also on hand is a daughter, Roxanna (Vanessa Ferlito), a struggling television actress living in Hollywood who is waiting for a call from her agent about a part. Will Roxanna hook up with her hunky but shady childhood friend Ozzy (Jay Hernandez), who carries a gun along with a potentially lethal grudge against a neighbor? Ms. Ferlito and Mr. Hernandez lend the movie a smidgen of heat.  The most engaging moments of “Nothing Like the Holidays” are the festive party sequences in which the characters throw off their troubles to dance in the bodega and pour into the street in their Christmas finery. Their troubles momentarily forgotten, the residents of Humboldt Park really know how to enjoy themselves.  “Nothing Like the Holidays” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has a little violence and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>December 12, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>