<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> FOR a few blissfully underdressed years in the 1950's, Bettie Page was the pinup queen of the universe, or at least of lockers, garage walls and private stashes across the country. Blessed with a killer body and the perkiest smile this side of Sandra Dee, Ms. Page (she turns 83 this month) looked equally at ease wearing a homemade bikini or a fine mist of ocean spray. And while few people looked as happy naked as she did — the young actress Gretchen Mol, who plays her in Mary Harron's exuberant biographical film "The Notorious Bettie Page," comes charmingly close — in 1957  she buttoned her sweater for good, leaving the neon world of titillation and tease without a trace.  For years, Bettie Page was a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside a web of expertly tied rope. Although she did her share of cheesecake, even gracing Playboy in nothing but a Santa hat and a rosy blush, she achieved her initial infamy as a bondage model. (Later, it was her disappearing act that fueled her notoriety.) In the early 1950's, she began working with the brother-and-sister team Irving and Paula Klaw (played by Chris Bauer and Lili Taylor), posing for untold numbers of photographs and 8- and 16-millimeter film loops with such self-evident titles as "Betty's Exotic Dance in High Heels." (Her first name was usually misspelled.) To satisfy the specialty market, the Klaws on occasion tied up their most popular model and stuck a ball gag in her mouth.  In all likelihood it was these more outré images of Bettie crawling along a carpet in fetish heels or daintily spanking another seminude cutie that caught the government's censorious attention. (Now these fantasies seem almost quaint.) In 1955, Senator Estes Kefauver, a Tennessee Democrat and presidential hopeful who five years earlier had chased crime bosses like Frank Costello, turned his attention to pornography. (Around the same time, this same atomic-age Comstock helped put a muzzle on the comic-book industry in the name of preventing juvenile delinquency.) Ms. Harron and her screenwriting partner, Guinevere Turner, open their story with Bettie waiting to testify before  Kefauver's subcommittee, shut out of the courtroom where a succession of men are lecturing one another on the evils of scantily clad women.  Perhaps because Ms. Harron wrote about punk music in the 1970's (hers is one of the contributing voices in Legs McNeil's oral history of the scene, "Please Kill Me"), she comes across as the kind of enlightened chick who knows how to have a good time. Both of her previous features, "I Shot Andy Warhol," about the Pop artist's would-be assassin,  Valerie Solanas, and "American Psycho," her excellent appropriation (and evisceration) of Bret Easton Ellis's  novel,  exhibit a shrewd, at times bitingly funny intelligence when it comes to what women want and why. In her work with Ms. Turner, in particular, who was also her screenwriting partner on "American Psycho" (Ms. Turner also helped write the lipstick-lesbian romance "Go Fish"), Ms. Harron manages to have her pleasure, visual and otherwise, and her politics, too.  In this regard she receives terrific support from her obviously enthusiastic star. Until now, Ms. Mol has been best known for her premature designation several years ago as Hollywood's newest It Girl. The label seemed to plague her, and she all but faded from view despite promising turns in little-seen films. Maybe because she felt protected by her female director and female producers (six out of seven), or emboldened by the material, or maybe because she knows how beautiful her gently padded silhouette looks in the raw, Ms. Mol takes to this tricky role with the carefree expressivity you tend to see only in young children who have learned the joys of nudity, usually when their parents are throwing a dinner party. When she strips, Bettie soars.  That's to the good of the film because while the pinup was mildly notorious, the fully dressed woman wasn't all that interesting. Born in Tennessee in 1923, she studied to be a teacher, veering into modeling after landing in New York. Initially, she posed for camera clubs, shutterbug groups that paid models for private sessions. (A year before she hung up her garters, The New York Times ran a classified advertisement for one such session: "Shoot model in glamorous clothes eves 8 PM, Sat 2 PM Bettie Page and others. Concord Camera Circle, 118 W 47th St.") Rather surprisingly, some of the clubs were racially integrated, and it was a black man, Jerry Tibbs (Kevin Carroll), who gave Bettie her trademark when he suggested bangs to obscure her prominent forehead.  Ms. Harron moves fluidly through Bettie's early years, which included brutal abuse that might have had something to do with why she entered a profession that allowed her to create and control a sexualized image of herself. Even so, while Ms. Harron and Ms. Turner don't shy away from these dark episodes — and, notably, end Bettie's story before age and the really bad times intrude — they are too smart to draw a direct line between the traumas and the person who survived them. A self-made woman, Bettie Page created an enduringly resonant persona out of an arsenal of smiles and sneers, and her impressively pliant figure. Depending on the costume, the photographer (two of the finest were women, Paula Klaw and Bunny Yeager) and her own ingenuity, she was a dark angel, a harem girl, a naturist or a very naughty miss, but she was also always her own woman.  If the inner Bettie remains somewhat out of focus here, even to the beatific finale, it's largely because what made her a sensation — both in the 1950's and the 1980's revival that made her into a modern cult figure —  wasn't  her acting aspirations or the religious convictions that might have pushed her to leave modeling, but that she was a genius of the body. It's a truism of art history that while men act, women appear, smiling demurely away from the gaze of the viewer. In many of her photographs, by contrast, Bettie looks straight into the camera with a grin that is by turns twinkling and devouring, and flips that old truism on its head by turning her appearance into a performance. She knows what you want; she wants it, too.  In keeping with its subject, "The Notorious Bettie Page" is principally a work of gorgeous surfaces, shot mostly in silvery black-and-white film by the cinematographer Mott Hupfel, with an occasional splash of saturated color. Like the Klaws, Ms. Harron ties Bettie up and ties her down, puts her in towering boots and cinched corsets. Every so often, she complicates the story a little, as when she introduces John Willie (Jared Harris in top form), the bondage artist and publisher of Bizarre magazine, who devised some of Bettie's more outrageous poses. When he asks Bettie how she reconciles her love for God with her profession, she refers to Adam and Eve naked in the Garden of Eden. John Willie's idea of paradise wears more clothes, but he gets the picture, ball gag or no.  "The Notorious Bettie Page" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes female nudity, kinky outfits, bondage and intimations of sadomasochism. </text>
      <date>April 14, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>