<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>To say that Elisabeth Kübler-Ross meets David Lynch in the twisty paranoid thriller "November" is not to suggest that this surreal cinematic puzzle is at all profound or that it even wants to be. The movie, directed and edited by Greg Harrison from a screenplay by Benjamin Brand, refers to Kübler-Ross's  stages of grief in chapter titles like "denial" and "acceptance." And its aggressively spooky surrealism, its evocation of multiple realities (it has three different endings) and its method of obsessively circling back in time recall Mr. Lynch's "Mulholland Drive." But these are just references in a cleverly assembled film, shot and edited on digital video for a pittance (reputedly $150,000). "November" wants only to be an entertainingly squirmy mind tease. As the movie follows Sophie Jacobs (Courteney Cox),  a college photography teacher recovering from the trauma of her boyfriend's murder, it offers no deep insights into the human condition. In the same way that a crossword puzzle tickles the mind without asking to be taken as literature, "November" plays games for the sake of game-playing. It also has a pretentious streak. One clue it flashes is the recurrent image of a newspaper whose front-page headline asks, "Is modernism dead?" The story returns repeatedly to Nov. 7. That was the day that Sophie and her boyfriend, Hugh (James Le Gros), went out for dinner and afterward stopped at a convenience store because Sophie, still hungry, wanted a snack. In the first of the film's several recapitulations of that evening, Sophie waits outside in the car and talks on her cellphone to a lover, Jesse, with whom she recently ended an affair. In the store, a robber barges through the door and demands Hugh's cash. When Hugh pleads that all he has is a credit card, he is shot to death, along with the owner. In later versions of the story, Sophie herself is an eyewitness hiding behind a shelf. There are more pieces to this puzzle and more cinematic references. Sophie gives a lecture to her students in which she declares that what is left out of a picture can be as important as what is shown within its frame. (Think "Blow Up.") In class, she sees (or imagines she sees) in her slide carousel a mysterious photo of her car parked in front of the convenience store. Is it real? And if so, who took the picture and how did it get there? She demands that Officer Roberts (Nick Offerman), the police officer  investigating the crime, track down its source. There are recurrent scenes of Sophie having lunch with her mother (Anne Archer) and of Sophie visiting a psychiatrist (Nora Dunn) in a building whose elevator doesn't work. But the spookiest moments observe Sophie at home alone. Ominous banging on the ceiling loosens the pictures on her walls. A peephole into the next apartment is revealed. She receives mysterious telephone calls from a distressed, faraway voice that through the static sounds like Hugh's. These images of a mind crumbling into madness recall Roman Polanski's creep show "Repulsion." Until the middle of the film, "November" withholds the emotional meat of the story. We belatedly learn that because of Sophie's affair, Hugh had moved out of their apartment, and that on Nov. 7, the couple were reuniting. In addition to being traumatized by Hugh's murder, Sophie is coping with three kinds of guilt: the guilt over her affair, guilt for feeling responsible for the murder by asking Hugh to stop at the store and the guilt of having survived him. Ms. Cox, radically deglamorized for "November," is a drab screen presence, a kind of Neve Campbell manqué. Mr. Le Gros's Hugh, a workaholic lawyer who is devastated by Sophie's betrayal, has more dimension. But "November" is not really about character. It is about states of mind and the post-traumatic stress that breaks down the line between the conscious and unconscious minds. As for the death of modernism, the question seems inserted as a red herring. "November" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>July 22, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>