<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “New York, I Love You” is the second installment in a franchise of urban anthology films that began in Paris and is scheduled to touch down soon in Rio, Shanghai, Mumbai and Jerusalem. My own sentimental heart is holding out for Dayton, Ohio. Eventually, like a cinematic version of Google Earth, these movies, the brainchild of the producer Emmanuel Benbihy, will cover every inch of the globe with big-name actors and tiny romantic epiphanies. It may not be a project that will make the world smaller or friendlier — only, perhaps, a bit more precious.  Not that the 11 shorts in “New York, I Love You” are all that bad. It’s a nice-looking city, after all, even if the interstitial skyline and traffic montages assembled by Randy Balsmeyer are about as fresh as the postcards on sale in Times Square. Each vignette was shot in two days, and the roster of directing talent includes Mira Nair (“The Namesake” and the forthcoming “Amelia”), Fatih Akin (“Head-On” and “The Edge  of Heaven”) and Natalie Portman, making her debut behind the camera. (She also plays a Hasidic diamond broker in Ms. Nair’s contribution.)  But in spite of some attempts at human and neighborhood variety, the stories have a  self-conscious sameness, as if they were classroom assignments in an undergraduate fiction-writing class. Which, in a way, they are. Each filmmaker seems to have staked out a different part of town, though only one, Joshua Marston (“Maria Full of Grace”), has ventured beyond the tourist-friendly precincts of Manhattan. Apparently nobody loves Queens, the Bronx or Staten Island. Or Harlem, for that matter. And while the ideas of love explored on the East and West Sides are sometimes platonic, parental or intergenerational, they are also predominantly white and heterosexual.  Nobody should expect the directors, a pointedly non-hometown team — other notable names include Yvan Attal from France, and Jiang Wen from China — to plumb the depths or mine the grit of the real New York. They have, instead, composed a flurry of valentines to a fantasy version of the city, one culled from other movies and also from literature. You might get a hint of Martin Scorsese or Woody Allen here and there, but just as pronounced are the inflections of J. D. Salinger, Paul Auster, O. Henry and many decades’ worth of contributors to the Talk of the Town section of The New Yorker.  All of which might be tolerable in small doses, but somehow, once they are stitched together, the pieces of “New York, I Love You” make up a parallel city that no one would want to live in, much less visit. And this is in part because most of the New Yorkers on display here are confections, hothouse flowers planted in a soil of arch dialogue and watered with studied sprinklings of surprise.  These people have a funny — actually a tiresome  —  habit of not being what they seem, at first, to be. Thus the young man (Anton Yelchin) in Brett Ratner’s prom-night anecdote (in which, by the way, no cars burst into flames) allows himself to be fixed up with the daughter of an avuncular pharmacist (James Caan). The girl is played by the charming Olivia Thirlby, and a morsel of drama is produced by her date’s discovery that she uses a wheelchair.  That situation plays out more like a smutty shaggy-dog story than a sweet slice of life, but Mr. Ratner and Jeff Nathanson, who wrote this section, seem to be working, in their literal-minded way, from the same template as other, more overtly poetic contributors. Chance meetings have a way of yielding  reversals that seem as diagrammed as chess moves. Men in particular — a young thief (Hayden Christensen), an obnoxious pick-up artist (Ethan Hawke), a middle-aged businessman (Chris Cooper) — receive comeuppances that only they fail to anticipate. The women who supply them (including Robin Wright Penn and Maggie Q) tend to be savvier and more enigmatic, but no less limited.  It’s somewhat surprising how plot driven, how shaped, the chapters in “New York, I Love You” seem, given the current vogue for open-ended, observational cinema about city life. I’m thinking of younger American directors like Andrew Bujalski and Barry Jenkins (whose “Medicine for Melancholy” could just as well have been called “San Francisco, I Love You”) and also of the filmmakers who have brought cities like Taipei, Tehran, Bucharest and Buenos Aires to rough and vivid life over the past decade.  New York, like Paris and Los Angeles, is both overexposed and underexplored in movies, and of the love letters assembled here only two linger in the mind after this 110-minute speed-dating session is over: Ms. Nair’s diamond-district encounter (with Irrfan Khan as well as Ms. Portman), and Allen Hughes’s impressionistic study of the anxious aftermath of a one-night stand, starring Bradley Cooper and Drea de Matteo. Otherwise you would glimpse more interesting stories, and more arresting images, on a twilight cab ride across the East River.  “New York, I Love You”  is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). There are 11 stories in the naked city, and in some of them people get naked.</text>
      <date>October 16, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>