<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> If you thought Abu Ghraib was a laugh riot then you might love “Observe and Report,” a potentially brilliant conceptual comedy that fizzles because its writer and director, Jody Hill, doesn’t have the guts to go with his spleen. The story, in short, turns on a psycho shopping mall security chief, Ronnie (Seth Rogen, putting the lump into lumpen proletariat), who rules his retail roost with a Taser, a trigger-hair temper and some smiley-faced sycophants. Like the pettiest of dictators, Ronnie preys on the weak in the service of power (in this case the mall itself). He’s the Lynndie England of this dumber-and-dumbest yukfest.  That’s admittedly overstated, but sadism is this movie’s currency. The standard line about Mr. Hill, whose other credits include the movie “The Foot Fist Way” and the new HBO series “East Bound and Down,” is that he has carved out a place in the pop-cultural firmament by exploiting his characters’ perceived awkwardness. But while Ronnie is socially clumsy, his ineptitude is a contrivance, a mask that initially entertains (we laugh at him), only to be more or less discarded when he turns hero — at which point, we’re meant to laugh less at him and more at everyone else. The comedies of the Farrelly brothers and Judd Apatow hinge on a similar misfit-turned-hero dynamic, but Mr. Hill adds a nasty twist to the formula.  The twist here is Ronnie, a veritable catalog of dysfunction whose drop-dead drunk of a mother (Celia Weston) describes him as having been a special-needs child. Ronnie pops prescription pills day and night, presumably for his self-confessed bipolar disorder. At work, where he is soon preoccupied with capturing a serial flasher (Randy Gambill), he swaggers around the mall like a Wild West sheriff — though because he’s more Deputy Dawg than Dirty Harry, the joke is definitely on him. He bosses around his rent-a-cop underlings, including his deputy, Dennis (a heavily lisping Michael Peña), and John and Matt (John and Matt Yuan), a support team that seems to have been assembled specifically to neutralize any complaints about how Ronnie treats nonwhites.  Not that Ronnie is a race hater. However technically inept a director, Mr. Hill is too professionally shrewd to barrel down that particular road and, more important, there are too many studio dollars at stake here to risk outraging ethnic and racial groups that could be buying movie tickets. Instead Mr. Hill thumbs his nose at politically correct sensibilities, notably through Ronnie’s mutually hostile encounters with a mall worker he calls Saddamn (Aziz Ansari), who has taken a restraining order out against him. Mr. Hill defuses this potentially explosive relationship by making sure that Saddamn is as verbally hostile as his foe, which I guess is supposed to make it O.K. to laugh when Ronnie punches him in the face.  By far the most outrageous instance of Mr. Hill’s disarming his own bombs occurs when Ronnie beds Brandi (Anna Faris, rising above the muck), a cosmetics clerk who’s impervious to his attentions until the flasher brings them together. During an ensuing date, Brandi gobbles pills, guzzles tequila and even sputters puke, prompting Ronnie to kiss her square on the messy mouth. What follows next should have been the shock of the movie: a cut to Ronnie having vigorous sex with Brandi who, from her closed eyes, slack body and the vomit trailing from her mouth to her pillow, appears to have passed out. But before the words “date rape” can form in your head, she rouses herself long enough to command Ronnie to keep going.  Comedy is often cruel, of course, but before 1968, the year the movie rating system was instituted, directors couldn’t squeeze laughs from the suggestion of date rape, as Mr. Hill tries to do here. Like action and horror filmmakers, comedy directors now push hard against social norms with characters who deploy expletives, bodily fluids and increasing brutality. Mr. Hill has upped the ante in this extreme comedy scene not only by creating a working-class, bipolar bully who lives with his alcoholic mother, but also by asking us to laugh at this pathetic soul — and his miserably constrained life — as well as at the violence he wreaks. The dolts in “Dumb and Dumber” had hearts of gold. Ronnie has a gun.  Mr. Hill says his movie was inspired by “Taxi Driver,” a self-flattering comparison. Like those of Travis Bickle, Ronnie’s delusions of grandeur do end in a paroxysm of blood. Yet while Martin Scorsese might be overly fond of screen violence, part of what makes that film profound and memorable is how the thrill of violence, its seduction, is always in play with a palpable moral revulsion. No such dialectic informs “Observe and Report,” which exploits Ronnie and his brutality for laughs. This lack of critique might make the movie seem daring. But it’s hard to see what is so bold about a film that, much like the world outside the theater, turns the pain and humiliation of other people into a consumable spectacle.  You could argue, I suppose, that there is no real difference between Ronnie shooting an unarmed man and a comic who throws a custard pie in another person’s kisser: they both make (some) audiences laugh. To insist on that difference is, among other things, to introduce politics and morality into the conversation,  and, really, who wants that when you’re watching a Seth Rogen flick? It’s far better and certainly easier, as the old movie theater slogan put it, to sit back and relax and enjoy the show. That, after all, is precisely what Hollywood banks on each time it manufactures a new entertainment for a public that — as the stupid, violent characters who hold up a mirror to that public indicate — it views with contempt.  “Observe and Report” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film contains bloody gun and fisticuff violence, vomit-adorned sexual congress and full-frontal male nudity. </text>
      <date>April 10, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>