<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Offside,” the new film from the Iranian director Jafar Panahi, is a sports movie in which the game takes place entirely out of sight. The setting, most of the time, is a stadium in Tehran, where the Iranian national soccer team is facing Bahrain in a qualifying match for the World Cup. We hear the cheers and groans of the crowd and some improvised play-by-play from a few spectators, but like the film’s main characters — die-hard supporters of the team, some of them adorned with face paint in the red, white and green of the Iranian flag — we never see what is happening on the field.  Those unlucky fans are young women, whose attempts to see the match live are stymied by the police and by strict rules forbidding the mixing of the sexes. Trying to pass for boys, a half-dozen of them have been rounded up and confined to a makeshift holding pen on a ramp outside the stadium walls. The young soldiers who are their captors seem to be just as confused and demoralized as the women themselves, and the film’s rich, pointed comedy arises from the sense that all of them, men and women alike, are trapped in an absurd, insoluble predicament.  Which is not to say that they suffer equally. In a previous film, “The Circle” — one of the best works of cinema to come out of Iran in the past decade — Mr. Panahi followed a collection  of women through the streets of Tehran as they tried to evade arrest, family violence and other forms of injustice. That film painted an unsparing, unsentimental picture of the way laws and social customs are often arbitrarily and harshly enforced in Iran.  While the gist of “Offside” is the same, its tone is more insouciant, as it celebrates the guile and toughness of its heroines while casting a sympathetic glance at the ethical quandaries facing their jailers. The men want to do their jobs, to follow the rules, and in a few cases to protect the virtue of their captives from what they perceive as a risk of dishonor, but mostly they want peace and quiet and a chance to sneak a glance at the soccer field to see how their team is doing.  Instead they find themselves mired in an endless series of quarrels and negotiations. Perhaps because of censorship that limits what can be shown, Iranian movies are often propelled by argument, which Mr. Panahi’s restless camera turns into its own kind of action. An inspired piece of farce unfolds when one of the girls announces that she has to use the bathroom in a stadium that only has facilities for men. But the lightheartedness is often shadowed by the threat of real trouble, since even the lighthearted breaking of a silly rule can have serious consequences. (It also turns out that one of the women has gone to the game for reasons far more grave than fandom.)  Part of the film’s risky, transgressive energy arises from the circumstances of its making. Denied official permission to shoot “Offside,” Mr. Panahi went ahead under the pretext of making another, less provocative film. And he concludes with a remarkably exuberant sequence that doubles as a celebration of his own sneaky success. It’s not giving anything away to divulge that at the end Iran wins the game, since “Offside” has already made clear that such a victory, like the outcome of any other sporting event, is unlikely to really change anything.  “Offside” is rated PG. It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>March 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>