<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Off the Black” Nick Nolte dives beneath the blubber to bare the weary soul of Ray Cook, an automobile junkyard operator pushing 60 who also umpires high-school baseball games. A heaving wreck of a man, Ray lives alone in a seedy cottage near a railroad track and drinks himself into a stupor each night in front of the television.  Although he leaves Post-it messages in the refrigerator reminding himself to keep to a three-beer limit, he is incapable of following his own rules. In more sober moments he videotapes himself recounting the day’s activities for a diary. As he leaves a medical examination, his doctor throws up his hands in frustration; he wouldn’t know where to begin operating. We get the message: Ray’s days are numbered.  “Off the Black,” the feature-film debut of the director James Ponsoldt, tells the formulaic story of Ray’s last hurrah, in which he blackmails a teenager into posing as his son and accompanying him to his 40th high-school reunion. As he and the pretender, Dave Tibbel (Trevor Morgan), go through the ritual, Mr. Nolte’s craggy face and phlegmy growl register every seismic rumble of Ray’s troubled psyche. And he and Mr. Morgan (likeably fresh but far from dewy-eyed) sustain a convincing rapport.  This modest film could easily have skidded into the mawkish marshland where countless mentor-protégé, father-son dramas have suffocated. But for the most part it steers away from the worst clichés of that tear-drenched genre.  Ray and Dave first cross paths in a male version of meeting cute. Umpiring a ballgame in which Dave is pitching, Ray makes a critical call that walks a batter who scores the winning run. (The title “Off the Black” refers to a pitch that just misses the strike zone.) In revenge Dave and two teammates vandalize Ray’s property, strewing the trees with toilet paper, scrawling graffiti on the pavement outside the house and breaking one of his car windows.  As they flee, Ray wakes from his haze, grabs a gun and rushes outside, where he catches Dave and drags him into the house. Once they calm down, the frightened boy agrees to clean up the mess if Ray doesn’t call the police.  As Dave undoes the damage, the two become acquainted, and Ray develops enough of a liking for the vandal to take him fishing on the local river (the movie was filmed in upstate New York) and to offer him fishy advice. (“If you haven’t fished, you don’t know anything about women.”)  The movie follows Dave into his own troubled home where his father, a professional photographer (Timothy Hutton in an underwritten role), has been depressed since his wife left two years earlier. Frustratingly, the movie offers no explanation of why she left.  Dave’s family history is only one of several plot strands that seem as if they might have been edited out of the movie. Dave also has an uneasy relationship with his younger sister (but why?) and develops a flirtatious friendship with a single mother (Rosemarie DeWitt) who is a friend of Ray’s (but how good a friend and from where?). As a rehearsal for the reunion, Ray drags Dave to a hospital to visit Ray’s father (Michael Higgins), who has Alzheimer’s, and play the old man’s grandson; Dave passes the test.  “Off the Black” is so much Mr. Nolte’s movie that it couldn’t exist without him. His character is the latest in a long line of Hemingway-esque ruins, marinated in beer and testosterone, who have become Mr. Nolte’s specialty.  As fond as he is of these guys, Mr. Nolte has the wisdom and acting smarts not to sentimentalize them. In these roles you often have the sense of this wonderful actor casting a pitiless, smirking gaze into the mirror as he contemplates his own decaying magnificence.  “Off the Black” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes some profanity.</text>
      <date>December 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>