<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ff the Map," a portrait of modern-day pioneers braving the wilds of New Mexico in 1974, stays as far away from the movie mainstream as its characters remain detached from the teeming hubbub of American mass culture. Slow, ruminative and dusted with wisps of folksy humor, the film, directed by Campbell Scott from a screenplay by Joan Ackermann, has neither the arc nor the dramatic beats dictated by screenwriting manuals. As it shuffles along a flat dramatic landscape to its own deliberately poky rhythms, an acceptance of its pace requires considerable adjustment. Even then, the film often frequently gets stuck in one of the ruts that scar the dirt road it travels. Arlene (Joan Allen) and Charley  Groden (Sam Elliott)  and their smart-aleck, super-intelligent daughter Bo (Valentina de Angelis), live on a small isolated farm in the heart of coyote country near Taos; distant blue mountains line the horizon. Subsisting on Veterans Administration checks and earnings from handicrafts (about $5,000 a year), the Grodens are proudly self-sufficient, do-it-yourself virtuosos. Charley's best friend, George (J. K. Simmons), is their only regular visitor. The Grodens' life, for all its bohemian appeal, is no hippie idyll. As the story begins, Charley has sunk into a clinical, nearly catatonic depression that has turned him into a weepy crying machine, and the restless 11-year-old Bo announces that she has applied for a credit card. Then who should stumble onto their property but an I.R.S. agent, William Gibbs (Jim True-Frost), dispatched from Albuquerque to find out why the Grodens have failed to file any income tax returns for the previous seven years. William, the farthest thing from a bureaucratic ogre, is a lost soul who explains that his lifelong depression began at the age of 6 when he arrived home from school to discover his mother's suicide. In short order, he is stung by a bee and contracts a high fever that keeps him at the Grodens' homestead. When he recovers, he immediately blurts out that he has fallen deeply in love with Arlene, who shrugs off the confession. The movie, which Ms. Ackermann adapted from her own play, is narrated by the grown-up Bo (Amy Brenneman), seen only in flashes. Her flighty voice-over includes swatches of poetic reflection that only the most independent-spirited film would dare keep intact. One major riff is a meditation on the curvature of the earth as imagined after gazing toward the horizon from the shores of Cape Cod. That soliloquy inspires a 41-foot-long painting undertaken by William, who deserts  Internal Revenue to live with the family and be a full-time artist. With a director, screenwriter and star who have deep roots in the theater, "Off the Map"  is more than anything an actor's  film. Ms. Allen, whose straight brown hair streams down her back, is completely convincing as a capable, unsentimental workhorse with a huge reserve of patience. The only time she loses her composure is upon discovering the dead body of a coyote, which she lays to rest with a Hopi Indian ritual. If Ms. Allen's strong performance in "The Upside of Anger," which also opens today, makes you crave a double dip of her talents, here is a rich second helping. Mr. Elliott, who grounds his portrayal of a depressed man with a steady bass note of humor, matches her in depth, as does Ms. de Angelis as the impulsive, impatient Bo, itching to fly the coop. Their performances try to fill the gaps of a story that finally adds up to less than the sum of its disconnected parts. "Off the Map" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>March 11, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>