<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> We shall not cease from exploration  And the end of our exploring  Will be to arrive where we started  And know the place for the first time.  These lines, from “Little Gidding,” the last of T. S. Eliot’s “Four Quartets,” have an abstract, mystical cast. But when the British filmmaker Terence Davies recites them in his cinematic memoir “Of Time and the City,” they acquire a bracing and poignant specificity.  Mr. Davies started in Liverpool, the eponymous city in this lovely, astringent film and the setting for much of his other work, including “Distant Voices, Still Lives” (1988),  “The Long Day Closes” (1992) and the trilogy made up of  “Children,” “Madonna and Child” and “Death and Transfiguration.”  “Of Time and the City” is this director’s first documentary,  and it revisits some of the themes of those earlier autobiographical movies, in particular the pains and pleasures of growing up Roman Catholic and gay in postwar Britain.  The visual content of  “Of Time and the City” consists largely of archival clips of Liverpool from the 1940s to the ’60s, their nostalgic charm darkened by accompanying music and by the counterpoint of Mr. Davies’s dry, at times dyspeptic voice-over narration. His voice thickens with emotion as he recalls the delights of juvenile moviegoing or the ritual of a holiday trip to New Brighton, and hardens with contempt when he turns his gaze on the hoopla surrounding Queen Elizabeth’s coronation in 1953.  That lavish pageant — “the Betty Windsor show,” in Mr. Davies’s sarcastic formulation — took place at a time when many of Her Majesty’s subjects were still reeling from the trauma of war and economic hardship. “After farce, realism,” Mr. Davies says, as pomp on screen dissolves into pictures of poverty and desperation.  Realist though he may be, Mr. Davies is also a surpassingly lyrical filmmaker. Which is not to say  there is anything soft, sentimental or pretty about his sensibility. He may look backward with some fondness at the dowdy, workaday Liverpool of his childhood, and regard with horror the cheap, modernist housing projects that concentrated misery in the name of relieving it, but he hardly clings to a rosy view of the good old days. There was too much pain and longing, too much sexual and spiritual confusion, for any of that.  Nor does his profound love of his native city seduce him into civic boosterism. Liverpool’s 20th-century claim to fame rests on its mid-’60s contributions to popular music, but Mr. Davies is not a fan, preferring Bruckner to the Beatles and Mahler to the Merseybeat sound.  And while he professes an early and abiding love for the art form in which he works, his deepest cultural affinity seems to be with poetry. “Of Time and the City,” with its meditative tone and thematically (rather than chronologically) determined structure, might be classified as an essay film, but it is, even beyond that generic description, a stubbornly and thrillingly literary work.  Indeed, in spite of the care with which its pictures were assembled, the movie acknowledges — even insists upon — the limitations of the cinematic image.  Those fuzzy, faded scenes of mothers pushing prams, fathers heading off to work, shops and churches and factories are all in themselves ephemeral, trivial, mute. They are given eloquence partly by their juxtaposition in a collage, but even more by the words that accompany them. And while some of these belong to Mr. Davies himself, a great many are borrowed — from Sir Walter Raleigh and Percy Bysshe Shelley, in addition to Eliot and others. Or perhaps not borrowed, but claimed, as part of a birthright whose precise function is to draw out the common meaning of individual experience.  To rescue some fragments of the English poetic tradition from academic oblivion might not have been Mr. Davies’s principal intention in making “Of Time and the City.”  If it had been, the film would have been sour and didactic. Instead, it is a deeply personal piece of art that never descends into the confessional or the therapeutic, and a work of social and literary criticism that never lectures or hectors, but rather, with melancholy, tenderness and wit, manages to sing.</text>
      <date>January 21, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>