<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The O in “O’Horten” stands for Odd, which is something of a translinguistic pun. It is the first name of the main character, a train engineer on the Oslo-Bergen line whose retirement initiates what action there is in this restrained, bittersweet comedy. And Odd Horten, a pipe smoker of few words and regular habits played by Baard Owe, is, true to the English meaning of his perfectly ordinary Norwegian name, a somewhat eccentric fellow.  As is the movie devoted to him, written and directed by Bent Hamer, whose name also looks like a bit of Anglo-Nordic wordplay. A craftsman who favors slightly crooked tools, Mr. Hamer has come to specialize in movies about men with offbeat sensibilities and curious work situations. His 2003 feature, “Kitchen Stories,” examined a group of social scientists observing the domestic habits of bachelors in 1950s Sweden. It was followed two years later by the English-language “Factotum,” whose very title evokes odd jobs and whose hero, played by Matt Dillon, never lasted more than a day or two in any of them.  Odd Horten has more dedication and discipline than that, and he is rewarded with a silver-plated miniature locomotive after 40  years of service. A railway man to the end, he has never been in an airplane and causes some havoc when he visits a friend at the airport, where the rules and protocols are nothing like what he’s used to.  Horten’s adjustment to his new life is Mr. Hamer’s main theme, one he explores with a dry, unsentimental warmth. Here is a fellow who has spent most of his life ruled by a timetable and traveling in straight lines. What will happen when he is allowed to stray, to meander, to loaf?  The film answers the question in part by adhering to the rhythms of its hero’s newly aimless existence. It is less a single narrative journey than a series of excursions and wanderings, some of them down dead-end paths, others through neglected areas. Oslo and its environs have a stately, careworn look, and the omnipresent snow muffles even painful or intense emotions. Horten’s cool, quizzical stoicism seems like an apt response to this environment, which makes you think that maybe he isn’t so odd after all.  “O’Horten,” made up of meticulously constructed, deadpan scenes that turn on Keatonesque visual jokes, shows some affinity with other recent films of similar geographic provenance. The slightly anachronistic mood and décor, as if we had wandered into a neighborhood untouched since sometime in the middle of the 20th century, shows clear affinities with the work of Aki Kaurismaki of Finland, many of whose characters are more dissolute versions of Horten.  Mr. Hamer’s self-enclosed set pieces — Horten, stumbling into a strange apartment through the window, finds himself a prisoner in a young boy’s bedroom; Horten, stuck on a runway, lights up his pipe; Horten, in the passenger seat, survives what must be the gentlest fatal car accident in history — are like sweeter variations on the mordant visual jokes that are a specialty of the Swedish director Roy Andersson (“Songs  From the Second Floor,” “You, the Living”).  Other parallels come to mind: Jim Jarmusch without the relentless pursuit of cool; a more modest, less clowning Jacques Tati. But Mr. Hamer’s quiet, curious cinematic universe is its own special place. Not a lot happens there — a guy buys a pipe, or drinks a beer, or attempts a ski jump — but it is anything but dull. This is also a world of feelings that, however small or indirectly expressed, are authentic and recognizable. “O’Horten” is about frustration, patience, kindness and the wildness that lurks in even the calmest hearts.</text>
      <date>May 22, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>