<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "One Last Thing ..." is shrewdly divided against itself. What begins as a small, cleareyed drama about a teenager with terminal cancer morphs into a gauzy tear-jerker. This flip-flop from realism to sentimentality conjures the image of a public official who spouts the unvarnished truth, quickly regrets it and spends the rest of his term in office backtracking and mending fences.  The movie reverses the usual relationship between storytelling and medicine: the coating of the pill may be bitter, but inside all is sugar. Whether it works as an antidepressant may depend on your attitude toward death and the afterlife; the movie is a firm believer in living happily ever after in the Hereafter.  In its favor "One Last Thing ...," directed by Alex Steyermark from a screenplay by Barry Stringfellow, has a likable cast. Michael Angarano plays the dying 16-year-old protagonist, Dylan, as a smart, spunky kid with unshed baby fat and raging hormones. If the character is too noble and fearless to be true, at least Mr. Angarano doesn't force Dylan into sentimental contortions. Even better is Cynthia Nixon, who adroitly underplays the role of his careworn, widowed mother, Karen.  Mother and son live in Marcus Hook, Pa., an industrial port outside Philadelphia. When a charitable organization called United Wish Givers arranges, amid much hoopla, to grant Dylan his final wish, he changes his mind at the last minute. Instead of going fishing with his football idol, Jason O'Malley (Johnny Messner), he announces that what he really wants is to spend a romantic weekend with his favorite blond supermodel, Nikki Sinclair (Sunny Mabrey).  A sour, spoiled brat whose career is in trouble, Nikki has to be dragged to Marcus Hook by her agent, Arlene (Gina Gershon), for a photo op with Dylan, during which she is barely civil. The chances of their meeting again seem slim. But the boy is determined to get his wish, and with some miraculous intercession, courtesy of the saintly footballer and rejected fishing buddy — who catches him on a cable-access show auctioning sports memorabilia — Dylan finds himself the recipient of $10,000.  Over his mother's protests, Dylan and his best friends Ricky (Matthew Bush) and Slap (Gideon Glick) travel to New York for a wild weekend at a fancy Midtown hotel (also compliments of Jason) during which Dylan plans to locate Nikki. Fortunately his picture lands on the front page of The New York Post; in the Big Apple he is Prince for a Day.  As "One Last Thing ..." seesaws between the surreal and the gritty, it suggests Martin Scorsese's "After Hours" revamped as an after-school special with an R rating. While scenes of the boys softening the hearts of hard-bitten New Yorkers wouldn't seem entirely out of place in a Shirley Temple movie, those of Ricky and Slap being hustled by lap dancers at a strip club mince no words. Meanwhile Dylan has recurrent hallucinations involving his dead father (an uncredited Ethan Hawke) and a mystical encounter with a Hindu guru.  The movie subjects Nikki to the same back-and-forth treatment. A booze-swilling, pill-popping cliché of self-destruction, she also has misty, watercolor memories of the true love she left behind in her hometown. She and Dylan eventually reconnect, on friendlier terms than before.  In addressing Dylan's illness, the movie is frustratingly nonspecific. He suffers nosebleeds and bouts of fatigue, and his doctor speaks of tumors, but the medical facts are never spelled out. Because we never learn the whys and wherefores of his father's death, the movie leaves hanging the implication that Dylan's disease might be inherited. That kind of cagey reticence I would call cheating.  "One Last Thing ..." is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes profanity.  One Last Thing ...</text>
      <date>May 5, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>