<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is an all-too-brief moment in “The Other Man” when this muddled little dud of a melodrama emits a dangerous charge. It arrives when Peter (Liam Neeson), a software designer who lives near Cambridge, England, discovers e-mail correspondence and pictures on the computer of his absent wife, Lisa (Laura Linney), that reveal her affair with another man. Peter, who has fancied himself happily married for 25 years, is seized with sexual jealousy that quakes from within and transforms him into an anguished, wild-eyed monster; you can see his blood boiling.  Lisa, a high-end shoe designer, has mysteriously disappeared without leaving word of her whereabouts. Suspecting she has gone to meet her lover, Ralph (Antonio Banderas), whose name and address in Milan Peter uncovers through unscrupulous computer sleuthing, he flies to Italy, bent on murdering his rival.  No sooner has he arrived and spotted his prey than the movie fizzles like a lighted firecracker dunked in ice water. Peter trails Ralph into a chess bar where they strike up a conversation and play an exceedingly dull game of chess, during which Peter, without disclosing his identity, elicits juiceless trivia about the affair.  Though Mr. Banderas’s Ralph has fiery eyes and dresses nattily, he is a self-described loser who, Peter notes with contempt, has pink hands. Long before Peter leaves Milan, any tension has drained away.  It was reasonable to expect that with its triple-barreled cast and a reputable director, Richard Eyre — whose last film, “Notes on a Scandal,” established him as a fearless observer of nastiness and kink — “The Other Man” would sniff around the fouler recesses of the characters’ psyches. Instead it holds its nose. The scorching erotic fever found in a movie like “Unfaithful,” which “The Other Man” fitfully tries to emulate, is entirely missing.  The smiley-faced computer pictures of Lisa and Ralph resemble the same cheerful travel-brochure photos you would find in an ad to visit a glamorous locale (in the movie it is Lake Como), the only addition being one snapshot of exposed breasts. The sexual temperature remains a safe, nap-inducing 98.6.  “The Other Man,” whose screenplay was adapted by Mr. Eyre and Charles Wood from Bernhard Schlink’s short story, bets all its dramatic chips on a whopping plot gimmick that is revealed two-thirds of the way into the film. That twist, which I wouldn’t dream of giving away, is so poorly prepared that instead of shocking you, it leaves you scratching your head and wondering what signals you missed. The remainder of the movie dribbles away in a hasty attempt at catch-up.    “The Other Man” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>September 11, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>