<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>ny Navy Seal is equipped with the latest in freedom-fighting gadgetry. Straps, pockets and belts hold guns, grenades and various homing devices. The primary visual gag in "The Pacifier" involves one Seal on a top-secret baby-sitting mission who retrofits his  weapon-holders to keep baby formula and diapers at the ready. In this movie, Similac is as precious as Semtex, and bottle fatigue is akin to battle fatigue. Disney's new family flick is chipper and occasionally clever as it sends up the high-tech know-how required by 21st-century parents. In this case, a professor who has invented a mysterious microchip dies at the hands of terrorists. With the victim's wife away on a mission of her own, the government sends in a one-man security force: the fearless Shane Wolfe is deemed adaptable enough to serve this fatherless family. Playing the special-ops warrior with a heart-thawing assignment, Vin Diesel turns his thuggish frown upside down and lends his nasal hoarseness to a cloying lullaby. In that sense and many others, the action-picture hero's image-modifying role looks much like the former gangsta rapper Ice Cube's recent road-trip-with-kids movie ("Are We There Yet?") or the craggy Tommy Lee Jones's latest mission as a protector of cheerleaders ("Man of the House"). Mr. Diesel could not have succeeded as a genre-switcher without the proven television talents of the film's able ensemble. Brittany Snow, the teenage star of "American Dreams," plays the eldest daughter, who at first is Shane's in-house enemy No. 1. ("Whoa. Personal bubble invasion!" she yells when he comes in close to chastise her bratty behavior.) Faith Ford, of "Hope &amp; Faith," and Lauren Graham, of "The Gilmore Girls," give an Ivory-girl glow to the cast's maternal figures. Carol Kane, of "Taxi," as a messy nanny, and Brad Garrett, of "Everybody Loves Raymond," as a Barney Fife-ish vice principal, clown it up as feckless scolds and come to rather sadistic ends. The film, directed by Adam Shankman ("Bringing Down the House"), suggests that children should talk about their grief and show respect for overtaxed parents. But its prevailing lesson, one that will instruct children in the audience and delight their ticket-buying parents, is the value of discipline. "We're gonna do it my way - no highway option," the commando commands, when child-stoked chaos threatens his domain. Soon, the children fall in line. With practice, they start enjoying the results of exercise routines, commitments to personal goals and shows of force against bullies. For those without children to pacify, however, two afternoon hours in the theater for this parable might feel misspent. As Mr. Diesel instructs his lollygagging charges: "You're burning daylight. Now move!" "The Pacifier" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has a scene that involves violent explosions and victims.</text>
      <date>March 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>