<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>alindromes" was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from A. O. Scott's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 15, 2004. This unrated film opens today in Manhattan at the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village, and in Los Angeles on Friday. "Palindromes," the latest film by Todd Solondz, is dedicated to the memory of Dawn Wiener, the unhappy young protagonist of his second feature, "Welcome to the Dollhouse." A sequel of sorts, the new movie begins at Dawn's funeral and follows the appalling adventures of her 13-year-old cousin, Aviva, for whom the dead girl serves as both inspiration and cautionary tale. In the first of this movie's short chapters, each named for a character, Aviva, a secular Jew from the New Jersey suburbs, is portrayed by an African-American girl, one of eight actresses to play the role. As Aviva makes her way, Candide-like, through a sordid world of sexual violence and cultural antagonism, her appearance changes - from black to white, fat to thin, brunette to redhead and, at one point, to that of Jennifer Jason Leigh. The effect is to keep you off balance and at a remove. That is not such a bad thing, because you will want to be as far away as possible. I say this with a heavy heart, since I have long admired Mr. Solondz for his honesty, his guts and his willingness to sniff out the few remaining taboos in modern American life and turn them into sick jokes. Some critics will no doubt say that he has gone too far this time, that rape, child molestation, abortion and the killing of doctors who perform abortions are not fit topics for his unsettling blend of mockery and melodrama. The real problem, it seems to me, is not that Mr. Solondz goes too far, but that he seems to have no particular direction in mind, no artistic interest beyond the limitless ugliness of humanity. Lurking in this ghastly tale of Aviva's intentional pregnancy, her unwanted abortion and her temporary adoption by a family of evangelical Christians are some provocative ideas about motherhood and the fragmentation of American moral life. But the expression of these ideas radiates a sour contempt for every human connection and emotion. Aviva's mother (Ellen Barkin) is a loving suburban mom who is also a simpering hysteric whose tears are mocked without pity. Aviva's grim adventures are a form of revenge on her mother, enacted less by the daughter than by the filmmaker. The human landscape of "Palindromes" is a vista of grotesqueness, dishonesty and creepiness. These are qualities Mr. Solondz has explored before, but this time he fails to make them interesting, partly because he lets himself and the audience off the hook.  </text>
      <date>April 13, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>