<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At the outset of Nick Jasenovec’s “Paper Heart,” the actress and comedian Charlyne Yi (playing a purportedly fictional version of herself) claims neither to need nor believe in romantic love. Over the course of the movie, however, she will be nudged toward conformity by two parallel forces: the actual testimonies of firm believers and the fictional unfolding of a fumbling affair. And since this is an American story, Ms. Yi’s conversion will come about in the quintessentially American way: as the result of a road trip.  An unconvincing mash-up of the real and the fake, “Paper Heart” wavers between identities to no clear purpose and to its considerable creative detriment. The clumsy premise follows Ms. Yi and a director (named Nick Jasenovec but played by Jake Johnson) as they solicit love stories from a variety of regular Americans, most of whom are delightful and none of whom appears to be in on the movie’s meta-joke. Rather these segments, cherry-picked to enhance a loosely predetermined narrative (by Ms. Yi and Mr. Jasenovec), serve chiefly as props for a scripted romance between the leading lady and the actor Michael Cera, an attachment so tentative and pathologically gawky that it’s almost painful to watch.  Your enjoyment of “Paper Heart” will hinge almost entirely on your receptiveness to Ms. Yi and the extreme iteration of social awkwardness she represents. Either naturally or as a manufactured comic persona (there’s really no way to tell), she appears to be 23 going on 12. (When she dons a wedding dress, she’s like a little girl playing dress-up.) Wearing a permanently baffled expression and a succession of androgynous jeans and hoodies, she shuffles through the movie without acting ability or, it seems, basic survival skills. Lost in the aisles of a supermarket, she and Mr. Cera  (who have been romantically linked in real life) are as helpless as kittens;  you would think neither had seen packaged food before. Their extreme lack of sophistication is faintly disturbing, like a real-life example of one of Al Franken’s “lowered expectations” skits from an old “Saturday Night Live.”  Aggravatingly self-aware, “Paper Heart” achieves focus only in the engagingly candid, no-frills interviews. “I originally wanted to shoot a documentary because I felt the interview subjects were more interesting than me,” Ms. Yi explains in the press notes. She should have followed her instincts: from a judge in Texas to bikers in Oklahoma City, from a wedding-chapel proprietor in Las Vegas to a wryly affectionate gay couple in New York City, the interviewees are by turns funny, earnest and effortlessly touching. Illustrated by occasional snippets of charmingly primitive puppetry, their contributions cry out for the embrace of an authentic nonfiction film. Too bad no one was listening.  “Paper Heart” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Adult language and infantile behavior.</text>
      <date>August 7, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>