<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Paprika,” a gorgeous riot of future-shock ideas and brightly animated imagery, the doors of perception never close. A mind-twisting, eye-tickling wonder, this anime from the Japanese director Satoshi Kon bears little relation to the greasy, sticky kid stuff that Hollywood churns out, those fatuous fables with wisecracking woodland creatures selling lessons in how to be a good child so you can grow up to be a good citizen. Model behavior isn’t on the menu in “Paprika,” and neither are dinky songs and visuals. Here, when a woman sprouts a pair of wings, she doesn’t only flit about like Tinker Bell; she’s also pinned captive to a table, a man’s hand slithering under her skin.  If this doesn’t sound like your childhood animated flick, it isn’t. But neither is it Ralph Bakshi, the guy who tried to make cartoon movies grow up in the 1970s by way of Fritz the Cat. It’s old news that the great Japanese director Hayao Miyazaki has done his part to steer animation away from Disney-influenced juvenilia, but in the past decade or so, directors like Mamoru Oshii (notably with the virtuosic “Ghost in the Shell 2: Innocence”) and Mr. Kon have pushed animation film hard into more overtly adult realms. Like the “Ghost in the Shell” animes,  “Paprika” explores that intersection between the human and the machine, including the lands of enchantment you can travel to when you plug in, boot up and drop out.  Based on a novel by the Japanese author Yasutaka Tsutsui, and written by Mr. Kon and Seishi Minakami, the dense, rather overly plotted story hinges on a nifty little gadget called the DC Mini, an experimental therapeutic device a psychiatric institute has developed to tap into patient dreams. This dream machine shows enormous promise — and obvious dangers — but several have gone missing, as has one institute employee. Most of “Paprika” concerns the search for the errant DC Minis and the employee, an endeavor that consumes the institute’s resident attraction, Dr. Atsuko Chiba (voiced by Megumi Hayashibara); her brainiac colleague Dr. Kosaku Tokita (Toru Furuya),  a mountainous blob of a man and the inventor of the DC Mini; and the troll-like Dr. Torataro Shima, a k a the Chief (Katsunosuke Hori).  There’s more, including Toshimi Konakawa (Akio Ohtsuka), a detective with a comic-book flat-top and the kind of broad shoulders that tend to carry a world of troubles. Called in to investigate the scene by the Chief, an old friend, Konakawa comes equipped with his own alternative realities, namely a recurring nightmare set in a circus in which every performer and spectator resembles him, and a persistent dream that looks like a greatest-hits reel from big-screen entertainments. In this headily conceptual, gracefully edited interlude, Konakawa swings through a jungle on a vine like Tarzan, loincloth and all, only to end up tussling with a man in a genre thriller, inspiring one of the film’s most poignant philosophical riddles: Where do the movies end and our dreams begin?  Dr. Chiba and Konakawa each chase the wayward DC Minis down different paths. The detective starts visiting an Internet site that leads him deep into curious dominions where he revisits scenes from his distant and recent past, while Dr. Chiba infiltrates other people’s dreams by way of a DC Mini. In one of these reveries, she visits a near-deserted amusement park where an encounter with a chubby-cheeked doll nearly ends with her death. In time, the barriers separating the real and the imaginary dissolve like paper in water, as Dr. Chiba, Konakawa and a spritelike woman called Paprika — who springs into view whenever Dr. Chiba happens to be around — slip deeper into their substitute realities.  That sounds complicated and it is, a bit. That said, if you keep your eye on the screen and don’t overworry the plot particulars, you will be rewarded with a cavalcade of charming, gently outré and beautiful hallucinations. In “Paprika,” Mr. Kon bombards us with popping visual delights, including a dementedly cheery parade of inanimate objects in which household appliances, drumming frogs, beckoning cats, grinning dolls and even a red Shinto gate march in lockstep, sucking up human passers-by along the way. It can take a moment to situate yourself amid this splendidly controlled chaos. But this superabundance works to one of the film’s themes, namely that our fantasies, including those opened up by the Internet, are pulling us away from the material world and, perhaps, more dangerously from one another.  There’s something sinister about the dreamscapes in “Paprika,” fluidly rendered in both hand-drawn and 3-D animation, which may seem peculiar for moviegoers used to more benign animated fantasies. For all its gaudy glories, the film buzzes with a sense of unease about the rapidly changing relationship between our physical selves and our machines, a topic that Mr. Kon engages with as much sophistication as writers like Neal Stephenson and Michel Houellebecq, if rather more brevity. This anxious hum doesn’t dilute the delight of watching Paprika jump from one representation to another — from a pane of glass into an image on a T-shirt — but it invests this film with a fascinating tension. Mr. Kon shows us the dark side of the imaginative world in “Paprika” that he himself has perceptively brightened.  “Paprika” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It contains a sexual assault, naked animated breasts, maniacally grinning dolls and various leaps into the void. </text>
      <date>May 25, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>