<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> You may not learn everything you want to know in “Patti Smith: Dream of Life,” an impressionistic portrait of that punk godhead, but you learn just about everything you need. Created over a heroic 11 years, it was directed and mostly shot by Steven Sebring, a high-end commercial photographer whose perseverance and conspicuous unfamiliarity with, or disregard for, the conventions of nonfiction cinema (not to mention the apparently deep-enough pockets that freed him to follow his own muse) have inspired a lovely, drifty first feature that feels less like a documentary and more like an act of rapturous devotion.  For old punks and new, such devotion is easy. Ms. Smith was born (in 1946),  wrote poetry, made rock ’n’ roll history, changed the world, part of it anyway.  “Dream of Life” tells some of that story, intimately and yet at arm’s length. If you want to know about punk, what it was like to play CBGB when it mattered (or on its final night, as Ms. Smith did in 2006),  look elsewhere. The same goes if you want to know what it was like to be on top of the world and on top of the charts, to watch Robert Mapplethorpe get his nipple pierced, sit at the feet of William S. Burroughs and shack up with Sam Shepard at the Chelsea Hotel.  All of those things happened sometime after 1967, the year Ms. Smith left South New Jersey  for New York. She shares tantalizingly  little about her unformed and formative years in the film, which opens with the image of galloping horses, horses, horses, horses and her speaking in present-day voice-over, narrating in that inimitable flat accent (“leanin’ on the paakin’ meter,” as she sings in “Gloria”), swiftly tallying the ups and dreadful downs, the births and deaths  that  had helped shape her until now. The film has barely begun before she’s offered forth a life’s worth of headline news, a strategy that allows Mr. Sebring and Ms. Smith, who is as much a collaborator as a subject, to fill the next 100 or so minutes with fragmented beauty and song.  For the most part, it is a song of life — by turns joyous and elegiac, warm and vibrantly present, a mosaic of moods and moments from one woman’s richly lived time on earth. Against the odds and punk’s dumber tendencies, Ms. Smith didn’t die young or succumb to the usual rock clichés. She did fade away, though intentionally: in 1979 she dissolved her band, the Patti Smith Group, leaving New York and her escalating fame behind for an apparently contented life as a suburban Detroit housewife, tucking into domesticity with her husband, the guitarist Fred Smith, and their children, Jackson (a son) and Jesse (a daughter). Then, in 1994, Mr. Smith died of heart failure.  The next month, her only brother, Todd, died too.  Ms. Smith re-emerged and joined Bob Dylan (a fugitive backstage presence here) on tour in late 1995. Mr. Sebring, who had met her that same year during a magazine photo shoot, started to tag along. He continued to do so over the next decade, shooting her performing on and off the stage (she never seems to turn off, though she does put her hand over the camera lens)  in color and high-, sometimes low-contrast black-and-white 16-millimeter film.  He followed her home and abroad, watched as she did a rubbing of Gregory Corso’s gravestone in Italy, visited  Rimbaud’s birthplace in France with a tattered copy of “A Season in Hell” and strolled through Jerusalem. A patient observer, Mr. Sebring kept shooting as she kept roaming, memorializing and living.  For the most part it’s a fairly relaxed trip. Ms. Smith’s pretty-boy looks have mellowed into a kind of weathered handsomeness — when her long, lean face is framed by two braids, you can imagine her leading a wagon train west or standing solitary guard on the prairie — and her vibe is similarly tempered and temperate. Yet while she seems very much at peace with herself and with her ghosts, she still burns white hot onstage, thrashing and raging (against George W. Bush, against the Iraq war) with the same propulsive energy and purpose that first drove this one-time poet to turn up the volume alongside the guitarist Lenny Kaye.  (He’s still around too.) For her  rock ’n’ roll feels like a mission and the fountain of life.  Working with the editors Angelo Corrao and Lin Polito, Mr. Sebring creates a structure for the film in which past and present seem to flow effortlessly and ceaselessly into each other. The little girl hovering next to Ms. Smith backstage becomes the young woman visiting John Lennon’s Central Park memorial with her mother. And so it goes, elegantly. The film’s central image, one Mr. Sebring returns to again and again, is of Ms. Smith in a softly lighted room filled with photos, mementos and miscellaneous bits and pieces, a room that’s as much a manifestation of memory as a physical space. Here in this refuge Patti Smith coos to her cat and flirts with Mr. Shepard, who drops by for a duet and briefly stops time.</text>
      <date>August 6, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>