<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The flimsy new Hilary Duff comedy "The Perfect Man" has a moral of sorts. Ms. Duff's character, Holly Hamilton, is so distracted in the classroom by her own silly schemes that  she is oblivious to the quotation from Sir Walter Scott that her English teacher scrawls across the blackboard: "Oh what a tangled web we weave,/ when first we practice to deceive."  Holly's deception is at least well meaning. It involves inventing and sending e-mail messages from a nonexistent secret admirer to cheer up her glum, husband-hungry single mom, Jean (Heather Locklear). A baker who specializes in garish multitiered cakes, with clashing colors that evoke electric rainbows of toxic dye, Jean is so desperate to remarry that she has fallen into a pattern of bonding with the first remotely eligible man to cross her path.  Each time an instant relationship fizzles, Jean grieves to Patsy Cline records, then moves to a new city with her two daughters, Holly and her younger sister, Zoe (Aria Wallace), a 6-year-old bespectacled spelling bee fanatic. In the movie's opening scenes, Jean's flight from her latest louse lands the three of them in Brooklyn.  Ms. Duff, who is pushing 18, has arrived at the awkward age when she is too old to be a tweener role model trying on a bra and too clean-cut to be a mean girl, although her 2004 film "A Cinderella Story" found her menaced from all sides by her sadistic, snooty peers. She has invested so much of her star capital in being good that she is boxed in by her own wholesomeness. That's unfortunate, because Ms. Duff, who has an abrasive edge to match her coarse, medium-good looks, never seemed especially wholesome. Angelic she's not.  "The Perfect Man" toys with the notion of mother-daughter role reversal, in which Holly teaches Mom the courage not to keep running away. Ms. Locklear's Jean is blandness personified. The actress resembles a pool of runny vanilla yogurt with a pallid seam of strawberry: blond hair, creamy complexion and features so perfect and perfectly nondescript that they blend into nothingness. The range of Ms. Locklear's lobotomized acting runs from mild irritation to mild melancholy, expressed without expression.  The man who supplies the ideas and the name of Jean's invented secret admirer, Ben Cooper (Chris Noth), is the handsome bachelor uncle of Holly's best friend, Amy (Vanessa Lengies), and the owner of a bistro. As Ben's fluttery right-hand man, Carson Kressley from "Queer Eye for the Straight Guy" makes his movie debut, playing a kind of gay Stepin Fetchit, a creature so dizzy that he assumes a group of construction workers must be stragglers from a Village People convention.  The wittiest character, though,  isn't Mr. Kressley's worn-out stereotype but Jean's co-worker Lenny Horton (Mike O'Malley), a weepy lug obsessed with the band Styx who falls head over heels for his vanilla yogurt dream girl the moment he lays on eyes on her. Even after he screeches "Lady" under her window, Jean is so desperate for a husband that she refuses to rule him out as a possibility. You can't get more desperate than that.  "The Perfect Man" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has mild innuendo.</text>
      <date>June 17, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>