<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Do you suffer from blockbuster bloat? Do wisecracking guinea pigs give you the willies? Are you sick of ugly truths and icky, shticky juvenilia? Are you in the mood for mean, lean entertainment, some gratuitous R-rated nudity, totally unnecessary bloodletting and a slam-bang twist of the narrative knife? A B-movie-style throwback that’s consistently diverting and blissfully free of morals and messages, “A Perfect Getaway” is just the thing for the summertime movie blahs: it’s a genuinely satisfying cheap thrill.  A few wedding video clips introduce Cliff and Cydney Anderson, who, shortly thereafter, are seen rushing around Hawaii preparing for a honeymoon adventure. The eccentrically matched Steve Zahn and Milla Jovovich play Cliff and Cydney, who, after loading up on gear, head off on a long hike toward a remote stretch of paradisiacal beach. As the blue, blue ocean spreads out below them, they hug a coastal trail, trading alohas with other hikers, including Nick (Timothy Olyphant), a hard body with a sly smile and a long blade strapped to one calf. Nick, it emerges, has a few tales to tell — one involving a bullet to the head — some seemingly taller than others. He’s awfully hard to kill, giggles his girlfriend, Gina (Kiele Sanchez).  A dark cloud drifts in fairly early, when news breaks that a young couple has been butchered on another island, setting off predictable alarms (in them, in us). Cliff and Cydney briefly huddle, weighing their options and casting worried glances at Nick. Throwing caution and apparent good sense to the wind, they stick with Nick and Gina, and together the four make for the beach. As they journey, Nick’s quirks grow curiouser and curiouser, and his tales grow progressively more far-fetched. A self-proclaimed American Jedi, he flexes his muscles and a violent skill set, at one point even bagging a goat that Gina, having suddenly produced a knife and a pair of pink rubber gloves, expertly guts.  Working from his own screenplay, the director David Twohy sets an easy if increasingly anxious tone and a brisk, functional pace. Cliff, it emerges, is a screenwriter with his first movie in preproduction. Nick, casting glances at Cliff, seizes on this information,  and it soon becomes a wedge between the writer and the warrior, the nominal geek and the anointed brute. You need a new story, Nick lectures Cliff, before plunging into a mildly comic meta-discourse on what makes a good thriller. It’s the kind of self-reflexive moment that usually means you’re watching a movie by a film-school grad. Here, the knowing cine-chatter cranks up the tension and serves as a clever, to quote Nick, “red snapper” (i.e., red herring).  This is nice, tense work from Mr. Twohy, a genre veteran with a patchy record of screenwriting hits, misses and demi-successes,  like the tight Harrison Ford vehicle  “The Fugitive”  and the tasty supernatural flick “Warlock,” recommended for its indelible image of a human tongue sizzling in a pan. He also directed the science-fiction thrillers “Pitch Black” and “The Chronicles of Riddick,” which were both weighed down by the mounting fame and attendant lugubriosity  of their star, Vin Diesel. Like “Below,” Mr. Twohy’s spooky submarine horror thriller with a tight first hour and no stars, “A Perfect Getaway” suggests that he does better without big bangs or big names. The most impressive special-effects moment here involves a flap of skin stirring ominously in the wind.  Mostly Mr. Twohy just plays on our familiarity, even exhaustion,  with this kind of thriller, as he nudges us this way and that, drops heavier and heavier clues and with his editor, Tracy Adams, quickens the pace and heart rates too. In one nifty chase sequence  the screen splits into two and then three, allowing you to see who’s chasing whom. The four leads furnish the requisite frightened and fearsome looks, as well as the ripped musculature and the self-consciousness about genre that you often find in neo-exploitation cinema. Because they’re also good actors, you actually care if their characters make it out alive. Having tamped down his comic side, Mr. Zahn does a fine impression of a rabbit, while the regrettably underemployed Mr. Olyphant makes like a world-class hunter.  “A Perfect Getaway” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Gun, knife, hatchet, rock, bow-and-arrow,  fist-and-foot violence.</text>
      <date>August 7, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>