<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “The Perfect Holiday” Nancy (Gabrielle Union), a divorced mother of two boys and a girl, glumly faces Christmas in New Jersey without a man in her life. Rubbing salt in her wounds is her ex-husband, J-Jizzy (Charlie  Murphy), a preening rap star with whom she is locked in a custody battle. Swathed in chinchilla, he is stymied on his current project, a Christmas album that includes gems like “I Love the Ho Ho Hos.”  When Nancy’s daughter, Emily (Khail Bryant), overhears Mom confiding to a friend that all she wants for Christmas is a compliment from a man, she passes along the wish to the handsome Santa at the local mall. In real life he is Benjamin (Morris Chestnut), a conveniently unmarried, struggling songwriter whose latest opus, a squishy mound of seasonal goo of the sort J-Jizzy could never write, reaches the rapper’s hands at an opportune moment.  Benjamin, who noticed Nancy at the mall, takes Emily’s cue, tracks down the mother and delivers the requested compliment, then disappears. Nancy and her posse eventually find him, and romance blossoms. The only obstacle to happily-ever-after is Nancy’s older son, John-John (Malik Hammond), who takes an instant loathing to Benjamin. But the chances that Santa is Mr. Right are about as good as those of hearing “Jingle Bells” in a department store during the Christmas season.  Santa and J-Jizzy each have comic sidekicks. Santa’s is Jamal (Faizon Love), a plus-size elf who, when called upon, has trouble squeezing into a Santa suit, and Jizzy’s is his exasperated manager, Delicious (Katt Williams).  Lurking on the sidelines are Queen Latifah as the unctuous Christmas angel who narrates the story, and Terrence Howard as her troublemaking opposite, Bah-Humbug.  “The Perfect Holiday,” directed by Lance Rivera, is that most dispiriting product, a formulaic movie that doesn’t believe in itself. The farcical contortions are stiff, the jokes flat, the romance half-baked, the acting rote and the familial bonhomie lukewarm. Watching the movie is like reaching into a Christmas stocking and pulling out handfuls of cheap plastic toys that are broken.  “The Perfect Holiday”  is rated PG (Parental Guidance suggested). It has some mildly off-color humor.</text>
      <date>December 12, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>