<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Phoebe in Wonderland,” a tremblingly sensitive family drama that decomposes in  its last half-hour, examines the difference between the growing pains of a gifted child and the possibility of more serious mental illness. When  9-year-old Phoebe Lichten (Elle Fanning) auditions to play Alice in a school production of “Alice in Wonderland,” childish superstition drives her to act out self-punishing rituals to earn the part. In one she repeatedly washes her hands until they are raw. Another involves executing painstakingly counted-out dance steps on the sidewalk without landing on a crack.  Phoebe, who wins the role, becomes the pet of the drama teacher, Miss Dodger (Patricia Clarkson), a fierce defender of alienated, artistically inclined children. When Jamie (Ian Colletti), the boy chosen to play the Queen of Hearts, finds a homophobic epithet sprayed on his costume, Miss Dodger sternly lectures the children on the honorable history of men playing women in Shakespeare’s time. Her speech rings as the personal screed of the filmmaker Daniel Barnz, who makes his feature writing and directing debut with “Phoebe in Wonderland.”  The girl’s mother, Hillary (Felicity Huffman), who is turning her  doctoral thesis on “Alice in Wonderland” into a book, worries that Phoebe is resentful of  the time she spends on the book. But as Phoebe increasingly gets lost in daydreams in which the people in her life become figures out of “Alice in Wonderland,” her behavior signals deeper problems. She injures herself making a daredevil leap from a catwalk above the stage; in a fit of pique she spits at a fellow student.  This is a movie whose adult male characters —  Phoebe’s father, Peter (Bill Pullman);  her principal, Mr. Davis (Campbell Scott);  and Dr. Miles (Peter Gerety), the ineffectual psychiatrist she visits —  are well-meaning, clueless dolts. It is up to women to save the day.  Ms. Clarkson’s drama teacher appears to be the movie’s mouthpiece for creativity and self-expression until she refers to everyday people as “horrible normals,” and the balance between supportive teacher and irresponsible enabler tips toward the latter. (Ms. Clarkson, whose character exudes an air of mysterious knowingness, is, as usual, wonderful.)  The aching maternal concern Ms. Huffman brings to her “Desperate Housewives” character, Lynette Scavo, is amplified to self-lacerating anguish in “Phoebe in Wonderland” as her empathy fails to soothe her daughter. As Phoebe, Ms. Fanning, completely refraining from melodrama or show business cuteness, gives a touching, subtle portrayal of a troubled child. When this smart, pretty, imaginative, emotionally stricken little girl fearfully admits she is unable to control her self-destructive compulsions, you feel for her.  But at a certain point “Phoebe in Wonderland” throws up its hands as though at a loss of where to go next or what to say. Phoebe is given a label, Tourette’s syndrome, for one aspect of her behavior, but it seems more like a symptom than a diagnosis. Here, the movie collapses on itself.  Miss Dodger has abruptly and mysteriously disappeared. The children take charge of the school production, and suddenly they burst into an inane production number that suggests something out of a bad Disney musical; this is odd, seeing as the play wasn’t conceived as a musical.  Soon after that the movie simply stops dead in its tracks, as though the  money had run out and the project had been called off in the middle of a scene that makes no psychological or dramatic sense. It leaves you frustrated and annoyed.  “Phoebe in Wonderland”  is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>March 6, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>