<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The not-so-funny   funniest moment in “The Pink Panther 2,” the second installment of the beloved franchise since its resurrection three years ago with Steve Martin as the vainglorious, bumbling French inspector Jacques Clouseau, takes place at the Vatican. The pope has just had a priceless ruby ring snatched off his finger by a thief who has already stolen the Magna Carta, the Japanese imperial sword and the Shroud of Turin. (Somewhere along the line the Pink Panther diamond, a symbol of France, is also pilfered once again.)  As a so-called dream team of investigators from Britain (Alfred Molina), Japan (Yuki Matsuzaki) and Italy (Andy Garcia) question the pope, Clouseau rummages through a closet stuffed with papal vestments, impulsively tries one on and rushes to the balcony overlooking St. Peter’s Square. Leaning forward to bestow a blessing, he loses his footing,  tumbles head first from the balcony and clings to a flagpole, robes flapping along with his arms and legs.  Such hoary slapstick routines, invariably rushed, are all there is in “The Pink Panther 2,” a movie whose remaining cast list — John Cleese (replacing Kevin Kline from the first installment), Lily Tomlin, Jean Reno, Emily Mortimer, the Bollywood beauty Aishwarya Rai Bachchan —  suggests something a little more refined than this hodgepodge of juvenile pranks.  Ms. Tomlin’s character, Mrs. Berenger, a spinoff of her Tasteful Lady, represents the movie’s only attempt to be a comedy of manners. A police instructor on etiquette, she tutors Clouseau, whose every third sentence is a sexist or racist slur — as when she overhears him saying to his Japanese colleague, “I suppose you will be wanting sushi, my little yellow friend” —  on politically correct speech.  It is tempting to think of the revived franchise as the sort of misbegotten renovation that can take place when an architectural landmark, say, the original Pennsylvania Station, is replaced by a banal, anonymous structure. The original “Pink Panther” movies, I should hasten to add, were hardly landmarks. Respectable comedies with a modicum of sophistication, they were anchored by the presence of  Peter Sellers, a comic genius whose every tic suggested an upheaval of subversive mischief.  As much as I admire Mr. Martin’s cooler brand of comedy, his Clouseau lacks the demonic glee Mr. Sellers put into a character who seemed to originate from the inside out. Mr. Martin’s Clouseau is a skillful gloss right down to the phony French accent, which lacks the layers of oratorical pretension Mr. Sellers put into it. Why is it, I wonder, that any number of actors can play James Bond, while Clouseau now and forever belongs to Mr. Sellers?  Although the stunts come thick and fast in “The Pink Panther 2,” they are jammed together in a way that gives most of them barely enough time to register. The director Harald Zwart, taking over from Shawn Levy, has so little trust in his routines and in the audience’s attention span that none is allowed to develop into a belly-laughing classic.  In no particular order these are some of those gags: Clouseau accidentally burns down the same restaurant twice. Posing as a flamenco dancer, he tramples on his partner’s feet. While ineptly sleuthing around in the mansion of a suspect (Jeremy Irons), he is unknowingly captured on surveillance cameras and ends up falling down a chimney. Exploring a rack of expensive wines in a snooty restaurant, he nearly tips it over, and the bottles sliding from their niches become pins in a mammoth juggling exhibition. He bungles at karate with the sons of his sidekick Ponton (Jean Reno). He goes haywire with a fire extinguisher.  Mr. Martin works hard to get the few laughs he can from such strenuous business. He seems to be having a reasonably good time. But this is the stuff of the Three Stooges. That’s all well and good if you know what not to expect.  “The Pink Panther 2” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has mild sexual innuendo.</text>
      <date>February 6, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>