<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> IT'S hard to think of a big-budget Hollywood picture with less reason for existing than "Poseidon," Wolfgang Petersen's remake of "The Poseidon Adventure," Ronald Neame's much-derided, much-beloved 1972 disaster-kitsch classic based on a Paul Gallico novel. Well, maybe "Mission: Impossible III." And, for that matter, "RV," "Failure to Launch," "Rumor Has it," "The Pink Panther," "Bewitched," "The Dukes of Hazzard," and ... you know what? Just forget I said anything.  Anyway, Mr. Petersen's "Poseidon" is unlikely to replace the original in the hearts of action-hungry moviegoers, though it will probably expunge the memory of the earlier, made-for-TV remake (and also, perhaps, of the 1979 sequel, "Beyond the Poseidon Adventure"). The hard-working cast does a lot of screaming, climbing and death-defying in soaking-wet evening wear, but they can hardly hope to match the ripe absurdity of Shelley Winters, Red Buttons and — in one of the great plug-ugly he-man overacting contests ever committed to celluloid — Gene Hackman and Ernest Borgnine.  Oh, well. The original, like other specimens of its period and genre, mixed dinner-theater histrionics with stunts and explosions, rising to a campy, earnest grandeur that today's technology-driven, committee-made products rarely attempt, let alone achieve.  That said, Mr. Petersen is pretty good at digital and mechanical showmanship, as well as something of a specialist in maritime distress, having made his name with "Das Boot" 25 years ago and returned to the sea in 2000 with "The Perfect Storm." Accordingly, he approaches "Poseidon" as a series of problems in applied physics, subjecting various liquids and solids to a series of extreme thermodynamic and gravitational tests.  A good deal of seat-of-the-pants engineering savvy is also required of the characters in the film, who must respond to a disaster that strikes their cruise ship in the early hours of the new year, right after toasts have been made, songs sung (by Fergie of the Black Eyed Peas) and expository dialogue delivered.  In due course we meet the designated survivors (though in some cases the designation will of course be temporary). Kurt Russell plays Robert Ramsey, a protective dad whose daughter, Jennifer (Emmy Rossum), is on board with her boyfriend, Christian (Mike Vogel). Robert's foil — the Borgnine to his Hackman, or the reverse — is Dylan Johns (Josh Lucas), a professional gambler who was once  in the Navy.  We learn that last, hardly irrelevant fact in between explosions, cries of distress and feats of breath-holding, which is how we discover all kinds of other interesting information: for example, about the arrangement that led Elena (Mia Maestro) to board the ship as a stowaway, and about Robert Ramsey's precruise career. Apparently he was not only a heroic firefighter, but also, "for a while," the mayor of New York City. Mostly, though, the dialogue in Mike Protosevich's script consists of shouted practicalities: "I got a vertical shaft about 10 yards ahead!" "That's got to be the propeller tube!" "It's our only option!" "Let's go!" "Gotta keep moving!"  And the chief virtue of "Poseidon" is that it does. The picture conducts its business in an unprepossessing 100 minutes. The ship capsizes, thanks to a "rogue wave," at around minute 15, leaving the captain (Andre Braugher) a moment or two in which to look noble and give Fergie a farewell hug before the flipped-over ballroom is inundated, much as it was 34 years ago.    Meanwhile Dylan, determined to save his own skin, becomes the reluctant leader of a scrappy band that includes, in addition to those already mentioned, a waiter named Valentin (Freddy Rodríguez), who has sheltered Elena, and Nelson (Richard Dreyfuss), an architect, whose heartbroken suicide attempt was interrupted by that  wave. Let's not forget Molly (Jacinda Barrett), who has had a moment of flirtation with Dylan, and her young son, Conor (Jimmy Bennett), an imperiled child being obligatory in a movie of this kind. (In Hollywood I believe this is known as the Dakota Fanning clause.)  But I almost did forget Kevin Dillon, playing a creep  who goes by the name of Lucky Larry. "You don't just get the nickname Lucky Larry," this fellow observes, swigging booze from a hip flask as he prepares to cross a narrow catwalk over a pool of flaming oil. "You gotta be lucky!" Gee, I wonder if he'll make it back to dry land, or even across that burning fuel. I also wonder if the black and Hispanic characters will outlive their white counterparts, or if the winner of an Oscar for best actor will give his life to save a mere SAG award winner for a supporting role on television.  Actually, I don't wonder, and you won't either. "Poseidon," intermittently concerned with blueprints and floor plans, is pretty much pure boilerplate: a reasonably well-executed throwaway that, when you finally get around to seeing it in its proper setting, will make you glad you decided to travel by air instead of by sea.  "Poseidon" is rated PG-13. Many dead bodies are displayed, but the survivors keep their clothes on and their language clean.</text>
      <date>May 12, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>