<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> We Americans may be fond of conspiracy theories, but on screen they tend to seem overdone and implausible. The elaborate webs of intrigue that sustain most political thrillers usually offer too much speculation and too little insight, and are in any case diversions from reality rather than attempts to engage it. "The President's Last Bang," a tight, sober and strangely comical new film from South Korea, tells a tale that may sound far-fetched, but that is all the more crazy for being true.  On the night of Oct. 26, 1979, President Park Chung Hee, whose authoritarian rule had lasted for most of two decades, was shot to death by the head of the Korean Central Intelligence Agency. Though the assassination came in the wake of student protests and pro-democracy agitation, the killer's political motives have remained a bit opaque. Im Sangsoo,  who wrote and directed the film, declines to illuminate them, presenting the events of the night in a detached, procedural manner that leaves ample room for psychological rumination. Baik  Yoonshik   who plays Kim Jae Kyu,  the K.C.I.A. director, has a haggard, melancholy face that suggests a weary stoicism. His main fellow conspirator, a young, gum-chewing agent named Ju (Han Sukgyu)  seems to be motivated by a mixture of loyalty to his boss and restless ambition, though for what is not entirely clear.  The film moves deliberately, taking in various  points of view, including those of two young women, a student and a folk singer (Cho Eunji  and Kim  Yoonah), who have been recruited to spend the evening with the president, whose womanizing habits are established in a very funny early scene. He seems more like a mob boss than a head of state, which is probably Mr. Im's point. "The President's Last Bang" depicts a closed, secretive world of power and protocol, at once elaborately punctilious and floridly corrupt.  The concentric, competing inner circles of power - the intelligence establishment, the military, the president's bodyguard - seem to exist in an environment hermetically sealed off from the country they are supposed to lead. Nearly all  the film's action takes place at night, in a cordoned-off safe house, and the final scenes lead us on a surreal tour of Seoul's huge, empty government buildings, which resemble nothing so much as remote space stations in a science-fiction movie.  It is hard for an outsider to parse Mr. Im's intentions in revisiting this traumatic moment in his nation's authoritarian past. The mood of his film, which provoked some controversy when it was released in Korea (where it was nonetheless a hit) is neither angry nor nostalgic, but clinical and perhaps also a bit cynical. Nobody wins in this bloody game, and heroism and villainy coexist along a narrow spectrum of behavior. And yet this kind of cynicism also feels like the prerogative of a democratic sensibility, which can peer into the highest sanctum of power and see the same messy, ignoble human behavior that exists everywhere else.</text>
      <date>October 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>