<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Kimberly Joyce (Evan Rachel Wood), the smirking 15-year-old alpha girl who spins a toxic web of lies and deceit in "Pretty Persuasion," is a screen monster worthy to stand beside Suzanne Stone, Nicole Kidman's fame-obsessed television weather reporter in "To Die For."  Kimberly's father, Hank (James Woods), is a wealthy, foul-mouthed Beverly Hills electronics magnate in a perpetual rage, whose spewing of vicious ethnic and sexual epithets between snorts of cocaine suggests the onset of Tourette's syndrome. As they say, the apple doesn't fall far from the tree.  In her upscale private high school, situated in the 90210 ZIP code that everyone loves to hate, Kimberly glides through the corridors like a malignant princess, oozing contempt as she tosses poisoned roses to her courtiers. Early in the film, she remarks that there are just too many "worthless, annoying people on this planet," and she means it.  An obscene, misanthropic go-for-broke satire, "Pretty Persuasion" is so gleefully nasty that the fact that it was even  made and released is astonishing. Much of it is also extremely funny. Any satire worth its salt should not be afraid to offend, and "Pretty Persuasion" flings mud in all directions with a fearless audacity. As its bilious vision splatters across the screen from a hot center of disgust, the high school becomes the movie's symbol of a culture submerged in an acid bath of celebrity worship, envy, greed, material obsession and vengeful selfishness.  The satire can be recklessly excessive. In the movie's zeal to cover all bases, it even brings in the war in Iraq, in which Kimberly's older brother was killed, and which she refers to as "Operation Iraqi Freedom" with a venomous sarcasm. Later, when confronted with the pain she has caused, she dismisses the accusation with a shrug and remarks, "Every war has its casualties."  Kimberly loathes her new stepmother (Jaime King), whom she accuses of sleeping with the family dog. After eavesdropping on Hank having phone sex, she mockingly repeats the smutty dialogue to his face. At school, she is flanked by two sidekicks, the air-headed Brittany (Elisabeth Harnois), who thinks the word podiatrist means pedophile, and Randa (Adi Schnall), a shy Middle Eastern student whom she introduces to pornography and teaches how to purge.  "I respect all races but I'm glad to be white," Kimberly announces airily. She goes on to rank the races according to personal preference and then tosses off a dirty joke about how Arab women become pregnant.  The film's ingenious, far-fetched plot revolves around the touchy subject of sexual harassment in the classroom. For reasons that are revealed only in the film's final minutes, Kimberly persuades Brittany and Randa to join her in lodging false complaints of sexual abuse against their English and drama teacher, Percy Anderson (Ron Livingston). All three girls have personal axes to grind, but their grievances stem from his ego-wounding remarks, not from any boundary-breaking intimacy.  Technically, Percy may be innocent, but in his heart he's not. Although the movie makes it clear that he would never molest a student, his fantasies are another matter. In one of the funniest scenes, he buys his wife, Grace (Selma Blair), a short gray skirt for her birthday that is identical to the girls' school uniforms. After cajoling her into putting it on, he persuades his wife to writhe in front of him like a teenage temptress and to put on a sexy voice and read a provocative essay on discipline that Kimberly wrote during detention.  The scandal Kimberly sets in motion comes right on the heels of a Columbine-like massacre at another school in nearby Bel Air. A planned television puff piece on Kimberly's school suddenly becomes a tabloid news feature pursued by a fame-hungry reporter, Emily Klein (Jane Krakowski). A stand-in for every preening, self-righteous bimbo in the infotainment business, Emily happens to be a lesbian. When the scandal breaks, she becomes Kimberly's biggest champion as well as her latest conquest in the girl's lengthening list of people seduced as part of her nefarious master plan for glory and revenge.  Ms. Wood, who made a memorable debut in "Thirteen" as a girl going wild, brings an icy poise to her role that is entirely convincing and a little unnerving. Now that Christina Ricci has outgrown her niche as Hollywood's ranking bad girl, Ms. Wood has the field all to herself, and she holds it with an imperial command.  "Pretty Persuasion" was directed by Marcos Siega (who has a music-video background) from a screenplay by Skander Halim. Visually it has the deceptively bright pop gloss of products like "American Pie" or "Wedding Crashers," which are much less cutting-edge. The movie doesn't go soft until the confusing final minute; in that minute, you wish it had kept its heart in the freezer.  Watching "Pretty Persuasion" is like passing through a sudden, violent thunderstorm; behind it, the air is fragrant, and the visibility extends to the horizon. Think of the movie as a clearing shower.</text>
      <date>August 12, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>