<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Almost everybody who arrives at age 50 more or less intact carries memories of an earlier stage of life in which a wilder, unformed self lurched and blundered through young adulthood before making a fateful decision to settle. It could be a career choice or a long-term relationship, or both. For the title character of Rebecca Miller’s wry, acutely observant drama “The Private Lives of Pippa Lee,” her comfortable landing is her marriage to a successful book publisher 30 years her senior, whom she describes in a candid running voice-over as her rescuer from a life adrift.  Ms. Miller’s fourth film, adapted from her novel of the same name, “The Private Lives of Pippa Lee” stars Robin Wright Penn, an actress not known for playing demure types, as Pippa, the buttoned-up wife and caretaker of Herb (Alan Arkin), a loudmouth intellectual pushing 80, who lives large and is not about to calm down, despite his frailty. Having recently moved from Manhattan to an upscale Connecticut retirement community jokingly nicknamed Wrinklesbury, the Lees find themselves at loose ends.  While Herb, who has had three heart attacks, denies old age and infirmity, Pippa, who has given him two children, both now grown, is beginning to exhibit signs of nervous exhaustion. She sleepwalks in the middle of the night, leaving the kitchen in shambles, and occasionally trances out behind the wheel of a car; she has taken to sneaking cigarettes.  The movie zigzags between the poised, middle-aged Pippa who assiduously monitors Herb’s blood pressure and concocts sumptuous dinners of butterflied lamb and perfectly crusted crème brûlée for the literati, and her memories of growing up with a histrionic, Dexedrine-addicted mother, Suky (Maria Bello). After fleeing home at 16, Pippa spent aimless druggy years hanging out on the bohemian fringe of New York. The younger, frizzy-haired Pippa is played by Blake Lively (of “Gossip Girl”), and the physical resemblance between Ms. Lively and Ms. Penn is striking.  Your first reaction to Pippa’s life in Connecticut may be to heave a sigh of relief that she made it safe and sound into sedate upper-middle-class comfort. But as scenes flash by of Pippa’s tumultuous youth, you increasingly realize that she is going through the motions of domestic bliss. When her husband’s best friend, Sam (Mike Binder), describes her as an enigma, he means it as a compliment. To Pippa it is proof that she has lost her sense of identity.  If the film fits into the dreaded category known as the dysfunctional family drama, it steers away from the weepy clichés and quasitherapeutic mumbo-jumbo that have given the genre a bad name. The movie gazes steadily and without sentimentality at upper-middle-class angst as old age and death loom, and there is suddenly too much time to fill. Its refusal to push the usual emotional buttons and its insistence that we not pass moral judgment on its characters’ erratic behavior make it an exceptionally cleareyed assessment of a stratum of American life that Ms. Miller, daughter of the playwright Arthur Miller, should know firsthand.  At the same time, it is not strictly realistic. Pippa’s childhood memories are almost cartoonlike, and the movie’s occasionally chirpy, dispassionate attitude can be off-putting. Pippa recalls the past in a detached, mild-mannered voice with a subtle edge of bitterness that seems to belie her inner turmoil. It is the voice of a sophisticate whose cynical insights camouflage internal anguish.  The film’s meticulous performances bring nearly a dozen complex characters at least to half-life. Some of the sharpest belong to Zoe Kazan as Pippa’s daughter, Grace, a headstrong photojournalist; Robin Weigert as Pippa’s kindhearted lesbian aunt Trish; and Julianne Moore as Trish’s ferocious lover Kat, who enlists Pippa to pose with another woman for sadomasochist photos. Winona Ryder as Pippa’s histrionic best friend, Sandra, and Shirley Knight as her blowzy next-door neighbor Dot, are also memorable. Keanu Reeves, his chest tattooed with a portrait of Jesus, plays Dot’s glum, compulsively honest son, a ne’er-do-well with whom Pippa develops an awkward romantic friendship.  Together Ms. Penn and Mr. Arkin create a portrait of a marriage in which you sense the intertwining crosscurrents of devotion, boredom, anger and gratitude. As the movie shows, the decision to settle is only the beginning of a new phase and can be undone. As people keep changing, stasis is the enemy. A happy ending is never guaranteed.    “The Private Lives of Pippa Lee” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has nudity, sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>November 27, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>