<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Saverio Costanzo's film "Private" distills the Israeli-Palestinian conflict into a nightmarish microcosm  when a midnight raid by Israeli soldiers on the house of a peaceful, well-educated Palestinian family turns the home into an occupied territory.  Imprisoning the family on the ground floor and commandeering the upstairs as a lookout,  the soldiers tell the confined  that under no circumstances are they to go upstairs.  The home is that of Mohammad (Mohammad Bakri), a Palestinian school principal who believes in nonviolence; his wife, Samiah (Areen Omari); and their five children: a large, isolated two-story stone house  in a crossfire zone between a Palestinian village and an Israeli settlement on the West Bank. While their house is occupied, the family members are allowed to go about their business during the day; at night they are confined to the living room.  Their predicament, their internal conflicts and their edgy relationship with their captors, who become a bit more humanized as the story goes along, make "Private" an emotionally and politically loaded allegory.  Like the recently released "Syrian Bride," it is a film in which a no man's land, in this case the gray area between battle lines, acquires a symbolic weight.  The first feature film by Mr. Costanzo, an Italian documentarian, "Private" is based on a true story. It was filmed documentary-style on digital video with hand-held cameras, in southern Italy, where the rocky terrain resembles that of the West Bank.  To leave or to stay: that is the question posed throughout the film. The family members have different answers. Mohammad, dead set on remaining, offers compelling reasons for staying put. Mr. Bakri, a Palestinian actor, personifies a benign but strict paternal authority who holds the divided family together. You can see his backbone stiffen when challenged. He refuses to show fear, even during a hair-raising scene in which a gun is pointed at his head for a very long moment, while his family watches in terror.  Samiah, who wants to leave for the safety of the children, lets it be known that she is staying under duress. The scared younger children also want to go. But the fiery oldest daughter, Mariam (Hend Ayoub), who has just been accepted into a German medical school, would rather stay, defying her father's insistence that she seize her academic opportunity.  She and Jamal (Marco Alsaying), the older of two teenage boys, endanger the family with their acts of  rebellion. In scenes that build an excruciating tension, Mariam sneaks upstairs, hides inside an armoire and observes the soldiers through a crack in the door that she narrows and widens. As she observes her captors watching television and bickering, she glimpses their confusion and boredom, and they become real.  Jamal  rigs an explosive device and catapult near the greenhouse that the soldiers  repeatedly tear down because it interferes with their sightlines. Militant Arab television stokes his fantasies of himself as a holy Islamic warrior.  Upstairs in the rooms occupied by the soldiers, their commander, Ofer (Lior Miller), copes with the same challenges to his authority as those faced by Mohammad.  But "Private" also shows the human instinct to fight  oppression, even if that rebellion risks disaster. It's what oppressed people do.</text>
      <date>November 18, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>