<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In Jane Anderson's bittersweet, satirically savvy film "The Prize Winner of Defiance, Ohio," Julianne Moore portrays a downscale version of the picture-perfect 1950's housewife she played in "Far From Heaven" and "The Hours." In the earlier movies, Ms. Moore's character was a doggedly supportive spouse who cracked under pressure. Here, her alter ego, the real-life Evelyn Ryan, is an anchor of resourcefulness and optimism in a sea of trouble.  "The Prize Winner of Defiance, Ohio," adapted from a memoir by Terry Ryan, tells the true story of the author's mother, Evelyn, who reared 10 children through a domestic nightmare. Evelyn's bitter, self-loathing husband, Kelly (Woody Harrelson), a would-be band singer whose show-business hopes were dashed when an accident destroyed his voice, works at a dead-end in job as a machinist and squanders his meager paycheck on booze.  Using her skills as a jingle writer, Evelyn enters and wins the television contests that proliferated in the 50's and early 60's, when contestants were invited to describe the benefits of a product, often in catchy rhymed verse. Evelyn's winnings in cash and products keep the family afloat.  The film is the first theatrical feature directed by Ms. Anderson, whose credits include the television movies "Normal" and "The Baby Dance." But she is best-known as the Emmy Award-winning writer of the screenplay for "The Positively True Adventures of the Alleged Texas Cheerleader-Murdering Mom," a 1993 movie that recounted the story of an ambitious mother (played by Holly Hunter) who hired a hit man to kill her daughter's rival for the high school cheerleading squad.  Like that movie, "The Prize Winner of Defiance, Ohio" sustains the slightly zany, offbeat tone of a surreal documentary that never loses sight of its characters' emotional lives. Pungent musical seasoning is supplied by the 50's hits of Les Paul and Mary Ford, whose loopy, space-age guitars and overdubbed vocals distill a period mood of compressed giddiness.  Every now and then, Evelyn addresses the camera. And every so often one of her jingles comes to life like a genie released from a bottle, as a smiling group of women in 50's costume materialize to harmonize and whirl before your eyes before they retreat into the heavenly supermarket whence they came.  Such moments capture a sense of the American home in the 1950's as a technological wonderland in which miraculous appliances like televisions and freezers and food products like frozen vegetables arrived heaven sent to lighten a housewife's workload. Coinciding with the decade's explosive affluence, these wonders infused the rigidly conformist social climate with a whoosh of wide-eyed optimism.  In the film's most delightful scene, Evelyn wins an opportunity to charge through a supermarket and pile everything she can grab within 10 minutes into a giant shopping cart. Like a military strategist, she carefully plots her invasion. Once in the store, she makes certain to grab exotic gourmet items she could never ordinarily afford like caviar and capers and, at Kelly's request, shrimp cocktail. When she brings home the loot, her husband is initially too resentful of her success to sample the treat she has thoughtfully remembered to take for him.  Never mind that Ms. Moore's Evelyn appears impossibly svelte and pneumatic for a woman who has given birth to 10 children, or that the announcements of her winnings are a little too conveniently timed to solve the family's immediate financial crises. These exaggerations underline the pluck and true grit of a woman who convincingly transcends the grim feminist cliché of the downtrodden domestic goddess as a victim who swallows her disappointment, tolerates an abusive husband and sacrifices all  for her children.  In the film's most revealing and touching moment, the teenage Terry (Ellary Porterfield), nicknamed Tuff, badgers her mother to admit she has had a miserable life. Evelyn rebuffs her by declaring how she treasures the moments like the one she is just now sharing with her daughter on a rare trip out of the state. This talent for living in the now attests to Evelyn's astonishing spiritual strength.  The film's political attitude could be described as sensibly post-feminist. If the movie pays tribute to the 50's ideal of the subservient domestic goddess, it does so conditionally. Observing Evelyn with a rueful blend of admiration and sympathy, it sees her as a magnificent exception. In a deft insertion, the movie slyly alludes to that vintage daytime game show "Queen for a Day," which simultaneously enshrined and humiliated its desperately needy contestants.  As you watch Evelyn endure Kelly's rages, sulks and such outrageously irresponsible acts as taking out a second mortgage on the Ryan home without telling her, you admire her ability to deflect his fury with her sweetness and her courage to confront him when necessary without flying into a fury. But you also hold your breath each time he arrives home from work, red-faced, glowering and itching for a fight. Mr. Harrelson, instead of portraying Kelly as monster, plays him as a loving but broken man, wallowing in shame and self-hatred but trying in his pitiful way to be a responsible father and breadwinner.  Gently, affectionately and with wit, this lovely movie gives the 1950's its due, but not for a moment does it go overboard and make you want to go back there.  "The Prize Winner of Defiance, Ohio" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language and disturbing images of domestic conflict.</text>
      <date>September 30, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>