<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The Broadway production of "The Producers," with Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick as Max Bialystock and Leo Bloom, was apparently such a sensational show that a great many people were willing to pay $100 to see it.  Judging from the show's success, they seem to have gotten their money's worth, which raises a fascinating question, as much an economic as an aesthetic puzzle. Here is a movie version of the musical, with the same director (Susan Stroman), the same book and lyrics (by the tireless Mel Brooks, aided on the book by Thomas Meehan) and much of the same cast. Tickets cost a tenth or less of what the best seats did on Broadway, with the added value of Uma Thurman doing a Swedish accent in high heels and a short dress and Will Ferrell as a nutty Nazi. So why isn't this a bargain?  Or to put it even more bluntly, how come the movie feels, in every sense, like a rip-off? Nobody expects the jokes to be fresh or the songs to be any good. Some of the big laugh lines have been provoking groans since the first, nonmusical "Producers" movie way back in 1968, and probably even longer, since even that film was a fond, nostalgic embrace of a dying show business tradition. And no one - probably not even Mr. Brooks himself - would suggest that he belongs in the pantheon of American theatrical composers. ("I'm gonna put on shows that will enthrall 'em/ Read my name in Winchell's column"? It ain't Rodgers and Hammerstein. It ain't even M. C. Hammer.) So it may take a faithful rendering on-screen to reveal the real essence of "The Producers" in its musical incarnation - its vulgarity, its cynicism, its utter lack of taste, charm or wit.  I don't just mean that the show's retrograde humor - drooling over showgirls, sending up antiquated homosexual stereotypes - is offensive. The intention seems to be simultaneously to mock that kind of humor and to enjoy it, as if you could double your laughter that way. Perhaps onstage you could, but that speaks less to the vitality of Mr. Brooks's imagination than to the terminal morbidity of the Broadway musical. Once upon a time - that hazy 50's New York golden age in which "The Producers" seems to take place - musical theater was the class of American pop culture, a source of democratic delight and artistic ingenuity. Now, many big musicals represent the lowest common denominator: theme park attractions for tourists.  The movie audience, I suspect, is more discriminating. In any case, no effort has been made to adjust the show to the scale of the movie screen. Mr. Lane rants and mugs with his characteristic energy and agility, but you wish he would modulate just the tiniest bit. Or failing that, that Mr. Broderick could dry off enough to function as an interesting foil, rather than as a flailing, hysterical ninny.  Ms. Stroman, meanwhile, does not have the filmmaking instincts to match her deft, emphatic choreography. The close-ups may cause you to cower under your seat or reach for an umbrella to fend off the spray of saliva that seems about to pour from the screen. At other times you may find yourself involuntarily yelling "Watch out!" to Ms. Thurman, who is frequently in danger of bumping her head on the top of the frame.  She, however, is the one bit of genuine radiance in this aggressively and pointlessly shiny, noisy spectacle. As Ulla, the long-stemmed receptionist, would-be actress and apple of Bloom's eye, she alone turns a tired joke into good, crazy fun. Gary Beach, as the flamboyantly gay director Roger DeBris, and Roger Bart as his muse, Carmen Ghia, try for something similar, but it would take a lot more than a ball gown and a song called "Keep It Gay" for them to succeed.  The loud, lavish crudeness of "The Producers" reduces its one interesting idea to incoherence. Bialystock and Bloom hatch a scheme to produce a guaranteed bomb, "Springtime for Hitler," in order to bilk their elderly investors. When opening night arrives, it is something of a relief, though also a source of confusion. Here are numbers that are supposed to be bad, which must mean that the rest of the movie is bad by accident.  "The Producers" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some leering, naughty jokes and a smattering of profanity.</text>
      <date>December 16, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>