<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “The Promotion” tells you everything you might want to know but were too uninterested to ask about working as an assistant manager in a supermarket. As this sweet, ineffectual comedy follows two sad sacks competing for the job of manager at a new branch of a Chicago grocery chain, it pointedly avoids the raucous bad-boy clowning of the typical Everyguy farce. Think of it as a polite, tightly muzzled “Clerks.”  The feature directorial debut of Steven Conrad, who wrote the screenplay for “The Pursuit of Happyness,”  “The Promotion” also emulates the television comedy “The Office” by showing that even the dreariest workplace is a quirky little universe unto itself. It flouts the rules of Hollywood comedy by refusing to make the competition the usual struggle between a naïve straight arrow and a treacherous snake. Both Doug (Seann William Scott) and Richard (John C. Reilly) are reasonably likable, youngish men with glaring personality flaws. No matter who wins, both seem destined for lives of mediocrity.  Because both Mr. Scott and Mr. Reilly have played unhinged wild men in earlier movies, you keep waiting for “The Promotion” to burst out of its shell and allow the characters to play outrageous dirty tricks on  each other. But even when the opportunity presents itself, they are too decent to practice that kind of guerrilla warfare.  Frisky, clean-cut Doug,  who narrates the story, is so sure of  victory that he foolishly makes plans to buy a house and lies to his wife (Jenna Fischer) about winning the competition before it has been decided.  When he’s struck in the head with a bottle after mishandling a group of troublemakers who hang out in the parking lot,   he overreacts and sprays Mace in one boy’s face.  Richard,   a garrulous, glad-handing Canadian from a sister store north of the border, is married to a Scottish scold (Lili Taylor). A recovering substance abuser, he stokes his shaky ego by listening to fatuous motivational tapes and sneaks an occasional joint.  But the movie’s whimsy is undercut by its portrayal of the contemporary workplace as a cheerless corporate boot camp overseen by a grim board of directors that is as stern and vigilant as a military tribunal. The supermarket environment is so dreary you might even nickname the movie “The Pursuit of Unhappyness.”  “The Promotion” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and some strong language.</text>
      <date>June 6, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>