<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Snappy repartee with the ring of real conversation among people who are never at a loss for a remark is something every self-respecting Manhattan sophisticate imagines can be channeled into a screenplay with the crackle of vintage Woody Allen. That elusive tone is sustained through enough of Maria Maggenti’s film “Puccini for Beginners” to make it a rarity.  The movie, a screwball comedy of sexual confusion with lesbian inclinations, photographed in digital video all over Manhattan, comes more than a decade after Ms. Maggenti’s promising debut, “The Incredibly True Adventure of Two Girls in Love.” It captures the neurotic self-absorption of a class of academic and literary New Yorkers who put enormous stock in precisely verbalizing every opinion and emotion, using terms like “paradigm shift.”  At the same time, it carries off the difficult feat of making this tiny segment of the chattering class more or less likable. Compared with these intellectually refined people, the characters in “Will &amp; Grace” and “Sex and the City” are crude, materialistic boors.  It all looks easy when it’s carried off this smoothly. But as any number of stilted duds can attest, applying a Philip Barry or Woody Allen sensibility to 21st-century New Yorkers in their 30s is as delicate a craft as diamond cutting. It’s even riskier when you begin with a premise as debatable as the theory mouthed by the movie’s narrator and main character, Allegra (Elizabeth Reaser): that sexual identity is a “totally old-fashioned concept.”  A writer of obscure novels who lives somewhere in downtown Manhattan, Allegra has this revelation while on the rebound from her relationship with Samantha (Julianne Nicholson), a lover who abruptly leaves her to be with a man (Brian Letscher). Samantha’s farewell is accompanied by a list of the usual grievances; Allegra is savvy enough to recognize as legitimate the charge that she was withholding and passive-aggressive.  Before long, Allegra is distracted from her heartbreak by Philip (Justin Kirk), an assistant professor of philosophy at Columbia whom she drunkenly flirts with at a party, and who is undeterred by her assertion that she is a lesbian and that even if she sleeps with him, he can expect nothing to come of it. In bed, they discover they have sizzling chemistry, and Philip, whose six-year relationship with another woman has lost its spark, separates from her to pursue Allegra.  Mr. Kirk, who played a similarly articulate 30-something nice guy with quirks in the recent “Flannel Pajamas,” owns this emerging urban stereotype: a reasonable, fairly attractive, well-educated straight man who bends over backward to be a reliable, understanding mate and fails despite his best intentions.  A Woody Allen scenario turns into Noël Coward when Allegra meets blond, high-strung Grace (Gretchen Mol) coming out of a movie (“Holiday”), and the two strike up a friendship with a flirtatious undertow. Unbeknown to Allegra, Grace is Philip’s soon-to-be-ex. When they meet again, Grace impulsively throws herself at Allegra; again chemistry sizzles. As Allegra proceeds to juggle her two lovers, she becomes intoxicated with her sexual power. Grace is the least developed member of the triangle; all we learn about her is that she is studying glass blowing.  What unfolds is a modern bedroom farce in which inconvenient cellphone calls to Allegra from both Philip and Grace and her lame cover-ups take the place of closet doors hiding the lovers of cheating spouses. There is an inevitable moment of reckoning.  The comic structure is buttressed by familiar tropes. There is a divided Greek chorus, one half of which is a pair of Japanese sushi chefs who comment (over subtitles) on Allegra’s assignations. The other half consists of Allegra’s two best friends: Nell (Tina Benko), her haughty, acid-tongued lover before Samantha, and Molly (Jennifer Dundas), a lonely part-time caterer. As in Woody Allen films, peripheral people occasionally turn to the camera and mouth off.  The key to Allegra, in whom Ms. Reaser finds a satisfying mixture of self-centeredness and sympathy, is her passion for opera. A major drama queen, she swoons over a scene from “Turandot,” unaware that her friends are nodding out with boredom. After the performance, Allegra announces her theory that “Turandot” is both misogynist and feminist. Even among New York operagoers, I suspect, only a minuscule percentage would come up with such a notion and debate it with so much heat.   </text>
      <date>February 2, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>