<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> From the mean streets of Copenhagen — they evidently exist — comes the “Pusher” trilogy, a pungent dose of Denmark rot. Written and directed by Nicolas Winding Refn, this tough trio of underworld thrillers sticks so close to its rogues’  gallery of gangsters, suckers and murderous megalomaniacs that you can almost taste the hate and smell the stomach wounds. Given an appetite for grisly crime flicks, they make for a delectably nasty epic.  Previously released in the United States in 1999, the  first “Pusher” traced the downward spiral of a petty thug named Frank (Kim Bodnia) as he scrambled to make things right with Milo (Zlatko Buric), a superbad kingpin. Frank’s fate went unresolved at the end of the picture (Mr. Refn excels at the ambivalent finale), while that of his sidekick Tonny (Mads Mikkelsen) seemed certain, there being only so much bludgeoning a head can handle.  Left for dead, a casualty of his buddy’s furious desperation, Tonny survives and is resurrected as the antihero of “Pusher II: With Blood on My Hands.” We pick up his story in jail, and wince as he’s promptly served a fresh beating by the inmates. Once paroled, his skull a Frankenstein quilt of scars and tattoos, Tonny goes cruising for more bruising.  This time it’s a family affair, with his icy father, Smeden (Leif Sylvester Petersen), offering shady business opportunities and intolerable acrimony. Plus there’s a newborn son courtesy of a former fling with zero mothering skills but a great talent for snorting cocaine. Once more the walls close in, options are squeezed,  and the conclusion is indeterminate, but the material has matured. Where “Pusher” worked fresh texture and authenticity into a classic noir template, “Pusher II” reaches toward the mode of hyperrealist allegory perfected by the Dardenne brothers. Tonny’s tale is kin to, and might well have been called, “The Child.”  “Pusher III: I’m the Angel of Death” risks repetition as it puts Milo through the paces run by Frank and Tonny. Yet by now the atmosphere is so thick, the talk so assured, the performances so disciplined and the fear so fearsome, that Mr. Refn’s final iteration of his pattern achieves the hard, bright light of an archetype from hell.  We catch up with Milo at a Narcotics Anonymous meeting on the morning of his daughter’s 25th birthday, for which he has promised to cook for 50 guests, a task seriously derailed by the unexpected appearance of 10,000 hits of Ecstasy. Gripped in a nightmare of multitasking and increasingly strung out on drugs, Milo maneuvers against a new generation of pushers — and the villains in his soul.  The trilogy comes to its terrible, inevitable end with a sequence that renders men into meat, a thing to be bought, butchered, consumed and expelled. A word to the squeamish: it does this most literally. The “Pusher” films pull no punch. They’re a knockout.  PUSHER  </text>
      <date>August 18, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>
