<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>acing Stripes" is a ragtag patchwork of themes from several children's classics: the girl-horse love story of "National Velvet," the cross-species envy of "Babe" and the farmyard banter of "Charlotte's Web." When a baby zebra is accidentally abandoned by a traveling circus, a kindly farmer named Nolan Walsh (Bruce Greenwood) rescues the trembling foal and takes it home to be raised by his animal-mad daughter, Channing (Hayden Panettiere). Young Stripes (with the voice of Frankie Muniz of "Malcolm in the Middle") grows up believing that like the Kentucky thoroughbreds on the other side of the fence, he is a born racehorse. After a few humiliating matchups with his far faster equine counterparts, Stripes vows to devote his life to training for the "Kentucky Open," and - to everyone's astonishment but the audience's - the little zebra that could winds up in the winner's circle. This small, slight film manages to combine an endearingly dinky quality with a hefty dose of directorial ambition. While children thrill to the spectacle of animals that talk, their parents will imagine the nightmare of directing a feature-length film with mainly nonhuman actors. Most of the animation is done "Babe"-style, as live animals speak through computer-animated mouths. Unfortunately, the equine face is nowhere near as naturally expressive as the porcine one, and much of "Racing Stripes" is disconcertingly reliant on close-ups of horse heads that look as nobly immobile as slabs of lumber. But the children at the screening I attended seemed spellbound, and you have to respect the craftsmanship behind a film whose credits include "goat wrangler." Among the human actors, Mr. Greenwood seems to have parachuted in from another movie - he plays the wary, resigned Walsh with a nuanced elegance that's likely to be lost on four-foot-tall audience members giggling at pony poop. As Walsh's daughter and Stripes's jockey, Ms. Panettiere overdoes her character's indeterminately rural accent (there's a lot of ridin' and hopin'), but she has a sweet, old-fashioned screen presence that may qualify her as her generation's Hayley Mills. The vocal talent is top-notch: Dustin Hoffman, as a gruff Shetland pony named Tucker, is so precise in his delineation of the character that by the end of the film, the animal has come to resemble the bewigged Hoffman in "I {oheart} Huckabees." Other celebrity beasties include Mandy Moore as a sexy filly, Whoopi Goldberg as a levelheaded goat and Joe Pantoliano as Goose, a big-city pelican on the run from the mob. Mr. Pantoliano's frenetic dialogue is laced with "Sopranos" and "Godfather" references that are at once too sophisticated to amuse youngsters and too pointless to entertain their parents, but the gangling bird's broad physical comedy will hit its mark with both. Steve Harvey and David Spade, as two scatologically inclined flies named Buzz and Scuzz, cheerfully contribute to lowering the tone, while Snoop Dogg, who's been known to steal other films singlehandedly with his sly wit, gives a lazy performance as a lazy bloodhound. "Racing Stripes" is unlikely to ascend to the pantheon of perennially watchable children's films, but like its hero (and that of every other horse-racing picture yet committed to celluloid), what it lacks in skill, it makes up for in heart. "Racing Stripes" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some slightly objectionable language and numerous close-ups of manure.</text>
      <date>January 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>