<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>The actress Alison Eastwood’s first feature as a director, “Rails &amp; Ties,” has a functional visual style and an abundance of drama that would go unnoticed in the close-up, actor-oriented world of television. The film is so self-consciously unadorned, so   humble and plain, that it feels as if its director didn’t want us to think that she was trying to make some kind of cinematic statement. She hasn’t. Though she serves her actors well enough and sometimes even better than that, her grasp of the medium and its expressivity is less sure. Ms. Eastwood’s smartest move was to tap Kevin Bacon for one of her leads. As Tom Stark, an emotionally tamped-down railroad engineer with a dying wife, Mr. Bacon gives the film gravity and energy. Unlike Marcia Gay Harden, an appealing actress who takes on the role of the terminally ill wife, Megan, with rather too much enthusiasm, Mr. Bacon plays it as cool as he can. He’s brusque in word and severe in gesture, tightly wound, withholding. He keeps the character back from us, in reserve, even when called on to execute an important moment, as when he has to angrily sweep Tom’s model train to the ground. Even Mr. Bacon’s gently lined face seems in retreat, as if his very skin and flesh had withdrawn. The overloaded story, written by Micky Levy, would challenge even a more practiced director. One afternoon, while running  his train from Los Angeles to Seattle, Tom slams into a car parked on the tracks. Inside is the body of a psychologically ravaged younwoman (Bonnie Root), who, in her insanity and desperation, has also tried to do away with her 11-year-old son, Davey (Miles Heizer, a newcomer and a real find). As the train bears down on the car, Davey escapes just in time. Unmoored and unloved, this lonely, sad and impressively resourceful boy makes his way to Tom and Megan’s house of illness and miscommunication. Only those who have never seen a movie need to be told what happens next. Despite the impossible setup and some unfortunate scripted clichés and miscalculations (two railroad men deliver a précis on the modern railway for our benefit alone), Ms. Eastwood does manage to tap into something honest and unexpectedly moving at times. She’s particularly good at handling the interplay between Mr. Bacon’s inhibited performance and Mr. Heizer’s periodically near-hysteric one. Her work with Ms. Harden satisfies less; the actress has her moments but she tends to hit her notes with excessive force, banging away too loudly for this otherwise quiet film. The whole thing improves greatly during its second half, after the story’s incredible coincidences have given way to Tom, Megan and Davey just living everyday, ordinary life, trying to find ways to fit together with kindness and with love. Family affairs are a tricky business, even behind the scenes. It may seem unfair to point this out, but Ms. Eastwood has done herself no favors by tapping some crucial members of the filmmaking team that works for her father, Clint Eastwood, which of course only invites scrutiny and comparison. “Rails &amp; Ties” was shot by Tom Stern, the cinematographer for Mr. Eastwood’s last five films. Here, Mr. Stern keeps things simple and by and large bright, which is presumably what was asked of him, and affords no hint of his genius for chiaroscuro. Mr. Eastwood’s new production designer, James M. Murakami; one of his editors, Gary D. Roach; and his longtime costume designer, Deborah Hopper, also contributed to “Rails &amp; Ties.” Their work serves Ms. Eastwood’s caution. Everything looks professional if undistinguished. “Rails &amp; Ties” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Brief female nudity, adult language, death.</text>
      <date>October 26, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>