<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Courage is just well-concealed fear," declares Roy McCormick (Martin Lawrence), a disgraced basketball coach banned from the Ohio college circuit after throwing one too many tantrums on the court. This sensible word definition is offered to soothe a 13-year-old scaredy-cat  who plays for the Smelters, the downscale junior high school team that the newly humbled Roy is reduced to coaching.  His overnight transformation of a group of scraggly losers (often by scores of more than 100 to 0) who barely know the basics of the sport into potential champions is the paint-by-numbers story of the innocuous family comedy "Rebound." Short on laughs, if supremely inoffensive, this sleepy nonentity of a movie finds Mr. Lawrence in his huggable teddy bear mode. A mischief-making fire may glint at the corners of his eyes, but it remains safely contained behind a veneer of niceness.  "Rebound" is a children's sports movie that runs on almost no adrenaline. Although it's about competition, energetically speaking, it can't get with the program. At times the movie, directed by Steve Carr, seems so bored with itself that it dozes off while still on its feet.  The gentle humor occasionally ripples up from the collision of pubescent stereotypes, who behave more like 8-year-olds than middle schoolers. Most of the jokes revolve around two useful oddballs recruited by Roy. The first to join, Big Mac (Tara Correa), is the only girl on the team and by far its most aggressive member. A stocky, pugnacious tomboy with the temper of a pit bull, she is failing at math until the other new recruit, Wes (Steven Christopher Parker), a geeky, 6-foot-2 bookworm, begins to tutor her. Pit Bull and Bean Pole develop a case of puppy love.  For good measure, "Rebound" is obliged to throw in some adult puppy love as well. Roy has eyes for Jeanie Ellis (Wendy Raquel Robinson), the attractive single mother of the Smelters' best player, Keith (Oren Williams). But to get a date, he has to jump through hoops to prove he's no longer a selfish, tantrum-throwing prima donna.  The strait-laced movie rewards its characters of all ages for behaving like nice little boys and girls who care more about the team than about themselves. The goody-goodies will feel that special little glow of getting A-pluses, being teacher's pets and, in the case of Roy, receiving an approving kiss from a curvaceous surrogate mommy.  "Rebound" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>July 1, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>