<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Red Doors,” the oceanic divide between generations in a Chinese-American family is epitomized by the relationship of its glum paterfamilias, Ed Wong (Tzi Ma), and Katie (Kathy Shao-Lin Lee), the youngest of his three daughters. A 60-year-old retiree who sits around watching old home movies of his little girls, Ed has plunged into a suicidal funk. But every time he begins to act on his self-destructive urges, Katie barges in on him, barely noticing his distress.  On one occasion she interrupts him as he is tightening a noose around his neck. On another she appears as he is reclining in a bathtub with razor blades at his side. Her obliviousness to his pain would be unsettling if “Red Doors” weren’t a comedy. But this agreeable, lightweight movie, written and directed by Georgia Lee, turns the malaises of a suburban family into bittersweet farce that teeters between cheeky humor and surface pathos.  Ultimately “Red Doors” (the title refers to the Wongs’ red front door, whose color is supposed to bring good luck) loses its nerve and wraps up its interlocking family crises in a cozy blanket of reassurance.  Katie’s personal behavior is as extreme as her father’s. A ferociously headstrong high school student who wears her hair in two jutting pigtails, she leads a hip-hop dance troupe in school and, to her parents’ annoyance, pumps rap into her ears at the dinner table. Those dinners are traditional Chinese meals passed around on a Lazy Susan.  Katie is consumed by her treacherous quasiromantic pas de deux with Simon (Sebastian Stan), a fellow high school student who lives next door and with whom she has never spoken a word. Acutely aware of each other but silent by tacit agreement, these teenagers, who exchange meaningful poker-faced looks when they pass each other in the halls, are engaged in a tit-for-tat war in which they play increasingly grisly practical jokes on each other.  He sends her a present of a dead rodent. She drops a burning bag of dog feces on his doorstep. After igniting a small explosion in his school locker, this teenage caricature of the Asian woman warrior with American junk culture in her blood is given a warning by school authorities.  Each of the three Wong sisters exemplifies a different mode of cultural assimilation. Samantha (Jacqueline Kim), the eldest, is the dutiful high achiever. A successful businesswoman, she is engaged to be married to Mark (Jayce Bartok), an Ivy League yuppie whom the movie unabashedly despises. Samantha still carries a torch for her old boyfriend Alex (Rossif Sutherland), a drippy singer-songwriter with patches of facial hair who regards her with a moist cow-eyed longing.  The shy middle sister, Julie (Elaine Kao), is a medical student who begins to emerge from her shell when Mia Scarlett (Mia Riverton), a flirtatious television starlet visiting the hospital to study for a role, puts the moves on her after Julie helps her through the trauma of seeing a chest cut open. Julie is besotted with this Angelina Jolie-manqué, until the star treats her carelessly; then Julie shows her mettle.  “Red Doors” pulls together three well-worn subgenres of independent cinema. The moldiest is the suburbia-as-hell cliché that was revived by “American Beauty” and whose solemnity “Red Doors” tries to subvert with humor. The second is the drama of cultural assimilation within several generations of a family and the tension between the puritanical old ways and the freewheeling new ones. In these movies (“Red Doors” included) it often boils down to the choice of a wedding dress. Finally there is the coming-out story.  If these three subgenres are folded together comfortably in “Red Doors,” which is handsomely photographed, they don’t add up to something larger than the sum of their parts.  “Red Doors” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian); it has sexual situations.</text>
      <date>September 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>