<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Reign Over Me,” Don Cheadle plays Alan Johnson, a Manhattan dentist in possession of the usual trappings (at least in movies) of comfort and success: a silver Volvo, a big apartment, a lovely wife (Jada Pinkett Smith), two children and a vague but acute feeling of malaise. Like the investment banker being played by  Chris Rock on a nearby screen at the multiplex (in “I Think I Love My Wife”), Alan is not so much unhappy as bored by his own contentment.  The character may be a bit of a cliché, but the performance is typical of Mr. Cheadle, which is to say flawlessly understated and  intensely interesting. Behind Alan’s unruffled, buttoned-up facade — the smiles of professional courtesy and domestic agreeableness —  lie barbs of hostility and humor that pop out   to keep you alert and off balance.  Alan is one half of the movie’s buddy-picture pairing. The other is Charlie Fineman, Alan’s former college roommate, who is played by Adam Sandler. Mr. Sandler’s performance is by no means understated, but neither is it typical. Rather it is the kind of role that tries to force you to see a familiar performer in a radical new light. Mr. Sandler has ventured outside his big-baby persona before,  notably in “Spanglish” and in “50 First Dates,” but this is the first time he has shouldered so much dramatic weight.  And the burden is about as heavy as they come. Charlie, once a successful dentist like Alan, came undone when his wife and three daughters died on board one of the 9/11 planes. The writer and director of the film, Mike Binder, does not withhold this information, but he does approach it coyly, allowing his characters to speak about the attacks in allusions and euphemisms most of the time.  Charlie himself is in a state far beyond denial. In his grief he has regressed into a kind of shaggy preadolescence — which makes him, come to think of it, a version of the standard Sandler character after all. Charlie zips around Manhattan on a motorized scooter and retreats into a world of video games, compulsive late-night kitchen renovation and classic rock, which he listens to on headphones he wears like a protective helmet. Though his unkempt hair shows signs of graying, his diction is childlike, and his emotional weather resembles that of a toddler: the pursuit of endless gratification punctuated by occasional tantrums.  Like “The Upside of Anger,” in which Mr. Binder benefited from fine work by Joan Allen and Kevin Costner, “Reign Over Me” uses the rhythms and moods of comedy to explore, and also to contain, overpowering feelings of loss, anger and hurt. And like that earlier movie, this one is maddeningly uneven.  It’s rare to see so many moments of grace followed by so many stumbles and fumbles, or to see intelligence and discretion undone so thoroughly by glibness and grossness. And it is puzzling, and ultimately draining, to see a film that waves the flag of honesty — Face your demons! Speak from your heart! Open up! — turn out to be so phony.  The best scenes are those that give Mr. Cheadle and Mr. Sandler room to play against each other, to bring their very different temperaments into a workable syncopation. The premise of their relationship is fairly schematic. Alan, who resumes his friendship with Charlie after years of being out of touch, tries to coax his old pal back into contact with the world around him, while Charlie’s life of compulsive play allows Alan a furlough from his confining responsibility. The two actors perform the dance of superego and id with impressive ease and suavity.  But Mr. Binder strews their path with obstacles. A subplot involving Saffron Burrows as a would-be patient who propositions Alan in his office seems like a leftover from “The Mind of the Married Man,” Mr. Binder’s dreadful HBO series. Another, with Liv Tyler as a therapist, is superfluous and wearisome. Worse, as Mr. Sandler moves from mumbling repression of Charlie’s pain to tearful expression of it (with songs by Bruce Springsteen and the Who punching hard on the audience’s emotional buttons) this director’s approach to the 9/11 theme starts to feel crude and exploitative.  A recitation of the events of that day, especially coming after a series of lovingly shot Manhattan streetscapes, can’t fail to tighten throats and moisten eyes. But that makes the big therapeutic payoffs at the end feel easy and unearned.  By that point you may feel used as well as used up. The delicate insights toward which “Reign Over Me” at first seems headed, and the psychological subtlety of much of the acting, are squandered in revelations and confrontations that belong in a made-for-TV weepie. Mr. Binder can be a smart writer and a fluent director, but he can’t quite keep his dumb ideas from getting in the way of his good ones. He’s a bit like Charlie without Alan, spinning his wheels and lost in his own head.  “Reign Over Me” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and sexual references.</text>
      <date>March 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>