<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In my neck of the woods, a subscription to basic cable costs $50 a month. For that price you receive the usual network staples and standard cable offerings like “Top Chef” and Comedy Central’s raucously silly “Reno 911!,” which pops up two, sometimes three times a day in repeats and new episodes. At that rate, each episode of “Reno 911!” costs a little more than a buck, which seems a much better deal than whatever your local movie theater plans on charging for the slapdash, on-and-off funny and exceedingly lazy feature-length (barely) version of the show, “Reno 911!: Miami.”  As on the show, the film offers eight comic actors of varying improvisational talents and interest playing Reno, Nev., sheriff’s department officers with no discernible abilities. First among players is Lt. Jim Dangle, the pint-size peacock played by Thomas Lennon, one of the film’s three writers. With his mustache, muscles and short shorts, Lieutenant Dangle looks like a Tom of Finland miniature, something to put on the shelf next to the Village People action figures. Mr. Lennon squeezes a lot of mileage out of his outfit, but he also has slyly effective timing, which he puts to good use in his scenes with the two other writers: Robert Ben Garant, who also directed the film and plays Deputy Travis Junior, and Kerri Kenney-Silver, who plays Deputy Trudy Wiegel.  The film’s title more or less says all you need to know about the story, the action and the point: “Reno 911!” plus Miami. Lured by the prospect of a police convention and all the hilarity those gatherings promise, the officers hit Miami and its unsuspecting population. Confusion ensues, as do slapstick, shtick, stereotypes, wisecracks, misunderstandings, fat jokes, gay jokes, masturbation jokes, yet more masturbation jokes, some unfortunate sex and a few dead bodies. Dwayne Johnson puts in a genial cameo as a macho man to die for, and Paul Rudd shows up doing a lousy (presumably intentionally so) riff on Al Pacino as Tony Montana, wielding a weed-whacker instead of a chain saw. A dead whale and an enormous prosthetic buttocks round out the laughs.  It’s funny what different contexts can do. On television, where it’s broken into small chunks and interrupted by blocks of commercials, “Reno 911!” can make for a diverting pastime. When blown up for the movies, however, the same jokes don’t carry anywhere near the same zing. The commercials serve an important rhythmic function, since they impose time constraints on how long each comic bit lasts: funny bit, commercial, funny bit, commercial. The self-consciously threadbare story lines — in one episode, a deputy tries to marry while the others guard Liberace’s piano — work well with the piecemeal comedy. Yet what feels amusingly anarchic on the small screen feels underdeveloped and disjointed on the big screen, perhaps because instead of commercials gluing the jokes together there’s dead air.  “Reno 911!: Miami” runs 84 minutes, or about as long as four back-to-back episodes without the ads. And indeed 10 of those minutes seem gobbled up by the bloated closing credits, which include comic odds and ends along with the usual data. Mr. Lennon and Mr. Garant are funny guys; they’re also awfully busy, having written a handful of recent titles, including the hit “Night at the Museum” and the forthcoming comedy “Balls of Fury.” “Reno 911!: Miami” provokes some chuckles and minor hoots, but it’s a disappointingly sloppy affair that feels as if it had been thrown together with little more than spit and a belief in the enduring good will of the show’s fans, some of whom might actually be hoping for a movie.  “Reno 911!: Miami” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes vulgar language and some partial nudity.</text>
      <date>February 23, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>