<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The tears and the blame mix uneasily in “Reservation Road,” a grim, mechanistic thriller about death and suffering, life and healing among the civilized. Based on a well-received novel by John Burnham Schwartz, who shares screenwriting credit with the film’s director, Terry George, this is one of those sadistic exercises that puts its characters through the wringer without saying anything true or meaningful, like what it takes to get out of bed those mornings when you think the sun will never again rise with you.  Crying at the movies can be intensely satisfying, but you need to feel as if your tears have been justly earned. It may be reassuring, a pleasant lie, to think that better filmmakers appeal to our emotions, not merely prey on them, but the great directors need hearts of killers and stone-cold calculation to have their way with us successfully. It takes a talent for murder for a director to rip out our insides, to show us a beloved young son turned into so much road kill in front of his father. But it takes a true sense of cinema to ensure that we don’t hate the movie and its maker for doing that to these characters and to us.  Mr. George has neither enough ice in his veins nor the filmmaking skill to pull off the wretched business of sacrificing a child for a fictional contrivance. He made me tear up while watching this movie, but he also made me grit my teeth. He did more honest work in “Hotel Rwanda,” a drama about that country’s tribal genocide, which clearly stirred him. His heart is in the right place in this new film too, but the novel’s moral complexity trips him up, as does its scale. The death of a child is a tragedy in close-up, but the death of hundreds of thousands of children is so overwhelming it forces us to step back. We think about the horror (or we flee), not just feel it.  “Reservation Road” hasn’t been made for contemplation. It’s a blunt instrument: crudely plotted, badly acted, simple-minded, unpleasant. The child, 10-year-old Josh (Sean Curley), dies shortly after the film opens — as well as in the tell-all trailers — in front of his horrified father, Ethan (Joaquin Phoenix). The hit-and-run killer, Dwight (Mark Ruffalo), slows down but doesn’t stop, and keeps on going and going through one improbable narrative turn after another. As the police investigation drags on, and Ethan’s wife, Grace (Jennifer Connelly), tries to manage her grief, Ethan starts searching, first for comfort, then the killer. He drops into survivor chat rooms and then, in a grave screenwriting mistake, hires Dwight’s law firm.  In his novel Mr. Schwartz separates the three main characters psychologically and emotionally, more or less existentially segregating them by chapter. The film jettisons this fractured pattern and brings the three directly into play with one another through  didactic editing and coincidence. It’s no longer enough that Dwight has a son about the same age as the dead boy, or that his former wife (Mira Sorvino) gives Ethan and Grace’s  daughter piano lessons, as she does in the novel. Ethan now has to shake Dwight’s hand and solicit his help. Instead of confronting his crime in searching solitude, Dwight now looks into the face of fatherly anguish, mainly, it seems, so he can feel the necessary trauma in turn.  The film’s insistence on turning Dwight, a volatile man of uncertain character on the page, into a weak-willed but essentially decent and loving father on the screen, smacks of the worst kind of moviemaking compromise. Did the filmmakers think we couldn’t handle something darker, a little moral complication, an unattractive lead character? Did the studio suits? The casting of Mr. Ruffalo, an appealing actor whose yielding face seems to plead for forgiveness even when there’s nothing to forgive, feels particularly calculating, designed to make Dwight seem less troubling and less dark. Curiously, Mr. Phoenix makes Ethan so rigid with loss that the character comes across as more unyielding and demented than crazed by sorrow, which adds one of the few moments of ambiguity in an otherwise  obvious work.  “Reservation Road” wants to say something about grief, wrath and vengeance, which suggests that it’s angling for some kind of post-Sept. 11 relevance.  But its insistence on turning Ethan and Dwight into equals — both loving fathers, both racked  with pain — flattens the story’s ambitions. (Surely Dwight fled the scene not simply because he wanted to protect his own child from harm.) The film tries to draw parallels between the two with maddeningly schematic editing: one man walks up to his front door; there’s a cut and the other man walks inside his house. All we learn from these forced connections is that these two men enter their homes through their front doors. The entranceways to their deeper selves remain shut tight.  “Reservation Road” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Death leads to expletives and a brandished gun.</text>
      <date>October 19, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>