<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Resurrecting the Champ” is a cautionary fable that every journalistic go-getter dreaming of front-page bylines would do well to heed. Though the story is distantly based on fact, its  protagonist, Erik Kernan (Josh Hartnett),  is fictional. His sudden reversal of career fortune, following a brief, heady triumph, lends the movie moral traction.  The film’s jumping-off point is an article by J. R. Moehringer, published in 1997 in The Los Angeles Times Magazine. It told the story of an obscure 1950s boxer, Battlin’ Bob Satterfield, who was discovered living on the streets. It went on to be a finalist for a Pulitzer Prize, an award Mr. Moehringer  won three years later for another feature.  In the movie, directed by Rod Lurie from a screenplay by Michael Bortman and Allison Burnett, the setting has been moved to Denver and the fictional Denver Times, where the triumph of Erik, an eager-beaver sportswriter, curdles into the nightmare of a sloppy, overeager journalist who didn’t do his homework. For Mr. Lurie, who specializes in political subjects, “Resurrecting the Champ” is an encouraging return to film following the rise and fall of his television series “Commander in Chief.”  Samuel L. Jackson plays a would-be boxing legend, calling himself Satterfield but known on the streets of Denver as the Champ, who once sparred with Rocky Marciano and came close to a shot at the heavyweight title. Erik first spots the Champ defending himself against three young bullies who ridicule his boasts, then beat him to a pulp.  Dressed in rags, his skin crumbling like old parchment and his hair in matted salt-and-pepper dreadlocks,  the Champ is by turns poignant, wily, secretive, charming and pugnacious. And he can still throw a punch when half sober. At his most charismatic he has the aura of a holy fool, maniacally trotting behind a shopping cart filled with junk that he refuses to let Erik examine because, he says, the contents are too personal. Mr. Jackson’s champ is entirely convincing, and frequently incandescent.  Erik, sensing a career  coup, befriends the bedraggled old fighter and takes him to a match he is covering. Impressed with the Champ’s canny assessment of the combatants, he puts some of those observations into his  article and gains a modicum of respect from his grim, critical boss, Metz (Alan Alda), who until then had dismissed his writing as mechanical and colorless. Without telling Metz, Erik approaches the  newspaper’s Sunday magazine with the story of Satterfield and is given a green light.  “Resurrecting the Champ” captures the hard-boiled tone of a big-city newsroom almost perfectly. Several of the strongest scenes involve a weary, unsmiling Mr. Alda and David Paymer as the more gregarious editor of the  magazine, who gives Erik his break by putting his  article on the cover.  As the friendly but mutually exploitative relationship of Erik and the old fighter deepens, their give and take has just enough of an edge to make you squirm. The movie becomes a tentative detective story in which old photos and a vintage fight film become ambiguous clues to the life and career of the Champ, whom many have presumed dead.  The Champ, for all his lovability, has a streak of cunning in his bright, bloodshot eyes. Although he is genuinely down and out, you wonder how much of  his holy-fool role is just a hustler’s pose.  The journalistic aspect of “Resurrecting the Champ” is the toughest part of the film.  Things turn icky when the subject turns to father-son hero worship. Late in the film Erik reveals that his father, a legendary sportscaster, is not quite the man Erik wishes he were.  When Erik wows his  6-year-old son  with made-up stories about his friendships with sports stars, you wince at how desperately he strains to win his son’s adoration.  For reasons that are never satisfactorily explained, Erik has separated from his wife, Joyce (Kathryn Morris), a fellow reporter for The Times. Joyce is so tense and ashen that you wonder what happened to their marriage, but the movie offers no clues.  As the story takes a predictable turn from disgrace toward redemption, the film sacrifices credibility for a weepy, pandering pseudosincerity. For Mr. Hartnett, who has the most screen time, Erik is a much less demanding role than his policeman in “The Black Dahlia,” a movie he almost single-handedly sank with his clueless, wooden performance. Playing a handsome, feckless journalist on the fast track to celebrity, he doesn’t have much more to do than fill out the image of a gung-ho  all-American dad with fixable character flaws.  “Resurrecting the Champ” does make  a delicious, incongruous swerve into satire when the overnight star Erik is flown to Chicago by a cable network to be a commentator at a prizefight. Here he meets the network’s cynical, motormouthed casting director, Andrea Flak (Teri Hatcher), who regales him with an outrageous speech about how “the one thing people don’t want is the truth” and then puts the moves on him.  Ms. Hatcher imbues the role with far more snap and wit than she brings to the insufferable Susan Mayer on “Desperate Housewives.” It’s good to see her brain functioning again.  “Resurrecting the Champ” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</text>
      <date>August 24, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>