<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  A nominee for best foreign-language film at this year’s Oscars, Götz Spielmann’s “Revanche” is a tidy, glum thriller that aims for a tone of sour humanism, perched just on the near edge of cynical despair. Traveling from a decidedly unromantic Vienna to a weary-looking but still picturesque stretch of Austrian countryside, the film also spans the distance from lower-depths realism to moral fable.  Or tries to, at any rate. Mr. Spielmann seems to be after a combination of starkness and psychological complication, and the result is a pileup of motives and implications that undermine the blunt impact of the story. But the characters and situations are interesting enough, and the filmmaking is sufficiently skilled to provide a measure of reasonably thoughtful entertainment.  Like many other recent international art films — notable examples include Ulrich Seidl’s “Import/Export,” also from Austria, and Ozcan Alper’s “Autumn,” from Turkey — “Revanche” features an Eastern European prostitute, thus raising the audience’s awareness of global sex trafficking while conveniently satisfying its desire for a beautiful naked woman to ogle. Tamara (Irina Potapenko) works in a Viennese brothel and spends her spare time with her lover, Alex (Johannes Krisch), an underworld small-timer, more gofer than gangster. Alex is clearly out of his league, but part of what appeals to Tamara about him is that he is an unambitious, unthreatening loser, and therefore as close to a nice guy as she is likely to find.  But when she is offered a promotion — with some ugly strings attached, most likely — Alex tries to reinvent himself as a gallant outlaw, a knight errant who will use his criminal wiles to rescue his beloved from evil. His plans go horribly, inevitably wrong, in a way that is both surprising and genuinely upsetting — the single moment when “Revanche” achieves some real emotional force.  After that it settles down into a moderately diverting psychodrama about a city mouse exiled to the country, where the inhabitants include a crusty old codger and an anxious policeman and his bored, sex-hungry wife. The performances are solid, and the film as a whole works as a modest, satisfying little crime story. Nothing exceptional, though such movies are perhaps rarer these days than they used to be.</text>
      <date>May 1, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>