<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There is a lot of jittery cigarette smoking and sloshed-down booze in “Revolutionary Road,” a waxworks edition of the corrosive, furiously unsentimental novel by Richard Yates about an unhappy marriage. Set in the lonely-crowd milieu of 1955, though published in 1961, the novel tracks the  unraveling of Frank and April Wheeler, a handsome young couple who have been trying and failing to keep disappointment at bay by pretending that, despite their suburban address  —  despite a life calibrated to the commuter rail schedule, their two small children, well-stocked bar and picture window that looks over a front lawn as manicured as a cemetery  — they are not like everyone else.  Frank and April  —  Leonardo DiCaprio and Kate Winslet in the film  —  are crippled by their own acute self-consciousness and their sense that they are superior to the excruciating banality they have fallen into. Fantasies about what Frank calls his “own exceptional merit” haunt the couple, a delusion they cling to like a lifeline and that registers as mutual neurosis and a symptom of some vague, larger social ill. They don’t have much sympathy for each other, and Yates has next to none, though by the time his sad, sad book reaches its terrible, jolting climax, the emotion you will probably feel most acutely is pity, for the Wheelers and perhaps even for the man who has brought them to such merciless life.  Nothing much happens in the story, just two ordinary lives coming apart at the seams. Like the novel, the film begins with a disastrous community theater production of “The Petrified Forest” in which April has the lead female role as the greasy-spoon waitress who dreams of going to France. The play is a flop, but instead of shrugging it off with a laugh as do their next-door neighbors Milly and Shep (Kathryn Hahn and David Harbour), the Wheelers embrace the failure. They drink it in deeply and let it fill them up and then, fortified by it, start hurtling insults at each other, turning the modest public embarrassment of a local play gone wrong into an affirmation of their mutual contempt and loathing.  Things continue to fall apart as Frank shuffles between the traps of office and home, and briefly into the arms of another woman (Zoe Kazan). There’s a short, sweet reprieve when, out of the blue, April decides that the only escape for her and Frank is to pack up the kids and move to Paris, where, she insists, he will at long last be able to find himself and become the man she desperately wants him to be. Paris will be their way out of suburbia and the ticky-tacky little box on a hillside on that cruelly named street, Revolutionary Road. But it’s also clear from the deadening claustrophobia of Sam Mendes’s visual style and the pounding monotony of Thomas Newman’s score that their exit is blocked.  “Revolutionary Road” is the kind of great novel that Hollywood tends to botch, because much of it takes place inside the heads of its characters, and because the Wheelers aren’t especially likeable and  because pessimism without obvious redemption is a tough sell. It’s hard to think of many directors who could do it justice: Nicholas Ray, who in films like “On Dangerous Ground” and “In a Lonely Place” conveys an intimate acquaintance with twinned despair and self-loathing, might have made it work, and perhaps Paul Thomas Anderson. Mr. Mendes, a British theater director and occasional dabbler in the movies —  “American Beauty,” “Road to Perdition,” “Jarhead”  —  seems like a bad choice to take on “Revolutionary Road,” though not because of a lack of talent.  Certainly there’s no shortage of talent in the movie, which displays all the fastidious attention to detail  —  the sack suits that seem to be swallowing Frank whole, the touches of Danish modern in the Wheeler living room  —  you expect from this kind of prestige production. Mr. Mendes himself is a prestige number, of course, as are the two appealing stars, who shed a great deal of sweat and tears trying to put across their characters. They enter the story with their fists in the air, and it isn’t long before they’re slugging away at each other, absorbing low blows and landing brutal hits, which they continue to do to the bitter end, in between angry, accusatory speeches about the lousiness of their lives.  If those blows don’t resonate, it’s largely because Mr. Mendes’s investment in this story feels professional, diagnostic. Part of what makes the novel so powerful, beyond its familiar American theme of self-discovery, is its unwavering fury and how each intimate and acid word feels personal, as if Yates had dredged them up from some place deep inside his own being. No one gets off the hook in “Revolutionary Road,” least of all its author, whose insistence on stripping his characters down to the marrow is so relentless it can’t help but feel like an act of self-flagellation. As a film director, at least, Mr. Mendes comes across as too coolly diffident for that kind of blazing heat. He keeps his distance.  Mr. DiCaprio closes that distance in a few scenes in which you see Frank’s fear  —  of failure and of success too — mixing in with his vanity: with his wide, uncertain, panicked face he shows you what a dreamer without a dream looks like. Ms. Winslet, who’s married to Mr. Mendes, has a tougher time with April, who comes across as something of a noble sufferer when, as a minor character (a memorable Michael Shannon) cannily intuits, she has always played an active part in the Wheeler Family Tragedy. Mr. Mendes stages this tragedy grandly, symbolically  —  in one scene he places April and Frank in front of their car headlights to emphasize that they’re playing a role  —  forgetting that this isn’t just theater, but also something like life.  “Revolutionary Road” is rated R. (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian.) Adult words and traumas. </text>
      <date>December 26, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>