<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> By turns clever, impassioned, incoherent and silly, “Revolver,” the fourth film by the writer and director Guy Ritchie, is a macho parable of a fallen man striving for grace.  Mr. Ritchie’s regular collaborator, Jason Statham, stars as Jake Green, an ex-convict seeking revenge against a malevolent casino owner named Dorothy Macha (Ray Liotta). Green hopes to bankrupt Macha by means of “the formula,” an equation he devised in the joint.  After Green embarrasses Macha on his own gaming floor, Macha orders him whacked but is foiled by a mysterious loan shark named Zack (Vincent Pastore of “The Sopranos”). Soon after, Zack and his dapper partner, Avi (André Benjamin), inform Green that he has a fast-acting, fatal disease and hint that there’s a world beyond the one he can see.  “Revolver” doesn’t stint on fun. Mr. Pastore’s terse ultimatums and Mr. Benjamin’s silky exposition are a hoot. Mr. Statham adds another vivid panel to his gallery of smart brutes. As Sorter, a stoic gunman with superhuman hearing, Mark Strong steals every scene he’s in. As Macha, a decadent, insecure sadist, Mr. Liotta conveys spiritual anguish while clad in bikini briefs and eyeliner, a feat that Ingmar Bergman never asked of Max von Sydow.  Yet the movie clearly has so much more on its mind than escapism that viewers may demand, “Who is this director, and what has he done with Guy Ritchie?”  “Revolver” is built around title cards quoting famous philosophers on power, deception, war and chess, and it ends with jejune sound bites from guru figures (including Deepak Chopra). The characters fear an unseen Mr. Gold who variously represents greed, pride, the ego and Satan. The movie’s title teases both the purgatorial cycle of self-limiting thought and the possibility of spiritual evolution (represented by images of cats, crucifixion and sarcophagi). When a major character renounces violence, Mr. Ritchie frames him so that gold leaves on the wall behind his head form a halo.  As if to italicize the notion of the self as protagonist in life, the filmmaker gives Green and Macha narration that anticipates and critiques events and sets the action in a neo-noir dreamland rife with allusive proper nouns. (The macho Macha is a mini- Machiavelli.  Say that five times fast.)  The most audacious bit in “Revolver” is a gunfight in which Sorter uses his hearing to target unseen foes while Mr. Ritchie fractures screen space like a Cubist on a bender. Runner-up is a long scene of Green debating himself in an elevator.  The movie’s hit-to-miss ratio is hardly Olympic caliber, but Mr. Ritchie deserves credit for chutzpah. After his third film, “Swept Away” — a putrid remake of the Lina Wertmüller classic starring his wife, Madonna — he could have photocopied his two hits, “Lock, Stock and Two Smoking Barrels” and “Snatch,” and been credited with a return to form.  He chose instead to make a film whose DVD version could plausibly be filed under “action,” “mystery,” “religion” and “self-help”: the first metaphysical lad-mag movie.  “Revolver” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for pretty much everything.</text>
      <date>December 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>