<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>f you like your antiheroes tall, pale and existential, you won't do better than Georges, the anti-czarist assassin at the heart of Karen Shakhnazarov's historical drama "Rider Named Death." Georges, played by the steely-eyed Siberian actor Andrei Panin, is a thinly veiled fictional version of Boris Savinkov, a Socialist agitator who wrote an autobiographical novel, "The Pale Horse," on which the film's story is based. Georges leads a ragtag band of terrorists in Moscow at the turn of the 20th century, each member motivated by a different set of principles. Erna (Ksenia Rappoport) makes bombs, driven by a fanatical passion for the cruel and distant Georges. Vanya (Artyom Semakin) is a wide-eyed student, a Christian idealist who refuses to bomb an aristocrat's carriage when children are present. Fyodor (Rostislav Bershauer) is a true anarchist, a hardened peasant who believes in the dissemination of terror as a general practice. Finally there's Georges, who, if we're to believe the chilling story he tells his married lover, Elena (Anastasia Makeeva), kills for no other reason than sheer boredom. The four take on the project of assassinating the Grand Duke Sergei Aleksandrovich (Vasiliy Zotov), a remote symbol of the aristocracy with whom Georges becomes increasingly obsessed as the group's attempts on his life collapse into chaos. Though Dostoyevsky and Nietzsche are never explicitly invoked in the revolutionaries' desultory musings on fate and individual responsibility, there is an unmistakably philosophical bent to their discussions (often conducted in sumptuous nightclubs over vodka and caviar). The source of the terrorists' financial support is as obscure as the origin of their social outrage, since poverty and oppression are seen only in the abstract. Despite the philosophical burden it assumes, "The Rider Named Death" remains a vaguely political costume drama, an unexceptionable museum piece that takes place in an exquisitely recreated Moscow of nearly a century ago. To make a film in 2005 that asks audiences to sympathize with the plight of a band of terrorists is an intellectually audacious gesture. But "The Rider Named Death" fails to draw, even indirectly, any possible parallels with current unrest, whether in the former Soviet Union or the Middle East. For a film about revolutionary passion and the political uses of violence, it is strangely bloodless.</text>
      <date>March 18, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>