<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Judd Apatow neither wrote nor directed “Role Models,” the newest entry in the increasingly worn-out “boys will be babies until they are forced to grow up” school of arrested-development comedies. But he might as well have. Directed by David Wain (“Wet Hot American Summer”), it follows the silly misadventures of two flailing Peter Pans who are forced to do community service to avoid jail time. These superannuated brats, Wheeler (Seann William Scott) and Danny (Paul Rudd), are temperamental opposites. Wheeler is the same drooling skirt chaser, with the same idiotic grin, that Mr. Scott played in the “American Pie” movies. Danny is a whining, misanthropic underachiever who realizes he is in an occupational rut but is too depressed to do anything about it. Wheeler and Danny are best friends (who knows why?) and traveling salesmen who peddle a nauseating-looking energy drink called Minotaur. It is marketed to Southern California high school students, with the slogan “taste the beast,” as a healthy substitute for a drug high. Wheeler appears in costume at school assemblies as the hairy corporate mascot, Minotaur Man, while Danny half-heartedly delivers the product’s official good-health spiel to blank-faced students. Wheeler loves his work, but Danny, who suspects the drink may be poisonous, loathes it. He vents his discontent to his girlfriend, Beth (Elizabeth Banks), a successful lawyer, who becomes so fed up with his bellyaching that she dumps him. After an especially dismal presentation in which Danny veers off script and disparages Minotaur, he goes ballistic in a traffic dispute that destroys the company truck; both he and Wheeler receive 30-day jail sentences. Beth negotiates a compromise: they can avoid jail with 150 hours of community service. The alternative to prison is a mentor program for troubled youth called Sturdy Wings, founded by Gayle Sweeny (Jane Lynch), a gung-ho do-gooder and former cocaine addict who is so full of herself she comes across as a fire-breathing zealot. (Imagine a demented Suze Orman with heavy personal baggage.) Gayle, who won’t shut up about her addiction and recovery, inspires a zany performance from Ms. Lynch that transcends her turn as Mr. Rudd’s ever-lustful boss in “The 40-Year-Old Virgin.” With the ferocity of a drill instructor and the boundless confidence of a self-help guru who combines psychobabble clichés with embarrassingly explicit confessions, Ms. Lynch’s Gayle redeems the movie from utter banality. In the movie’s running joke the big brothers are more immature and brattier than the little ones they are charged to instruct. Until the roles are reversed, the film’s mommy surrogates, including Beth and Gayle, will have nothing to do with them. Wheeler’s “little brother,” Ronnie (Bobb’e J. Thompson), has an even dirtier mind than his mentor and suggests a foul-mouthed Gary Coleman. Danny’s little brother, Augie (Christopher Mintz-Plasse), is a teenage über-geek, cut from the same cloth as Fogell, a k a McLovin’, Mr. Mintz-Plasse’s character in “Superbad.” He lives in the fantasy kingdom of Laire, an elaborate dungeons-and-dragons-like live-action role-playing game whose players dress up as knights, damsels and wizards in the Middle Ages — a world a teenage misfit can get lost in. Although “Role Models” pokes fun at the game, Laire is taken seriously enough to be the vehicle for both Augie’s and Danny’s redemption once Danny enters the game. The movie would have been much funnier, not to mention genuinely subversive, had it laid waste to both the pretensions of Sturdy Wings and the fantasies of Laire. But for the crowd-pleasing finale, in which the players don Kiss makeup for a final battle, “Role Models” pours sugar and cream on everything and turns it to mush. “Role Models” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and profanity.</text>
      <date>November 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>