<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>tuffed with treacle and moral uplift, the new Irish film "Rory O'Shea Was Here" sounds sweet enough to rot your teeth. Consider the possibilities and try not to wince: two physically disabled young men break from their institutional confines and wheel their way into the good graces of all they encounter. Yet despite the periodic twinkling, the occasional detours into sentimentality and, most egregiously, the syrupy soundtrack that threatens to engulf the story at every turn, "Rory O'Shea Was Here" is better than the usual three-stage journey of courage, heartbreak and redemption. In this case, the triumph of the human spirit comes with a small bitter chaser. Key to the film's modest success are its performances, notably from the leads, Steven Robertson as a long-term institutional resident named Michael Connolly, and, in particular, an estimable James McAvoy as the titular renegade who introduces rebellion into the Carrigmore Home for the Disabled. Overseen by clucking, professional worriers (played by Brenda Fricker, among others), Carrigmore is silent as a tomb, and about as much fun, when Rory arrives one afternoon, hair arranged in artfully pomaded spikes. Stricken with Duchenne muscular dystrophy, a degenerative disease that affects the voluntary muscles, this 20-year-old has lived much of his  life in a wheelchair, one that most of his caretakers would clearly prefer to keep in permanent park. But as Michael and the rest of the Carrigmore crew shortly discover, to both their delight and mounting alarm, Rory is anything but confined. Free-wheeling and blissfully foul, he ventures into territory that the able-bodied take for granted, like the local pub, where he hits on women and picks a fight with a drunk because Rory is young and bored and restless, just like everyone else. There's more to his rebellion, as Jeffrey Caine's screenplay gradually makes clear. In essence, a two-hander about a pair of irrepressible spirits, "Rory O'Shea Was Here" also carries a forceful argument about the rights of the disabled in between its melodramatic peaks and valleys. For Rory, raging against suffocating institutional benevolence isn't just a matter of punk posturing; it is a question of human dignity. Directed by Damien O'Donnell, "Rory O'Shea Was Here" doesn't offer many surprises, either in narrative or aesthetic terms, though it does provide an unexpected diversion with an attractive caretaker (Romola Garai). Mostly, though, the film presents the story of two men who face life the way real people do, with glints of anger, eddies of frustration and, every so often, a sense of existential futility. These two wear neither halos nor holy smiles. And, in contrast to the spoiled, overage children who populate our screens and were hideously ubiquitous at the recent Sundance Film Festival, where "Rory O'Shea Was Here" played, the young heroes of this small, emotionally satisfying movie are not after our pity. Be prepared, however, if you end up giving them a few of your tears. "Rory O'Shea Was Here" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). The film has some salty language, most of which will be very familiar to teenagers and child sophisticates.</text>
      <date>February 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>