<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Beto and Tato Verdusco are half brothers who work together at a banana plantation and live with their extended family in a village in southern Mexico. When the two of them are suddenly (and somewhat improbably) plucked from rural proletarian obscurity and turned into professional soccer players in Mexico City, they achieve fame as Rudo and Cursi, nicknames that can be translated more or less as tough and corny.  “Rudo y Cursi” lives up to its name, as do its sweet and scrappy heroes, who are played with antic energy by Diego Luna (Beto, the tough one) and Gael García Bernal (Tato, the corny one). Written and directed by Carlos Cuarón, the movie tells its story haphazardly but with a winning measure of swagger and style. It mixes soap-opera sentimentality with playful, jumpy aggression and dresses a bittersweet, rags-to-riches fable in the bright clothes of pop satire.  It is hard to believe that seven years have passed since Mr. Luna and Mr. García Bernal seduced the international movie audience in “Y Tu Mamá También,” an exuberant road picture written by Mr. Cuarón and his brother, Alfonso, who also directed it. In that film they played rich kids from Mexico City traversing the countryside and finding sexual kicks and intimations of mortality amid the picturesque poverty.  In “Rudo y Cursi” (produced by Alfonso Cuarón’s new company, Cha Cha Chá), that journey is reversed, and the themes are more social than metaphysical. Tato and Beto, country boys dropped down in the big city, struggle with fame, wealth and the caprices of life in a media-saturated consumer culture.  The brothers’ adventures are diverting and occasionally touching without being entirely convincing. Their rise is engineered by a talent scout with the nickname Batuta (baton), who also delivers some mock-philosophical voice-over narration. A genial parasite, played with sly good humor by the Argentine actor Guillermo Francella, Batuta brokers a career first for Tato, a speedy and surefooted forward, and then for Beto, an indomitable goalkeeper. They are hired by rival teams, which sets up a climactic fraternal showdown during a big game.  On the way the fortunes of the brothers (and the rhythms of “Rudo y Cursi”) bounce and skitter as each one struggles with vice and temptation. Cursi’s real passion is not soccer but music, and so he pursues an ill-starred second career as an accordionist and balladeer. His signature song is a norteño version of the old Cheap Trick hit “I Want You to Want Me,” the video for which is one of the film’s comic highlights. His bid for pop stardom is accompanied by a dream-come-true tabloid romance with Maya Vega (Jessica Mas), a television hostess he and his buddies used to fantasize about back home.  Rudo is a devoted family man (his wife, who finds fulfillment peddling dietary supplements, is played by Adriana Paz), his equilibrium undermined by his hot temper just as his good fortune is threatened by his compulsive gambling. Neither brother seems especially well equipped to deal with success, and Batuta certainly isn’t much of a mentor.  But Mr. Cuarón also has trouble managing the tone of the film as it swerves from light-hearted absurdity toward a darker, more cynical view of its characters and their fate. Too often he allows “Rudo y Cursi” to coast on the likeability of its stars, who seem at times to be enjoying themselves more than their characters are able to.  And while the film is lively and engaging, it also, in the end, feels a little thin, largely because it is unsure of how earnestly to treat its own lessons about fate, ambition and brotherly love. There is a lot of velocity in this ultimately familiar tale of rising and falling, but not much gravity. “Rudo y Cursi” is partly about the consequences of taking a game much too seriously, but at the same time it treats everything else — life, death, love, money — like a game.  “Rudo y Cursi” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity, drug use, brief violence and nudity.</text>
      <date>May 8, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>