<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The beleaguered man-boy Dennis Doyle (Simon Pegg) is always running, running, running, an activity befitting the hero of the  British  comedy titled “Run, Fat Boy, Run.” In the film’s prologue he runs away from his pregnant fiancée, Libby (Thandie Newton, charming in a largely reactive role), minutes before their scheduled wedding. When we catch up with him years later, he’s a chubby security guard sprinting after a shoplifter. Soon after, Dennis decides to enter the same marathon as Libby’s rich American boyfriend, Whit,   to show Libby and his now elementary-school-age son, Jake,  that he can make plans and see them through. “You can’t even finish a sentence,” Libby says.  “Fat Boy” will never be mistaken for art. It’s “Rocky” by way of “There’s Something About Mary,”  an inspirational fantasy with guy’s-guy banter and gross-out humor (including a blister-popping scene that seems to be  this film’s answer to the hair gel bit in “Mary”). Yet it’s effective and affecting; much of its impact comes from its images of Dennis running and its conviction that there’s a difference between running toward something and running away.  Mr. Pegg — the star and co-writer of “Shaun of the Dead,” “Hot Fuzz” and “Fat Boy,” which is derived from a  script by Michael Ian Black that was originally set in America — never shies away from Dennis’s pathetic essence. Even when training for a marathon he can’t seem to stop smoking and eating junk food. But Mr. Pegg also gives us enough of a sense of Dennis’s capacity for self-transformation that his mission seems both plausible and inspiring.  Mr. Pegg is abetted by a strong supporting cast that includes  Hank Azaria as the laid-back yet ferociously competitive Whit; Matthew Fenton as the sweet but never-cloying Jake; and Dylan Moran as Dennis’s best friend, Gordon, a degenerate gambler with a penchant for slightly cryptic declarations. (In the aftermath of the blister scene Gordon states, “That was the second most disgusting thing I’ve ever had in my eye.”)  The film’s mix of droll banter, lowbrow slapstick  and melancholy song montages suggests that its  director, the former “Friends” star David Schwimmer, has seen “The Graduate” more than once. The movie is formulaic, and there are times when Mr. Schwimmer and his writers overdo things (particularly in the finale, which finds Whit, previously a human-scaled jerk, indulging in cartoon villainy).  But its assembly-line aspects are countered by touches that translate drama into metaphor, like the scene in which Dennis and Whit  walk with Jake, each would-be daddy tugging at one of the boy’s hands, wishbone style, and an earlier scene in which Whit warns Dennis that every marathoner hits a wall — an admonition that pays off in the marathon sequence when Dennis encounters a  chillingly effective visualization of that wall.  “Run, Fat Boy, Run” is the kind of movie that’s apt to be dismissed a goofy lark.  It is that. But it’s also a rare comedy that believes  in its own message, and that could inspire the depressed and the demoralized to grit their teeth and keep running.    “Run, Fat Boy, Run” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned).  Profanity, nudity and gross-out slapstick.</text>
      <date>March 28, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>