<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Like its source, Augusten Burroughs’s best-selling memoir, the new movie “Running With Scissors” is by turns hilarious and appalling. Set in an era of garish interior design (nicely captured by Richard Sherman, the film’s production designer, and his colleagues) and dubious social experiments, the film is a chronicle of adult weakness and poor judgment seen through the eyes of a bright teenage boy. Joseph Cross, a 20-year-old actor with an intelligent face and a pleasant manner (he also has a small role in Clint Eastwood’s “Flags of Our Fathers”), plays young Augusten, who is sent to live with his mother’s psychiatrist.  But that hardly captures the grotesque real-life comedy that Ryan Murphy, a creator of the cable series “Nip/Tuck,” sets out to portray as the director and writer of this film. Augusten’s mother, Deirdre, is played by Annette Bening in a performance that is a minor classic in the monstrous-movie-mom pantheon. Deirdre, whose husband (Alec Baldwin) is an easily distracted, frequently exasperated alcoholic, dreams of being a famous writer. Or, rather, she is convinced that she already is one, if only the world would wake up and acknowledge her gifts. Her son believes in her, or at least humors her, which makes her abandonment of him especially cruel, and also more than a little self-destructive.  Ms. Bening’s precise, pitiless tracing of her character’s decline from feisty defiance to pathetic, overmedicated self-delusion gives the film an emotional weight it might not otherwise have. As is often the case with adaptations of this kind, the loss of the first-person voice creates a dramatic void at the heart of the story. Engaging as he is, Mr. Cross often seems like more of an observer than a participant, and his Augusten seems curiously invulnerable to the madness that surrounds him.  Seeking solace and support in her crumbling marriage and her stalled ambition, Deirdre falls under the sway of Dr. Finch, her therapist, who hovers somewhere on the spectrum between utter charlatan and complete lunatic. Brian Cox, who was Hannibal Lecter before Anthony Hopkins took over the franchise, is very good at playing this type of character, and he is by turns charismatic and absurd, charming and frightening, channeling his own tendency toward hamminess into Dr. Finch’s histrionic personality. Dr. Finch lives in a huge wreck of a house — the decorating scheme, when it is visible amid all the filth, might be described as acid-trip Victorian — into which Augusten is dropped like a stray animal. He joins a menagerie that includes Dr. Finch’s daughters, Natalie (Evan Rachel Wood) and Hope (Gwyneth Paltrow), and their mother, a fluttery, stringy-haired, terribly damaged enabler played without vanity by Jill Clayburgh.  Add Joseph Fiennes as a patient of Dr. Finch’s who becomes Augusten’s lover and Gabrielle Union as Deirdre’s new flame, and you have an impressive scrapbook of well-observed, offbeat performances, which is almost enough to make “Running With Scissors” worthwhile. The problem is that the efforts of the actors don’t add up to much more than a series of uncomfortable, funny-horrible vignettes in a scattered, shapeless movie. Despite the tale’s undeniably horrific elements, Mr. Murphy conveys little sense of real anguish or danger, and he holds the characters at arm’s length. With the exception of Deirdre, whose willingness to sacrifice her son and her sanity to a mirage of personal fulfillment takes a visible toll on her, they seem static and a little unreal, freakish specimens of human failure pinned to a velvet cushion so we can watch them squirm, and squirm along with them.  “Running With Scissors” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has many disturbing scenes of sexuality, drug use and age-inappropriate behavior and professional misconduct.</text>
      <date>October 20, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>