<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Russian Dolls" belongs to a long line of airy French films that induce a pleasant buzz of Euro-envy. As its attractive characters, on the verge of 30, whiz between Paris and London on the Eurostar express and jaunt off to St. Petersburg for a wedding, you wish their American screen counterparts were as comfortable in their skins and as relaxed about sex. These people know how to enjoy themselves;  their Hollywood peers find it difficult to stop competing long enough to take a deep breath and drink in the moment.  That said, "Russian Dolls," written and directed by Cédric Klapisch, has not much on its mind beyond updating the lives of characters some of us already know. These are mostly the same people (played by the same actors) who shared a Barcelona apartment in Mr. Klapsich's 2002 comedy, "L'Auberge Espagnole."  In the years since, Xavier (Romain Duris), the womanizing charmer who narrates the sequel, has put his literary ambitions on hold while he  grinds out a trashy soap opera about love in Venice for television executives who encourage him to embrace clichés. (From the little we see of this show, it's simply wretched.) He also begins ghostwriting the autobiography of Célia (Lucy Gordon), a spoiled  British supermodel who whines the usual complaints about fame, and seduces him.  Mr. Klapisch's style might be described as Truffaut Lite. He treats digital video with some of the same devil-may-care playfulness that  Truffaut brought to film. Sequences are sped up, one scene is broken into digital patches, the timeline is scrambled, and fantasies embellish reality. Mr. Duris's Xavier suggests a 21st-century Antoine Doinel, Truffaut's fictional alter ego, portrayed by Jean-Pierre Léaud in the series that began with "The 400 Blows" and ended with "Love on the Run."  As Xavier flits from city to city and bed to bed, he also suggests a contemporary descendant of George Roundy, Warren Beatty's Hollywood hairdresser in "Shampoo," but without George's pathos. "Russian Dolls" comes the closest to "Shampoo" when Xavier's ex-girlfriend Martine (Audrey Tautou), a dedicated environmentalist and single mother of a young boy, berates him for leading a selfish, meaningless life, but her words carry no weight.  When Xavier hooks up with Kassia (Aïssa Maiga), a beautiful Parisian sales clerk from Senegal, the movie toys momentarily with the theme of interracial love. When he asks his lesbian pal Isabelle (Cécile de France), now a financial journalist, to pretend to be his fiancée to please his 98-year-old grandfather, and she in turn persuades him to put on drag, the movie touches tentatively on the subject of sexual fluidity.  So what is "Russian Dolls" really about? Like its forerunner, it is a generational group portrait of young, smart, sexy, well-educated Europeans at work and at play, but now it is several years later, and choices have to be made. The shallowness of this idealized depiction of European cultural homogeneity is largely camouflaged by the comfortable fit of its director's sensibility with the actors' likable, lived-in performances.  An apt alternative title for "Russian Dolls" might be "Lovers Without Borders."  Because Xavier speaks English as well as French, he continues to work on the soap opera after it becomes a French-British co-production broadcast in English. When his casual friend William (Kevin Bishop), a London stagehand who is the brother of Wendy (Kate Reilly), his English collaborator on the soap opera, falls in love at first sight with a Russian ballerina, William spends a year studying Russian, then flies to St. Petersburg to pursue her.  Mr. Duris, the wiry, crooked-toothed actor whose sensational portrayal of a musically gifted tough guy in "The Beat That My Heart Skipped" last year suggested a fusion of Jean-Paul Belmondo and Alain Delon, here is almost a dead ringer for the early-1960's German star Horst Buchholz. As weasly, glib and opportunistic as he may be at times, Xavier still hasn't lost his soul. And Mr. Duris's performance leaves you anticipating a third serving of Gallic froth, flavored with a hint of sadness, several years hence.</text>
      <date>May 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>