<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> When God appears to Ralph Walker (Adam Butcher), the plucky 14-year-old hero of Michael McGowan's desperately sentimental movie, "Saint Ralph," he is wearing a Santa suit. That alone should tell you everything you need to know about the film, set in a Roman Catholic boys' school in Hamilton, Ontario, in the 1950's. This crude, inspirational tear-jerker is as sweet as a bowl of instant oatmeal smothered in molasses. It should please those who honestly believe that Santa Claus and God are synonymous; others may retch.  Except for its soundtrack, which features a mawkish, heavily orchestrated rendition of Leonard Cohen's "Hallelujah," which the movie uses without regard to what the song is really about (a relationship), "Saint Ralph" looks and sounds a lot like a product of really, really old Hollywood. Once upon a time, the role of Father Hibbert, a mildly rebellious teacher who disobeys orders and coaches Ralph to run in the 1954 Boston marathon, might have been played by Bing Crosby, and Ralph by Mickey Rooney. Here Campbell Scott handles the Crosby role with poise and aplomb. Mr. Butcher's Ralph, who in the movie's opening scene confesses to 22 impure thoughts, suggests the young Mr. Rooney with a dirty mind.  All the hackneyed stereotypes are in place. Ralph's beautiful, saintly mother, Emma (Shauna MacDonald), hospitalized with an unidentified illness, is a maternal angel; even when she falls into a coma, an air of holiness envelops her. Jennifer Tilly applies her grating vocal honk to the role of Emma's spunky, good-hearted nurse, Alice. Ralph is cheered on in his crusade by his first crush, Claire (Tamara Hope), who wants to be a nun and dispenses bogus spiritual wisdom: if he rubs his knees with sandpaper until they bleed, then kneels in a pan of alcohol, she says, his quest will be advanced.  But the movie's biggest cliché is the school's stern headmaster, Father Fitzpatrick (Gordon Pinsent). A rigid disciplinarian who spies on his students from his office window with binoculars, he emits ominous growls when told that Father Hibbert is teaching the boys Nietzsche.  Little Ralphie's dream of running in the Boston marathon is ignited when Father Hibbert remarks offhandedly that the boy's winning would be a miracle equivalent to Jesus' conjuring loaves and fishes. Ralph takes him literally and convinces himself that if he wins, his mother will wake from her coma.  The story culminates with the big race. And guess who shows up in Boston to run with Ralph on the sidelines and spur him on when his strength flags? That's right: Santa himself.  "Saint Ralph" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual innuendo and a scene of masturbation.</text>
      <date>August 5, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>