<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In "The Aristocrats," Penn Jillette and Paul Provenza's brilliant essay-film on the world's dirtiest joke, Sarah Silverman provides one of the few genuinely unsettling and provocative moments. Stripping away the frame ("A guy walks into a talent agent's office ..."), she tells the joke from inside, from the perspective of someone for whom it is not funny at all. Which makes it funnier than ever, as well as decidedly squirm-inducing.  In "Sarah Silverman: Jesus Is Magic," she tries, with mixed results, for a similar effect. The film, directed by Liam Lynch, is basically a recording of a one-woman show Ms. Silverman performed last year at a North Hollywood theater, with a few musical numbers and backstage sequences thrown in for the sake of variety. The songs include a mocking ode to the stars of pornographic movies, which Ms. Silverman performs in a velvet evening gown; a perky sendup  of racial sensitivities; and a version of "Amazing Grace" in three-part multi-orifice harmony.  Ms. Silverman's comedy is built, to a large extent, on the discrepancies between her appearance and her material. It's not just that she is reasonably pretty. She also comes across, at least at first, as nice, smart and responsible - the kind of girl (never mind that she is almost 35) your parents would encourage you to be friends with or to take to the prom, more teacher's pet than Heather.  But then she opens her mouth, and the vilest, filthiest things you've ever heard come pouring out of it. Scatology! Baby killing! Masturbation!  Shocking, isn't it? Most of the humor in "Jesus Is Magic" depends on the scandal of hearing a nice, middle-class Jewish girl make jokes about rape, anal sex, the Holocaust and AIDS. She makes fun of religion. She riffs on 9/11. But Ms. Silverman is not smashing taboos so much as she is desperately searching for them. Her pauses and quick reversals of tone, her way of inserting the point of a joke parenthetically into a deceptively rambling delivery or arriving at it a few beats late - the rhythms of her act suggest a desire to catch the audience off guard, to find its unprotected soft spots.  But the audience, at least in North Hollywood and probably at movie theaters as well, is way ahead of her. It laughs happily at everything she says, even before she has turned the queasiness into humor. She has only to utter the sentence "I was raped," and the crowd bursts into chuckles, before she has even converted the setup into a punch line. In other words, those in her audience are comfortable, which means that the performer has to act out discomfort on their behalf, supplying her own awkward silences and moments of hesitation. Ms. Silverman is good at this - her gift for mimicking the prevailing modern tones and idioms of piety, hypocrisy and wounded innocence is considerable - but she may be working a little too hard.  The tradition she wants to join is that of Lenny Bruce and Richard Pryor, and in some ways she faces greater challenges than they did. Not just because she is a woman in a profession defined and dominated by men, but also because it is not as easy as it used to be to separate the hip from the square. What Bruce did with obscenity and Mr. Pryor - especially in his first concert film - did with race was to find the outer boundary of the audience's tolerance and push beyond it, confronting and confusing the satisfied self-image of the liberal, sophisticated public.  This kind of transgression has long since become ritualized and normalized, and Ms. Silverman's act is the latest evidence that mocking political correctness has become a form of political correctness in its own right. Her version of insult humor is actually flattering, both to herself and to those who find it funny. She depends on the assumption that only someone secure in his or her own lack of racism would dare to make, or to laugh at, a racist joke, the telling of which thus becomes a way of making fun simultaneously of racism and of racial hyper-sensitivity. (Like many young, otherwise deracinated Jewish comedians, Ms. Silverman falls back on her ethnic identity as a way of claiming ready-made outsider status.)  Everything she says is delivered through enough layers of self-consciousness - air quotes wrapped in air quotes - to make anyone who finds it offensive look like a sucker. She even makes fun of the idea that she might be thought of as an "edgy" comedian. And indeed she isn't. Ms. Silverman is a skilled performer, and "Jesus Is Magic" is occasionally very funny, but don't be fooled: naughty as she may seem, she's playing it safe.</text>
      <date>November 11, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>