<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Wasting no time, "Secuestro Express" kicks off with an opening montage depicting a brutal way of life in a troubled Caracas, Venezuela, and never lets up its relentless assault on the senses. Literally translated as "Kidnapping Express," the title refers to a thriving but deadly abduction business to which many poverty-stricken Latin Americans have turned as a means to secure quick cash.  A trio of hoodlums set their sights on an attractive young couple, Carla (Mia Maestro) and Martin (Jean Paul Leroux), who are just about to head home after a wild night of partying. Once they've been snatched and the ransom demands have been phoned in to Carla's father (Rubén Blades), the victims face a hellish endurance test while awaiting the money's arrival - knowing there's no solid guarantee for their lives even after they've been paid for.  The film, written and directed by Jonathan Jakubowicz and shot on digital video, uses a variety of surprisingly effective gimmicks. The jarring speeded-up and slow-motion scenes effectively evoke a sense of dread, raw urgency and adrenaline-filled drug rushes (reflecting the perpetual narcotic intake of both captors and captives). Split-screen segments, commonly used to bring proximity to characters separated by great distances, here cleverly reveal the simultaneous actions of people located in the claustrophobic setting of one car.  Brief moments of peace occasionally materialize from within the chaos, and it's then that the complexity of the characters - perfectly cast across the board - can be glimpsed. As stereotypes are stripped away, the villains become more human, even sympathetic. And while Martin's truly unflattering colors reveal themselves, Carla begins to feel more at ease with her kidnappers, perhaps because their cruelty isn't as personal or painful.  Whenever a feeling of calm or security starts to set in, the film spins out of control again - each time escalating to an even more extreme level. The constant threat of violence and rape is difficult to endure, but the unpredictable "Secuestro Express" is more than just a dizzying thrill ride laced with small doses of pitch-black comic relief. It manages to raise awareness of frightening  real-life class wars and deep-rooted corruption in a world where the cops are more treacherous than the crooks, and no one can be trusted. Even the most hard-core criminals have to watch their backs, because there is always someone more dangerous lurking around every corner.  "Secuestro Express" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has harsh language, violence, sex and drug use.</text>
      <date>August 5, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>