<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Making a film about the life of an artist is a risky proposition. The paint box arrives full of clichés and unexamined assumptions about the creative temperament, and these grow more assertive if mental illness is part of the biographical material. You are likely to end up with a lot of huffing and puffing and mystification, rather than any real insight into the mysteries of the work.  There are exceptions. Maurice Pialat’s “Van Gogh” (1991), one of a slew of movies about that unhappy genius, is one, and “Séraphine,” Martin Provost’s new film, winner of seven Césars, including best film, is another. Maybe French movies about painters with a special gift for rendering flowers are exempt from the usual banal biopic logic. Not that “Séraphine” escapes entirely from the genre’s default settings. Still, its energies are devoted, for the most part, not to dissecting childhood traumas or recirculating stale cultural gossip, but rather to examining the alchemy by which perception is transformed into vision.  And Mr. Provost makes the case that Séraphine de Senlis, who was born Séraphine Louis and took the name of her hometown, not far from Chantilly in central France, was a visionary. That is not what the other residents of Senlis would have said. Making a meager living as a housekeeper and laundress, Séraphine (Yolande Moreau) is, when we first encounter her, an eccentric and slightly pathetic local character, a figure of pity and sometimes mockery, her dignity protected by a temperament that is at once sharp and childlike, and by a talent that she views as guided by angels.  She has the good luck to work for Wilhelm Uhde (Ulrich Tukur), a German collector and art critic who is rusticating in Senlis and struggling with some demons of his own. Uhde, an early patron of Picasso and Braque, was also famous for having discovered and popularized the work of Rousseau, a Belgian customs officer whose vibrant and exotic paintings seemed to come from nowhere and find their way to the very center of modern consciousness. Séraphine strikes Uhde as a similar kind of artist: self-taught, working in isolation and producing work that seems uncannily out of this world and ahead of its time.  He rejects the habit of calling this kind of art “naïve,” preferring the term “primitive modernism.” Nowadays Séraphine would most likely be called an outsider artist, and her difficult and incomplete assimilation into the marketplace is central to the film’s drama.  The relationship between her and Uhde is a chaste, complicated love story. A gay man in a small town, a German living in France on the eve of  World War I, he is in some ways more of an outsider than Séraphine, who is both rooted in and confined by her life in Senlis.  Their partnership, and Séraphine’s career,  are interrupted by the outbreak of war, and brought to a crisis later by the Great Depression, but these historical catastrophes, while they shape Mr. Provost’s narrative, do not dominate the film.  Instead, the director is properly immersed in the sensual and spiritual dimensions of Séraphine’s art, which grows out of an ecstatic — both in the erotic and religious sense — engagement with the natural world. She paints fruits and flowers in arrangements that at first look merely decorative, like the patterns on wallpaper or pottery, but that on closer examination are charged with a marvelous and unsettling power.  The same might be said about Ms. Moreau’s performance, which is passionate, humorous and heartbreaking. A large, slow-moving woman with a wide, fleshy face and small, intense eyes, she is graceful and elusive, giving clues to Séraphine’s rich and vivid inner life without spelling out or overdramatizing her peculiar and perhaps unknowable state of mind.  The mystery of Séraphine de Senlis — who died in a mental hospital in 1942 and whose work survives in some of the world’s leading museums — is left intact at the end of “Séraphine.” Rather than trying to explain Séraphine, the film accepts her.</text>
      <date>June 5, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>