<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The clang of swords mixes with the sounds of the whispering wind, rustling leaves, singing birds and the occasional unsettling din of Norwegian black-metal music in “Severed Ways: The Norse Discovery of America,” which tracks two Vikings lost in the New World in 1007. Independent to the nth degree, the movie is the mad creation of  a young American, Tony Stone, who not only wrote, directed and edited  “Severed Ways,” but, as one of the warriors, also slaughters a chicken and defecates on screen. Standing in the forest at one point, he even begins head-banging, thrashing hair so luxurious that it’s a wonder that he isn’t scalped immediately.  The inspiration for this D.I.Y. epic — part art-cinema oddity, part home-movie extravaganza — is the real expedition by Thorfinn Karlsefni, an Icelander who planned to settle in the New World. Karlsefni hoped to inhabit an area on the northeast coast of Newfoundland that Leif Ericson  had set eyes on seven years earlier and named Vinland. (The movie was shot in Newfoundland and on land in rural Vermont owned by Mr. Stone’s family.) The settlement didn’t last because the Vikings had a nasty habit of slaying native peoples, whom they called skraelings. This penchant for killing at first sight, the historian Jared Diamond has dryly noted, “was not a promising start to establishing friendships.”  “Severed Ways” opens with the two errant Vikings, Orn (Mr. Stone, the blond) and Volnard (Fiore Tedesco, the brunet), leaving a beach littered with the bodies of men pierced with arrows. Determined to find others of their kind, they set off across breathtaking vistas and head into the past (via flashback), their dreams and encounters with man and beast. Mr. Stone, working with two cinematographers and shooting in digital, makes the most of the natural terrain, capturing its rough beauty in long shots and close-ups that convey the travelers’ evolving intimacy with their surroundings. He skillfully conveys this same change through the montage and framing, as his initially intentionally choppy cuts and Cubistic imagery give way to more unhurried edits and classic tableaus.  Not much happens, even as everything does. The two Vikings, speaking minimal, sometimes amusingly translated and idiomatic dialogue in Old Norse (“We’re toast if we stay here”), construct a shelter, build a fire, trudge through the woods, occasionally bicker and trudge some more. Mr. Stone, who studied with the independent filmmakers Peggy Ahwesh and Adolfas Mekas at Bard College, clearly has no use here for the ups and downs of conventional narrative. Instead, he pays scrupulous, almost loving attention to the details of survival (the Vikings chop a lot of wood) and to how being immersed in this strange world changes the men physically, existentially and spiritually, how it gets under their nails, rubs into their skin and finally settles into their souls.  This, at least, suggests the movie’s loftier ambitions, if not what always transpires on screen. Though there’s no doubt that Mr. Stone is as serious as a heart attack when it comes to creating an air of authenticity — hence the sloppily butchered chickens and authorial defecation — he never settles on a coherent tone for the movie. The idioms, excrement and heavy-metal flourishes certainly goose up the gritty realism, but they also undermine the movie’s moments of grandeur. (Given the Nazi fascination with Norse myths, the decision to use music by Burzum, a favorite of white supremacists, is unfortunate at best.) In one scene Mr. Stone manages to invoke Werner Herzog; in the next  his characters are running around like costumed geeks at a comic-book convention.  That said, American independent cinema could use more young filmmakers who go off the story grid. Far too many,  having embraced the workshop maxim “write what you know” with grave literalness, seem to believe (wrongly) that their first loves, screwy families and adolescences merit their own movies. Yet in drawing heavily from their lives, few end up being able to transcend the narrow confines of their  stories, to push past the realm of the self. “It is a delicious thing to write,” Flaubert rejoiced, “no longer to be oneself, but to circulate in the whole creation one speaks of.” If nothing else, Mr. Stone, from his tangled hair to dirty feet, has taken himself and his story into the beyond  —   way, way beyond.</text>
      <date>March 13, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>