<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The most notable thing about “Sex Drive,” an aggressively puerile, fitfully amusing and sluggish teenage sex comedy, is that it reserves all its creativity for ways to revolt and ostensibly delight its target audience. Highlights/low points: clubbing borderline road kill to death; super-kinky, super-icky sex; a geriatric flasher.  The basic idea is familiar (one virgin, an online hookup, a road trip), as are the backdrops (the mall, suburbia); the central conceit (the hero wants sex but, gee whiz, Andy Hardy, what he really wants is love); the character dynamics (triangular); the repartee (“dude”); the hormonally charged desperation (tasteless sight-gag alert); and the cast composition (many young B-  and C-listers). The probable inspirations include “Fast Times at Ridgemont High,” the “American Pie” movies, “The Sure Thing,” the documentary “Devil’s Playground” and every project Judd Apatow has ever breathed on. From the looks of the cherry GTO Judge that rumbles through the story, someone here has watched the Monte Hellman classic “Two-Lane Blacktop.”  The movie was directed by Sean Anders, who, with John Morris, adapted it from a young-adult novel by Andy Behrens. Mr. Anders doesn’t do much with the camera, although the cinematographer Tim Orr, who has shot all of David Gordon Green’s features, certainly knows how to throw pretty light on a scene. Mr. Anders doesn’t have the flair, or perhaps the heart, for gross-out comedy, with timing that tends to lose the beat midjoke. But despite the usual crass exploitation of young female flesh, he does generally right by his cast. The sweetheart leads, Josh Zuckerman and Amanda Crew, are easy to spend time with, and Seth Green as an Amish hipster and Clark Duke as an unlikely lady-killer hit every sweet-and-sardonic note with panache.  “Sex Drive” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Gunplay, raunchy language, partial male nudity and many bared female breasts.</text>
      <date>October 17, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>