<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Correction Appended When the Apollo 11 astronauts toured the world after  their July 1969 moon landing, recalls Mike Collins, the pilot of the mission’s command module,  he  heard the phrase “We did it” everywhere they went. The “we,” he remembers in David Sington’s documentary “In the Shadow of the Moon,” didn’t refer to Americans, or to any nationality, but to the human race. Millions around the world who had watched on television as men walked on the moon for the first time felt that  they had participated in a great adventure that ennobled the species. If Mr. Collins’s recollections make you swell with vicarious pride, they may also make you shudder. When was the last time the wonders of technology received such wholehearted endorsement? If today’s world is even more strife-torn than the world of 1969, when the Vietnam War was raging, one reason may be that the same technology that produced Apollo 11 has since come under a cloud. The good vibes are gone. The tone of international political discourse has toughened, and the United States is increasingly viewed as an arrogant, dangerous superpower. The concept of a cooperative multinational “we,” working together for world peace,  with America leading the way, is almost as quaint as the cozy concept of “the global village.” The planet that looked so pretty to Mr. Collins from 240,000 miles away is more fragile than we realized. That’s why “In the Shadow of the Moon” is  such a morale booster. The power of its archival images hasn’t diminished with familiarity. There is Earth, spinning in space, a blue and green paradise ringed with clouds. And there is the moon’s surface, up close and forbidding, with shadowy craters like pockmarks: a place of absolute desolation. Yes, we did it. Mr. Collins, who    offers his memories in a tone devoid of grandiosity,  is the most articulate of the 10 astronauts from various Apollo missions interviewed in the film. While Buzz Aldrin, Apollo 11’s lunar module  pilot, and Neil Armstrong, its overall commander, walked on the moon, Mr. Collins never set foot on it. His regrets seem minimal. In down-to-earth language he describes the same feelings of awe and humility that millions back on Earth experienced when looking at the pictures relayed from afar. Putting his thumb in front of his face, he marvels, he could make the Earth disappear. Mr. Aldrin’s observations aren’t as indelible, while those of the notoriously private Mr. Armstrong, who refused to participate in the film, are secondhand. Mr. Collins and Mr. Aldrin both express awe at Mr. Armstrong’s coolness under pressure and his ability to come up with the perfect phrase — “that’s one small step for a man, one giant leap for mankind”  —  when the occasion demanded. But Mr. Armstrong’s absence  leaves the movie with a hole. A grainy vintage television excerpt of his parents on the game show “I’ve Got a Secret” doesn’t begin to fill the gap. Around the story of Apollo 11  the documentary spins a sketchy history of the NASA space program, beginning with its cold war origins. It includes President John F. Kennedy’s famous 1961 speech to Congress declaring his goal of putting a man on the moon before the end of the decade and bringing him safely back to earth. It recalls how the Apollo program nearly ended in January 1967 when a flash fire erupted on Apollo 1 while it was on the launch pad during a simulated countdown,  killing three astronauts. When a manned mission finally left Earth’s orbit in December 1968 and circled the moon, President Kennedy’s goal suddenly seemed attainable. Apollo 8 and 10 took men close to   the moon’s surface, and on July 20, 1969,  the dream was finally realized. A creepy footnote is an excerpt from a sad television speech prepared for  President  Nixon to deliver should the Apollo 11 mission fail. Threaded through the film are fragments of taped interviews with eight other Apollo astronauts:   Alan Bean, Gene Cernan, Charlie Duke, Jim Lovell, Edgar Mitchell, Harrison Schmitt, Dave Scott and John Young. These snippets appear almost randomly, in no particular order, and it is impossible to keep track of who’s who.  Cumulatively, however, they create a group portrait of explorers with “the right stuff”: men with a much higher resistance to fear than average. Mr. Collins remembers the intense physical sensations that he experienced during the Apollo 11 mission but that he never associated with panic. What could have been more terrifying than the moment when the module’s computer was found to be overloaded, just as Mr. Armstrong and Mr. Aldrin were about to touch down?  But Mr. Armstrong calmly went about improvising a solution. If there was a lack of fear, there were a thousand little worries. Through every phase Mr. Collins fretted about the details that had to mesh for the mission to be successful. But he never feared for his life. That, in a nutshell, is the right stuff. “In the Shadow of the Moon” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested) for mild language, brief violent images and incidental smoking.</text>
      <date>September 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>