<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> At first glance, and frequently thereafter, “Sherrybaby” appears to fit comfortably into a familiar class of movies. The film, written and directed by Laurie Collyer, was shown at the Sundance Film Festival earlier this year, and emerged from the affiliated Sundance Lab, where the downbeat and the redemptive are mixed together according to a scientifically precise formula and shot on digital video.  The grim realism of the opening scenes — the inside of a bus, a battered city street, cigarette smoke, rain — and the mopey, acoustic-guitar-driven music foreshadow the story to follow. Sherry Swanson (Maggie Gyllenhaal) has just been released from prison after three years. A former heroin addict, she must now grapple with the demons of addiction while trying to reconnect with her young daughter, Alexis (Ryan Simpkins), now living with Sherry’s brother, Bobby (Brad William Henke) and his wife, Lynette (Bridget Barkan).  In the midst of these large struggles, she needs to tend to the mundane necessities of finding a job, dealing with her parole officer (Giancarlo Esposito) and fighting the daily temptation to slip back into drug use.  What screenwriters call the arc of the story is visible from the outset, and some of the scenes in “Sherrybaby” have a familiar look and feel. But what distinguishes the film from its many peers is the quality of Ms. Collyer’s writing — which rarely reaches for obvious, melodramatic beats — and the precision of Ms. Gyllenhaal’s performance. She  treats the character neither as a case study nor as an opportunity to show off her range, but rather as a completely ordinary and therefore arrestingly complicated person.  In those first scenes Sherry’s face is a captivating puzzle. Listening to music on her earphones, clutching the paper bag of her belongings, she lets a smile play across her mouth, a sign that incarceration has not erased her capacity for pleasure. Ms. Gyllenhaal’s long legs suggest a self-confidence that is subverted by the stoop of her shoulders, a tall girl’s defense against unwanted attention.  And sometimes Sherry demands attention, easily seducing the manager of the halfway house where she lives just after her release and coolly using her sexuality to secure the job assignment she wants (working in a day care center). But sometimes she looks as if she wants to curl up into a ball and disappear, and the war between these impulses is at the heart of her drama, which in the end involves her attempt to construct a workable identity for herself.    Part of this is the desire to be a mother, a longing that drives some of the film’s most delicate and emotionally risky scenes. Sherry, whose relationship with her father (Sam Bottoms) has a creepy intimacy, has a hard time behaving like an adult around Alexis; it’s almost as if, when she’s with the little girl, she wants to turn into her, or to escape into a shared, private world of innocent play. This puts her at odds with Lynette, who she thinks, with some justice, is in competition with her for Alexis’s affection.  As Sherry, a middle-class suburban woman as well as an ex-convict, tries to figure out who she is, she finds some support from Dean (Danny Trejo), a fellow ex-convict and recovering addict who is both a link to Sherry’s past life and an example of successful liberation from it. Their relationship is tender, ambiguous  and treated  —  by both actors and Ms. Collyer —  with tact and understatement, which are the principal virtues of the movie and, somewhat paradoxically, the source of its cumulative intensity of feeling.</text>
      <date>September 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>