<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Every year, Hollywood cuts yards of so-called romantic comedy from bolts of synthetic cloth. The elegant and exquisitely tailored "Shopgirl,"  written by Steve Martin,  based on his slender novel of the same name, and directed by Anand Tucker ("Hilary and Jackie"), puts most of them to shame. As it relates the delicate, almost anecdotal story of a young woman looking for love in modern Los Angeles, the movie reveals what is missing from most others of its kind: the fact of sex  and the possibility of heartbreak, which is to say the very conditions of romance itself.  American commercial cinema is happy to crack dirty jokes and sing maudlin hymns to matrimony, but "Shopgirl," which is both funny and sweetly sad, aims for something other than salaciousness or sentimentality. It is partly about how the specter of love can give ordinary life a feeling of risk and enchantment, a process that Mr. Tucker discreetly recapitulates on screen. The crisp and lovely images (shot by Peter J. Suschitzky), though never self-consciously pretty, turn drab daily reality into a satisfying aesthetic experience. And the movie's jewel-like moments of humor and disappointment are tastefully laid out on the velvet cushion of Barrington Pheloung's luxurious orchestral score.  All that string-heavy music makes "Shopgirl" feel a bit like an older movie - a 1950's Technicolor romance or a 40's weepie, perhaps - but the setting and characters are thoroughly contemporary. Mirabelle Buttersfield (Claire Danes), as charming as her name, with just the right hint of oddness, commutes every day from her modest apartment in Silver Lake to her job selling gloves at Saks Fifth Avenue in Beverly Hills. Not the practical, hand-warming kind (this is Los Angeles, after all), but the long, thin-fingered accessories that once were a requirement of feminine glamour and have been demoted to the status of indulgent caprice. Mostly, she stands behind a counter, removed from the main retail action, as the camera admires her from a discreet distance.  Ms. Danes, whose performance is flawless, is certainly lovely enough to invite such admiration, but she does not go out of her way to solicit it. The movie's conceit depends upon our ability to believe that Mirabelle, who moved to California from Vermont, is lonely and overlooked - not quite an ugly duckling, but someone whose diffident, melancholy temperament might render her invisible in a world more interested in flashy display. (Such display is embodied by one of Mirabelle's co-workers, a gold-digging blonde played with marvelous verve by Bridgette Wilson-Sampras.) With her student loans, her futon furniture, her poky pickup truck and the antidepressants in her medicine cabinet, Mirabelle could be one of countless recent college graduates fumbling through early adulthood in the drifting, wanting state that sociologists used to call anomie. (This condition, as it afflicts the young, was uncompromisingly captured in Andrew Bujalski's decidedly unromantic "Funny Ha Ha.")  What Mirabelle needs, Mr. Martin's introductory voiceover tells us, is someone to recognize and appreciate her, to pluck her out from the crowd and confer a sense of specialness on her. The movie itself does this, of course, and so do the other two main characters, who become unwitting rivals for Mirabelle's affection.  The first suitor is Jeremy (Jason Schwartzman), who chats her up one night in a Laundromat. (To judge from his overall personal hygiene, it's probably a rare visit.) Jeremy, who works for a manufacturer of amplifiers ("I'm involved in stenciling"  is how he puts it), represents the incisive caricature of a familiar generational type - the emo-slacker-hipster-doofus. Whether he is oblivious to his own immaturity or proud of it is hard to say. But his childishness is not without a certain appeal, and in any case he is available, so Mirabelle, panicked by her own need and isolation, goes on a less-than-thrilling date, and later - even less thrillingly - to bed with him.  And then along comes Ray Porter, a well-dressed older man with impeccable taste and unlimited resources, who is also recognizable to anyone not actually in "Shopgirl" as its screenwriter and narrator. Mr. Martin, with his silvery suavity and mutedly sardonic voice, has long since proven himself a mild and sensible guy, as well as an acute comic miniaturist. Ray's relationship with Mirabelle at first resembles the thwarted romance between Bill Murray and Scarlett Johansson in "Lost in Translation" (whose writer and director, Sofia Coppola, happens to be Mr. Schwartzman's first cousin). But Ray turns out to have more in common with Don Johnston, the middle-aged bachelor Mr. Murray plays in Jim Jarmusch's "Broken Flowers." Both Ray and Don are solitary, soft-spoken seducers, who have made their money in unspecified computer-related enterprises and who lead lives of serene and solitary good taste.  There is something attractively wistful about Ray, and also something calculating. In the course of his affair with Mirabelle, which occupies the long middle section of "Shopgirl," you can feel a chilly whiff of cynicism troubling the warm, romantic air. The literature of an earlier age would have used words like mistress or kept woman to describe Mirabelle, who happily accepts Ray's impressive generosity. The idea of buying and selling is right there in the film's title. But in a milieu as defined by consumerism as this one - the opening shot lingers over all the good stuff for sale at Saks - it may be difficult to conceive of a love that is not to some degree also a transaction.  Which is not to say that this is "Pretty Woman" all over again. Quite the contrary. That movie simplified and falsified a complicated (and objectively ugly) connection between its main characters, whereas this one finds complexity in a relationship that appears to be perfectly simple. Ray, who delights in giving Mirabelle nice presents, is a bit stingier with his emotions, and tries, after their first night together, to establish parameters and time limits. Mirabelle, swept up in his gallantry, is at a disadvantage. She has only herself to give.  Mr. Martin and Mr. Tucker neither minimize nor overstate the inherent cruelty of this scenario; nor do they deny its potential for tenderness and intimacy. The most complimentary and the most damning thing to be said about Ray is that he is a gentleman; he lives by a code that may ultimately be self-serving but that nonetheless obligates him to do his best to behave decently. Jeremy, on the other hand, seems altogether feral, if not infantile, driven by his immediate needs and impulses and oblivious to the rules and expectations that make society work.  And, it should be added, that make love possible. The thinnest, funniest strand in the  braided narrative of "Shopgirl" involves Jeremy's eccentric journey in the direction of maturity, a trip aided by self-help tapes and a wise rock musician. But Jeremy's growth is, in a way, the key to the movie, which depends on the recognition that people change, and indeed change one another. This process is both farcical and painful, a doubleness Mr. Tucker manages to acknowledge without sliding into coarseness or melodrama.  "Shopgirl" is a resolutely small movie, finely made and perhaps a bit fragile. Under the pressure of too much thought, it might buckle and splinter; the characters might look flimsy, their comings and goings too neatly engineered, their lovability assumed rather than proven. And it's true that none of them are perfect. From where I sit, though, the film they inhabit comes pretty close.  "Shopgirl" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Without being too graphic or crude, it's about how adults talk and behave.</text>
      <date>October 21, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>