<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “I wish I had friends,” laments 11-year-old Toe Thompson (Jimmy Bennett), a picked-on kid with a mouth full of metal and a ZIP code full of weirdos. Toe’s lack of companionship, however, has less to do with his orthodontist than with the peculiarities of his suburban neighborhood: the ominously named Black Falls, home to Black Box Industries and locus of excessive looniness.  Structured as five short stories connected by Toe’s irksome narration, “Shorts” surges forward and rewinds, pauses and skips around as if  controlled by a remote-wielding toddler. This narrative device, assisted by appropriate on-screen graphics, soon becomes tiresome, but it’s emblematic of a film that is dancing as fast as it can to entertain. Yet despite a plot crammed with mini-aliens, maxi-crocodiles and a variously sized James Spader, the movie never engages more than our eyes.  The story’s MacGuffin is a rainbow-hued wishing rock that bounces from one character to another, granting computer-generated fantasies and causing predictable pandemonium. Since this is a tale for tykes, the rock must enlighten as well as gratify; so the avaricious owner of Black Box (a criminally underextended Mr. Spader) learns that his children need more attention than his bank balance, while Toe’s workaholic parents (Jon Cryer and Leslie Mann) finally comprehend that talking is healthier than texting. Everyone learns what it means to be terrorized by technology — something of a paradox  in a movie whose characters, story and emotions are fatally subordinate to a tsunami of special effects.  The least convincing of these invigorate the Black Box, the company’s sole product: a strange, multipurpose gadget that resembles an ebony Rubik’s Cube and can serve as everything from a cheese grater to a solar panel. This utopian utensil — a wishing rock for the consumer — allows for a mild skewering of our infomercial culture and, especially, our increasingly decentralized workplace. Presenting a labor-saving device whose development monopolizes the time and labor of every adult in Black Falls, the movie revels in an absurdity that parents will appreciate even if their kids do not.  Concocted by Robert Rodriguez, a kind of filmmaking Black Box (he wrote, directed, edited, produced, photographed, composed some of the music and supervised the visual effects), “Shorts” feels underwritten and overdressed. Though adept at homing in on the things that kids find hilarious — boogers, loogies, not-blinking contests — Mr. Rodriguez (whose bifurcated brain flips easily from “Grindhouse” gore to “Spy Kids” kookiness) leaves his adults in the lurch. Even the estimable William H. Macy, as a germophobic scientist, is forced to play most of his scenes from inside a Hazmat suit.  Thank heavens for little Jolie Vanier. As Helvetica Black, whose Beryl the Peril demeanor and ingenious nickname (“Typeface”) enliven many a doldrum, this pint-size Christina Ricci is a real find. She’s not enough, though, to rescue a movie so conventional as to urge us to be careful what we wish for. Like a sequel, perhaps?  “Shorts” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). A telepathic baby, a bodacious older sister and a raging blob of mucous.</text>
      <date>August 21, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>