<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Jeff Nichols’s “Shotgun Stories,” a drama about warring clans of brothers in small-town southern Arkansas, defines the classic western phrase “doing what a man’s got to do” as both a moral imperative and a biological compulsion. The movie is filled with unremarkable men who would rather die than appear weak.  The doom-spiral narrative of “Shotgun Stories” starts with the death of the patriarch, Hayes, who sired two clans of boys with two women. In his first marriage he was a violent alcoholic who never gave his children proper names; to this day they’re known only as Son (Michael Shannon), Kid (Barlow Jacobs) and Boy (Douglas Ligon).  The old man walked out on his family, then became sober, remarried, came to Jesus and had four more sons: Cleaman (Michael Abbott  Jr.), Mark (Travis Smith), Stephen (Lynnsee Provence) and John (David Rhodes). The second Hayes family owns a cotton and soybean farm and is comfortably middle class. Son, in contrast, works at a fish hatchery and lives in a shack near a freeway: his wife, Annie (Glenda Pannell), recently took their son, Carter (Cole Hendrixson), and moved out because, Son says, she was tired of his gambling. Kid sleeps in a tent in Son’s yard, and Boy lives in a van by the river.  When the father dies, his first three sons crash his funeral. Son calmly declares that just because the elder Hayes reformed doesn’t make him a good man, then spits into the open coffin.  Much of the film’s ensuing violence is staged obliquely or kept off camera, but it’s still shocking because of its juxtaposition with mundane images of daily life. Childish insults, cruel pranks and awkward assaults coexist with middle-school basketball practices and trips to the grocery store and carwash.  The feud’s main players know they’d all be better off if they stopped fighting, but they keep sabotaging peace offerings with huffy macho taunts.  Mr. Nichols and his cinematographer, Adam Stone — the longtime second-unit photographer for the filmmaker David Gordon Green, who helped produce “Shotgun Stories” — often frame their tortured, self-destructive  characters within wide shots of depopulated streets, verdant fields and placid bodies of water, acknowledging the beauty these men are too self-involved by rage to see.  The cast’s detailed but subtle performances deepen Mr. Nichols’s characters in ways that become clear only upon second viewing. Mr. Shannon’s constricted line readings and prematurely aged gait suggest the patriarchal burdens that Son bears without complaint. Mr. Ligon’s performance as the slobbish, amiable, easily flustered Boy is the film’s moral center. Shambling through the film’s final third, his bruised face squashed atop a neck brace, he’s a battered Everyman, torn between decency and hate.  “Shotgun Stories” is as cool-headed as its characters are reckless. Not only are there no heart-rending flashbacks to Son, Kid and Boy’s childhoods, but we also never even see a photo of their father. Son’s back is covered with shotgun-pellet scars, but we get only a sketchy account of how he acquired them. The film is a here-and-now American potboiler and a stripped-down parable that can be appreciated by any culture.  It’s telling that the factions disagree on who started this mess. Cleaman, Mark, Stephen and John blame Son’s disruption of the funeral. Son blames his father’s long-ago viciousness, then charges his mother (Natalie Canerday) with demonizing his father’s new family: “You raised us to hate those boys, and we do, and now it’s come to this.”  Son tells his half-brother Stephen, “This started a long time ago.”  Stephen’s reply is as much wish as threat: “Well, somebody’s gonna finish it.</text>
      <date>March 26, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>