<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Like smog settling over Los Angeles, a creeping sense of anomie haunts the Hollywood power players and parasites sidling nervously through “Shrink,” a portrait of a disenchanted therapist to the stars and his clientele. Directed by Jonas Pate from a screenplay by Thomas Moffett, based on a story by Henry Rearden, this dissection of a soul-sick community of self-medicating actors, writers and agents would like to think of itself as a contemporary “Play It as It Lays,” only kinder and gentler.  “Shrink” doesn’t peer into the abyss as fixedly as “Play It as It Lays,” the 1970 Joan Didion novel or its screen adaptation by the director Frank Perry (for which Ms. Didion wrote the screenplay with John Gregory Dunne). Nor does it have the ruthless satiric thrust of Robert Altman’s “Player,” or the pungent gallows humor of a Bruce Wagner novel.  But its central character, Dr. Henry Carter (Kevin Spacey), is afflicted with the same metaphysical malaise that engulfed Ms. Didion’s characters. A widower whose wife recently committed suicide for reasons left unspecified, Carter is a best-selling author of pop psychology books who has grown to believe that he can’t fix people and that his profession is useless. During a television interview (Gore Vidal conspicuously overacts the role of host) Carter has a meltdown and tears up the pages of one of his books.  No actor is better than Mr. Spacey at conveying a bone-deep cynicism, in his case usually accompanied by a malicious, needling wit. But Carter, pacified on marijuana, booze and cigarettes, doesn’t have the leftover energy to be nasty. One of the most revealing shots finds him passed out in the early-morning hours on a poolside lounger at his sleek home in the Hollywood Hills, empty bottles at his side. Only once in the movie, when his father (Robert Loggia) stages an intervention, does he snap out of his lethargy long enough to get on his high horse and angrily refuse treatment.  The doctor’s clients, many of whom are professionally interconnected, make up an unglamorous composite picture of players and hopefuls in the Southern California entertainment axis. The most vivid are Patrick (Dallas Roberts), a superagent and hypochondriacal worrywart suffering from extreme obsessive-compulsive disorder; and Jack (an uncredited Robin Williams), an alcoholic movie star who frets about his possible sexual addiction while refusing to acknowledge his drinking problem.  Mr. Roberts’s character gets off some nifty zingers; in one he sneers that he hasn’t seen a movie since “Titanic,” which had a “spoiler alert — the boat sinks.” Nostalgically recalling his premarital wild days, Mr. Williams’s character draws from an endless storehouse of amusingly raunchy euphemisms.  Other characters, none of whom is as sharply drawn, include Patrick’s perky, unmarried assistant, Daisy (Pell James), who is pregnant and dreams of being a producer; Shamus (Jack Huston), a self-loathing Irish movie star whose careless mixing of pharmaceuticals catches up with him; and Kate (Saffron Burrows), a beautiful actress with a cheating husband, coming to grips with the fact that she is no longer 27 in a youth-obsessed profession.  The one Hollywood outsider among Carter’s clients, Jemma (Keke Palmer), is a troubled African-American teenager and avid movie lover, recovering from a family tragedy, whom he treats pro bono. Jemma develops a conflicted friendship with another Carter client, Jeremy (Mark Webber), an unscrupulous, aspiring screenwriter.  These characters are mostly too sketchy and their connections too contrived for “Shrink” to jell as an incisive ensemble piece. But the atmospheric cinematography (by Lukas Ettlin) and hovering music (by Brian Reitzell and Ken Andrews) lend “Shrink” a queasy downbeat mood.  Mr. Spacey’s therapist, bearded, bleary-eyed and exuding dejection, is not someone you would recommend to a friend seeking help. If we really knew our therapists’ closely guarded personal stories, whom would we trust?    “Shrink” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has drug content, profanity and sexual references.</text>
      <date>July 24, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>