<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>t seems churlish to be too hard on "The Sisterhood of the Traveling Pants," a fresh-scrubbed, eager-to-please movie based on Ann Brashares' best-selling young adult novel. Like the four teenage girls at its center, the film makes up in charm  what it lacks in sophistication. The sisterhood of the title is formed when the girls, best friends since childhood, are about to be separated for the summer for the first time. On a shopping trip, they find a pair of thrift-store jeans that mysteriously flatters all  of them, despite their different shapes and sizes. Deciding that the jeans must be magic, they make a pact to share them for the summer, each wearing them for a week  and then mailing them to the next friend. These peripatetic pants connect the  four separate stories as we follow the girls through their summer adventures. Carmen (America Ferrera), the writer of the group (who also narrates the film in voice-over), is the half-Puerto Rican child of divorced parents. She's over the moon about spending a summer alone with her father (Bradley Whitford), until she discovers that he's moved in with a lily-white Southern woman (Nancy Travis) and her two annoyingly perfect children. Painfully shy Lena (Alexis Bledel) is off to visit her grandparents in a village in Greece, while flamboyant Bridget (Blake Lively), a star athlete, is heading to soccer camp in Mexico. The cynical Tibby (Amber Tamblyn) is the only one stuck at home for the summer, working at a Wal-Mart-like superstore and making a video "suckumentary" about all the losers in her hometown. Of these four plots, the story of Carmen's blended family is by far the most consistently engaging, largely because of the vibrant presence of Ms. Ferrera, who has been a talent worth watching since her film debut in 2002 in "Real Women Have Curves." The Lena and Bridget story lines, centered as they are on ill-starred puppy love, will have less emotional resonance for anyone over 12, while the tale of Tibby and her video documentary founders in bathos after the introduction of a dying child (Jenna Boyd) who slowly breaks down Tibby's sarcastic facade. "The Sisterhood of the Traveling Pants" has plenty of plot twists that grownups will see coming a mile away, but that's no reason to deny its pleasures to the less jaded younger set. "The Sisterhood of the Traveling Pants" is rated PG. It has some mild profanity and references to offscreen sexual situations.</text>
      <date>June 1, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>