<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One of the all-too-uncommon joys of summer is the movie that is so flat-out ridiculous that you can't help  enjoying it. Summer has long been the season for disposable entertainments, the time when air-conditioned comfort means more than what flickers onscreen. The recent drift toward seriousness, though, may have complicated matters somewhat, since big, smart movies like "Batman Begins" and big, sober movies like "War of the Worlds" may be making it tough for scraps of fluff like "The Island" to find their audience.  Still, if the box-office woes of "The Island"  suggested that popcorn movies had gone totally gourmet, "The Skeleton Key" offers sound proof that summer remains as down-market and nutrition-free as ever. One of the most enjoyably inane movies of the season, this faux Southern Gothic offers an embarrassment of geek pleasures: Kate Hudson running around in a T-shirt and underwear, a scenery-chewing villain, intimations of unspeakable evil, slamming doors and equally slamming edits and an introductory course in hoodoo, a folk religion born in the South. All this and Gena Rowlands, Peter Sarsgaard and John Hurt, too, a divine troika who look perfectly content to be neck-deep in so much Spanish moss and hooey.  Ms. Hudson is the star of this show and as a New Orleans hospice worker named Caroline she fits the plucky-heroine-in-panties role with determination, or perhaps just resignation. Scarred by her father's death, which she missed because she was on the road with a band (an odd plot point, given that Ms. Hudson played a rock groupie in her best movie to date, "Almost Famous"), Caroline wants to find a more meaningful job, one in which she will make a difference. To this end she hires on as a private nurse, a well-paying gig that ushers her into the strange company of Violet Devereaux (Ms. Rowlands) and her husband, Ben (Mr. Hurt), who is apparently on the fast track to the sweet hereafter after a debilitating stroke.  Caroline's new job also puts her smack dab in the middle of the bayou, a location that inspires the director, Iain Softley, and the screenwriter, Ehren Kruger, to indulge in almost every conceivable regional and genre cliché. In addition to the aforementioned Spanish moss, the touristic tableaus of the Big Easy, the blues and requisite beads of sweat, the filmmakers also trot out an old blind lady with a milky stare, a handsome stranger (Isaach de  Bankolé in a sliver of a part) who, rather bewilderingly, asks Caroline if she speaks French, and the usual frightful accouterments. Pickled body parts? Check. Faded photographs of unhappy people in period dress? Check. A stuffed dummy in a blond wig? Check. A magical circle in chalk and blood? You bet.  It takes Mr. Softley a while to get the film in gear, which is understandable since it doesn't make much sense. Apparently, the Devereaux mansion was once home to some bad people and may now be haunted or just in need of structural repair.  It would spoil the film's meager pleasures to say more, though it must be said that the film contains a jarring scene of a double lynching. Like some directors who only dip into horror (until they can get back to making serious movies), Mr. Softley oversells his scenes with fussy visuals, as if such filigree could obscure what lies beneath. The lynching occurs in a flashback that oscillates between color and black and white and contains more tilted camera angles than the entirety of "Titanic." It's all very arty, as if lynching were just an empty shock tactic.  That scene tears a hole in the story that might be difficult to repair if "The Skeleton" were not such a throwaway. Happily, thanks to the game supporting cast and a plot that grows progressively more harebrained, the film soon returns to its business of making you jump in your seat while you laugh at your own gullibility. Given Ms. Rowland's part in goosing those jumps, a note to her management team seems in order: Wes Craven and Tobe Hooper, among many other purveyors of modern dread, would probably be happy to know that Bette Davis, the great scream-queen from horror classics like "What Ever Happened to Baby Jane?," finally has a credible successor. All Ms. Rowlands needs now is a picture worthy of her splendid menace.  "The Skeleton Key" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It features a disturbing double lynching and the usual haunted-house boos.</text>
      <date>August 12, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>