<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> For anyone who hasn't grasped the connection between the ruthless pecking order of the suburban American high school and the popularity of movies and games in which geeky adolescents dream themselves into becoming superheroes, "Sky High" should help explain the world, or at least the world of entertainment.  This zippy Disney adventure-comedy, crammed with special effects, asks that age-old rhetorical question, "Is there life after high school?," and answers it with a cheerful "Not really."  The movie, directed by Mike Mitchell ("Surviving Christmas") from a screenplay by Paul Hernandez, Mark McCorkle and Bob Schooley, is a clever hybrid of Harry Potter (its nerdy 14-year-old hero, Will Stronghold, has magical powers) and "The Incredibles" (Will belongs to a family of superheroes). The live action and computer animation are so thoroughly interwoven that you can easily lose track of what is what.  In the movie's clever premise, Will (Michael Angarano) is a freshman at an elite school (Sky High) for future superheroes and heroines, situated in the stratosphere. On his first day of school, Will, in a Peter Pan moment, boards a yellow bus that looks perfectly ordinary until it sprouts wings and jet engines and lurches into the blue yonder.  Its location may be heavenly, but Sky High, which is held aloft by an antigravity mechanism and hidden above a cloud bank, is less than celestial. With its jocks, nerds, bullies and mean girls, it is just like every other suburban high school, only more so. As for the faculty, the school nurse has X-ray vision, the science teacher is a conehead, and the coach a bully.  Without bearing down too heavily, "Sky High" suggests that the rigors of high school leave permanent emotional wounds. Upon his arrival, Will finds himself lined up with the other freshmen in the gym and tested for superhero aptitude. Coach Boomer (Bruce Campbell) brutally divides the incoming flock into heroes (the future stars) and sidekicks (the wannabes).  At these amusing auditions, one student shape-shifts into a guinea pig, another multiplies into a cheerleading squad, another melts into a squishy puddle of ick, and one wisp of a boy wows the student body by becoming a two-ton iron man.  Because Will's parents (both Sky High graduates) are world-class superheroes passing as real estate agents, great things are expected of their son. His father, Steve, a k a the Commander (Kurt Russell, playing it exactly right, with a slightly raised eyebrow and a faint smirk), is shown in an early scene donning Superman-like garb and saving a city from a giant robot. Will's mother, the Florence Henderson-like Josie, a k a Jetstream (Kelly Preston), has comparable gifts.  But Will, who has fooled his father into thinking he has a son who has achieved superpowers, fails his orientation and is herded into the sorry ranks of the sidekicks. He is also attacked by Warren Peace (Steven Strait), a glowering rebel who can set his hands and arms on fire at will. A divided soul, Warren is the product of a mixed marriage between a superheroine and a supervillain whom the Commander punished; he has a chip on his shoulder against the Stronghold clan.  Will's wounded confidence is boosted by the fawning attentions of Gwen Grayson (Mary Elizabeth Winstead), a senior and the most popular girl in school, who makes a beeline for him. Swept off his feet, he suddenly has no time for Layla (Danielle Panabaker), the girl next door and his closest childhood friend, who is itching to be his sweetheart and happens to have power over plants.  Because "Sky High" is a Disney family film, it can't begin to depict the adolescent temptations of drinking, drugs and sex. Although Will gives a forbidden party in his parents' home, it is strictly juice and cookies, raucous play and loud music. With little effort, Will comes into his powers, is promoted to the school's hero studies program and becomes the leader he was meant to be.  But a darker current ripples under all the superhuman perk. High school ostracism, whether avenged (as in "Carrie") or healed ("Never Been Kissed"), the movie suggests, is never forgotten. In its friendly way, "Sky High" opts for vengeance, which is wreaked at a homecoming dance by an unlikely villain. In one of the movie's wittiest conceits, many of the students are transformed into burbling infants, a nifty metaphor for what high school society, with all its jostling ids, is really all about.  "Sky High" is rated PG (Parental Guidance suggested). It has some strong language and mild innuendo.</text>
      <date>July 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>