<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Filmed mostly in winter, in browns, grays and soiled whites, “Sleepwalking” sustains a mood of unrelenting bleakness, wearing its aesthetic of desolation like a badge of integrity. Integrity and quality, unfortunately, are not synonymous. “Sleepwalking” may linger in downscale territory where few movies — even indies — dare to tread, but it has far too many flaws to make it a likely candidate for awards consideration. And isn’t that kind of recognition the only commercial hope for gloomy kitchen-sink dramas?  Set in northern California and Utah but filmed in Saskatchewan, the movie, directed by William Maher from a screenplay by Zac Stanford (“The Chumscrubber”), evokes a depressed environment of ugly, cramped apartments and flimsy shacks, junk furniture, muddy backyards and chain-link fences. As its characters eke out a marginal existence, they are defined by this oppressive milieu. When they break the rules, the police, social service agencies and debt collectors are poised to crush whatever hopes they have left. As the song says, “Them that’s got shall get/Them that’s not shall lose.”  How is an 11-year-old girl brought up in such conditions to find a better life? That’s a question Tara Reedy (AnnaSophia Robb) hardly dares ask. As the film begins she and her reckless, slatternly mother, Joleen (Charlize Theron), have been evicted from the house where they were staying with Joleen’s latest boyfriend, who was busted for growing marijuana. Tara has no choice but to trail along glumly as Joleen is reduced to begging her meek, ne’er-do-well younger brother, James (Nick Stahl), to take them in.  No sooner have they moved into James’s dingy apartment than Joleen runs off with a truck driver, leaving Tara with her uncle, who works on a road-building crew. After missing one too many days on the job, he is fired. He and Tara end up crashing in the basement of his married best friend, Randall (Woody Harrelson). It isn’t long before Tara lands in a foster home.  In a last-ditch effort to put down roots, James snatches Tara from foster care, packs them into a car and drives to the childhood home he and Joleen fled many years earlier. The scenes of James and Tara, who agree to pose as father and daughter, developing a familial bond while on the road give the movie its only glimmer of sweetness. Once they arrive at the Reedy homestead — a run-down cattle and horse farm that is an American gothic house of horrors — they are immediately put to work as unpaid slave labor by the monstrous paterfamilias (Dennis Hopper).  “Sleepwalking” is the kind of movie in which every character tic and nuance of dialogue has to be perfectly calibrated for it to ring true. In the early scenes, a careful attention to detail leads you to hope it might succeed. But as Mr. Maher, in his feature directing debut, brings in surreal touches and puts on literary airs, the film’s grip loosens, and its vernacular turns increasingly wooden.  In the most glaring moment, James, describing his life, uses the movie’s title in a baldly inserted statement. A clever fantasy sequence in which Tara is observed by two young boys while lounging poolside at a motel, wearing pink sunglasses and roller skates, seems to belong to another movie. Before it reaches a tentative, unsatisfying ending, “Sleepwalking” metamorphoses from meticulous social realism to horror thriller.  If the performances are strong, the casting isn’t quite right. Mr. Stahl’s James is a little too sensitive and well spoken for the role of a born loser. Ms. Theron’s Joleen should have been closer to Amy Ryan’s crude, careless mother in “Gone Baby Gone.” Ms. Robb’s Tara is the best thing in the movie. This tense, wary Lolita — albeit one with no inclination to play teasing games — understands her lowly station in life. As much as she cares about her mother, she is determined not to follow in her footsteps. Her only choice is to grit her teeth and bide her time.  “Sleepwalking” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, strong language and violence.</text>
      <date>March 14, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>