<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Are we in a movie?” wonders Felix Bonhoeffer, the addled, decrepit screenwriter played by Anthony Hopkins in his  experimental satire “Slipstream.”  “Everything’s a movie,” snaps Bette Lustig (Fionnula Flanagan), an actress in the troubled film Felix has been desperately rewriting. She and Felix have been languishing along with the unhappy cast and crew on the project’s dilapidated set in the Mojave Desert, built years ago (according to the “Slipstream” production notes) for a Dennis Hopper film.  Their exchange encapsulates the single idea bandied about in “Slipstream,” which Mr. Hopkins wrote and directed and for which he composed the score. It is his third film as a director and his first as a quasi-avant-garde filmmaker working well outside the mainstream. It might be described as his “Mulholland Drive,” the far superior David Lynch film to which “Slipstream” owes an enormous debt. (Fellini’s “8 ½” is another obvious inspiration.)  The weary, unassuming Felix is the opposite of Mr. Hopkins’s Richard M. Nixon, Pablo Picasso and Hannibal Lecter, in that it provides him with no opportunities for flashy impersonation or lip-smacking melodrama. As he reaches into his bag of tricks, he can’t resist pulling out images of Nixon and  Hitler (whom he also impersonated, in a television movie). Such self-referential flashes suggest a “why not throw in the kitchen sink?” attitude toward experimentation, not to mention playful self-parody.  Most of the movie takes place inside the head of Felix, whose latest project, a violent melodrama, has fallen apart in midproduction. After the off-screen death of its star, Matt Dobbs (Christian Slater), who had taken the movie into his own hands and begun rewriting the script, its incompetent, Vicodin-addicted director (Gavin Grazer) can’t handle the pressure.  Throwing up his hands, he desperately telephones his producer Harvey Brickman (John Turturro), a raving madman who orders Felix to fix the movie. As the script is rewritten, characters played by Michael Clarke Duncan and Camryn Manheim interject (sometimes on Felix’s own computer) to protest that their roles have been diminished.  As a director Mr. Hopkins, much like his character, comes across as a befuddled observer of his own film, whose style is a compendium of avant-garde techniques and narrative tricks wielded willy-nilly to suggest deeper meanings below a hyperkinetic surface. Among other surreal happenings, time moves backward and forward, objects change color, and Felix has near-death experiences that may or may not be real. The entire story could be interpreted as a dying screenwriter’s life flashing before his eyes.  The film’s centerpiece is a scene from the stalled movie in progress in which Mr. Slater’s character Ray, a psychotic hitman, and his ominous sidekick Geek (Jeffrey Tambor) storm into a highway diner and menace the patrons and staff for their own amusement. If Mr. Slater has a fine time overacting the part of B-movie villain, you can’t help but wonder if Mr. Hopkins knows how mediocre and hackneyed this film within a film is. Is it a joke? Or has he recycled Hannibal Lecter one too many times? Stuffed with references to old movies and insider lore about life on a movie set, much of “Slipstream” feels like a loosely connected series of jokes.  The most prominent among its old-movie references is the original “Invasion of the Body Snatchers,” whose star, Kevin McCarthy, appears in clips from the 1956 film and as his contemporary self. But if that science-fiction classic serves as an all-purpose metaphor for the blurring of reality and movie fantasy, and of the double vision of an actor today and his younger celluloid self, it isn’t woven satisfactorily into the story.  “Slipstream” suggests that after years of diving into the souls of other people, some of them famous, Mr. Hopkins has special knowledge of how the lines between the real people and the fictional characters can blur. It’s not a new idea. The author Neal Gabler identified this phenomenon in the title of his book, “Life, the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.” But for an actor like Mr. Hopkins, disappearing into another character, especially a historical figure, must be a far more unsettling deconstruction of reality than for the casual moviegoer observing the transformation. That is a notion “Slipstream” might have explored more fruitfully, had it focused its wandering attention span, kept its camera steadier and figured out what it wanted to say.  “Slipstream” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language and some violent images.</text>
      <date>October 26, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>