<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In the overheated, hapless "Slutty Summer,"  waiters hiss at one another throughout the film's daylight hours. Then, when the sun goes down, the same pouty posse gallivants around Manhattan's same-sex cruising spots, voicing fears of being picked up by Mr. Wrong or, worse, left alone altogether.  The film is a labor of love for Casper Andreas, who wrote, directed and starred in this first feature. For the actors he has chosen, it's a labor of lust, with copious necking and grappling required. For the audience, it's just a labor.  The film's biggest disappointment is not the scrappy cast, which features a standout performance by the Welsh-born natural Jamie Hatchett, whose heavy-lidded languor suits his bad-boy Lothario character. In another role, Jesse Archer employs his barbed tongue as a dreamboat who loves 'em, leaves 'em and gracelessly bad-mouths 'em the next day. For her part, Virginia Bryan is an accomplished batter of eyelashes with an unquenchable thirst for the sauce.  Sadly, the weak element is Mr. Andreas, who saved the noble lead role of Markus for himself. Dumped after years of monogamy, Markus attempts to sort though the woes of Splitsville and the sorry prospects for new love, but often his cause becomes too hard to champion. Mr. Andreas has some stilted lines to spit out, and his faint Swedish accent slows what should be some rapid-fire repartee.  He did, however, recognize a story worth telling, and he poses a few interesting questions about how meaningless sex might mask other problems. But this point is delivered in a package that is too loosely wrapped. The East Village gay contingent and the crystal-meth gay contagion deserve a big-budget exploration, a sweet-and-sour saga that might match the West Hollywood valentine that Greg Berlanti, the television writer and producer, delivered in his film "The Broken Hearts Club."  Strangely, given all the talent in that Land of La Chappelle, such a film has not emerged. At the very least, perhaps "Slutty Summer" will prompt some director to fashion a film that deserves a place alongside the heartache Rufus Wainwright has captured in song and the mores that Mike Albo has sent up onstage.</text>
      <date>June 10, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>