<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In “Snow Cake” Sigourney Weaver peels off layers of urbane sophistication to play Linda Freeman, a high-functioning autistic woman living in a rural Ontario town called Wawa. With her face scrubbed clean of makeup and wearing an expression that shifts between infantile delight and childish indignation, Ms. Weaver gives a technically accomplished performance. She is so far outside her comfort zone that you scan her body language for signs of the haughty female warrior lurking behind Linda’s blank innocence. But that person is nowhere to be seen.  Linda, who supports herself stocking the shelves of a local grocery store, has phobias galore. Compulsively neat, she refuses to take out the garbage. When her dog vomits on the kitchen floor, she is thrown into a state of terror. Mostly, however, she takes joy in life. Behind the house is a trampoline on which she spends afternoons gleefully jumping up and down. A favorite winter pleasure is eating snow (hence the movie’s title).  When Linda’s temperamental opposite enters her life, “Snow Cake” turns into a sugary life lesson: a disabled person becomes a holy innocent healing sick, world-weary souls. The object of partial redemption is Alex Hughes (Alan Rickman), an embittered middle-aged Briton recently released from prison after serving time for killing a man.  It is a violent death that throws Linda and Alex together. While on the road to Winnipeg, Alex is accosted in a diner by Linda’s hitchhiking 19-year-old daughter, Vivienne (Emily Hampshire), who pesters him for a ride. He sourly agrees. Shortly after they hit the highway, his car is slammed off the road by a truck, and Vivienne dies. Guilt-stricken, although the accident was not his fault, he decides it is his duty to visit his dead passenger’s mother and deliver the news in person.  Unaware of Linda’s condition, Alex is nonplused when she shrugs off her daughter’s death. He ends up staying in her house until after the funeral. They become friends and Scrabble opponents who play the game by Linda’s wacky rules, which allow the use of nonexistent words like “dezlious.”  “Snow Cake,” directed by Marc Evans (“Resurrection Man”) from a screenplay by Angela Pell, partly camouflages the banality of its concept with its meticulous performances. Ms. Weaver is convincing precisely because she doesn’t oversell the upbeat life lessons her character imparts to Alex; a less gifted actor would grab every opportunity to promote Linda as the radiant incarnation of a live-in-the-moment, we-are-all-children philosophy. Even the name “Freeman” sends the message.  Mr. Rickman’s Alex is a pill. A scowling, baggy-eyed misanthrope whose grumbling tone and suspicious gaze convey defeat, he is occasionally capable of sardonic self-deprecation. “I don’t have baggage; I have haulage,” he remarks. “Snow Cake” coyly holds back the whys and wherefores of his imprisonment until late in the movie, when he exchanges confessions with Linda’s attractive next-door neighbor, Maggie (Carrie-Anne Moss).  An anomaly among Linda’s cozy neighbors, Maggie is a sex-starved divorcée who invites Alex to dinner with one thing in mind. He obliges, and they begin an affair. But Alex is so much older, and exudes such an air of crumpled exhaustion, that the relationship begs credibility.  So do a lot of other elements in “Snow Cake.” Like “I Am Sam,” it is a film that tests your cynicism. Those charmed by cute contrivances like “dezlious” may devour “Snow Cake” as eagerly as Linda munches on snow.</text>
      <date>April 27, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>