<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>n intersibling death match reminiscent of Sam Shepard's "True West," the independent feature "Solitude" details the tortured, possibly incestuous relationship between Hilary (Mary Thornton), a dark, hyperactive young woman with grand ambitions, and her brother, Louis (Patrick Belton), a twitchy, bipolar idler who lives in a cramped Phoenix apartment filled with the moldering remains of recent takeout meals. Hilary turns up on Louis's doorstep with her new girlfriend, Soledad (Ronne Orenna), an amateur painter whom Hilary hopes to turn into the next big name in desert landscape art. Ostensibly, Hilary has come to ask her brother for the use of his car, so the two women can visit a potential dealer in Flagstaff. But Hilary's real motivations run much deeper and darker. The car is just an excuse to introduce the sweet, trusting Soledad to the bitterly sarcastic and fiercely destructive Louis, and set her up as a reluctant witness to the cruel psychological games the two siblings have been playing for most of their lives. "Are you sure you don't want a beer?" Louis asks Hilary as they warm up for the evening's entertainment. "Because you are going to need one." Written and directed by Susan Kraker and Pi Ware, "Solitude" has the claustrophobic feel of an Off Off Broadway storefront production, despite the sweeping desert landscape that frames the events. As Louis and Hilary slash away at each other, digging into a traumatic childhood dominated by a dismissive father and a depressive mother, they seem to merge into a single, angry mass. If they are not physically involved with each other (the film remains coy on that point), they are more emotionally intertwined than most married couples. The screaming matches make for some vivid theatrical moments, and Mr. Belton is particularly good at conveying Louis's manic ups and downs. He has one extended monologue, in which, with the help of a stuffed toy, he acts out the history of Louis's twisted relationship with his domineering father. The scene is very funny until Mr. Belton deftly allows it to spin out of control, his wit turning to bile and his polished delivery to screaming hysterics. Just what value "Solitude" has beyond such acting moments is debatable. The drama ultimately feels  like a clinical study without wider resonance.   Where Mr. Shepard's psychological slug-outs seem to reflect wider cultural issues, "Solitude" seems concerned  only  with  its own effects. "Solitude" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has vulgar language and some sensuality.</text>
      <date>January 7, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>