<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> LIKE those other big-screen intangibles, chemistry is easier to recognize than explain. Cary Grant and Ingrid Bergman combust beautifully in Hitchcock's "Notorious," while the then-married Tom Cruise and Nicole Kidman just sputter in Kubrick's "Eyes Wide Shut," two soggy sticks without the requisite friction. In "Ocean's Eleven," George Clooney relieved Brad Pitt of the burden of being the most beautiful man in the room, and the results were nose-tickling fizzy, as playfully sexy and artless as the most classic of screwball pairings.  In "Something New," a pleasantly diverting romance about a black woman (Sanaa Lathan) and a white man (Simon Baker) forced to transcend prejudice, hair extensions and a few awkwardly staged scenes in order to be with each other, the chemistry between the leads is as unmistakable as the setup is contrived. As Kenya McQueen, a top executive in a Los Angeles accounting firm, Ms. Lathan wears the kind of smart suits that speak (never shout) consummate professionalism. Kenya lives to work, and if her datebook remains blank after-hours such is the apparent price for being young, successful and the new owner of a tastefully appointed house with a garden in desperate need of plowing and planting. Enter the gardener, Brian (Mr. Baker), muscles rippling.  Reader, he digs her  —  and she digs him, this being a Hollywood fantasia. First comes k-i-s-s-i-n-g, and then comes some lightly steamed boudoir nuzzling, including the best toenail-polishing since "Lolita," followed by the expected complications with family and friends. The lovely Ms. Lathan, who established her big-screen bona fide a few years ago in another romance, "Love &amp; Basketball," and the similarly attractive Mr. Baker, an underemployed Australian who waxes hot ("L.A. Confidential") and cold ("The Ring Two"), don't just look good together; they feel right in sync. Their easy, sensual rapport partly owes something to the generally sure hand of the film's director, Sanaa Hamri, making a fine feature debut, and something else, something indefinable, to the delectable mysteries of two bodies in cinematic motion.  The screenplay, written by another newcomer, Kriss Turner, places those bodies in some familiar situations (a clinch in the rain), but it also gives the actors more than the usual romantic fluff and nonsense. Race is the obvious complicating factor here, but it is class  —  the perception as well as the reality of such difference  —  that gives the story its piquancy. The daughter of a prominent doctor (Earl Billings, who has the warmly gruff thing down) and a status-conscious mother (the reliably entertaining Alfre Woodard), Kenya works and plays according to the rules. For her that means extensions, not her natural curl, and a quest for what she and her friends call the IBM  —  or Ideal Black Man  —  a mate of impeccable pedigree and comparable earnings.  Brian throws Kenya for a loop not only because he's white, but also because he has dirt under his fingernails. As it turns out (this being a Hollywood fantasia), he isn't actually an inarticulate earthy brute out of D. H. Lawrence or Harlequin, but a landscape architect. Still, the battered ride, devoted golden retriever, community-garden work, rumpled jeans and artfully applied smudges are enough to give a former debutante pause. "He's the help," exclaims Kenya's brother, Nelson  (Donald Faison), after he refuses to shake Brian's hand. A buppie with a sports car and a succession of equally expensive girlfriends (one of whom speaks pitch-perfect Valley Girl), Nelson  is a model of clueless consciousness, a man who chides his sister for crossing the color line even as he goes through women like Kleenex.  For the most part, the Moroccan-born Ms. Hamri, who has directed music videos for Prince and Mariah Carey, among others, sells the story's tougher bits as well as she does the mush. The filmmaker has a nice sense of some of the less cinematically exploited areas of Los Angeles, like the upscale black neighborhood where Kenya lives and power walks, and the Magic Johnson Starbucks where she first meets Brian on a squirmingly uncomfortable blind date that says more about racial anxiety than the entirety of "Crash." "Something New" is a love story, but it is also very much about the education (and liberation) of a thoroughly modern miss who wears her identity as an Ideal Black Woman with righteous pride and, at times, a bit like armor.  "Something New" isn't especially new, which is actually part of its low-key charm. There's something reliably agreeable about watching two pretty people go through the usual romantic motions, especially since Big Hollywood seems to have more or less given up on love, perhaps because it's also more or less given up on women. This year's Oscar race, with its pathetic lineup of nominees for best actress and a specialty-division frontrunner about two men in love, offers further proof of just how inconsequential distaff stories now are to the majors. Which, in turn, partly explains why plausible straight romances are as rare (and tiny) as gemstones, like Richard Linklater's "Before Sunset." "Something New" looks modest indeed by comparison, but the film is good news nonetheless  —  it's a store-bought valentine with real heart.  "Something New" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). The film has some discreet lovemaking and one scorching dance number.</text>
      <date>February 3, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>