<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Ever since he hustled (or was smuggled) onto the festival circuit in the mid-1990s with a couple of entertaining, ramshackle short films  —  modest lovelies like “Where’s the Money, Ronnie?”  — Shane Meadows has been busily carving out his own corner in British cinema. Though the broken-in faces and broken-down places change ever so slightly, the stories and the storytelling have remained consistent enough to make Mr. Meadows something of a brand director, one with a familiar visual sensibility and view of the world that says, yes, there will be blood, but  most people are fundamentally decent and good.  There’s rather less blood than usual in “Somers Town,” an agreeable if slight, vaguely sketched character study times two , which clocks in at 70 fast minutes, including credits. Decency and goodness are much in abundance if not initially visible in the form of Tomo (Thomas Turgoose), a pugnacious teenage runaway from the Midlands who, shortly after landing in London, befriends Marek (Piotr Jagiello), a lonely Polish teenager whose ubiquitous still camera is meant to suggest, I suspect, that he has a sensitive soul. Along with his father, Mariuz (Ireneusz Czop), a construction worker whose cheery disposition hides darker truths, Marek lives in the centrally located London area that gives the movie its title. The two boys meet, clown around, flirt with a French waitress (Elisa Lasowski). That’s about it.  Mr. Meadows explains on his Web site (shanemeadows.co.uk),  that the movie originated with a pitch to the filmmaker from Eurostar, the rail company that operates, among other lines, the  train service between Paris and London, in the tunnel colloquially known as the Chunnel. Eurostar wanted to know, he continues,  “if I would make a feature-length project around the Somers Town area of Kings Cross, using kids from there, Paris and possibly Belgium.”  Maybe the company was trolling for younger customers; it runs trains out of  the neighborhood.  Mr. Meadows doesn’t say. He does clarify, however, that after turning down the project, he changed his mind, suggesting his frequent collaborator, Paul Fraser, who wrote some of his best-known films, like “A Room for Romeo Brass,” for screenwriting duties.  The new movie, digitally shot in black and white, was paid for by Eurostar and, as it happens, includes a brief interlude in Paris (Belgium was left off the itinerary), where Tomo and Marek are reunited with the flirtatious French waitress in the shadow of the Eiffel Tower. Mr. Meadows says on his Web site that he retained creative control of the movie, which is good to hear. He doesn’t mention whether  he and his cast and crew made the voyage from London to Paris on the Eurostar. I hope they traveled first class. Whatever the case, if you’re not freaked out by traveling underwater, it is a nice, fairly short trip,  though, at some three hours, it will eat up twice as much of your life as this movie.  In keeping with the  travel motif, Film Forum will show the movie with “A-Z,” Sally Arthur’s five-minute animated ode to the essential  London street guide.</text>
      <date>July 15, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>