<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The spiritual godfather, as it were, of the comic British charmer “Son of Rambow” is Sylvester Stallone at his fiercest and certainly his gruntiest.  Slathered in sweat and wearing a rag that circles his head like a tourniquet, Mr. Stallone is instantly recognizable as the Reagan-era avenger who first materialized in the instantaneous 1982 camp classic “First Blood.” He rises from the screen like a phoenix from the ashes, even if for the two boys at the center of “Son of Rambow,” who savor his every ponderous, violent move, he’s more of a muscle-bound Tinkerbell ushering them into a new world.  A likable, lightly sticky valentine to childhood, the 1980s and the dawning of movie love, “Son of Rambow” was written and directed by Garth Jennings and produced by Nick Goldsmith, the duo behind the underappreciated fantasy “The Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy” (2005). Like that film, this one involves a snug community of oddballs and outcasts whose eccentricities, pluck and fundamental good cheer have long been durable staples of British screen comedy. The beating heart of this particular grouping is Will Proudfoot (Bill Milner), a lonely child with a single mother (Jessica Stevenson) and an artistic itch, whose fundamentalist faith  has made him a pariah at school, second only to its resident bad boy, the devilish Lee Carter (Will Poulter).  In screen romance fashion, the two boys meet cute if somewhat cruelly. A member of a Christian sect  that forbids television, movies and apparently smiling, Will is quietly sitting in a school hallway (while the rest of his class takes in some audiovisual instruction), when Lee erupts into his field of vision like a bomb. Having been ushered out of his classroom rather more rudely than Will (and to the robust cheering of his fellow students), Lee instantly bounces a ball off the other boy’s unsuspecting head, creating a fatal attraction that starts off like Krazy Kat and Ignatz Mouse, and soon morphs into something far softer. (Lee throws the ball hard, but Mr. Jennings makes sure it doesn’t hurt too much.)  What kicks the story into gear, turning two wary children into blood brothers, is Rambo. The movie-mad Lee, who lives with his negligent older brother, Lawrence (Ed Westwick), in a mausoleumlike manor next  to a nursing home (their absent mother is married to the facility’s owner), runs a steady video dubbing operation. He’s also making his own screen epic in hopes of winning a television contest. When this would-be DeMille accidentally introduces Will to Rambo, the image of the tough guy serves as a shock to the sheltered (and fatherless) boy.  Rambo — invincible, unyielding — liberates Will, exciting his already effulgent imagination and creating a bond with Lee, his first real friend. But Rambo also enslaves him, making this introspective loner hungry for friendship and film alike.  Working in a self-consciously quirky key that owes a strong debt to Wes Anderson’s “Rushmore,” Mr. Jennings keeps his busy pieces in harmonious play, creating a miniaturized world as detailed, painstakingly determined and insulated as an ant farm. He crams the frame with bright colors and comic bits of business; tosses in an interloper, a French  Billy Idol  called Didier (Jules Sitruk); and makes room for the occasional melancholic stretch.  And although the film’s visual style feels more borrowed than organic, there’s enough truth to Will and Lee’s actions — and to the uninflected, touching performances of the two young leads — to keep the film humming along, even when Mr. Jennings veers into sentimentality and lets one too many tear drop.  “Son of Rambow” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Innocuous childish violence.</text>
      <date>May 2, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>