<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Soul Men” is a raucous, rambling comedy, offering some laughs, some groans and a feast for fans of the musical idioms it mocks and celebrates. It is also something of a bittersweet experience for fans of Isaac Hayes, who has an extended cameo as himself, and Bernie Mac, who plays Floyd Henderson, half of a has-been vocal duo reunited for one last show.  Mr. Hayes and Mr. Mac both died after the movie, directed by Malcolm D. Lee, was shot, and the loss of Mr. Mac, whose time in the pop-culture spotlight was tragically brief, feels especially acute. In a stand-up routine immortalized in Spike Lee’s “Original Kings of Comedy,” Mr. Mac showed he could wring more laughs and more insight out of a single obscenity than anyone since the heyday of Lenny Bruce. And as the star of a network sitcom (“The Bernie Mac Show,” which ran on Fox from 2001 to 2006), he showed that he could be a warm and friendly family man without sacrificing his penchant for provocative, truculent candor.  On television, though, and in the PG-13 movie “Oceans Eleven” and its sequels, Mr. Mac had to curb his tongue. “Soul Men” not only allows him room to explore the nuances and inflections of profanity, but it also pairs him with Samuel L. Jackson (as Louis Hinds, Floyd’s onetime singing partner), certainly no slouch when it comes to wringing poetry out of the blue Anglo-Saxon linguistic heritage.  To say that the chief pleasure of “Soul Men” is watching these two men swear at each other is in no way to sell it short. There is also some hitting and gunplay, but that’s pretty superfluous. Once these guys start yelling at each other, all Mr. Lee really has to do is keep the camera running.  They also sing, which is riskier but still pretty good fun. Louis and Floyd, long estranged, are brought back together by the death of Marcus Hooks (John Legend), the Grammy-winning superstar for whom they sang backup in the old days. Their own careers were less glorious. Louis served a prison sentence, and Floyd cycled through a bunch of marriages before being dumped in a retirement community by his nephew. Marcus’s passing offers them the chance for a comeback, and also the opportunity to explore some road-movie clichés en route from Los Angeles to the Apollo Theater in Harlem.  Along the way they encounter Mr. Hayes and some less interesting, equally familiar stock characters, including a hip-hop thug (Affion Crockett), a doughy white nerd who loves black music (Adam Herschman) and Jennifer Coolidge. They also trip over some unconvincing sentimentality involving Cleo (Sharon Leal), the daughter of a woman both men once loved.  Mostly, though, “Soul Men” is driven by the volatility of Louis and Floyd and by its savvy, affectionate exploration of the history of R&amp;B. The movie’s nostalgia for the old days of soul is playful and relaxed, but — in contrast to, say, the pious and misguided “Dreamgirls” — its grasp of the relevant musical idioms is meticulous. The story is a hectic and haphazard affair, but the soundtrack of well-made soul covers and the cruder music of Mr. Jackson and Mr. Mac’s foulmouthed one-upmanship provide a measure of satisfaction.  “Soul Men” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian).  It has some sex scenes and language as rough as the songs are sweet.</text>
      <date>November 7, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>