<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "A Sound of Thunder," by Ray Bradbury, is a short, elegant science-fiction parable about the dangers of going back in time and messing up the course of evolution.  "A Sound of Thunder," a scrap of late-summer damaged goods from Warner Brothers ostensibly based on Mr. Bradbury's tale, offers a somewhat different lesson. Directed by Peter Hyams from a script credited to (or perhaps blamed on) Gregory Poirier,  Thomas Dean Donnelly and Joshua Oppenheimer, it illustrates the dangers of turning a lean, elegant short story into a loud, noisy, incoherent B movie.  Slogging through a future Chicago overgrown with killer vines and menaced by ape-lizards, a character is heard to remark, "This can't be good." No, it can't. But there are many ways a movie can fail to be good, and "A Sound of Thunder" is, at least, not a dull, mediocre genre exercise. (If you want one of those, please help yourself to "Underclassman," also opening today.) Instead, this picture achieves a level of badness that is its own form of sublimity. You almost - please note that I said almost - have to see it to believe it.  Mediocre movies suffer from a deficit of imagination. Truly bad ones, in contrast, are afflicted by imagination run amok, unchecked by formal discipline or competence. Those ape-lizards, especially when they start to fly, are impressive in their way, as is the sheer volume of exposition that has been stuffed into Mr. Bradbury's tidy conceit.  In 2055, we learn, time travel ("an invention that could change the world or destroy it") has been commodified by a greedy mogul named Charles Hatton (Ben Kingsley). Hatton runs a business called Time Safari, which ferries tourists  back into the Cretaceous period to hunt dinosaurs. Someone has also apparently gone back to the 20th century to retrieve a truckload of double-breasted chalk-stripe suits and, to judge from Mr. Kingsley's white pompadour, Jack Valenti's hair.  Hatton is harassed by government regulators and also by Sonia Rand (Catherine McCormack), an angry blond scientist who disrupts one of his soirees with a Champagne bottle filled with blood. "A hundred years ago she'd be protesting the Internet or biotechnology," Hatton remarks, recalling the notorious anti-e-mail riots that roiled the Eisenhower administration.  Actually, Dr. Rand is trying to warn the world of the dangers of time travel, which become apparent after a prehistoric hunting trip goes awry. Leading a squad of scientists through the chaos and confusion that ensues is Edward Burns, who brings his usual dim stoicism to the role of Dr. Travis Ryer, a studly biologist.  The fake science in science fiction works best when sparingly applied, but "A Sound of Thunder" pours it on in buckets, making the story as murky as the cut-rate special effects. There is a talking computer, a holographic lion (all the real ones have been wiped out by some kind of virus) and lots of fast talk about time waves, wormholes and bio-filters.  Chicago, meanwhile, is overrun by murderous vines, giant insects and predatory dino-orangutan-bats. It also has an underground train system locals call "the subway," and a National League baseball team that has won the World Series twice. That may be pushing the limits of plausibility a little too far.  "A Sound of Thunder" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language, violence, a hint of sexuality and vicious flying ape-lizards.</text>
      <date>September 2, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>