<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Journalism is all about having the courage to write the truth even if it will get you mocked  by your relatives and co-workers, so here goes: “Space Chimps” is hilarious.  Yes, the name combined with the G rating might have parents thinking they should stay in the car while the kiddies go into the theater, but that would be a mistake. It would, among other things, cause them to miss one of the better one-liners of the summer, the capper in a string of chimp puns delivered by a title character. Waiting to read it here? You’ll wait a long time.  If “Wall-E”  pushes the boundaries of what can be done in an animated movie, “Space Chimps” proves that the old formula is still pretty effective when executed well. The old formula being a  child-friendly tale laced with deadpan asides for grown-ups and delivered by top-notch voice actors.  “Before man braved that first giant step, the brave stepped into the rocket,” a narrator intones as the film begins. “And the brave were chimps.”  And then we meet Ham III (Andy Samberg), the smart-alecky grandson of one of the original chimps in space, who has a job at a circus, being fired out of a cannon. He doesn’t aspire to much more, but events are conspiring to put him on a path to his true destiny: a space probe has been sucked into a wormhole, and there are plans to send a crew of chimps after it.  It’s an experiment to see if the chimps can survive wormhole sucking, and the space agency hunts down Ham for the publicity-stunt value, teaming him with Luna (Cheryl Hines) and Titan (Patrick Warburton, the chimp pun maker, who is a droll riot as always).  When do the adults in the audience first know that this film has plenty for them? When that space probe lands on a planet full of blobby things and plays the video it has brought along to tell alien life forms the story of Earth and its humans. Suffice it to say that this video was not properly vetted at NASA.  An evil blobby thing named Zartog (Jeff Daniels) uses the space probe as a weapon to terrorize the rest of the planet’s population (also to build a casino), and it is up to the space chimps to dethrone him. Kristin Chenoweth, the Broadway fave, is the voice of one of the ugliest cute characters in animation history, a thing with a giant head.  Back on the ground, Stanley Tucci leads the group of hapless humans who don’t realize how smart the space chimps are. The film’s writers, Rob Moreland and Kirk DeMicco (who also directed), slyly nod to assorted space movies and clichés. And the music, some of it by Blue Man Group, keeps things rolling along.</text>
      <date>July 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>