<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Special” burdens its hero, Les Franken (Michael Rapaport), with a double dose of movie-loser shorthand: he’s a traffic cop and comic-book fan. But a funny thing happens after he starts popping an experimental antidepressant called specioprin hydrochloride (trade-named “Special”). Les develops the ability to levitate, walk through walls and read people’s minds.  Awesome! Except that he is actually going bonkers.  Written and directed by Hal Haberman and Jeremy Passmore, “Special” puts an indie spin on the current Hollywood vogue for moody superhero psychodrama. Or looked at another way, it puts a Hollywood spin on the indie vogue for tales of solipsistic man-boys.  Either way, it doesn’t quite go far enough as psychological study or cultural commentary. Though Mr. Rapaport is affecting (and well cast) as Les, the character often feels condescended to, and his inner conflict becomes stranded in some desultory plot mechanics involving shady drug company executives.  “Special” takes the notion of the mentally unstable vigilante hero to its logical conclusion  —  outright delusion —  and offers an empathetic alternative to the nihilism of the recent Batman pictures. But ultimately it adds little to our understanding of the curious return of the superhero as our paradigmatic pop archetype.  “Special” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language and violence.  SPECIAL  Opened on Wednesday in Manhattan.  Written and directed by Hal Haberman and Jeremy Passmore; director of photography, Nelson Cragg; edited by Mike Saenz; music by Tom Wolfe and Manish Raval; production designer, Nathan Amondson; produced by Edward Parks and Frank Mele; released by Magnet Releasing. At the Landmark’s Sunshine Cinema, 139-143 East Houston Street, East Village. Running time: 1 hour 22 minutes.  WITH: Michael Rapaport (Les Franken), Paul Blackthorne (Jonas Exiler), Josh Peck (Joey), Robert Baker (Everett), Jack Kehler (Dr. Dobson) and Ian Bohen (Ted Exiler). </text>
      <date>November 21, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>