<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Many of us who grew up watching television in the 1960s and ’70s have fond if vague memories of “Speed Racer.” Those big-eyed characters (Trixie! Speed! Racer X!), their mouths never quite moving in sync with the dialogue; those bright colors and semiabstract backgrounds; those endless, episodic story lines. Whether we knew it or not, the series was a primer in the aesthetics of Japanese animation, the love of which we could later pass along to our children.  Failing that, I suppose we could subject them to Warner Brothers’ new live-action feature film, also called “Speed Racer,” which was written and directed by Andy and Larry Wachowski, the maestros of “The Matrix.” Like so many other expensive, technologically elaborate big-screen adaptations of venerable pop-culture staples, this movie sets out to honor and refresh a youthful enthusiasm from the past and winds up smothering the fun in self-conscious grandiosity. The childhood experience the Wachowskis evoke is not the easy delight of lolling in the den watching one cartoon after another, but rather the squirming tedium of sitting in the back seat on an endless family car trip, your cheek taking on the texture of the vinyl seat as some grown-up lectures you on the beauty of the passing scenery.  And yes, some of what you see in “Speed Racer” is indeed beautiful (as is the slyly old-fashioned orchestral score by Michael Giacchino). The colors pop off the screen as if someone had burst a giant bag of digital Skittles. Look at those red socks young Speed is wearing! Did you ever see a dress as yellow as the one on Susan Sarandon? (She plays Speed’s mom. John Goodman is his dad.) Or a classroom so brilliantly orange? These hues occur nowhere in nature. And I’ll grant that it is mildly interesting to sit back and contemplate the philosophical and artistic implications of having human actors populate a completely synthetic environment in which the familiar laws of optics and physical movement no longer apply.  You could, come to think of it, spend a pleasant hour in a museum looking at still images and short, looping video installations culled from the hectic, 2-hour-15-minute morass of this movie. And there may be a perverse integrity in the way the Wachowskis approach the material, which is to focus relentlessly on visual style while dispensing almost entirely with credible emotion or intelligible narrative. But this would be an easier case to make if the visual style itself were not so busy and incoherent.  Yes, the colors are hot, the set design is cool, and the sidekick chimpanzee is cute, but the action sequences — the hyperreal video-game kineticism on which the Wachowskis’ reputation for virtuosity has rested — are chaotic and nonsensical. The sleek computer-animated racecars flip, jump and slide from side to side, but few of their feats elicit anything like the amazement or surprise of, say, watching moderately skilled teenage skateboarders in a parking lot. To be truly sensational, action needs to make sense and to convey the tension and grace of real physical movement, however fanciful the objects in motion may be.  But at least those cars — including Speed’s Mach 5, faithfully replicated from the old cartoons — move. When it comes to storytelling, “Speed Racer” has nothing in common with its title. Not only does it surpass the grinding tedium of “The Matrix Revolutions,” but it does so with far less excuse. Back in the early years of this century, it was possible to pretend that the grim-faced expository noodling of the later “Matrix” movies was the vehicle for profound insights into — well, something. Go look it up on Wikipedia.  But “Speed Racer” is about a boy driving a car, surely a subject that cries out for linearity, simplicity, velocity. Instead the first half-hour layers flashbacks with portentous foreshadowings, generating pointless confusion about who is doing what and why. After his beloved older brother, Rex, is killed in an accident — or is he? — Speed (Emile Hirsch) is wooed by the oleaginous head of the Royalton company (Roger Allam), and also by Trixie (Christina Ricci).  There are, to be sure, some vague intimations of an allegory about the tension between art and commerce, between the mystical love of racing for its own sake and the mercenary impulse to subordinate that love to the profit motive. But this parable would be more compelling if “Speed Racer” were not so transparently trying to have it both ways, to be at once profoundly visionary and punchily commercial, and failing on both counts.  On just about every possible count really. The moments of wisdom embedded in the dialogue (Racer X: “Racing will never change. What matters is whether we allow racing to change us”) are as fatuous as the kicky catchphrases (Trixie: “Cool beans!”). Speed’s mischievous little brother (Paulie Litt) and his pet chimp are annoying rather than endearing. The mysterious Racer X (Matthew Fox) looks tired and grumpy, and the teen-idol charisma of the South Korean pop star Rain (he plays another daredevil driver) is wasted. Mobsters, detectives, sportscasters and ruthless rival racers all parade across the screen, but none of them generate the sparks of humor, danger, energy or nobility that would ignite a sense of pop magic. “Speed Racer” goes nowhere, and you’d be amazed how long the trip can take.  “Speed Racer” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some mildly naughty language and stylized violence.</text>
      <date>May 9, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>