<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> When Sarah Daniels (Sarah Jessica Parker), the dean of students at Belmont, a small liberal arts college in Vermont, calls in Patrick Chibas (Victor Rasuk), one of her brightest students, to tell him the good news that he qualifies for a $12,000 scholarship, she is unprepared for his response. Asked to fill out a form in which he designates his ethnicity, he refuses to call himself Hispanic. He insists that he is Nuyorican, someone born in New York of Puerto Rican descent. Sarah cajoles him into writing “Hispanic” for practical reasons, but that’s not the end of it.  This argument about terminology is the opening skirmish of “Spinning Into Butter,” the screen adaptation of a play by Rebecca Gilman that was well received when it opened nine years ago in New York after originating at the Goodman Theater in Chicago.  The movie is a methodical, not to say mechanical  and plodding, exploration of identity politics and language as a treacherous  minefield of hostility and evasion. The further you tiptoe into this territory, the more difficult it is to retreat.  The movie takes its title from “The Story of Little Black Sambo,” Helen Bannerman’s 1899 children’s book about a boy  in India who, to avoid being eaten by tigers, gives them his flashy new clothes; the jealous tigers chase one another  around a tree until they are spun into melted butter. The book was popular until the word Sambo became identified as racially derogatory. Like those tigers, the characters in the movie  run around  in circles until they become a rhetorical  blur.  The screen adaptation, directed by Mark Brokaw from a script by Ms. Gilman and Doug Atchison, is a smart, squirm-inducing exploration of the hidden, potentially explosive subtexts in dialogues about race and ethnicity. The story focuses on Simon Brick (Paul James), an African-American and model student who begins receiving racist threats, including an anonymous note warning him to go back to Africa.  As the harassment escalates, a rock is thrown through his window, and the college turns itself inside out to  uncover the culprit. The local news  media, led by an African-American anchor, Aaron Carmichael (Mykelti Williamson), become involved. And a forum, intended to air grievances and calm everyone down, opens  a Pandora’s box of resentments.  Many scenes are devoted to the deepening friendship, with a romantic undertow,  between  Sarah and Aaron, two people who like and respect  each other  but are continually having to explain what they mean. Before moving to Vermont, Sarah taught at a mostly black college in Chicago, where her rowdier students forced her to confront her own racism.  Reviewing the play in 2000, Margo Jefferson of  The New York Times  described “Spinning Into Butter” as a “post-comic, post-tragic farce,” although it isn’t at all funny. It is farcical only in the sense that its characters, especially the all-white faculty and the college president, Winston Garvey (James Rebhorn), are mouthpieces of ludicrous boilerplate reeking of condescension and incomprehension. Even the term minority is scrutinized and found poisonous.  “Spinning Into Butter” is less a movie than an essay.   Ms. Parker’s earnest, workmanlike performance typifies skillful acting that gives the characters as much dimension as the language allows. If that language generates plenty of heat, the characters’ inner selves rarely peek out from under the heavy political baggage weighing them down.  “Spinning Into Butter” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for strong language.</text>
      <date>March 27, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>