<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> When Nikki (Ashton Kutcher), a lanky, arrogant Hollywood stud, confides his secrets of seduction to the camera early in “Spread,” you wonder if this might be the breakthrough movie in which a male hustler is not required to pay for his sins.  We’re in the 21st century, after all. And Nikki, and the women on whom he preys (he has no home or car) operate on a level playing field where the combatants are buffeted without suffering mortal wounds or moral disgrace. The rules of the game are roughly the same as those in “Entourage” and “Californication.” Casual opportunistic sex practiced by beautiful people of both sexes is an easy-come, easy-go transaction. Each month, Nikki estimates, 30,000 hot young things arrive in Hollywood prepared for battle.  Mr. Kutcher, who sprawls around half-naked through much of the movie, exudes a goofy, rakish charm, but “Spread,” directed by David Mackenzie (“Young Adam”) from a screenplay by Jason Dean Hall, doesn’t attach to him a coherent story. Near the beginning of the film, he hooks up with Samantha (Anne Heche) a skinny, high-powered lawyer with a Mercedes and a sleek home in the Hollywood Hills that she boasts was once occupied by Peter Bogdanovich. In their moderately steamy nude sex scenes all over the property, they do it in a variety of positions. Midway in their affair, she undergoes vaginal rejuvenation surgery.  When Samantha goes to New York on business, Nikki, temporary lord of the manor, gives a party in her absence attended by other vacant, hard-bodied sybarites. Even after she returns just in time to catch him being serviced by a girl in a football helmet as they watch a game on television, Samantha remains unflappably in control, and their arrangement continues for a while longer.  “Spread” begins to crumble when Nikki meets Heather (Margarita Levieva), a beautiful young waitress who plays the same games he does. But as a character, Heather, who lies about almost everything, doesn’t add up. If she is the plaything of a wealthy New Yorker (who as glimpsed late in the movie is just as handsome as Nikki), what is she doing waiting tables in a Los Angeles diner? And why does Nikki fall for her? Is he captivated by a reflection of himself? And what kind of love is that? And why, if he is such a confident grifter, does he have nothing to show for it?  The movie’s lurking Puritanism is evidenced by the difference between Nikki’s explicit scenes with Samantha and his encounters with Heather. When love (if that’s the right word) is involved, “Spread” becomes so blushingly modest, it can hardly bring itself to show the sweethearts kissing, much less locking limbs.  More skin is shown in “Spread” than in most Hollywood movies. But despite twitches of insight into its characters and their world, “Spread” refuses go more than skin deep.  “Spread” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, nudity and profanity.</text>
      <date>August 14, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>