<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One of the ruling assumptions of American popular culture - or at least of American independent movies - is that everyone's adolescence is uniquely miserable. Coming of age, with its attendant thrills and traumas (generally summarized under the headings school, sex and parents), is an inexhaustible subject because no two people go through it in exactly the same way. Once we're safely afloat in adulthood, though, we can begin to recognize the universality of our earlier experiences, and we can be grateful when, amid all the prurience and sentimentality that attend representations of adolescence, someone manages to get it right.  This is what Noah Baumbach has done in "The Squid and the Whale," his fourth feature as a director (after "Kicking and Screaming,"  "Highball" and "Mr. Jealousy") and a superior example of a familiar genre. Or as one of the film's characters might put it, the "filet" of Sundance-beloved troubled-teen cinema. Told largely from the point of view of Walt Berkman (Jesse Eisenberg), a 16-year-old enduring the breakup of his parents' marriage in mid-1980's Park Slope, Brooklyn, "The Squid and the Whale" is both sharply comical and piercingly sad. Mr. Baumbach surveys the members of the flawed, collapsing Berkman family with sympathy but without mercy, noting their individual and collective failures and imperfections with relentless precision.  "Mom and me versus you and Dad." Those words, spoken by Walt's younger brother, Frank (Owen Kline), on a tennis court, are the first we hear, and they set the stage for what is to follow. After they split, the boys' parents, Bernard and Joan, work out a complicated, obsessively equitable joint-custody arrangement (it even covers the cat), but they can hardly prevent the boys from choosing sides. Frank is more comfortable with Joan (Laura Linney), whose infidelities appear to have precipitated the separation, while Walt is his father's angry partisan, as well as his devoted acolyte.  Bernard (Jeff Daniels), a novelist and creative writing teacher whose career has faltered, is a fountain of pompous judgments - the kind of man who can refer to Franz Kafka as "one of my predecessors" and dismiss "A Tale of Two Cities" as "minor Dickens" - which his older son has a habit of parroting. The film's narrative, a swift-moving series of short, pointed vignettes, traces the decay of Walt's view of Bernard, from worship to protectiveness to disillusionment. At the same time, Walt's initial fury at Joan softens, and by the end you have the feeling that he will eventually be able to accept his parents for who they are, a difficult and necessary accomplishment of maturity.  Not that Mr. Baumbach, whose own Park Slope childhood lies a film-strip's breadth beneath the surface of this picture, wraps everything up neatly. Family life, under the best of circumstances, is messy, and for all their sophistication and good taste, the Berkmans are an unruly and contentious bunch. Joan's fledgling literary efforts turn out to be quite successful, and at times she and Bernard appear to be enacting a Brooklyn-bohemian remake of "A Star Is Born."  That they are both writers is hardly incidental. Intellectual pride and creative ambition are woven into the family's identity. Bernard worries that Frank, who is 12 and who admires his oafish tennis instructor, Ivan (Billy Baldwin), is not sufficiently serious, while Walt, desperate for acknowledgment as an artist, passes off Pink Floyd's "Hey You" as his own composition at a school talent show. He also mimics Bernard's hypercritical, contemptuous manner with his sweet-natured girlfriend, Sophie (Halley Feiffer), whom he may also be punishing for Joan's transgressions.  There is more, including Frank's horrifyingly funny sexual awakening, Walt and Bernard's infatuation with one of Bernard's students (Anna Paquin, who played Mr. Daniels's daughter in Carroll Ballard's "Fly Away Home"), and Joan's affair with Ivan. All of it is handled with a slightly breathless intelligence. Neither the camera nor the actors ever stop moving, as though Mr. Baumbach, in addition to depicting Walt's desperate impatience, were also drawing on it as a stylistic and emotional resource.  His writing respects the prickly individuality of the characters - in particular the adults, who fall into habits of speech that seem like self-conscious tics to everyone but them. (Joan calls her boys Chicken and Pickle; Bernard is overly fond of that filet metaphor.) Ms. Linney is, as ever, charming and a little elusive, which fits Joan's defensive reserve. Much as she adores her sons, Joan pulls away from them a bit to assert her independence from Bernard, whose needy narcissism has clearly worn out her patience. As well it might - and yet Mr. Daniels, while clearly delineating Bernard's self-deluding vanity, makes him neither a monster nor a clown. He is, almost in spite of himself, a man of feeling, not above appealing to the pity of those he loves when he can no longer impress or intimidate them.  "The Squid and the Whale" is hard on him, but it does not let anyone else, young or old, off the hook. Its portrayal of a particular slice of the New York middle class at a recent moment in history is precise, but such accuracy is not the point of the exercise. The film's tableau of domestic absurdity is likely to tickle,  and also to lacerate,  anyone who has either raised a child or been one. The last scenes strike a clean, discordant note of devastating optimism: you have a feeling that Walt will be just fine, which is to say that he will grow to be just as screwed up as his parents, but in his own unique way.  "The Squid and the Whale" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Adults must be protected from the uncomfortable insights it may offer their children - especially those between ages 13 and 16 - into the nature of parenthood.</text>
      <date>October 5, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>