<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  A blockbuster of a documentary, Errol Morris’s “Standard Operating Procedure” is an inquiry into the prisoner abuse scandal at Abu Ghraib. It is, predictably, a bleak, depressing movie, but if you stick around through the end credits, you may also be in for a few surprises. In addition to the usual complement of helpers — a research coordinator, a consultant on  Iraq — the credits mention a costume designer, a wardrobe stylist, six hair and makeup people, an action consultant, an armorer, 5 set dressers, 7  animal handlers, 10 prop makers, 33 cast members and Danny Elfman, the longtime composer for Tim Burton.  It’s an estimable roll call, all the more so when you compare it with the average documentary or even a modest fiction film. The very scale of “Standard Operating Procedure” — evident in its costly-looking production values, special effects and elaborately choreographed re-enactments — suggests that Mr. Morris has grown weary of working in the margins to which documentary filmmakers are still too often relegated. “Standard Operating Procedure” is a big, provocative and — it goes without saying — disturbing work, though what makes it most provocative is that its greatest ambitions are for its own visual style.  In broad strokes the documentary addresses issues surrounding state-sanctioned torture, the abnegation of government responsibility and what happens when certain young male and female soldiers are left to their own ill-informed devices. In a director’s statement Mr. Morris explains that one force driving the project was the mass of photographs taken by American soldiers at Abu Ghraib that document, often in horrifyingly explicit detail, the prisoner abuse that they helped perpetuate. He and his team “set out to examine the context of these photographs” in an attempt to uncover what had happened outside the frame. For him the photographs function as both an exposé and a cover-up because while they revealed the horror, they also “convinced journalists and readers they had seen everything.”  It is all too easy to imagine that there are journalists and readers who are convinced they have seen everything there is to see — or to know — about Abu Ghraib. But to judge from the book on Abu Ghraib he published after he helped break the story in The New Yorker in May 2004, the inexhaustible Seymour M. Hersh  doesn’t appear convinced. And there are other journalists who continue to cover the story, and readers who seek out more information about it, including through documentaries like “Standard Operating Procedure.” Mr. Morris certainly wasn’t convinced that he had seen everything; he made this movie, which, at its finest and most focused, seeks to examine how seeing does — and does not — become knowing.  To that end, Mr. Morris employs two familiar documentary strategies: direct-address interviews and re-enactments in which actors restage actual historical events. Although re-enactments tend to raise alarms, particularly by viewers who confuse documentaries with journalism, interviews are often more problematic precisely because they look so straightforward, even transparent. Mr. Morris, who paid some of the interviewees who appear in “Standard Operating Procedure” — an unusual if not unprecedented documentary occurrence — frames his subjects in head-and-shoulder close-ups, which more or less mimics the closeness of one-to-one, person-to-person conversation. This sense of intimacy is further enhanced by a device that Mr. Morris developed called the Interrotron, which allows interviewees to look at his video image while they are being filmed instead of at the camera, much as newscasters look at teleprompters.  As a strategy, talking-head interviews appear to allow documentary subjects to speak for themselves, to raise their own voices, as it were. But when the filmmaker remains unseen and unheard, these interviews also tend to obscure that someone is always shaping the conversation, moving it in certain directions. Mr. Morris shouts out a few questions during the interviews but otherwise remains off camera, his presence evident only in his stylistic signatures, his tight framing and his aggressive editing. (Distractingly, he tends to cut into even the shorter interviews, and because he often slightly changes the angle of the shots with each edit, the talking heads appear to shift from one side of the screen to the other.)  Some of those heads, including that of Janis Karpinski, the Army Reserve brigadier general in charge of military prisons in Iraq before the scandal broke, will look familiar, not least because they appear in Rory Kennedy’s informative 2007 documentary, “Ghosts of Abu Ghraib.” A fascinating screen presence whose spooky light eyes never seem to blink, Ms. Karpinski, who was demoted to colonel, is the highest-ranking officer to have been punished for her participation. And because she is also the highest-ranking officer in “Standard Operating Procedure,” she sounds particularly impressive, dropping two-star names and insider dope with authority. She makes a good witness, though it becomes clear that, much like everyone else who appears here, she is mostly testifying on her own behalf.  That’s fine as far as it goes, but the problem is that none of it — not the interviews, not the lurid re-enactments — really goes anywhere. There is some mild fascination (or satisfaction), perhaps, in seeing how badly Lynndie England — the grinning pixie who was photographed with a leashed, naked prisoner — has aged. Yet like all the other low-ranking soldiers caught up in this nightmare, Ms. England says next to nothing of interest, not only because she appears to have been a cog in a much larger military machine, but also because Mr. Morris’s approach here is profoundly nondialectic. He lets her talk and talk but doesn’t challenge or engage her beyond a question about her age. The night of one photo shoot, she turned 21.  That’s a heart-sickening detail, and it points to a central issue that Mr. Morris takes up though doesn’t explore in real depth, namely that a group of young soldiers committed crimes at the behest of their superiors. Mr. Hersh, among others, has voiced his opinions on who deserves blame, but beyond a throwaway image of President Bush, Mr. Morris himself remains basically silent on this crucial point. Instead he lets the soldiers state their case, tosses in some nifty special effects (the photos zip about nicely) and, with extraordinary meticulousness and to no real analytic purpose, restages some of the worst images, a rhetorical gesture that registers as an unfortunate attempt to trump the originals.  Mr. Morris has used re-enactments in the past, including in his 1988 breakthrough, “The Thin Blue Line.” But nothing he has done previously approaches the level of fetishistic detail he achieves here, whether he’s showing us beautifully backlighted dust motes dancing in the prison air or an exquisitely photographed pearl of blood dangling from a brutalized prisoner’s, or rather actor’s, nose. The close-ups of the snarling, barking guard dogs summon memories of Stephen King’s “Cujo,” which makes sense, given that Mr. Morris’s epistemological quest has led him to reimagine Abu Ghraib in the vernacular of a cheap Hollywood horror flick. If nothing else, the dogs and their trainers serve as a reminder that Mr. Morris is, in his own singular fashion, very much in the entertainment business.  “Standard Operating Procedure” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Explicit images of real torture and graphic re-enactments of the same.</text>
      <date>April 25, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>