<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>tate Property 2" is the latest proof of the axiom that movies about organized crime are really about business. So while this brutal, chaotic chronicle of heavily armed drug dealers shooting it out in the streets of Philadelphia is likely to be cited as another example of hip-hop culture's irresponsible glorification of violence, or alternatively as an example of ghetto-outlaw authenticity, it is better appreciated (or disdained) as a raw, bracing expression of the spirit of capitalism. The title may refer explicitly to the prison system - it's how the incarcerated hero bitterly thinks of himself - but it also has a socialistic ring, an evident irony in a movie devoted above all to the celebration of free enterprise. The first "State Property" picture, released in 2002, was a thuggish variation on the classic American rags-to-riches tale, tracing the dazzling rise and partial fall of a Philadelphia drug dealer named Beans (Beanie Sigel). A glowering, truculent presence, built like a squat S.U.V., Mr. Sigel bulled through that movie with more energy than skill, as if bent on dispelling the notion that rappers automatically make good screen actors. It is not saying much to point out that the sequel is better than its predecessor (directed by Abdul Malik Abbott), which was crude and amateurish in every way. This time, Damon Dash, repeating his roles as producer and as Beans's scene-stealing rival, Dame, has also taken up the duties of director. He shows competence, and even occasional flair, cobbling together a fast-moving, voice-over-heavy tribute to "Scarface," "Goodfellas" and other touchstones of the gangster canon, with room for several cameos, including ones by Mariah Carey and Ol' Dirty Bastard, who died in November. Mr. Dash also pays ample tribute to his entrepreneurial acumen. Dame, who speaks in a manic whisper, is ruthless and sensitive, and while he enjoys the usual perquisites of criminal mogulhood, he is preoccupied with the expansion and maintenance of his global business empire. The character may be Mr. Dash's sly sendup of his own imperial drive because nearly every frame of "State Property 2" shows off the products of his commercial empire. Not only do the characters wear State Property jackets, T-shirts and caps, but they seem to drink only Armadale vodka, Mr. Dash's premium brand, and wear clothes from his Rocawear line. They approach their own business, though, in a rougher, less lighthearted way, through a plot sufficiently convoluted to require a spreadsheet (or at least a half-dozen narrators). Beans, languishing in the penitentiary, is befriended by his cellmate, a devout Muslim named Freeway (Freeway), and by a voluble Floridian known as El Pollo Loco (Victor N.O.R.E. Santiago). The three concoct a complicated scheme to shore up Beans's declining share of the Philadelphia cocaine market and also settle some scores with Dame, the mention of whose name provokes fantasies of homicide. Their apparently simple plan turns out to involve enough double- and triple-crossing to nudge the plot toward its final shootout, during which everything becomes more or less clear, including the setup for "State Property 3." "State Property 2" is rated R. It has violence, profanity, sexual situations and drug use.</text>
      <date>April 13, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>