<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>"A State of Mind" offers a rare and often chilling glimpse into the culture of North Korea, the world's least visited country, which Nicholas D. Kristof recently described on the op-ed page of The New York Times as "the most bizarre . . . most regimented, militarized and oppressive country in the world." Directed by Daniel Gordon, a British sports journalist whose first film, "The Game of Their Lives," documented the performance of the North Korean soccer team in the 1966 World Cup competition, "A State of Mind" follows two North Korean schoolgirls, 13-year-old Pak Hyon Sun and 11-year-old Kim Song Yun, as they train for a gymnastics performance in the 2003 Mass Games. "A State of Mind" offers a rare and often chilling glimpse into the culture of North Korea, the world's least visited country, which Nicholas D. Kristof recently described on the op-ed page of The New York Times as "the most bizarre . . . most regimented, militarized and oppressive country in the world." Directed by Daniel Gordon, a British sports journalist whose first film, "The Game of Their Lives," documented the performance of the North Korean soccer team in the 1966 World Cup competition, "A State of Mind" follows two North Korean schoolgirls, 13-year-old Pak Hyon Sun and 11-year-old Kim Song Yun, as they train for a gymnastics performance in the 2003 Mass Games. This staggering spectacle, a mass celebration of nationalism, athleticism and ideological unity, brings together more than 100,000 performers in Kim Il Sung Stadium in Pyongyang, where huge teams of brightly costumed acrobats tumble and leap in precise unison as children bearing colored flashcards create ever-shifting backdrop images of battles, slogans and the omnipresent faces of Kim Il Sung, the "Great Leader" who died in 1994, and his son Kim Jong Il, the current leader. The Mass Games are the result of millions of hours of preparation and training, some of which are witnessed here as the two girls report for rehearsals that, as the games draw near, can last up to 10 hours a day. On nationally mandated holidays (which include the birthdays of Kim Il Sung and Kim Jong Il), the girls take a break to promenade with their families in remarkably joyless public spaces. Yet the pleasure they take in simple things - a picnic by the river, a romp with the family dog - seems genuine. The families Mr. Gordon films are unusually privileged by North Korean standards. Though their apartments are cramped and barren, they have secure jobs, enough food and even luxuries like television and radio (although, as the voiceover points out, the state-supplied radio in every North Korean house is permanently tuned to the country's single government-run station and can be turned down but never off.) In interviews, the girls' parents openly discuss some of the hardships of life in North Korea, including the famine of the mid-1990's, referred to as the Arduous March. But the film's tone remains carefully neutral. Whatever political critique the film may contain is left implicit in the jaw-dropping final sequence, in which the girls, along with hundreds of thousands of their compatriots, finally perform their long-rehearsed dance at the Mass Games before an audience of bored-looking military bureaucrats, one of whom is seen consulting his watch during the show. As for the Dear Leader himself, a final subtitle informs us that state duties kept him from being able to attend the games at all.</text>
      <date>August 10, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>