<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> I will admit that I choked up a little at the end of “State of Play.” Not because the story was especially moving — or even, ultimately, all that interesting — but because the iconography of the closing credits tugged at my ink-stained heartstrings. The images are stirring and familiar, though in a few years’ time they may look as quaint as engravings of stagecoaches and steam engines. A breaking, earthshaking story makes its way from computer screen to newsprint. The plates are set, the presses whir, sheaves of freshly printed broadsheet are collated, stacked on pallets and sent out to meet the eyes of the hungry public. Truth has been told, corruption revealed and new oxygen pumped into the civic bloodstream. All that’s missing is a paperboy yelling “extra!” to crowds of commuters in raincoats and fedoras.  Those of us who work in the newspaper business are highly susceptible to the kind of sentimental view of our trade this movie offers, especially when the sentiment masquerades as tough-minded cynicism, which makes us go all dewy and reach for the bottle of rye we keep stashed in the bottom drawer of our battered metal desk. And anyone, in whatever field, who cherishes memories of “All the President’s Men” or “His Girl Friday” will smile when “State of Play,” directed by Kevin Macdonald (“The Last King of Scotland”), now and again hits the sweet spot of the genre.  On the other hand, those who recall the British television mini-series on which this is based, with its unsparing dissection of compromised and arrogant news media, are likely to be a bit dismayed. The narrative has been updated and condensed by a trio of talented screenwriters (Tony Gilroy, Matthew Michael Carnahan and Billy Ray), but what has been lost is less length or context than depth. This “State of Play” is both shallower and muddier than its clear-eyed source.  Russell Crowe, as Cal McAffrey, a scruffy, dogged metro reporter for The Washington Globe, engages in fine snappy banter with Rachel McAdams, whose character has the ultramodern job of political gossip blogger and the ripely old-fashioned name of Della Frye. The two of them are not remotely Cary Grant and Rosalind Russell — nor yet Robert Redford and Dustin Hoffman — but there is some fun to be had in watching them lock horns and ultimately join forces in pursuit of the big story.  The near-total absence of sexual tension between them is perhaps a concession to the mores of the modern workplace, but it also allows Cal to be ensnared in a dubious subplot involving Anne Collins (Robin Wright Penn), an old flame who happens to be married to a powerful young congressman who happens to be Cal’s college roommate and best pal. We will get to him in due course — his alleged doings and potential undoing are the motor that drives the movie’s frantic plot, and he is played by Ben Affleck — but let’s linger for another moment in the newsroom, while it lasts.  The battered old Globe has just been taken over by a media conglomerate (a development that only adds to the atmosphere of nostalgia), and the flinty editor (Helen Mirren) harangues her troops to bring in the hot copy that will sell some papers. A series of apparently unconnected events — a double murder in a dark alley; the apparently accidental death of a young congressional staffer; important hearings up on Capitol Hill — bring together Cal and Della, who present an amusing clash of journalistic sensibilities and generational styles.  Cal drives a filthy Saab, works at a desk strewn with papers and books, lives in a cluttered rat hole and takes notes with a pen. Initially he has nothing but contempt for Della, whose insouciant, opinionated approach seems to him to violate every tenet of his noble, ragged craft. She doesn’t even seem to own a pen! Della, naturally, regards Cal as a slow-moving, antediluvian creature marked for extinction. Each has so much to learn from the other. What Della learns, charmingly if none too plausibly, is that some stories lie too deep for blogs and can only truly live on the smudgy, crumply page.  The chance to explore the swiftly changing culture of Web-age journalism is one of several intriguing possibilities that “State of Play” squanders as it makes its jumpy, lumpy way toward a disastrous final plot twist. Della and Cal spar over journalistic ethics and habits, but their arguments carry no real dramatic force. And as their investigation proceeds, the movie uncovers some tantalizing themes that are either trampled or kicked aside. What promises to be a smart, sharp inquiry into the complicated intersection of private vice and political corruption — a vivid essay on the nature of power and the ambiguous pursuit of truth — turns into a superficially clever, self-important and finally incoherent thriller.  Congressman Stephen Collins (Mr. Affleck, wielding a Philadelphia accent as thick and inauthentic as low-fat cream cheese) is digging into the sinister dealings of a mysterious security contractor. When his lead researcher is run over by a train, all kinds of questions begin to pop up on cable television and the blogosphere. Was she sleeping with the congressman? Was her death really an accident? Cal tries to juggle professional duty and the obligations of friendship, and the screenwriters try to manage a blizzard of semitopical allusions while Mr. Crowe and Mr. Affleck allow themselves to be upstaged by top-notch supporting players like Jeff Daniels (as a partisan poobah) and Jason Bateman (as a sleazy D.C. fixer).  Mr. Bateman arrives too late to save “State of Play” from the train wreck of its third act but just in time to interrupt the speechifying with some louche and tasty line readings. And the best parts of the movie are details and atmospherics, which add up to a sense that in small ways, filmmakers come close to getting the story right even if the story itself turns out to be nonsensical.  “State of Play” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some violence, sexual references and swearing — just like a real-life newsroom.</text>
      <date>April 17, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>