<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The sight of Jessica Biel wiggling her shapely rear through the North Korean backcountry in the action flick "Stealth" isn't the most ludicrous image of our current movie season, but it comes close. As it happens, the most preposterous moment in this preposterous crypto-video game occurs after Ms. Biel's character, a United States naval pilot, parachutes from her stealth aircraft through a hailstorm of fiery debris, races across North Korea while chased by thugs with guns, and rushes into the arms of the man who risks worldwide nuclear holocaust to rescue her. Thanks, dude!  A hash of "Top Gun" and "Behind Enemy Lines," among myriad other influences, and topped with a soupçon of "2001," this story of three comrades up against a villainous miscellany has the makings of a kitsch classic. Any film that places romance above Armageddon and forces a fine actor like Josh Lucas to parade around in a swimsuit like a model for International Male would certainly seem to have the appropriate wrong stuff. Too bad that the screenwriter W. D. Richter and the director Rob Cohen, who has almost extinguished all the good will he built up from "The Fast and the Furious," don't seem in on the joke. Nor do members of  the cast, which includes Jamie Foxx and Sam Shepard, crack many smiles, despite the inherent hilarity of the material.  Set in the very near future during, as an opening scroll explains, the "mounting threat of terrorism," the story hinges on three stealth pilots - Ms. Biel's Kara, Mr. Lucas's Ben and Mr. Foxx's improbably named Henry Purcell - who zip around the globe putting out fires, fanning flames and swapping chummy barbs with Mr. Shepard's commanding officer. The pilots get along splendidly, but bashful Kara and flirty Ben look as if they would like to do more than pal around. Hence Mr. Lucas and Ms. Biel's swimsuit duet during a pointless sojourn in Thailand, an exotic backdrop for the usual military R&amp;R (beautiful locals with negligible English skills, etc.) and the only foreign country that these happy three visit and don't shoot up.  One of the pleasures of entertainments like the Bond films is that they work as a sort of travelogue, taking us places we've never been  (or at least to convincing facsimiles) and opening us to the world. Not so "Stealth," which, other than that Thailand layover, inspires no such wanderlust. The reason isn't that the film was mostly shot in Australia, which almost always looks inviting; rather, it's that almost every locale gets blown to bits almost as soon as the pilots come within shooting distance. Among the less fortunate territories: Myanmar, Tajikistan, North Korea and a corner of Alaska, all of which come under intense fire.  It's no wonder that in "Stealth" the planet usually looks better from 35,000 feet above ground, a vantage point that makes everything - including people, who alternately look like ants and characters in a video game - seem awfully distant and terribly unreal.  What's interesting about "Stealth" isn't its nitwit story, which largely involves a next-generation aircraft operated by a computer with a voice meant to evoke HAL 9000 that sounds more like an interminably snotty hotel clerk right before a phone bounces off his head. No, what's interesting about this movie - and many others of its kind - is that it continues the love affair Hollywood, that hotbed of liberalism, has long had with militarism. As is almost always the case in these movies, the fall guy here turns out to be a rogue bad apple who, though abetted by black-bag types and a shadowy politician, is lodged in an otherwise unsullied bushel of warriors. Like Kara, these boys fret about collateral damage, but are more obsessed with big bangs than little people.    "Stealth" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has a lot of explosions, a number of bloodless deaths and some adult language.</text>
      <date>July 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>