<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A spry teenage comedy that gets everything right, "Stick It" takes the usual batch of underdogs, dirt bags, mean girls and bimbos and sends them somersaulting through happy clichés and unexpected invention. As is to be hoped from a chick flick set in the world of elite gymnastics, the sass crackles, the soundtrack pops (to hip-hop, punk and Perry Como) and there are plentiful scenes, cleverly shot, of teenagers in leotards triple flipping with aplomb.  Jeff Bridges — bonus!  —  brings a center of gravity to these whirl-a-gig diversions as the affable Burt Vickerman, gymnastics guru semi-extraordinaire. Into his no-nonsense arms tumbles the resourceful and radiant Haley Graham (Missy Peregrym), an ex-champion turned slacker with a chip on her shoulder and a skeleton in her closet.  "Stick It" is the not-quite-predictable story of Haley's return to competition and how she liberates her past, learns its lessons and is joined by her teammates in leveraging this knowledge against the Man (here represented by uptight parents and judges with grudges).  It is a triumph for the writer and director Jessica Bendinger, who brings a sly eye and avid imagination to every scene, springing fresh rhythms and bold colors out of the formulaic material.  Not to be a killjoy, but the best stuff here isn't the cartwheels scored to Talib Kweli, excellent as they are, nor the bitchy banter about how totally "leotarded"  an outfit is. Culminating in a defiant act of subversion and solidarity, "Stick It" knows that some games are won by refusing to play. Forget girl-power bromides; here's a movie that lets young women reclaim their bodies (skilled, scrutinized, criticized and exploited) in order to embody genuine populism.  It's a lot of fun to see a genre movie leap over expectations; it's downright dizzying to watch it bounce on an ethos of spandex-clad resistance.  "Stick It" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Brash teenage girls speak their rude native tongue.</text>
      <date>April 28, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>