<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Stranger Than Fiction” gives Will Ferrell the kind of opportunity that movie and television clowns seem to cherish, which is to impress audiences with their restraint. Robin Williams does it every now and then, as does Jim Carrey — Bill Murray does nothing else these days — and now Mr. Ferrell, among the most uninhibited and dementedly spontaneous comic actors around, straightens his spine, buttons his lip and stares straight ahead. Perhaps without quite knowing it, the audience waits for a wink, a hint that some of the madcap spirit that animated pictures like “Talladega Nights,” “Old School,” “Anchorman” and “Elf” might be lurking inside the sober suit and diffident manner.  It is to Mr. Ferrell’s credit, and the movie’s, that he manages to be interesting without mugging or riffing, but rather by playing a highly controlled man in an impressively controlled manner. Harold Crick, who lives alone in a spartan apartment in an unspecified city (Chicago, it looks like), is an I.R.S. auditor who obeys an  unvarying routine. At least, that is, until the musings of the film’s voice-over narrator become audible not just to the audience but to Harold as well. Irked by the dry, British, female voice in his head, he is driven to seek out its source. He eventually discovers that he is a character in a novel being written by Karen Eiffel (an antic Emma Thompson), who is chain-smoking her way through an epic case of writer’s block, helped by a no-nonsense emissary from her publisher played by Queen Latifah.  The audience is aware of Harold’s situation long before he is, an example of dramatic irony, as we learn from Jules Hilbert (Dustin Hoffman), the English professor Harold turns to for help. I confess that I cannot be too hard on a movie that insists on the usefulness of literary theory, even though I was puzzled to see a book of “healthy dessert” recipes on Professor Hilbert’s office shelves. (Especially since the man seems to live on reheated, recycled coffee.)  But the professor, whom Mr. Hoffman impersonates with sly, absent-minded mischief, also functions as the movie’s internal critic. He takes its charmingly absurd premise seriously and thus enables the screenwriter, Zach Helm, and the director, Marc Forster (“Finding Neverland,” “Monster’s Ball”), to finesse some logical fuzziness. It’s never quite clear, for instance, what the parameters of Karen and Harold’s author-character relationship are. Did she call him into being ex nihilo? Does he have memories of things that happened before the novel (called “Death and Taxes”) commenced? Is he free, as long as she is blocked, to do things she does not intend or know about, or is she, in her role as narrator, strictly omniscient?  These questions preoccupy Harold less than another, basic issue, namely whether “Death and Taxes” is a comedy or a tragedy. This is a life-or-death matter for him, since he has overheard Karen foreshadow his imminent demise. The professor’s assessment is stark: citing the Italian novelist Italo Calvino, he notes that any story must fall into one of the two categories, affirming either the inevitability of death or the continuity (traditionally through the prospect of a marriage) of life.  This may be true in literature, but Hollywood has become expert at scrambling the generic codes, producing dramedies, comedic dramas and other such hybrids. And while “Stranger Than Fiction” traffics in a bit of darkly funny existential anxiety, it also finds room for romantic fantasy and sentimental uplift. Harold’s identity crisis converges with the flowering of a crush on Ana Pascal (Maggie Gyllenhaal), a baker who refuses to pay some of her taxes out of political  principle. Harold approaches her at first with agonized timidity and then with a bit more boldness, showing up at her bakery with an assortment of flours.  That’s a nice, whimsical touch, as is the guitar serenade that leads to a fumbling, ardent first kiss. There are also a few moments of pleasantly jarring absurdity that deepen the film’s evident debt to Charlie  Kaufman, author of “Adaptation” and “Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind.” But there is also something soft and unfinished about the movie; it wanders about in its own conceit, collecting stray moments of intelligence or feeling without adding up to very much. The ending is a nicely executed bit of metaphysical farce, in which all the strands of Harold’s fate converge, but the final notes are more than a little false. Rather than jarring or deepening your perceptions of the world, “Stranger Than Fiction” settles into a cozy, comforting realm that really isn’t very strange at all.  But that just may be what a critic is supposed to think; it’s what Jules Hilbert might say if he were writing this review from inside my head. And for all I know, he is.  “Stranger Than Fiction” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some disturbing images, sexual situations and strong language.</text>
      <date>November 10, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>