<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> James Ellroy, the self-described “demon dog” of American crime fiction, writes in a baroque, pulp prose style that hurtles along the page like a speed freak in a rocket, an image that I probably lifted from one of his books. In his fiction and nonfiction he rushes  forward fast, fast, fast, pausing regularly to do a little scat singing (“a hypodermic full of hyper-hazy, health-hazarding” stuff, from a 1998 short story called “Hush-Hush”), or to blow a hole through the page. He’s a demon dog, all right, with a bite as sharp as his bark.  Other than  Curtis Hanson’s 1997 elegant page-to-screen translation of Mr. Ellroy’s novel “L.A. Confidential,” the movies have generally failed to capture the true tone and texture of his dark places. Certainly that’s the case with David Ayer’s absurd if accidentally entertaining potboiler, “Street Kings,”  based on a story by Mr. Ellroy, who also shares screenwriting credit with Kurt Wimmer and Jamie Moss. The premise — the existence of an ultraviolent gang of cops operating inside the Los Angeles Police Department and wholly outside the law — has a vintage Ellroy tang, though it also pointedly summons up a host of that city’s  authentic police corruption scandals, from the 1930s through the 1990s.  Keanu Reeves plays Detective Tom Ludlow, a prime cut of  beef who’s part of a cultish, multicultural wrecking crew run by the silkily smooth Capt. Jack Wander (Forest Whitaker). A loner by violent disposition and tragic (dead wife) history, Tom bursts into the film, breaking any number of laws, and immediately enters a hell on earth (that would be Los Angeles) with bullets, blood, shattered bone and underage sex slaves. Good times! More seriously, and this is nothing  if not a deeply serious movie (I think), there are nothing  but bad times ahead, with even more blood — smeared, splattered, splashed and sprayed — mixed in with  vivid night photography, thumping tunes, boyz in the hood, ornamental women, casual racist insults and a lot of manly shouting.  Mr.  Ayer, who wrote “Training Day” and directed  “Harsh Times,” invests his work with palpable energy — his films feel urgent and at times, interestingly, close to desperate — but he has  next to no idea how to control or channel all that manic intensity. Much as he does in “Harsh Times,” he starts this new film in overdrive and keeps it there all the way to the exhausted, exhausting end, piling violent moment upon violent moment. And much like “Training Day” (in which Denzel Washington plays a swaggeringly corrupt cop) and “Harsh Times” (Christian Bale doing the wigged-out war veteran thing), this film pivots on a man who, having been schooled in violence and rewarded for lessons too well learned, has become captive to his own brutality.  Trained as a pit bull, stripped of fear and almost without any pity (especially for himself), Tom has no sense that he’s fighting for someone else’s gain. Mr. Reeves, his face and body somewhat thickened, perhaps by age or the role or both, looks like a middleweight boxer who’s reached the end of a very hard and long road. (Robert Ryan  had a lock on this type in  the 1940s and ’50s.)  Mr.  Reeves’s  natural sobriety works well for the part, as does his ability to play it stiff and straight and  a touch stupid. Tom’s slow-dawning awareness of the world he inhabits and his awful place in it is terribly obvious, as is his  metamorphosis, but neither is it devoid of pathos.  It’s easy to laugh at “Street Kings” for its bigger than big emotions, its preposterously kinky narrative turns and overwrought jawing and yowling, but there’s no doubt that it also keeps you watching, really watching, all the way to the end. The film can be unintentionally, often grotesquely, funny, nowhere more so than during the grandiose finale when Mr. Whitaker — never what you might call a quiet actor to begin with — cuts crazy loose and starts popping his eyes and sputtering the spit. What Mr. Ayer doesn’t appear to have realized — a mistake shared by Brian De Palma in his unfortunate adaptation of Mr. Ellroy’s crime novel “The Black Dahlia” — is that you don’t need to gild a 24-karat lily. It’s plenty shiny already.  “Street Kings” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Blood and bullets.</text>
      <date>April 11, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>