<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There are no supernatural happenings, just people under extreme stress succumbing to their worst instincts, in Stuart Gordon’s grim, expert little thriller “Stuck.” Mr. Gordon has enjoyed a cult following since his 1985 horror hit, “Re-Animator.” And “Stuck,” while not strictly a horror film, is steeped in gore and carries a seam of mocking gallows humor as relentless as that of “Sweeney Todd.”  Set in the same seedy urban environment as Mr. Gordon’s   faithful 2005 screen adaptation of David Mamet’s play “Edmond,” this largely two-character nightmare unfolds in the hellish tenderloin of Providence, R.I., and its outskirts. Tom Bardo (Stephen Rea), like the title character of “Edmond,” is a white-collar victim of downsizing, brutally evicted from his shabby apartment, who finds himself alone in the middle of the night on a park bench. While pushing a shopping cart donated by a friendly homeless man on the way to a shelter, he is struck by a car. Tossed onto the hood, Tom crashes through the windshield, where he remains stuck and near death.  The driver, Brandi (Mena Suvari), a hard-working  nursing home employee,  is high on booze and pills after a hellish day at work and a night of clubbing. Seeing her future in jeopardy, Brandi panics, drives home and locks the car in her garage, leaving the barely conscious Tom still lodged in the windshield while she decides what to do.  Based on a notorious incident in Texas in 2001, “Stuck” is exceptional because its characters feel like real people plunged into a disorienting situation in which they behave like monsters. Brandi, who can’t bear to face what she has done, goes berserk and blames Tom for her troubles. Her smooth-talking boyfriend, Rashid (Russell Hornsby), to whom she turns for help, is a two-timing drug dealer and thug.  John Strysik’s screenplay, based on a story by Mr. Gordon, goes out of its way to portray ordinary people at the mercy of sadistic bureaucrats who secretly relish the power they wield. A scene in an employment agency where Tom is told, after waiting for hours, that there is no record of him in the computer is enough to make you scream in frustration. Carolyn Purdy-Gordon, playing a snippy supervisor in the nursing home, is a scary contemporary Big Nurse.  Mr. Rea, a wonderful actor, spends the better part of the movie howling and moaning as Tom tries to force himself through the windshield into the front seat and escape. For Ms. Suvari, who since playing a high school vixen in “American Beauty”  has found her niche as a millennial Linda Blair with good taste in sordid material, “Stuck” is the latest small, nasty triumph.  “Stuck” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has violence, gore, nudity and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>May 30, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>