<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> This is the end, Danny Boyle sings  in his spooky and spookily beautiful science-fiction thriller, “Sunshine.” Mr. Boyle, the sly-boots British director of movies as seemingly different as “Trainspotting” and “Millions,” has a knack for turning dire setups and very bad things into visually arresting, tingly experiences, whether his characters are doing one another in by hook or by crook or through some robust chomping, as in his exemplary zombie flick, “28 Days Later.” The end may be nigh in “Sunshine” — the Sun is dying, as is, alas, poor Earth  — but Mr. Boyle is having a grand old time.  Old is an operative word here. Like a lot of science fiction, “Sunshine” owes as much of a debt to the past as to the speculative future, including some of the usual suspects, notably Stanley Kubrick’s classic head-scratcher, “2001: A Space Odyssey,” with flashy bits and pieces borrowed from “Alien” and “Blade Runner,” Ridley Scott’s back-to-back masterworks. Like the globe-trotters in Olaf Stapledon’s 1930 science-fiction novel, “Last and First Men,” who jump planets to keep the race going, humankind in “Sunshine” has been forced to extremes to survive the Sun’s collapse. The latest extreme is a manned spaceship with a nuclear payload that, when dropped on the dying star, will trigger a big bang to thaw our global freezing.  That’s the bright idea, or at least the most vivid one, in “Sunshine,” which also flirts with questions about scientific progress, ethics and the limits of rationality. For the young, overly pretty crew of white and Asian astronauts, the mission initially entails watching monitors, twiddling dials and counting miles. There are hints of discord, as when a fight breaks out between two crewmen, the pacific Capa (Cillian Murphy) and the macho Mace  (Chris Evans), a tussle wearily described by one of the ship’s two women, Cassie (Rose Byrne), as “an excess of manliness.” More alarmingly, the resident shrink, Searle (Cliff Curtis), has developed a fondness for staring into the Sun, bathing in its increasingly dangerous light.  As the hubristically named ship, Icarus II, races toward its fiery destination, the crew picks up an eerie distress beacon beeping from someplace out in the great black beyond. In the face of this unsettling unknown, the captain, Kaneda (Hiroyuki Sanada), keeps his cool, while the streamlined crew — including Michelle Yeoh as Corazon, Benedict Wong as Trey and Troy Garity as Harvey  — more or less keeps it together. But, like the Icarus of myth, these all-too-human voyagers who make like gods also risk punishment. Alarms sound, nerves shred, light flares, hope dims, and at one point and without much surprise, life ebbs, pooling picturesquely over the immaculate production design.  A first-rate, seemingly sweat-free entertainer, Mr. Boyle always sells the goods smoothly, along with the chills, the laughs and, somewhat less often, the tears. He’s wickedly good at making you jump and squirm in your seat, which he does often in “Sunshine,” but he tends to avoid tapping into deep wells of emotion. With the exception of “Millions,” about a motherless boy, Mr. Boyle’s movies are more likely to make you whimper than choke up or feel deeply. That’s to be expected because keeping the audience amused and distracted comes a little too easily to him. Like Steven Soderbergh, another cool, crafty dissembler, Mr. Boyle is awfully clever, which can be a great strength as well as a weakness.  In “Sunshine,” that cleverness is most evident in the fluid orchestration of the brisk editing, the prowling camerawork and unnerving sound design. As the ship moves closer to the Sun, and people and things begin to  fall apart, Mr. Doyle and his screenwriter, Alex Garland, goose their science fiction with action- and horror-genre beats, increasingly turning up the chills and thrills.  Less effectively, they also introduce a disappointing philosophical bogeyman. This creature enters late in the game with some blather that recalls, though with less poetry, some words of the replicant played by Rutger Hauer in “Blade Runner,” who offers the agonizing admission, “I’ve done questionable things.” (Kind of says it all, doesn’t it?) Mostly, though, the bogeyman just goes, “Boo!”  If “Sunshine” plays out more like a viscerally pleasurable diversion than an intellectually stimulating head trip, it’s largely because Mr. Boyle tends to lean on familiar genre stratagems and his estimable technique rather than risk anything by going too far out and freaky. Always an expressive colorist, he floods the screen with gold, splashes on the green and dots the image with jolting blue. He has enormous fun turning the lights up and down (your pupils will get a workout) and makes the most of the film’s major visual trope, a human eye. Again and again, he shows us human eyes blinking in close-up and the enormous round, golden shield that protects the ship from the Sun’s violence with its dead-eye gaze.  We look at all this looking, but what do we see? Beauty, for starters — the fast-approaching Sun looks like a hot, burbling and bloody stew — and death, of course. The crew members engage in a few deep-dish discussions, as in, Would you slit one man’s throat to save all of humanity? But this chatter is simply a way of moving the story forward and doesn’t open up larger questions of morality and scientific discovery, the domination of nature and the survival of the species. That may be because what’s most interesting about “Sunshine” isn’t whether the crew members survive but that they’re willing to blow themselves up for their beliefs.  “I think it will be beautiful,” says one, contemplating annihilation, which doesn’t make this the first movie about suicide bombers, only one of the more curious.  “Sunshine” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for bloody violence, adult language and intimations of the apocalypse.</text>
      <date>July 20, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>