<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Horny is as horny does in the sweetly absurd high school comedy “Superbad.” A tickly, funny tale of three teenage boys revved up by their surging, churning, flooding hormones, the movie joins the tumescent ranks of similarly themed works about male sexual desire — consider “Portnoy’s Complaint,” think “Porky’s” — and its somatic epiphanies, treacherous secretions, anguished lessons and apparently limitless storehouse of embarrassments. Behold the man (well, boy): fully sexed and wholly, touchingly virginal.  Written by Seth Rogen, last seen scoring in “Knocked Up,” and his childhood friend Evan Goldberg, “Superbad” follows two high school seniors — also named Seth and Evan — who together set off on a long night’s journey into the soul. Actually, what they do is try to booze up and party down with some school hotties during a nighttown adventure in missed opportunities and unexpected revelations. Time is short: summer looms, as does the fall, when Evan (Michael Cera, excellent) will depart for Dartmouth alongside his classmate Fogell (the newcomer Christopher Mintz-Plasse), leaving behind his academically challenged best friend, Seth (Jonah Hill). The future holds promise, even for Seth, yet also threatens the worst, especially if they don’t become some girl’s morning- after headache.  “We could be that mistake!” insists Seth, his voice shrill with hope and panic.  If the penis is puzzled in “Portnoy’s Complaint,” as Alexander Portnoy’s shrink believes, in “Superbad” it is thoroughly, stunningly clueless and as violently tremulous as a divining rod at Hoover Dam. Along with Fogell, a walking irritant with mad skills (he  procures a fake ID), Seth and Evan prowl their high school in search of — what, precisely? From their bawdy language, filled with vivid anatomical notes and gaudily colorful phrasing, the three would very much like to bed some “ladies,” as Fogell insists on calling them in a tragicomic bid at Kanye West suavity. The tearful joke being that these yapping pups wouldn’t know what to do with any woman, much less the bosomy babes of their whipped-cream and dirty dreams.  The divide between what a man says — and what he thinks he should say, especially to other men — and how he really feels inside largely defines the comedic ethos of Judd Apatow, one of the movie’s producers and its spiritual laughing light. Much like “The 40-Year-Old Virgin” and “Knocked Up,” both of which Mr. Apatow directed and either wrote or helped write,  “Superbad” largely works not because the jokes are funny, which they generally are, even on the spitometer. It works because no matter how unapologetically vulgar their words, no matter how single-mindedly priapic their preoccupations, these men and boys are good and decent and tender and true. They never take cruel or callous advantage. They call. They love. They marry.  Mr. Apatow traffics in such a cute, cuddly vision of modern masculinity that it seems rude to wonder if it’s honestly felt (which is what I think), self-flattering (ditto) or cunningly opportunistic (nah). Certainly it’s testosterone-heavy, if not exactly macho. And, indeed, part of what’s fascinating about Mr. Apatow’s ascendancy, and why the comedy moment belongs to him more than it does  either to the Farrelly brothers or to Ben Stiller and his mob, is how he has created — and come close to perfecting — a masculine variation on  aspirational wish-fulfillment movies like “Legally Blonde.” Except instead of perky, pretty women reaching up, up, up, Mr. Apatow offers  freaks and geeks aching to be worthy of those same women.  And if these guys aren’t especially worthy, well, such is the way of the wish-fulfillment fantasy. Mr. Apatow shamelessly stacks the deck in favor of his  underdogs — the future doctors, lawyers and Hollywood hitmakers of America, no doubt — but his intentions are generally righteous and his humor doesn’t depend too heavily on flatulence or sadism. Or filmmaking.  Given Mr. Apatow’s tendencies, it’s no surprise that the director of “Superbad,” Greg Mottola, doesn’t leave much of an imprint. Mr. Mottola, whose first and last big-screen effort was the fine 1996 comedy “The Daytrippers,” has spent much of the last decade working in network television (sometimes with Mr. Apatow) and it shows. In “Superbad,” his setups and camerawork serve the characters unobtrusively, as do the homey production design and costumes.  It’s a nice homeyness, lived-in and honest. Much like Mr. Rogen, who alongside Bill Hader puts in an unfortunately overextended appearance in “Superbad” as a dangerously juvenile cop, the young male actors in “Superbad” look as pleasantly, sympathetically real as they behave. They’re at a total and happy remove from the musclebound cartoons of prime-time and action-flick reveries.  Long and lanky, Mr. Cera moves like one of those teenagers whose body hasn’t yet fully caught up to his newly reached height. With his wide-open face and smile, he looks absolutely amazed by what he can see from a higher elevation (the world!). But of course he looks  surprised: he’s the top half of the exclamation point to the spherical Mr. Hill’s rolling big dot.  “Superbad” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Supernaughty.</text>
      <date>August 17, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>