<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Loud, dangerous and, to some, utterly pointless, Supercross is competitive motorcycle racing at its most extreme. Unlike its popular sister-sport Motocross, it is held mainly  indoors on twisty dirt tracks equipped with terrifying high jumps. The event serves as the backdrop for "Supercross: The Movie," a title indicative of the sheer lack of originality found in the latest in sports-themed action movies geared to speed-minded teens (with an attractive, young cast mostly plucked straight from television).  As with most films of this genre, the sport is interchangeable; if stripped away completely, the predictable little-guy-prevails premise remains. Here, the underdogs are the Carlyle brothers, KC (Steve Howey) and Trip (Mike Vogel), who struggle to make a living cleaning swimming pools but have big dreams of becoming Supercross champions. Though they come off as complete dunderheads, beginning and ending most sentences with "Dude" or "Bro," both brothers have hearts of gold - but the similarities end there. Trip is the younger and more adventurous one in riding and in spirit, whose bad temper keeps him from the corporate sponsorship that KC, the safer and less impressive rider, secures.  The ups and downs of the Carlyles' path to glory unfold in such a wholesome and saccharine way that it continually provokes unintentional giggles and eye-rolls, but it is still easy enough to cheer on the likable brothers - helped immensely by the fact that their love interests are not the typical cleavage-baring bimbos who flock to the sides of successful sports stars. KC's girlfriend Zoe (Sophia Bush) is an upper-class brunette lawyer-to-be with more smarts than both brothers combined. Trip's object of desire is Piper (Cameron Richardson), one of the few women competing in the racing circuit, and the more bike- and relationship-savvy of the two. In one of the film's many music-video-like montages, featuring corny songs with ridiculously literal lyrics, Trip and Piper connect in a motorcycle-riding love scene of epic cheese proportions.  Piper's dad (Robert Patrick, supplying the only substantial performance), represents something of a father figure to the recently orphaned boys (or so audiences are to assume; there is never a mention of a mother) and offers to sponsor Trip and eventually KC as well, once KC can no longer tolerate serving as "wingman" to his jerky  teammate, Rowdy (Channing Tatum).  The director, Steve Boyum, a 20-year-veteran Hollywood stuntman and  former Motocross racer, provides plenty of authentic dirt-flying motorcycle thrills, but the film's excruciating earnestness  and clunky script  frequently slow its energetic pace to a grinding halt.</text>
      <date>August 17, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>