<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It seems doubtful that “Surveillance,” a would-be transgression that tries to squeeze dark laughs from the spectacle of human suffering, would be taking up space in theaters if its director were not the daughter of a name filmmaker. Jennifer Lynch, spawn of David, has made one other feature, a 1993 botch-up titled “Boxing Helena,” about a surgeon who turns the object of his desire into his own Venus de Milo by amputating her healthy legs and arms. In an interview before its release, Ms. Lynch gushed that “obsessive love is like a series of amputations as you steal from one another.”  It’s impossible to know whether Ms. Lynch was having her playful way with the interviewer or not. Whatever the case, to judge from the evidence of both of her features, she remains committed to literalizing this unorthodox view of love, except that now she’s also drenching her (presumed) metaphor in gore. In “Surveillance,” which opens with a scene of a couple being slashed in their bed, she might still be entertaining modest artistic pretensions. But she’s now as in thrall to clever images of death and seeping, gushing, spurting blood as anyone in vivisectionist cinema. Mostly, though, she seems to want to shock you, which, given her father’s brilliant way of drilling your head and body with art, comes off as depressing.  If it seems unfair to compare her with her father, Ms. Lynch, much like Sofia Coppola, makes it easy. Once again, she hasn’t just cast actors, here Bill Pullman and Julia Ormond, who have worked with her father; she has borrowed ideas and visual motifs from his surrealistic storehouse and done her best to imitate his off-beat timing and uneasy humor. Credited as an executive producer, Mr. Lynch even sings the movie’s creepy closing song. It’s hard not to wonder if he helped her with her school projects when she was young, perhaps by making a severed ear out of papier-mâché or dioramas with angry dogs. He has not done her any favors here, however, because all of her images invite unflattering comparison to his.  Mr. Pullman and Ms. Ormond play a pair of unpersuasive F.B.I. agents — their black suits and crazy eyes betray them — who drive into a hicksville to investigate a crime. After some awkward stares and the obligatory Lynchian reference to a good cup of coffee, the agents start interviewing witnesses, including a little girl with the biggest brain in the room. As the story jumps among different versions of what happened — insert obligatory if misleading “Rashomon” reference here — the pace slackens even as the drip, drip, drip of blood turns into a geyser. During the big climax, one killer sexually straddles a victim who’s being strangled to death by a second killer, which indicates that Ms. Lynch’s ideas about obsessive love remain as, um, dicey as ever.  “Surveillance” is rated R. (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian.) Sexualized violence mixed in with lots of blood and bits of brain.</text>
      <date>June 26, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>