<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The small, arid no man's land in which the last third of Eran Riklis's tightly wound film, "The Syrian Bride," unfolds is between checkpoints at the Israeli and Syrian borders. This bleak area is tiny enough to allow people on either side to converse by bullhorn.  Here is where the Salmans, a family from Majdal Shams, a Druze village in the Syrian Golan Heights, annexed by Israel, finds itself embroiled in a bureaucratic nightmare. Because Syria does not recognize Israel, the Druze in the Golan Heights are cut off from Syria.  The Salmans have traveled to the border to bid goodbye to Mona (Clara Khoury), the youngest of two daughters, who is leaving home to wed a cousin, Tallel (Derar Sliman), a Syrian television star she has never met, in an arranged marriage. Once she crosses the border into Syria, she can never return.  Grim and unsmiling in her white wedding dress, the bride-to-be is determined to take her chances. The wedding photographer who trails after her capturing her every move on a video camera tries to make light of her anxiety: "Marriage is like a watermelon," he says. "You don't know what it's like until you open it up."  The monkey wrench thrown into the family's plans involves the stamping of her passport. Because Syria and Israel have no diplomatic relations, travelers with Israeli-stamped passports cannot enter Syria, which still considers the Golan Heights part of Syria. Neither of the officials at the checkpoints - a sympathetic Israeli who throws up his hands, and a bored Syrian who would rather watch television than deal with the crisis - will break the deadlock.  As Jeanne (Julie-Anne Roth), the Red Cross-affiliated intermediary who helped arrange the crossing, dashes back and forth trying to untangle the mess, phone calls to higher authorities in Jerusalem and Damascus go unanswered.  "The Syrian Bride" is not the first movie in which impenetrable borders become the symbol for all that's wrong in the Middle East. The recent documentary "Checkpoint," filmed at various blocked roads in the West Bank, revealed pervasive confusion, lack of communication and explosive frustration.  The no man's land in which the Salmans wait with mounting anger looms as the ultimate metaphor for stalemate and indecision. The impasse comes at an especially sensitive moment: the succession of Bashar al-Assad to the presidency of Syria after the death of his father has prompted demonstrations and raised border tensions. The film uses the situation to evoke a sense of the absurd, sometimes with dry, deadpan humor. At times it recalls Danis Tanovic's 2001 film, "No Man's Land," in which two wounded soldiers, one Bosnian, the other Serbian, confront each other in a trench between battle lines.  The idea of a no man's land also extends to the strained relations among the members of the Salman family. Mona's two brothers have returned for the wedding, each toting political and psychological baggage. Hattem (Eyad Sheety), the older brother, betrayed his father's code of tribal loyalty by leaving home eight years earlier to marry a Russian doctor (Evelyne Kaplun). The family patriarch, Hammed (Makram J. Khoury), a political militant under Israeli scrutiny, can hardly bring himself to look at his son.  Hammed is forbidden to accompany his daughter to the border, but he goes anyway, risking arrest. The younger brother, Marwan (Ashraf Barhoum), is a handsome, womanizing wheeler-dealer who lives in Italy and is involved in a shady import-export business.  Observing the family turmoil is Mona's married older sister, Amal (Hiam Abbas), an independent minded woman with two teenage daughters. She is unhappily married to Amin (Adnan Trabshi), a traditionalist who chafes at her independence. When he learns she has just been accepted at Haifa University to study social work, he protests that it will be a stain on his manhood.  Notwithstanding the movie's complex politics, the Salmans could be any family gathered for a ceremonial occasion. The excellent ensemble provides a finely shaded group portrait of the clan whose internal tensions are exacerbated by politics. The movie's final moments suggest that only a brave leap into the unknown can begin to untangle the mess.</text>
      <date>November 16, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>