<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In 1966, when we first meet them, Petey Greene (Don Cheadle) and Dewey Hughes (Chiwetel Ejiofor) present an easy, obvious contrast. Dewey, rising fast in the management ranks of a Washington R&amp;B radio station, favors trim suits and dark ties. When he speaks on the air, listeners are apt to mistake him for a white man. Petey, serving 10 years for armed robbery in a Virginia penitentiary, is a man of an altogether different — and, to Dewey, much lesser — sort. His speech is laced with profanities and put-downs, and he manages to look flashy even in prison, where he accessorizes his state-issued denims with bright red shoes and a flowery neckerchief.  Their subsequent friendship, which spans an era of social upheaval and fashion turmoil, is at the center of “Talk to Me,” Kasi Lemmons’s funny, earnest, affectionate new film. Ralph Waldo Greene, as Petey was called on his birth certificate, was a beloved figure in Washington’s African-American community from the late 1960s until his death in 1984 of cancer. A radio D.J., nightclub comedian and television host, he put himself forward as a no-nonsense voice of the streets, a funny, sometimes angry mix of trickster, prophet and provocateur. As portrayed by Mr. Cheadle, Petey Greene is a person of quick wit and tender heart, an irrepressible hustler whose fundamental integrity is never in doubt.  In its early scenes, the film, a long-gestating project made with the participation of the real Dewey Hughes and his son, Michael Genet (who conceived the story and shares screenwriting credit with Rick Famuyiwa), seems to be setting up Dewey and Petey as simple foils. When Petey, fresh from prison, arrives at Dewey’s station to claim the job he thinks was promised to him, the encounter plays out in bold sitcom strokes.  On one side is the uptight, upwardly mobile black man, eager to win favor with his even more uptight boss, E. G. Sonderling (Martin Sheen). On the other is Petey, rolling in on a tide of ghetto attitude, accompanied by his girlfriend, Vernell (Taraji P. Henson), a woman with a very big Afro and a very small dress.  This kind of standoff between hip and square — Sonderling purses his lips and says “What in blue blazes?”; Petey rolls his eyes and utters words you can’t say on the radio — was probably a cliché even in 1967. And of course Dewey, whom Petey calls Mr. Tibbs in mocking reference to Sidney Poitier’s role in “In the Heat of the Night,” is an easy target for blacker-than-thou derision. His demeanor and ambition mark him as an inauthentic black man, an Oreo, a sellout.  But “Talk to Me” starts out broad and schematic only to surprise you with its subtlety as it unfolds. Conveying the passage of time through the usual shorthand of clothes, hairstyles and vintage pop music, the movie nonetheless steers clear of the usual biopic conventions. Petey may be the charismatic, self-destructive center of attention — and Mr. Cheadle is as engaging and resourceful as ever — but the drama resides in his sometimes volatile, always closely observed partnership with Dewey. “You say the things I’m afraid to say,” Dewey remarks, “and I do the things you’re afraid to do.” While Petey brushes this off as greeting-card hooey, “Talk to Me” explores the idea of their symbiosis in a nuanced and insightful manner.  As soon as he takes the microphone as a morning disc jockey, Petey connects with his listeners, and his breakthrough moment comes when he helps to calm the city’s streets after the rioting that followed the assassination of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Dewey, who becomes Petey’s manager, pushes his friend and client toward ever bigger stardom.  His ambition causes a rift between them, and their relationship captures a basic tension within  African-American popular culture. Dewey, you might say, is eager to cross over, a desire represented by his dream of seeing Petey on “The Tonight Show” with Johnny Carson. Petey, for his part, is uncomfortable straying too far from the local public that sustains him. His mantra is “Keep it real.”  But to quote a song that appears in two versions on this movie’s superb soundtrack, compared to what? The sentimental way to tell the story would be to sneer at Dewey while painting Petey as an uncompromising hero. The filmmakers and the actors, thankfully, are too smart and too honest to go that route. While they pay homage to Petey’s militant, confrontational stance and to his hometown loyalty, they also respect Dewey’s discipline and his drive toward self-improvement. To its great credit, “Talk to Me” doesn’t ask the audience to choose a side, but rather invites us to appreciate the strengths and limitations of both men.  The result is a movie that offers uplift without phoniness, history without undue didacticism and a fair number of funny, dirty jokes. And Cedric the Entertainer in a plum-colored suit and Ms. Henson teetering on the brink of self- parody in platform shoes and skimpy skirts and never once surrendering her dignity.  “Talk to Me” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has abundant profanity, vulgar humor and sexual situations far beyond what the F.C.C. would approve.</text>
      <date>July 13, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>