<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Teenage horror-movie spoof, John Waters parody, No Nukes protest movie, twisted sex-education film, quasi-feminist fable, outrageous stunt: Mitchell Lichtenstein’s clever, crude comedy, “Teeth,” is all these and more.  Imagine Candy Christian, the title character of “Candy,” Terry Southern and Mason Hoffenberg’s satirical novel, as a contemporary mutant teen angel unknowingly afflicted with the mythical condition known as vagina dentata (a toothed vagina). In “Teeth” Dawn (Jess Weixler), that castration myth’s unfortunate embodiment, is a devout Christian who lectures on abstinence and leads the Promise, a group of teenagers who have pledged chastity until marriage. They wear red rings to certify their purity and go on group dates to shield one another from temptation. Dawn’s boyfriend, Tobey (Hale Appleman), has adopted the pledge, but reluctantly.  Ms. Weixler, whose performance earned her a special jury prize at last year’s Sundance Film Festival, suggests a younger, dewy Heather Graham. As Dawn breaks her pledge under fierce duress, her body responds involuntarily, and she wreaks traumatic damage to the unwelcome male intruders. But even after she knows how her body can react, she retains a quality of wide-eyed naïveté, as though that couldn’t really be happening.  The verdant tranquillity of the sleepy suburban town where Dawn and her surly younger stepbrother, Brad, have grown up is marred only by the belching cooling towers of a nearby nuclear power plant. Now and then the camera peers over the brilliant foliage with a smirking sense of mischief to observe these twin towers releasing ominous black plumes into the atmosphere. The movie implies that radiation is responsible for Dawn’s condition, not to mention her stepmother’s declining health and Brad’s satanic inclinations; everyone in the family may have mutated.  Brad is played by the heavy-lidded, ebony-eyebrowed John Hensley of “Nip/Tuck,” whose character on that show, Matt McNamara, attempted to circumcise himself in an early episode. Given the knowing attitude of “Teeth,” Mr. Lichtenstein, an actor turned writer-director, may have intentionally cast him as a sly reference.  The movie is filled with humorous winks. The grotto by a waterfall to which Dawn repairs for steamy love scenes that culminate in bloodcurdling howls of pain recalls a similar location in “Splendor in the Grass,” the 1961 melodrama in which chastity and sexual frustration drive Natalie Wood’s character into a mental hospital.  Dawn’s horrified awakening arrives when she and Tobey visit the waterfall unaccompanied, and one thing leads to another. When he forces himself on her, her body responds savagely, and he flees in agony leaving a part of himself behind. The distraught heroine scours the Internet for information and learns about the myth she incarnates. In the movie’s funniest scene she undergoes a gynecological examination in which the doctor, played by Josh Pais as a bossy, leering know-it-all, receives an excruciating surprise.  As much as you applaud its satiric nerve, once “Teeth” has demonstrated how far it will go, its joke becomes repetitive. Before the movie’s over, the screen is littered with severed pieces of the male anatomy, one of which is snapped up by a dog. Ho-hum. The problem with shockers, comic or otherwise, is that once the coup de grâce is delivered, there are no big surprises left.  “Teeth” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sex scenes and prosthetic anatomical parts.</text>
      <date>January 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>