<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The message about race relations in America conveyed by "The Tenants," a small, serious, but choppy and psychologically cauterized screen adaptation of Bernard Malamud's  1971 novel, is dire. In the novel, set in a soon-to-be-demolished Brooklyn tenement, two writers, one white and Jewish and the other black, struggle to be friends but fail to bridge the racial and ethnic divide.  The drama pits Harry Lesser (Dylan McDermott), a solitary author struggling to complete his third novel, against Willie Spearmint, a k a Bill Spear (Snoop Dogg), an unpublished African-American writer pounding out the latest draft of a work that's part fiction, part memoir.  Harry is the lone tenant holding out in a crumbling building whose landlord, Levenspiel (Seymour Cassel), keeps pestering him to leave, upping his buyout offer each time he visits. But Harry adamantly refuses to move until he finishes his novel. The phrase "until I finish my book" becomes a mordant comic leitmotif  illuminating the film's subtheme, the obsessive self-absorption of writers. Eventually, Harry loses the woman he wants to marry because he insists on finishing his book before doing anything else.  Willie, a part-time squatter in the desolate graffiti-scarred building where Harry is the last legal tenant, has appropriated a vacated apartment as his makeshift office. When not working there, he stays on and off with his white, Jewish girlfriend, Irene (Rose Byrne).  The two men meet when Harry, hearing the distant clack of a typewriter, investigates, discovers Willie at work and introduces himself. Before long, Willie pays Harry a call and warily asks him to read and evaluate his manuscript. Convinced that Willie means it when he demands an honest, no-holds-barred appraisal, Harry offers strong praise tempered with thoughtful criticism.  His negative words, though mild, drive Willie into a rage that unleashes a torrent of racial and ethnic abuse to which Harry refuses to respond. The gist of it is that Harry can't grasp Willie's writing because blacks and whites are fundamentally different.  When Willie's anger subsides, he returns for further advice and invites Harry into his mostly black social orbit, at which point the movie abruptly throws sex into the volatile mix. Once it does, a conflict already fraught with allegorical resonance slips over the line from semirealism into the theoretical.  Harry is seduced at a party by the black girlfriend of one of Willie's pals, inflaming the simmering racial distrust between the friends and nearly resulting in Harry's being beaten up. Shortly afterward, Harry announces to Irene that he has fallen in love with her and wants to marry her, and the two become lovers. She tells him her relationship with Willie is already on the skids and asks Harry to let her break the news that it's over, but he foolishly jumps the gun and does it himself.  The screenplay by David Diamond hardly bothers to lay the psychological groundwork for Harry's romantic choices. As portrayed by Mr. McDermott in a beard, the character seems weirdly obtuse in some ways and not in others, and the contradictions make no sense.  When hammered with Willie's inflammatory epithets, Harry, decent liberal that he is, refuses to take the bait and chooses his words carefully. But presented without rhyme or reason or emotional preparation, his relationships with women come across as theoretical constructions.  In its casting and direction (by Danny Green), "The Tenants" nervously sidesteps the black-Jewish issue by giving neither Harry nor Irene nor the overtly racist Levenspiel any recognizably Jewish characteristics; they don't even have Brooklyn accents. Because the movie is too scared to delve deeply into deeper issues of racial and ethnic envy and sexual stereotyping, only one side is heard: Willie's.  Where the movie does succeed is in insinuating the notion that mutual fear and hatred between  blacks and whites (and especially between blacks and Jews) are bone deep, potentially murderous and essentially unfixable.  Snoop Dogg, seizing his opportunity, inhabits the mind and heart of his anguished, fuming character with an electrifying conviction.  After making the first move to peel away poisonous layers of hate and suspicion, Willie is held back by his peers and ultimately co-opted and betrayed by the one man who held out the faint possibility of resolution. Even art is just another tool for leverage in a continuing power struggle.  "The Tenants" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity, racial epithets, violence and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>February 3, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>