<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Things We Lost in the Fire,” an earnest recovery drama in which Halle Berry and Benicio Del Toro give strong, grown-up performances, is the kind of awards-seeking Hollywood movie that bends over backward to prove that serious American movies can hold their own with the best films from overseas. They don’t, of course, except in very rare instances. The star system and the committee mentality, which methodically iron out the quirks from high-minded studio films, make it next to impossible.  It is a sign of this movie’s ambitions that DreamWorks went abroad to recruit Susanne Bier, the gifted Danish writer-director of “Open Hearts,” “Brothers” and “After the Wedding,” in hopes that she would stamp it with the imprimatur of “art.” On paper Ms. Bier, whose unsettling family dramas are the stylistic progeny of Ingmar Bergman via Lars von Trier — without Bergman’s heavy metaphysical baggage and Mr. von Trier’s trickster sensibility — is an ideal candidate for the job. She has the emotional radar of an astute, extremely tough therapist who refuses to avert her gaze from the ugliest family dynamics this side of a Noah Baumbach film.  But what could any director do with this soft, fuzzy, formulaic story of pain and “healing,” concocted by Allan Loeb, an American making his screenwriting debut? Healing, like “closure,” is a concept that when applied to the marketing of popular culture instantly signals emotional manipulation and bad faith.  Although it is impossible to know how much doctoring Mr. Loeb’s script underwent before reaching the screen, all signs point to a meticulous smoothing out of the story to make the movie adhere to someone’s misbegotten notion of an upscale art film with commercial appeal. Because the element of surprise, found in abundance in Ms. Bier’s homegrown films, has been removed, “Things We Lost in the Fire” feels disconnected from the real world.  It begins on a false note by observing the picture-perfect marriage of Brian (David Duchovny) and Audrey Burke (Halle Berry), a successful developer and his wife who live outside Seattle with their two beautiful children, a 10-year-old girl, Harper (Alexis Llewellyn), and a 6-year-old boy, Dory (Micah Berry). Between them, the children’s heads have enough ringlets for several Shirley Temple wigs.  As the movie begins, Brian is shot to death while intervening in a domestic dispute. The family is left in shock. Although Mr. Duchovny vanishes from the film, the notion of him and Ms. Berry playing a happily married couple defies credibility. The more we get to know grim, strait-laced Audrey, the idea that she would tolerate a husband who bears even the tiniest resemblance to Hank Moody, Mr. Duchovny’s sarcastic sensualist on the Showtime series “Californication,” is impossible to swallow. What you see is two stars without chemistry gamely going through the motions.  Enter Mr. Del Toro, playing Brian’s closest childhood friend, Jerry Sunborne, a recovering heroin addict living in a halfway house. After everyone else gave up on Jerry, Brian continued giving him handouts and encouragement in his fragile recovery, much to Audrey’s chagrin. Out of loyalty to Brian, she invites Jerry to stay in their garage for nothing in exchange for his helping around the property. Their edgy relationship, which for one brief moment heads toward romance, is the heart of the movie.  Each of the film’s two marquee names has a melodramatic set piece. Ms. Berry essentially reprises the kind of hysterical meltdown she performed in “Monster’s Ball,” which won her an Oscar as much for her nerve in becoming unstrung during sex as for her acting. This time her character is well-to-do, and no sex is involved.  Audrey is a typical Halle Berry character: a tense, tightly wound woman who regards the world with a wary, fearful hostility; hysteria lurks just under the surface. Even when she smiles, which is not often, her good mood is guarded. Ms. Berry’s beauty is at odds with her character’s seeming asexuality, which is why Audrey’s lovey-dovey moments with Brian feel perfunctory.  Jerry, by default, finds himself the children’s surrogate father, and the movie makes much of these cute kids’ small eccentricities and phobias: Harper’s secret habit of sneaking off to watch black-and-white films in a revival house with Brian, Dory’s fear of swimming in water over his head. As the children grow to trust and rely on Jerry, Audrey increasingly resents him, and she eventually throws him out of the house for presuming to usurp Brian’s role, although he has not presumed anything.  Jerry has his own midmovie meltdown when, suddenly homeless, he goes on a heroin bender and then, with the help of Audrey and her brother Neal (Omar Benson Miller), kicks drugs in a groaning and sweating ordeal as flashy as Frank Sinatra’s cold-turkey withdrawal in “The Man With the Golden Arm.”  Although neither Ms. Berry nor Mr. Del Toro can be faulted in their scenery-chewing moments, these star turns make you uncomfortably aware that they are Oscar-conscious auditions for the Big Prize. Their naked ambition subtly contaminates a movie that, despite its fine acting, has the emotional impact of a general anesthetic.  “Things We Lost in the Fire” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, drug taking and strong language.</text>
      <date>October 19, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>