<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Sang-hyun, the hero of Park Chan-wook’s “Thirst,” is many different things: a Roman Catholic priest; a selfless volunteer in a dangerous medical experiment; a reluctant faith healer with a cult following; a vampire. And “Thirst” itself, which won the Jury Prize this year at the  Cannes Film Festival, where Mr. Park has long been a favorite, is equally protean. It is a bloodstained horror movie, a dark comedy, a noirish psychodrama of crime and punishment, a melodrama of mad love, a freehanded literary adaptation (of Émile Zola’s “Thérèse Raquin”) and, of course, a vampire movie.  Unfortunately, it is also less than the sum of its parts — overly long, lacking in narrative momentum and too often choosing sensation over coherence. Mr. Park has an undeniable knack for choreographing bloody, sensual set pieces. While nothing in “Thirst” is quite as shocking or perverse as some of the best-known moments in his “Old Boy” or “Lady Vengeance” — by which I mean that no children are murdered and no live cephalopods swallowed whole — there are elegantly presented servings of sex and gore. Mr. Park and his cast offer moments of creepy, winking humor and also of intense emotion, a combination that is a hallmark of this director’s oeuvre.  The most vividly rendered feeling, suggested by the film’s title, is desire: for human blood, for sexual release and also for something purer and more soothing. Sang-hyun,  despite his vampirism (which follows his voluntary infection with a disfiguring tropical virus), clings to a sense of righteousness and decency. Instead of  maiming or killing innocent people, he discreetly slurps from the intravenous tube of an overweight patient in a hospital coma ward. Later on, when his appetite (and that of his lover) grows,  Sang-hyun proposes turning to assisted suicide rather than outright murder. Even his sexual hunger is shadowed by guilt and colored by tenderness as much as lust.  It helps that  Sang-hyun is played by Song Kang-ho, one of South Korea’s most inventive and reliably sympathetic actors. More somber and stiffer than he was in Bong Joon-ho’s “Host,”  one of the best monster-horror movies of recent years, Mr. Song broods and suffers persuasively. He also slyly signals some of the more preposterous aspects of his character. This poor priest, longing to help humanity, finds himself covered in blisters and under quarantine and then subject to sensory freakouts that are scant compensation for his superhuman powers.  Sensory freakouts are one of Mr. Park’s specialties. His colors — red in particular — are always bright and menacing, and his sound design foregrounds wet, intimate, icky noises. He is a virtuoso not so much of sex and violence as of the feverish states that incite such frenzies of carnality. In Sang-hyun’s case, involuntary bloodlust is redoubled by a more familiar kind when he finds himself infatuated with a young woman,  Tae-ju (Kim Ok-vin). The adoptive stepsister, and now the wife, of a sickly childhood friend of  Sang-hyun’s, Tae-ju lives with her husband (Shin Ha-kyun) and mother-in-law (Kim Hae-sook) in a state of Cinderella-like servitude. She is bored, bossed around and, she leads Sang-hyun to believe, grievously abused.  What develops between  Sang-hyun and Tae-ju should be, and sometimes is, a nasty little drama of mayhem,  revenge and remorse. Ms. Kim, at first the very image of girlish frailty, evolves from ingénue to femme fatale to demon, and exerts herself bravely in an effort to embody the film’s anxious and confused ideas about female sexuality.  These will be familiar to connoisseurs of recent vampire-obsessed popular culture, from “Twilight” to “True Blood.”  Tae-ju, who is initiated by Sang-hyun  into his sanguinary tribe, is at once a helpless victim and a wanton vixen. The difference between the lovers is indicative of the film’s queasy, quasi-misogynist ideas about eros and ethics. Sang-hyun  is morally stricken by his cravings, and when he can’t fight them he at least tries to bargain with their implacable demands. Tae-ju, once she overcomes her initial shyness, recognizes no such scruples or boundaries. She is a fantasy figure designed to scare and titillate boys who imagine that a sexually awakened woman is an uncontrollably destructive force.  Like other conceits  in the film, this fantasy has the potential to be more interesting than it is. Mr. Park seems almost to be making up  the story  as he goes along, gesturing toward themes that are never, so to speak, fleshed out. Soaked in blood though it is, “Thirst” leaves some essential cravings unsatisfied.  “Thirst” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sex, nudity, blood and gore.</text>
      <date>July 31, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>