<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>   If you’re a regular reader of movie reviews in this newspaper, you’ve no doubt noticed that most of them end with a brief italic note, written by the critic, explaining (and occasionally mocking) the film’s rating. For some readers, this is the most important part of the review, and for this critic it is often the hardest to write. The little boxes that appear at the bottom of the print advertisements are sometimes helpful — we all know nudity or drug use when we see it — but they can also be mystifying. What is “intense adventure violence”? Are “thematic elements” harmful to children? When the box says “some language,” just how much language does it mean? And which language? Would a movie with no language be less dangerous?  “This Film Is Not Yet Rated,” a feisty, intellectually engaging new documentary by Kirby Dick (“Sick,” “Derrida,” “Twist of Faith”) does not so much answer these questions as explore just why they are so difficult to answer. The Motion Picture Association of America, which devised the current rating system and administers it, can be a remarkably secretive organization. Founded by the major Hollywood studios to head off the threat of government censorship and run for most of its history by Jack Valenti, a former staff member in Lyndon B. Johnson’s White House, the association often seems more arbitrary and less transparent in its workings than any federal agency this side of the C.I.A.  To find out who serves on the ratings board and what criteria they use, Mr. Dick hires private detectives, who park outside its nondescript offices in the Encino section of Los Angeles, scribbling down license plate numbers and taking pictures of employees on their lunch breaks. Mr. Dick even rummages through trash bags and discovers important, if puzzling, clues about why “Memoirs of a Geisha” qualified for a PG-13.  These whodunit elements are interspersed with more conventional documentary material: interviews with filmmakers and scholars, clips from movies that have run into trouble with the board, and occasional sound bites from the irrepressible Mr. Valenti, who tells us that the folks who hand out the ratings are “neither gods nor fools.” That narrows it down a bit, though not enough for Mr. Dick, who uncovers some curious inconsistencies in the association’s accounts of its procedures. Do the clergymen who sit in on appeals board meetings — along with representatives of theater chains and film sales companies — have a vote or not? No clear answer is forthcoming. Does the ratings board take a harder line on sex than on violence? On gay sex than on straight?    The evidence Mr. Dick gathers and the testimony of directors like Kimberly Peirce (“Boys Don’t Cry”) and Matt Stone (“South Park”) paint the Motion Picture Association as an outpost of prudishness and repression. (Bingham Ray, former president of United Artists, goes further, describing it as “fascist.”) The record of its recent decisions suggests a special squeamishness about depictions of female sexual pleasure and a picayune fastidiousness about certain body parts. A glimpse of Maria Bello’s pubic hair, for instance, threatened to doom “The Cooler” to an NC-17. But then again, “A Dirty Shame,” John Waters’s 2004 film, received the same rating just for talking about certain outré practices while showing almost no skin at all. (When Mr. Dick submitted a cut of this film, it was slapped with an NC-17, an unsurprising outcome that led to some hilarious, Kafkaesque telephone conversations between him and Joan Graves, the chairwoman of the ratings board. IFC Films, which is not owned by a major studio and therefore not required to submit its releases to the association, is distributing the film without a rating.)  These decisions have commercial as well as artistic consequences, since some of the biggest theater chains, retail stores and video outlets avoid the NC-17 rating as a matter of policy. Filmmakers who want their movies to be seen — and who often need to fulfill contracts requiring that they deliver a film with a certain rating — are thus compelled to cut their films to the association’s standards, a process that often involves guessing just what those standards are.  Mr. Dick, unabashedly on the side of the filmmakers, is particularly concerned with art films — movies obviously intended for grown-up viewing that are nonetheless subjected to a regime ostensibly designed to protect children. But — at the risk of sounding like Maude Flanders — what about the children? How are parents supposed to navigate the flood tide of popular culture that engulfs their kids at younger and younger ages? Does this ratings system help? Could it be improved?  Mr. Dick’s lack of interest in these questions is frustrating, and the narrow scope of “This Film Is Not Yet Rated” makes it more of a culture-war broadside than a nuanced work of cultural inquiry. It is, nonetheless, an engaging and entertaining movie, one that tries to illuminate an aspect of moviemaking — and moviegoing — that is deliberately left in the dark.</text>
      <date>September 1, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>