<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Utah boasts 12 Republicans for every Democrat, mainly  because of its  large number of Mormons. So when Utah Valley State College in Orem  announced, just weeks before the 2004 election, the engagement of the fiercely liberal director Michael Moore to speak on campus, all hell broke loose - quite literally, in the view of the more outraged locals. But for  Steven Greenstreet, a 25-year-old former  Brigham Young University student,   the impending visit was an opportunity to chronicle one of the most virulent culture wars in recent Utah history.  Raw, chaotic and engagingly eager, "This Divided State" juxtaposes candid interviews with scenes of unrest as Mr. Greenstreet rushes gamely from one hot spot to another. Within days of the college's announcement,   town  and gown have  erupted with anti-Moore petitions, public hearings, threatened lawsuits and gleeful editorials in the  press. The student body president, Jim Bassi, and his vice president, Joe Vogel, are the target of vicious phone calls and hate mail, and a protest that begins by cloaking itself in a debate over Mr. Moore's $40,000 fee soon reveals its good-versus-evil subtext.  Spearheading the opposition is the local businessman and community advocate Kay Anderson, who offers the college $25,000 to cancel Mr. Moore's visit. "Free speech works because most of us know when to keep our mouths shut," rails Mr. Anderson, whose tortured logic enlivens much of the film. These spurts of unintentional humor are filmmaking gold, as when an anti-Moore student petitioner, Sean Vreeland, earnestly likens Utah's religious fervor to that of the Middle East. And though occasional moments of silliness intrude - rather too much time is spent in the company of Ken Brown, a Republican student who likes to flaunt his physical and sartorial resemblances to Mr. Moore - the film never descends to ridicule.  Many scenes are, in fact, extremely moving. Commenting on the furor,  William Sederburg,  the school's president,   admits to being overcome by emotion. "It almost feels like a college campus," he says, looking mildly astonished.  A Togolese exchange student explains what it's like to live in a country where freedom of speech is unknown. Most compelling of all are the Mormons who patiently stress that the practice of their  faith relies on tolerance and open-mindedness.  "This Divided State" may ring with death threats and heave with animosity, but its final message is a hopeful one: in one of the most conservative states in the country, there are at least as many open minds as closed ones.</text>
      <date>August 19, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>