<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A soulful blast from the past sparked by heart and a throbbing beat, “This Is England” returns us to 1983, when Ronnie and Maggie ruled their roosts with Teflon finesse and an iron grip. The place is a quiet town where rude graffiti litter the walls and teenage skinheads loiter, dressed in jeans, Ben Sherman shirts and Doc Martens boots, looking for something, anything, to do. The Falklands War has just ended, but another battle simmers on the home front, fueled by unemployment, rage, nationalism and the old ennui.  A modest, near-flawless gem, “This Is England” is the fifth feature by the young British director Shane Meadows, doing his best work since he first hit the festival scene in the mid-1990s with his hilarious, raw-hewn shorts “Small Time” and “Where’s the Money, Ronnie?” Like most of his films the new one takes place in the East Midlands, in England’s midsection, where Nottingham and Derby are, and where Mr. Meadows was born and, in early adolescence, became a skinhead. By turns gentle and brutal, “This Is England” is a humbly, if insistently political, autobiographical homage to that lost world of youth as well as a lament for its hopes, pleasures and passionate camaraderie.  As if returning to basics Mr. Meadows has, for this film, smartly departed from his reliance on familiar faces, some of whom have at times weighed heavily on his past work (Bob Hoskins in “Twentyfourseven,” Paddy Considine in “Dead Man’s Shoes”). The wonderful newcomer Thomas Turgoose gets most of the attention here, as 12-year-old Shaun, a spark plug with a lopsided stare, who lives with his mother and keeps his own counsel. Quick to anger, fast with his fists, Shaun plows through town like a tugboat, cutting a poignant, lonely swath through strangers and schoolmates alike until he’s affably taken off course by Woody (Joe Gilgun), a garrulous skinhead with pipe-cleaner legs and a small cross tattooed in the middle of his forehead.  In both its politicized long view and in its more important close-up story, “This Is England” is about the joy that can come with finding your tribe, of discovering and being accepted by those with whom you can find and be yourself. When Woody brings Shaun into his band of skinhead brothers, the boy lifts like a balloon. He giggles and smiles, and the hole that had recently torn through him, caused by the death of his father, starts to mend. Not long after Shaun laces up his boots and says goodbye to his long hair, Mr. Meadows shows him strolling about with his new friends in slow motion, their similar yet different forms shifting and moving harmoniously, flowing like tributaries toward a single destination.  There’s a boisterous honesty as well as a real edge to the friendship among the skinheads, who sometimes combust in giddy anarchy, as when they run riot with hammers through some abandoned apartments. Mostly out of work and at loose ends, they sit around idling and revving. As the pitch- and tone-perfect soundtrack pulses with Toots and the Maytals, the Specials and Ian Dury, they drink and smoke to excess, crowding into already cramped homes and bleak cafes, tossing insults at one another as both time and their youth seem to stand still. They have made their own world, but one with its own perils, notably Combo (Stephen Graham, brilliant and scarily real), who mucks up this idyll with spit and racist invective.  Mr. Meadows’s sentimentalism has sometimes gotten the better of his work, with tears and needlessly punishing violence, but not here. Shaun may embody pitifully hard times and bad breaks, but Mr. Meadows refuses to let him off the hook. In the film’s brilliant opening sequence — with its images of the Falklands War abroad set against anti-Pakistani violence at home — Mr. Meadows sketches out his interests and ethics with clarity and precision. Throughout the drama and heavy-hearted tragedy that follow he continues to bridge the personal with the political and revel in brotherhood while also warning of its dangers. He reclaims the best of these skinheads and their often-despised subculture, celebrating the finest in young men and women who were once united not under the Union Jack but under a groove.</text>
      <date>July 27, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>