<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Shot in bright, saturated color and set in a landscape of tall grass and wide-open space, “Tideland” unfolds on the borderline between fantasy and reality, which is familiar territory for its director, Terry Gilliam. In movies like “The Fisher King,” “The Adventures of Baron Munchausen” and “The Brothers Grimm” he has set out for that frontier, but this time he has stumbled into a different no-man’s land, the one between the merely bad and the completely indefensible.  To make a long movie short: Jeliza-Rose (Jodelle Ferland, who turned 10 while the film was being made) is the young child of two heroin addicts. Mom checks out early, and Dad (Jeff Bridges) does not stay around much longer — though his rotting (and later embalmed) body lingers. After a while I started to envy him, since duty required me to stay alive and awake for two hours during which misery masqueraded as whimsy and vice versa.  Jeliza-Rose, who charmingly cooks up her father’s fixes and lovingly removes the hypodermic from his arm as he nods off, takes refuge in make-believe from the tawdriness of her existence. Her confidants and companions are three severed dolls’ heads, and eventually some eccentric neighbors who seem like fairy-tale characters but are really a gothic sister-and-brother duo named Dell (Janet McTeer) and Dickens (Brendan Fletcher).  Jeliza-Rose’s encounters with them are filmed with Mr. Gilliam’s characteristic verve: swooshing camera movements, tilted frames, luridly exaggerated acting. The aesthetic is at once grotesque and dreamy, but not coherently so, since no distinction is made between the filmmaker’s perception and his heroine’s. The movie is as full of unmodulated shrieking, thumping and bric-a-brac as an amateur puppet show. The director places a heavy burden on young Ms. Ferland. To fully convey the registers of Jeliza-Rose’s consciousness — the delicate shadings of terror and self-consoling fancy, the volatile mix of precocity and innocence — is an enormous challenge, and rather than supporting her in it Mr. Gilliam uses her wide-eyed cuteness and her chirpy, Southern-accented voice as crutches.  The worst that can be said of the first two-thirds of “Tideland” is that it is tiresome. Toward the end it becomes creepy, and not in a good way. The sexuality of children, and its exploitation by adults, is about as delicate a subject as a movie can address, but a film like Gregg Araki’s “Mysterious Skin” proves that it can be done with seriousness and integrity, neither of which is in evidence here. Instead, Mr. Gilliam descends into curdled silliness. It might be said that his imagination knows no boundaries; it might be good if he found some.  “Tideland” is rated R. It has drug use, gruesome deaths and extremely icky sexual implications.</text>
      <date>October 13, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>