<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> A cramped metropolis of xenophobes and eccentrics living in a futuristic present: that is the image evoked in “Tokyo!,” a compendium of three surreal shorts whose relationship with one another might best be defined by the exclamation point in the title.  Two of the three are by French filmmakers: the New York-based Michel Gondry (“Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind”) and Léos Carax (“The Lovers on the Bridge”). The third and weakest contribution comes from Bong Joon-ho, the South Korean director of “The Host.” Both in its parts and in the sum of them “Tokyo!” is playfully and sometimes disorientingly apocalyptic. Opposite in spirit to the sensuous, humane “Paris Je T’Aime,” another recent directorial group portrait of a city, “Tokyo!” conjures alienation and dehumanization  In Mr. Gondry’s “Interior Design,” the most warm-blooded of the three, the relationship of Akira (Ryo Kase), an aspiring young filmmaker with delusions of grandeur, and his insecure, tag-along girlfriend, Hiroko (Ayako Fujitani), is tested as they scour the grotesque low end of Tokyo’s real estate market in search of an affordable rental. One hole-in-the-wall they visit is bug infested; in another they recoil at the sight of a dead cat on the floor. A third is a tiny pod with a porthole.  Because Hiroko doesn’t “do” anything in a society that identifies people by occupational labels, her shaky self-esteem crumbles in the cold, cruel city. In a witty cinematographic coup she undergoes a Kafkaesque metamorphosis and finds a strangely happy resolution, which Mr. Gondry engineers gracefully, with minimal special effects.  Akira, I should add, is no great shakes as a filmmaker. His idiotic contribution to the future of cinema, which he tests out at a screening of his no-budget opus, “The Garden of Degradation,” is to bring a smoke machine into the theater, which produces watery eyes and coughing fits among the invited guests.  The title  of Mr. Carax’s film is a French expletive that is also the name  of its main character, a subterranean half-human played with enthusiastic comic zeal by the director’s usual lead actor, Denis Lavant. With a white marble eye and a curling red beard, the green-suited “creature from the sewers,” as he is nicknamed by the media, speaks a nonsensical patois that only his mysterious French lawyer can understand. After popping out of a manhole, he begins wreaking havoc on the sidewalks of Tokyo, grabbing fistfuls of money and flowers from pedestrians’ hands and stuffing them into his mouth as he lurches down the street.  On his second trip above ground, he becomes a full-fledged terrorist who creates mass panic as he casually tosses grenades over his shoulder while staggering along. Soon his lair is raided, and he is dragged off in shackles and tried for murder.  On one level Mr. Carax’s film is a “Godzilla” spoof. But with its conspicuous references to World War II atrocities by Japanese soldiers in China, memorialized in underground graffiti, the movie is also a critique of Japan’s suppressed historical memory. Denial of the past, it implies, can keep those horrors buried for only so long before they explode in a volcanic rampage.  The protagonist of Mr. Bong’s “Shaking Tokyo” is also a loner, a so-called hikikomori, or shut-in (Teruyuki Kagawa), who has lived indoors for 10 years with minimal human contact. His hermetic existence abruptly ends when the delivery of his daily pizza coincides with an earthquake, and he connects long enough with the beautiful young woman who delivered it to fall in love with her. Roused from his isolation by passion, he ventures outdoors to find her.  As in Mr. Carax’s film it takes momentous forces erupting from underground to restore a semblance of reality and human connection in a city living inside a chilly science-fiction bubble.</text>
      <date>March 6, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>