<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It is hardly news that teenage sexuality is a subject that drives many people crazy. But how crazy? In “Towelhead,” a provocative satire of a culture that is paradoxically hypersexual and puritanical, it makes everyone bonkers. The men tend to be glowering beasts unable to keep their hands to themselves, and the female characters are either angry, judgmental watchdogs or witchy Lolitas not fully aware of their Circean powers.  The movie, faithfully adapted from Alicia Erian’s novel, is the first film  directed by Alan  Ball, the creator of “Six Feet Under” (and of the new vampire series “True Blood”),  and screenwriter of “American Beauty.” Set during the first gulf war,  in a spanking-new, upscale housing development on the outskirts of Houston, “Towelhead” is a crude but scathing portrait of suburban life.  In its preoccupations it might be described as “Son of ‘American Beauty.’ ”  If that first movie was a glum but polished man of the world, its offspring is a colicky baby who does a lot of screaming and yelling and banging of fists. Instead of the lush, well-tended landscape of “American Beauty,” the sterile tract housing of “Towelhead” is harshly ugly. The screenplay is talkier, and the acting more strident.  Mr. Ball can’t resist indulging in the kind of titillation that the movie deplores. Although “Towelhead” doesn’t actually show female-genital shaving, the insertion of tampons and the putting on of condoms, it goes right to the brink before the camera cuts away. It does, however, show menstrual blood, masturbation and discarded condoms. More to the point, its characters, no matter what their age, obsess about such things to the exclusion of everything else.  The misanthropy  of “Towelhead” is almost as uncontrolled as the male characters’ libidos. Even though Mr. Ball tries to humanize the men by showing their capacity for an awkward tenderness, the movie’s underlying attitude is that all men are dogs, especially when faced with virginal teenage flesh. Although the women are more sketchily drawn, with the exception of Toni Collette’s portrayal of a concerned neighbor in the housing development, they are viewed as avaricious bimbos.  The hysteria all swirls around Jasira (Summer Bishil), a juicy 13-year-old Lebanese-American girl with a healthy sexual curiosity, whose classmates taunt her with names like “towelhead” and “camel jockey.” Her father, Rifat (Peter Macdissi), a divorced Lebanese-born engineer who works for NASA but retains a straitlaced Middle Eastern code of values, frets about Jasira’s budding sexuality and dream of becoming a centerfold.  As the movie begins, Jasira moves to Houston from Syracuse,  where she has been living with her angry, embittered mother, Gail (Maria Bello). The catalyst for the move is inappropriate behavior toward the girl by Gail’s boyfriend, Barry (Chris Messina). On arriving in Texas, Jasira experiences immediate culture shock. Her father, observing her dressed like an ordinary American teenager, finds her outfit outrageously provocative and strikes her hard in the face.  To Travis Vuoso (Aaron Eckhart), the married Army Reservist next door for whose bratty young son she baby-sits, Jasira is irresistible jailbait.  A classmate (Eugene Jones) is equally besotted; Rifat pronounces him off limits because he is black; Jasira rebels.  “Towelhead” may have been conceived as a dark comedy, but it is rarely funny. It pointedly presents Rifat and Travis as an unlikely two of a kind. If one is an overprotective father, and the other a predator, both see Jasira as an inflammatory force of nature and tend to blame her for it.  Rifat’s obsequious new girlfriend, Thena (Lynn Collins), and Travis’s nasty wife, Evelyn (Carrie Preston), are both all-American cheerleader types. The two men conspicuously fly American flags on their small, manicured lawns. Rifat  is a rah-rah American warmonger who hates Saddam Hussein with a passion.  Jasira is a softer variation of Angela Hayes, the teasing, trash-talking cheerleader played by Mena Suvari in “American Beauty.” Like Angela, Jasira is not the person either her father or Travis sees through sexual eyes. Ms. Bishil, who is 20, creates a convincing portrait of a confused 13-year-old girl being manipulated from all sides.  In its depiction of a hapless young woman as the flashpoint of a culture war, “Towelhead” recalls the superior “Citizen Ruth,” in which a young woman’s pregnancy rallies vociferous   forces on both sides of the abortion battle.  Even more than in “American Beauty,” suburbia is portrayed as a hellish hothouse of repression and lust, where everyone minds everyone else’s business. In this overheated atmosphere the tension suggests the opposing worlds of “Wife Swap” and “Trading Spouses”  forced  together in a no-win conflict. The movie is a barely disguised hate letter to southern Texas.  Because “Towelhead” is set in pre-9/11  America, almost a decade before the presidency of George W. Bush, it is also a period piece. Evangelical Christianity has yet to be mobilized as a national political force, and Islamic jihadism is only a murmur beyond the horizon. The cracks in the political landscape may have formed, but they have not opened into the chasms they are today.  “Towelhead” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian).  It has scenes of sexual abuse of a young girl  and clinical sexual talk.</text>
      <date>September 12, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>