<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Transsiberian” is a handsomely remodeled variation of a cherished genre you might call the mystery-train movie. Updated by the director Brad Anderson (“The Machinist”), who wrote the screenplay with Will Conroy, it skillfully manipulates familiar tropes: innocents abroad, ominous glowering foreigners, conspiracy and duplicity, erotic intrigue. Until it fizzles in an anticlimactic train crash, it is extremely entertaining.  Ben Kingsley, seen briefly at the beginning of the movie before disappearing, only to re-emerge much later, plays Grinko, a duplicitous narcotics detective. A sophisticated embodiment of a cynical middle-aged Russian with a double vision of his country during and after Communism, he lends the movie a modern Dostoyevskian gloss.  As the ill-fated train whistles from Beijing toward Moscow through a desolate, snow-covered landscape, with many stops along the way, you lean back and prepare to get lost in a Siberian gulag where you can’t speak the language and have no global positioning system or even a compass for guidance. The paranoid mood intensifies during the first two-thirds, in which the suspense is comparable to that found in the best films of that mystery-train master, Alfred Hitchcock. Once the movie turns into an action-thriller aboard detached, runaway railroad cars, however, it ends up sidetracked.  The train, on which most of the movie is set, is  not to be confused with the luxurious  Orient Express of earlier train dramas. The rickety Communist-era relic has an overtly hostile crew, toilets that don’t flush and sleeping cars in which travelers are packed like sardines. Instead of glamorous, well-heeled tourists with stacks of expensive luggage, most of the passengers are sullen peasants and rowdy drunks. At each stop policemen with drug-sniffing dogs patrol the aisles.  Into this human clutter arrive Roy (Woody Harrelson) and Jessie (Emily Mortimer), a naïve American couple returning to the United States from China where they have been teaching English as part of a church-sponsored charity program. There are ominous portents. Early in the trip they are regaled with the story of a passenger from whom a corrupt Russian policeman extorted thousands of dollars and cut off two toes because the name on his passport was misspelled.  Roy is a chirping parody of the gregarious American abroad. Jessie, an amateur photographer, is a reformed bad girl with a history of drug and alcohol abuse. Roy met her when she had hit rock bottom and stood by her during her recovery. She still clings to a cigarette habit. While Roy longs for children, Jessie wants to put off having a family. For all her surface primness, underneath she is a reckless adventurer. When faced with sexual temptation, she muses darkly, “I sure wish I’d met you back in the day.”  That they break the mold of the picture-perfect all-American couple facing danger as a cozy unit injects the genre with a bracing psychological complexity. In a compelling performance, Ms. Mortimer takes her complicated character and runs with it.  With the arrival of their companions in the sleeper’s double-decker bunk beds, the mystery soup thickens. Carlos (Eduardo Noriega), a handsome Spaniard in his late-30s with a crooked flash in his eyes, and Abby (Kate Mara), a glum 20-year-old runaway from Seattle, are a suspiciously odd pair of international nomads who claim to be returning from a stint teaching English in Japan.  Carlos ogles Jessie, who pretends not to notice. A little later, when he shows her a sample from the suitcase of tchotchkes he says they are planning to sell in Amsterdam, you wonder if these little porcelain dolls might be stuffed with drugs.  At the Siberian city of Irkutsk Roy misses the train. As Jessie awaits his arrival the next day, Carlos and Abby stay by her side, and the movie teases you with the notion that something dreadful happened to him. With time on their hands, Carlos coaxes Jessie to take a bus into the countryside and hike into the forest to visit a crumbling church, leaving Abby behind in their seedy hotel. The rest of the drama hinges on horrific events that take place during this traumatic side trip.  Roy, returning safe and sound and chipper as ever, is accompanied by Grinko, whom he met and befriended in Irkutsk. With his glittering eyes and mocking smirk, dropping cynical aphorisms about Soviet versus capitalist Russia, Grinko is a fascinatingly ambiguous figure, simultaneously wise and corrupt, good and evil, with scary psychological radar. “In Russia, we have an expression,” he says, fixing his eyes on Jessie, who is frozen with panic. “With lies you may go forward in the world, but you may never go back.”  The cat-and-mouse game that ensues leads “Transsiberian” from tantalizing mystery into clanking melodrama.  “Transsiberian” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes violence, one scene of torture, strong language and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>July 18, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>