<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Jason Statham is the unlikeliest of high-octane action heroes. He is a stocky, ordinary-looking Englishman who doesn't come off all that swift. But as the ex-Special Forces operative Frank Martin, the impeccably dressed, blank-faced professional driver in "The Transporter" and now "Transporter 2" with more tricks - and lives - than James Bond, he's struck gold with a franchise-spawning role. The part allows for the exhibition of some impressive martial-arts skills (he performs almost all his own stunts) while requiring very little in the acting department.  After relocating to Miami from the dreamy French seaside, where the Euro-chic first film was set, Frank accepts a short-term assignment chauffeuring a wealthy family's young son. But before long, the boy, for whom Frank has developed a soft spot, is kidnapped and injected with a deadly contagious virus, intended to be passed along to his self-absorbed father (Matthew Modine, in an exceedingly thankless role) and his drug-enforcement colleagues. Frank, whose life is governed by his own strict set of rules, vows to save the boy's life and proceeds to do whatever it takes (the more insanely implausible, the better) to keep his word, while being aggressively pursued by the police, who believe Frank is in on the crime.  Taking over directing duties from Cory Yuen, who was responsible for "The Transporter" and did the martial-arts choreography here, is Louis Leterrier - clearly the right man for the job. In addition to serving as artistic director on the first installment, he also collaborated with the writer-producer Luc Besson on the Jet Li vehicle "Unleashed," released earlier this year.  Though both "Transporter" films are driven by the same empty-headed video-game slickness, "Transporter 2" surpasses its less focused predecessor on almost every level. There are no traces of a romance subplot, which bogged down the first film, freeing up space for even more car chases and fight sequences. And the French cop Tarconi (François Berléand), the closest thing Frank has to a friend, is back, with a more consequential role, helping track down the abducted boy and making up for Frank's lack of charisma.  Purely shallow but never dull, the film wisely pushes the limits of absurdity to the extreme, making it easier to submit to its sheer camp. But even with all thought processes deactivated, it's hard to tolerate the main female baddie (the newcomer Kate Nauta), who struts around in lingerie and red stilettos, toting large guns, while delivering one of the worst performances since Milla Jovovich, another clothing-deprived supermodel-turned-actress, appeared in Mr. Besson's "Fifth Element."  "Transporter 2" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes extreme violence.</text>
      <date>September 2, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>