<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The adults in “Treeless Mountain” do not appear purposefully cruel, though they often appear as cold, remote and mysterious as the stars in the sky. The film, the second feature from the Brooklyn-based writer and director So Yong Kim, tells a quiet, carefully observed story about two young girls — 6-year-old Jin and her 4-year old sister, Bin — who become orphans of a kind after their mother leaves them with relatives. Shot in South Korea, where Ms. Kim was born (her family immigrated to America when she was 12), it has the tang of real life, though this is realism that has been filtered through 60 or so years of world art cinema.  Ms. Kim, whose first feature was “In Between Days,” a minimalist exercise about an emotionally isolated teenager, has chosen a more accessible subject for her new film: the desertion of two children. Her style also feels more approachable: the film opens with close-ups of Jin (the serious-eyed Hee Yeon Kim, making her film debut) attentively following a lesson at school, a cozy perspective from which Ms. Kim never budges. (For much of the story, she is the only grown-up watching over the girls.) Jin and Bin (Song Hee Kim) live with their worried-looking mother (Soo Ah Lee) in a cramped Seoul apartment until suddenly they don’t, having been carted off to live with her sister-in-law, whom they call Big Aunt (Mi Hyang Kim).  A heavy drinker who directs the children to stack her empties, Big Aunt doesn’t come equipped with a warm, enveloping maternal bosom. She is negligent, cranky, resentful and given to voluble complaint. She doesn’t appear to want to care for the girls, which, in view of her dipsomaniac tendencies,  seems reasonable, even wise.  It’s a relief when, at the mother’s prodding, she takes them to their grandparents’ farm, partly because this development promises changes in scenery, tone and point of view, along with the promise of narrative tension. The scenery does change, but the tone remains unmodulated, the point of view claustrophobic, and no narrative tension emerges from the drifty, prettily shot, repetitive images of the children navigating everyday life. The grandmother (Boon Tak Park, a nonprofessional) does prove kind.  Through her close attention to Jin’s and Bin’s habits, exchanges and tears, which she captures with a low-placed camera and hushed sense of intimacy, Ms. Kim quickly pulls you into this Lilliputian world. You see what they see, learn what they learn. The problem is that while the children are lovely because they are children, there is nothing inherently interesting about them or their lives. Their predicament is the stuff of melodrama, but from the loose (if linear) narrative and pockets of ambiguity (why did the father leave?) it’s clear that Ms. Kim has positioned her film in a different tradition, one that borrows heavily from Yasujiro Ozu (specifically with the transitional shots tucked between scenes), Vittorio De Sica and other non-Hollywood masters, even as the story makes a beeline toward some unsurprising uplift.</text>
      <date>April 22, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>