<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Not all great love stories are the same; they just sometimes seem that way in Hollywood, and that isn't necessarily a bad thing. In the new studio release "Tristan &amp; Isolde," the lovers of Celtic mythology, Arthurian legend and Wagnerian libretto fall for each other far from the violent, Dark Ages machinations plaguing their two warring peoples. Tucked in a cave, they find "a place for us" (see "West Side Story"), discover that "parting is such sweet sorrow" ("Romeo and Juliet") and learn, to their peril, that "men and women can't be friends because the sex part always gets in the way" ("When Harry Met Sally"). In between the panting and parting, two young actors are positioned, if somewhat prematurely, for stardom.  Directed by Kevin Reynolds and written by Dean Georgaris, whose toniest credit to date is the unnecessary remake of "The Manchurian Candidate" (he also wrote "Lara Croft Tomb Raider: The Cradle of Life"), "Tristan &amp; Isolde" was once pegged as a project for Ridley Scott, who serves as one of its executive producers. The Sir Ridley connection may help explain the film's fine production values as well as the pervasive air of seriousness, both of which work to its advantage. Mr. Reynolds remains best known for the 1995 debacle "Waterworld" and has directed a handful of features since, most recently the indefensibly diverting "Count of Monte Cristo." Like that earlier period picture, "Tristan &amp; Isolde" has nothing new to say about either love or filmmaking, but that, too, isn't necessarily a bad thing.  Critics often complain that Hollywood has nothing new to offer, but part of the appeal of the old studio system was the regularity of its offerings. One Fred and Ginger movie looks pretty much like another Fred and Ginger movie, only "Swing Time" is better than "Top Hat." We want movies to be different, but not radically so, which helps explain our enduring love for genre and stars. There is something reassuring in the knowledge that a film with Brad Pitt will at least give us the pleasure of his company (though of course you could end up falling asleep to "Meet Joe Black"). Just as there is something undeniably pleasant about an entertainment like "Tristan &amp; Isolde" that delivers exactly what it promises, no less, no more.  To that end, what we get with this very familiar film are the winsome leads - James Franco as Tristan and Sophia Myles as Isolde - reading poetry that hadn't actually been written yet,  seminude in a cozy cave tucked into the Irish coast. Tristan, orphaned by the long battle between the English tribes and the Irish kingdom, has washed up on the emerald isle, wounded and in a state of extremely photogenic distress. Isolde, the daughter of the tyrannical Irish king, Donnchadh (the vigorous scene-chewer David Patrick O'Hara), has carted the wounded warrior into the cave, where she warms his body with hers and heals his wounds with medicinal herbs. Tristan soon recovers, only to fall into a more welcome state of helplessness when he casts eyes on his nurse. Fires are lighted, actual and metaphoric, followed by some discreet lovemaking.  It takes about 30 minutes longer than need be for it to go terribly wrong, but of course it does. Tristan returns home to his lord and surrogate father, Marke (a very effective Rufus Sewell), who is trying to join together the fractious English tribes against the Irish. In a scheme to wrest even more power, Isolde's super-mean father decides to auction her off to the best English warrior, and guess who that turns out to be. Tristan wins Isolde's hand, but not for himself. Isolde marries Marke and scurries around the palace with Tristan, throwing caution and perhaps even the fate of a unified nation to the wind. There are stolen kisses, beautiful hills, rousing battles and noble speeches about duty versus love. Happily, Enya is nowhere to be heard.  You've seen it all before; you'll see it all again.  "Tristan &amp; Isolde" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). There is some fairly bloodless fighting and some very chaste lovemaking.</text>
      <date>January 13, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>