<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  "Tropical Malady" was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Manohla Dargis's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 2. The unrated film, in Thai with English subtitles, opens today at the IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at Third Street, Greenwich Village.  Love is the drug, a game for two and, in the otherworldly Thai film "Tropical Malady," unabashedly strange. A fractured love story about the mystery and impossibility of desire, the film was directed by Apichatpong Weerasethakul, whose earlier features include "Blissfully Yours." Perched between two worlds, two consciousnesses and two radically different storytelling traditions, this new feature shows a young filmmaker pushing at the limits of cinematic narrative with grace and a certain amount of puckish willfulness.  Set in contemporary Thailand, "Tropical Malady" opens with soldiers taking photographs of one another in a field. Shot in the loose, hand-held style of much contemporary documentary, the scene seems perfectly ordinary until you realize that there's a dead body on the ground and that the soldiers are actually snapping trophy shots. The full import of this tableau doesn't become clear until much later, when Mr. Weerasethakul returns us to a similar-looking field (it may be the same one) as if to the scene of a crime. By then, the story's two principal characters, the shy country boy Tong (Sakda Kaewbuadee) and a beautiful soldier named Keng (Banlop Lamnoi), will have been stricken by the tropical malady of the film's title and fallen in love.  When "Tropical Malady" had its premiere at the 2004 Cannes Film Festival, the critical consensus was that the movie was difficult to the point of inscrutability. But the story is, notwithstanding a surprising rupture midway through, nothing if not simple. Most of the first half of the film involves the tentative blossoming of Tong and Keng's romance. In street scenes and country interludes, again shot in the intimate style of hand-held documentary, the men giggle and flirt; they share confidences, meals, music and adventures. As the days slip by imperceptibly, they take Tong's dog to a veterinarian's office, play games in the dark and descend into an underground temple where a small Buddhist icon sits draped in twinkling lights, a tinny recording chirping out Christmas music. Love blooms, however chastely.  Mr. Weerasethakul, who lives in Thailand and studied film and painting at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago, has an appreciation of the more humorous dislocations of globalization, like an aerobics class in the middle of a dusty town. "Tropical Malady" is filled with such minor disruptions (including a woman who talks about ghosts in one breath and "Who Wants to Be a Millionaire" in the next), but the biggest disruption takes place when the storytelling shifts from realism to allegory. Set in the deepest, darkest heart of the jungle, this part of the film finds Keng tracking a ghostly figure who periodically assumes the shape of a tiger. That the figure should turn out to be the soldier's elusive lover, the object of his desire, should come as no surprise. Frankly, I was more taken aback by the talking baboon.  Correction: July 2, 2005, Saturday: A film review on Wednesday about "Tropical Malady," which opened that day at the IFC Center in Greenwich Village, misspelled the name of the actor who plays Keng. (The error also appeared in an article on June 26 about the director of the movie, Apichatpong Weerasethakul, and in a review last Oct. 2, when it was shown at the New York Film Festival.) The actor is Banlop Lomnoi, not Lamnoi. </text>
      <date>June 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>