<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “I don’t want you to think I just used you or anything,” a polite young hunk says to Diane Ford (Michelle Monaghan), moments after their steamy tryst, as she hurries to leave their motel room in the opening scene of “Trucker.” A lean, attractive woman with a hard look in her eye, Diane is in such a rush to get back to work driving an enormous rig that she doesn’t bother to thank the stranger for a good time.  That kind of one-night stand has traditionally been the perquisite of macho kings of the road who drive the same kind of gigantic trucks Diane is shown operating with a brisk efficiency. Seizing a role that a decade ago would have been offered to Ashley Judd, Ms. Monaghan (“Eagle Eye,” “Kiss Kiss Bang Bang,” “Mission Impossible III”) makes the most of her character, a can-do, don’t-waste-my-time kind of gal without a shred of sentimentality, impatiently elbowing her way into a male-dominated occupation.  Diane’s free-spirited life is suddenly complicated when her estranged 11-year-old son, Peter (Jimmy Bennett), is dropped off at her California home without advance notice. The boy’s father, Len (Benjamin Bratt), whom Diane hasn’t seen in more than a decade, is in the hospital with colon cancer. Because his current partner, Jenny (Joey Lauren Adams), has urgent family business to take care of, the boy has nowhere else to stay but with his biological mother.  If Ms. Monaghan gives a possibly award-worthy performance in “Trucker,” the vehicle (if you will pardon the pun) doesn’t quite know what to do with her character. And so the movie, the first feature written and directed by James Mottern, turns into a conventional mother-child reunion drama that stops just short of becoming a fuzzy tear-jerking celebration of the emergence of Diane’s Inner Mom.  Rather than give up work and remain home, Diane decides to take Peter on the road with her. Warily, the mother and son begin to warm to each other. Diane shows that she cares by pitching baseballs to her son and going after some teenagers who harass him at a mini-mall. But she never loses her feisty edge. The movie’s biggest failure is its refusal to allow either mother or son a moment’s reflection about their years apart.  The movie throws in an awkward, underdeveloped subplot involving Diane and her drinking buddy, Runner (Nathan Fillion), a married next-door neighbor who, like every man to cross Diane’s path, is besotted with her. After one barhopping expedition, Diane, who holds her liquor better than most men, bodily drags Runner out of a pickup truck and plops him at his front door.  The truck stops, dispatching offices, highways and unglamorous neighborhoods through which Diane moves with a lithe, confident stride are minimally sketched in a movie that cries out for more detail and pungent atmosphere. When Mr. Bratt, looking seriously peaked, belatedly appears, his abbreviated scene with Ms. Monaghan leaves you wishing for more history about a connection that both agree was sizzling at its outset.  “Trucker” sometimes feels like a performance in search of a movie.  “Trucker” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has one sex scene and some strong language.</text>
      <date>October 9, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>