<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>uring the 28 years that the Berlin Wall stood, countless tunnels were planned as escape passageways from East to West. Roland Suso Richter's "Tunnel," based on harrowing true events, recounts the development of the most famous one, begun in 1961 by a determined, courageous team, whose quest for freedom and reconciliation with family and loved ones was all-consuming. The darkly atmospheric "Tunnel," originally shown on German television in 2001, is as deep and claustrophobic as the hole the group worked so intensely to excavate. Leading the grueling effort is Harry Melchior (Heino Ferch), the new East German swimming champion, whose four years of unjust imprisonment have reinforced his unrelenting anti-Communist beliefs. Refusing to continue competing for his country, he flees to the West as the borders are sealed. Because his sister and her family remain in the East, he prepares a daring rescue operation with the assistance of an engineer, Matthis, and an Italian-American, Vic (Sebastian Koch and Mehmet Kurtulus, in standout performances). They are joined by numerous volunteers hoping to rescue their own friends and family, and by the eager Fritzi (Nicolette Krebitz), whose solitary feminine presence complicates the team's relationships. The constant threat of capture or betrayal and a near-disastrous burst water pipe set the stage for a tension-filled drama. Tightly executed and packed with heroic moments, "The Tunnel" is only disengaging when the mechanics of the epic mission overshadow the characters. (It is possible that something was lost in the 30 minutes that were cut from the original television version.) In one poignant scene we witness two attractive young lovers tragically separated by the 12-inch-thick concrete Berlin Wall. One is dying from a gunshot wound, the other is helpless to reach him. In another scene, two members of the tunnel team discover that an out-of-place section of the wall is actually a prop from an American film being shot there. This alerts them to the outside interest in their plight, and they recruit NBC to provide a camera crew, and money, for their digging mission. Mr. Richter deftly intercuts grainy 16-millimeter black-and-white scenes to bring an immediacy to the inspiring material. By its breathless finale, "The Tunnel" has the emotional grip of the best prison-escape films. Here, the bars may be only metaphorical, except for the massive wall itself, but the film convincingly portrays the devastating, life-altering hardships and restrictions that the residents of the divided Berlin endured.</text>
      <date>April 29, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>