<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> One of the most intriguing (and persuasive) descriptions of how we grow compares our storage of memories, dreams and sensations to the information found on the concentric layers of a redwood tree. Experiences we assimilated at 3, 10, 17, 30,   whatever age: they're all  in a living archive, like the rings of a tree trunk.  Michael Cuesta's film "12 and Holding" flashes a laser beam on a particular ring: the moment between childhood and adolescence when unguarded emotions and fantasies still rule, but adult experience beckons. Until the very end of this poignant, beautifully acted film, when one of its three interwoven stories stretches credibility beyond the breaking point, it allows you to relive  the raw feelings of your 12-year-old self. If you were a sensitive, suburban middle-class geek, that experience could be especially uncomfortable and revelatory.  The film "12 and Holding" explores roughly the same territory Mr. Cuesta covered in his debut project, "L.I.E.," a cleareyed study of alienated Long Island teenagers that broached the subjects of pedophilia and teenage male prostitution.  Mr. Cuesta was one of three screenwriters for "L.I.E."; "12 and Holding" was directed from a first screenplay by Anthony S. Cipriano that is similarly fearless and empathetic with its young subjects.  The movie begins with the kind of shocking event that a typical film about childhood would reserve for much later. Two bullies retaliate against the boys who doused them with a pail of urine dumped from their treehouse. Returning at night with Molotov cocktails, the bullies set it on fire, unaware that it is occupied.  Scrambling to safety from the flames, one of the two tree dwellers, Rudy Carges (Conor Donovan), falls to his death. The other, Leonard Fisher (Jesse Camacho), suffers minor injuries and loses his sense of taste. To the fury of Rudy's parents, Jim (Linus Roache) and Ashley (Jayne Atkinson), the under-age arsonists receive sentences of only one year in juvenile hall and five years' probation.  Rudy's traumatized identical twin, Jacob (also played by Mr. Donovan), would have been in the treehouse had he not balked at the last minute and remained at home. Jacob, unlike Rudy, has a large purple birthmark on one side of his face, which he obscures under a hockey mask. The blemish has left him feeling less loved by his parents, especially his mother, who stews in a murderous fury at the light punishment.  Following Rudy's death, Jacob visits the juvenile prison holding the arsonists and  hurls violent revenge fantasies at one of them, Kenny (Michael Fuchs). But he keeps returning, and over the months a wary  friendship develops between them, partly because in that time Jacob is Kenny's only visitor.  Jacob belongs to a group of three friends, all from the ranks of the uncool, who huddle together for emotional support. Leonard is so obese that his inability to do a single chin-up in gym class prompts his junior high phys ed teacher to pronounce him the most out-of-shape child he has ever met. His life begins to change when that teacher hands him books on nutrition and exercise, and he begins to run.  When Leonard refuses to continue eating the fattening meals cooked by his dangerously obese mother, Grace (Marcia Debonis), she feels threatened and resentful. Out of concern for her health, he eventually takes desperate measures to force her to change her diet. If these scenes are the closest the movie comes to laugh-out-loud comedy, they have a sharply bitter undertone.  Malee Chuang (Zoë Weizenbaum), the third member of the triumvirate, is the pretty half-Asian only child of Carla (Annabella Sciorra), an angry divorced psychotherapist whose ex-husband has no interest in his child. Starved for a father, the girl develops a romantic fixation on Gus Maitland (Jeremy Renner), a former firefighter being treated for depression by Carla.  Malee takes picnic lunches to the construction site where Gus works and even snoops inside his house. Eavesdropping on his therapy sessions, she hears  of his obsession with a Blue Oyster Cult song, which she learns and performs (in another sad/funny moment) at a school talent show he attends. To tempt him into a relationship, she also begins dressing provocatively and wearing makeup.  This is the exceedingly rare film that understands how lonely, insecure preadolescent children can become so consumed by their feelings that they lose sight of ordinary boundaries and unconsciously act out their parents' darkest fantasies of passion and revenge. The movie wastes no time as it shuttles from one drama to another. It also loves its characters.  By observing children's interactions with adults from an emotional perspective that's closer to 12 than 35, it blurs the lines between  child and adult. Grown-up emotions may not be as urgent as those felt by children, but they're essentially the same feelings of pain, longing and rage.  "12 and Holding" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language, a scene of arson and an unusual candor about childhood sexuality.</text>
      <date>May 19, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>