<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “Unaccompanied Minors,” directed by Paul Feig and written by Jacob Meszaros and Mya Stark, presents a nightmarish, dystopian vision of contemporary America in which airline deregulation and the prevalence of divorce have turned our airports into grim holding pens for feral children and embittered workers. Not for the faint of heart, the movie is unsettling and startlingly true to life.  At least that’s how it seemed to me. To the minors I happened to be accompanying, it seemed to be reasonably good fun. Far from horrifying or enraging them, the failure of just about every grown-up except Wilmer Valderrama to behave decently and responsibly filled them with delight, much as the pervasive adult cluelessness provided the movie’s main characters with opportunities for mischief and friendship.  Set on Christmas Eve at a snowed-in Midwestern airport, “Unaccompanied Minors” assembles a squad of familiar adolescent movie types. There’s the nice guy, unfairly labeled a loser (Dyllan Christopher); the rich girl (Gina Mantegna); the angry delinquent girl (Quinn Shephard); the anti-social fat boy (Brett Kelly). In a remarkable feat of economy, the nerd, the black kid and the Jew are all rolled into the agile, jug-eared person of Tyler James Williams. Individually and then collectively, these children run afoul of Oliver Porter (Lewis Black), who is the airport’s director of passenger relations and the movie’s designated Scrooge. His underling, Zach (Mr. Valderrama), is torn between the demands of his boss and his compassion for the kids.  Mr. Black’s fellow alumnus from “The Daily Show,”  Rob Corddry, plays an environmental-activist dad who tries to rescue his children in a biodiesel-powered Mercedes. The explosion of that vehicle is one of a few moments of loud, obvious comic action that seem to have been included to justify the status of “Unaccompanied Minors” as a theatrically released motion picture, rather than the kiddie-cable seasonal special it should have been. In any case, this movie may be too much for sensitive parents to bear. Send your kids alone.  “Unaccompanied Minors” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some crude humor and a few very mild sexual innuendoes.</text>
      <date>December 8, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>