<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The latest bit of damaged goods offered up in the Miramax clearance sale, "Underclassman" plays like the longest episode of "21 Jump Street" ever made. It seems to have been conceived to help its star, Nick Cannon, make the transition from television tweener heartthrob to big-screen action hero. Mr. Cannon, whose idea the whole thing apparently was, has a loose, quick-talking charm - he was delightful in Charles Stone III's "Drumline" - but in this picture he tries on a series of secondhand movie star identities, trying so hard to be the next Will Smith or Eddie Murphy that his own personality all but dissolves.  The movie itself, directed by Marcos Siega from a script by Brent Goldberg and David T. Wagner, is a grinding hodgepodge of threadbare ideas. Even the songs on the soundtrack are out of date, and the picture seems unsure whether it wants to be a kid-friendly comedy or a rough-and-tumble PG-13 cop thriller.  Mr. Cannon plays Tracy (Tre) Stokes, a third-generation Los Angeles police officer who dreams of being an undercover detective but who mostly works beachfront bike patrol. Tre's improvisational approach to law enforcement annoys his grouchy, avuncular commanding officer (Cheech Marin), though not nearly so much as Mr. Cannon's lame one-liners are likely to annoy the audience. In any case, Tre's big chance comes when a student journalist at a fancy West Side private school is murdered, requiring an undercover investigation of the car-stealing and drug-dealing operation that is apparently infesting the school. So Tre talks his way into a group of campus alpha males (led by Shawn Ashmore) and does a bit of sleuthing. He also plays some basketball, indulges in some class clowning and develops a crush on a pretty Spanish teacher (Roselyn Sanchez).  There are a few halfhearted attempts to turn race and class into comedy, including one of the least convincing variations on the white suburban wannabe-black teenager ever committed to film. Apparently the spectacle of pale-skinned folk mangling hip-hop slang is endlessly funny - or at least easy. Fo-shizzle.  The picture's swerve toward equally unimaginative car chases and plot twists comes as something of a relief, though not as much as the sight of the end credits.  "Underclassman" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has violence, profanity and drug-related plot elements.</text>
      <date>September 2, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>