<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Undiscovered," the first film by the music-video director Meiert Avis and the writer John Galt, is about young people in Los Angeles who dream of becoming famous. And since the characters are played by young people who are themselves grasping for celebrity, the picture carries more than a whiff of the self-referential. In other words, if Ashlee Simpson appears to be playing herself, she probably is.  The movie begins in New York City, where the aspiring musician Luke Falcon (played by the musician and actor Steven Strait) has a brief but heart-stopping encounter with a willowy model named Brier (Pell James). More than a year later, they reconnect in Los Angeles, where Luke is pursuing his dream of becoming a singer-songwriter. Brier, despite the misgivings of her motherly agent, Carrie (Carrie Fisher), has come up with the original idea of parlaying her runway skills into an acting career.  Though filled with romantic contrivances and overlong musical numbers, "Undiscovered" is curiously lifeless. Bland actors portray single-cell characters in a plot scarcely more diverting than Ms. Simpson's reality vehicle, "The Ashlee Simpson Show." Here, she is Clea, an acting student who sings (quite a lot, though that probably has nothing to do with the fact that Ms. Simpson's father, Joe Simpson, is one of the film's executive producers).  When not mesmerized by Luke's wayward shirts and artistic integrity, she and Brier scheme to create fake buzz for him on the Internet. This backfires, of course, and Brier is devastated. "All we tried to do was make a nice guy a rock star," she wails. That's just what men love: women trying to run their lives for them.  Ms. Simpson may be a likable lightweight in the acting department, but beside the two leads she's a veritable Dietrich. While Ms. James drifts through the movie looking like an anesthetized Gwyneth Paltrow, Mr. Strait struggles painfully to emote. He should consider taking lessons from Peter Weller, who shows up for five minutes near the end of the film to play Wick Treadway, a hotshot record producer. Even wearing dark glasses and a suspiciously immobile expression, Mr. Weller displays more natural presence than any of his young colleagues; and when he tosses in a Hemingway quote, the moment is sublime. To hear RoboCop quote Hemingway is one of those surreal cinematic pleasures that can illuminate even the dimmest movie.  "Undiscovered" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual material, including dialogue, partial nudity, language and drug content.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>