<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> What would it be like if one day you discovered that you didn't remember anything  —  not your name, the mother who died, the friends who didn't, your lover's caress or the wet kiss of a snowflake on your cheek? Such is the premise of the thought-stirring documentary "Unknown White Male," which recounts the bizarre saga of an East Village loft dweller, Doug Bruce, who in July 2003 walked into a Coney Island hospital claiming not to know who he was, thereupon becoming either a heart-wrenching casualty of a medical anomaly or the prime suspect in a mystery yet to be solved.  That story, worthy of Oliver Sacks, is here told by one of the amnesiac's old friends, Rupert Murray. As he explains in voice-over, Mr. Murray befriended Mr. Bruce some 15  years earlier when the two were living in London  and, to judge by their up-dos in some battered home movies, under the spell of  the band  A Flock of Seagulls. The friendship survived both new-wave follies and Mr. Bruce's move to New York, where he worked as a stockbroker, a lucrative career he left in 1999 to take up photography. Around the same time, Mr. Murray was directing documentaries for Britain's Channel 4 (which commissioned  "Unknown White Male"), making him the right man at the right place.  Or so it would seem. Mr. Murray ticks off a raft of disparate influences for his film, including Man Ray, Andrei Tarkovsky and Luis Buñuel. It's a nice list, but the filmmaker would have done well to mix more documentaries in with his art-house  fare.  Crammed with friendly, sympathetic talking heads and pretty images of a stunned-looking Mr. Bruce, then 35, relearning life (he remembers how to walk but forgot   family and friends), the film comes up frustratingly short when it comes to the particulars. We meet the psychiatrist  who did the intake at the Coney Island hospital, for instance, and the doctor who checks a worrisome tumor, which may or may not have something to do with his memory loss. But conspicuously missing are any firsthand diagnostic discussions.  It's a puzzle why Mr. Murray doesn't include at least one doctor who has treated his friend expressly for his affliction (maybe he forgot), especially given that the ubiquity of amnesia as a narrative device and cultural metaphor makes amateur diagnosticians of us all. In Aki Kaurismaki's deadpan comedy "The Man Without a Past," the fictional title character embarks on a new life after a beating wipes clean his memories. That film opened in New York two months before Mr. Bruce popped up in Coney Island wearing flip-flops and carrying no identification. Like Mr. Kaurismaki's hero, the wanderer became a man not only without a past, but also without a self; from the image of the self-satisfied young man we see in the battered home movies, that may not be such a bad thing.  Documentaries without obvious grinding axes are usually taken at face value, but since its premiere at the 2005 Sundance Film Festival, "Unknown White Male" has received an unusual amount of scrutiny. A few news articles have questioned Mr. Bruce's honesty, suggesting that the film is the latest in mockumentary high jinks. The current  www.gq.com features a Q &amp; A with Mr. Bruce in which the interviewer wonders why the film doesn't include the factoid that he owns property in Panama. Mr. Bruce's wealth isn't interesting per se, but this is the sort of detail that a better filmmaker or perhaps one less personally invested might have used to ask the obvious: Is Mr. Bruce a bored rich guy whose interest in art resulted in a devilishly clever conceptual prank?  Maybe it doesn't matter. Would "Unknown White Male" be better, more watchable and less philosophically resonant if it turned out to be a hoax? I doubt it. The film isn't a document of historical evidence like "Shoah" or a journalistic inquiry in the manner of "The Thin Blue Line"; this is just one man's freaky saga, the kind that gets you to thinking about how our lives are built from wisps of memory and markers of memory like photographs. In this sense, whether Mr. Bruce is telling the truth (for what it's worth, I think he is) or has created a con as baroque as that of JT Leroy is less important than the story itself. Put another way, as Oscar Wilde wrote, "Lying, the telling of beautiful untrue things, is the proper aim of art."  "Unknown White Male" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). There are some salty words.</text>
      <date>February 24, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>