<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Correction Appended  For Luke Shapiro (Josh Peck) the summer of 1994 is a notably eventful time. In retrospect he will no doubt see it as the season when his life, as they say in the movies, changed forever. The movie  he is in, “The Wackness,” written and directed by Jonathan Levine, makes a good-faith effort to steer clear of such clichés, and succeeds and fails in roughly equal measure.  To attempt a story like this — about a young man’s sexual initiation, heartbreak and disillusionment with the adult world that he is about to enter — is to sacrifice a degree of novelty. Mr. Levine tries to compensate with a combination of historical authenticity and low-key emotional sincerity.  In the months between the end of high school and the start of college, a lot certainly happens to Luke, a shy, slack-jawed Upper East Sider who earns his pocket money by selling marijuana. His family is in danger of being evicted from its apartment. He spends a night in jail. The main thing, though, is that Luke falls in love with Stephanie (Olivia Thirlby), whose stepfather, Dr. Squires (Ben Kingsley), is both Luke’s psychiatrist and one of his clients. (It’s a barter arrangement, one kind of therapy exchanged for another.)  Stephanie is a popular girl, and Luke is a social misfit, but the main difference between them may be temperamental. She is a relatively optimistic, hedonistic soul, whereas he is a brooder and a worrier for whom the bong is always half empty. Or, as Stephanie puts it in a bit of dialogue that gives the film its title: “I look at the dopeness. You look at the wackness.”  “The Wackness” has its share of both. The wack side is exemplified by Luke and Stephanie’s self-conscious use of mid-’90s hip-hop slang, a verbal tic matched by a few too many fetishistic period details. Did I mention that the movie takes place in 1994? If that all-important fact slips your mind, Mr. Levine will supply plenty of reminders, from the shell-toed Adidas sneakers on Luke’s feet to the dropped names of Kurt Cobain, Notorious B.I.G., Forrest Gump and Rudolph W. Giuliani. Those were the days, right? No doubt. But the fussed-over precision of the historical moment feels more like a gimmick than a source of insight, much as the dreamy haze cast over Manhattan by Petra Korner’s cinematography looks like a ready-made, one-size-fits-all cloak of nostalgia.  But don’t think I’m forgetting the dopeness, which resides mainly in the idiosyncrasy of the characters and the skill of the actors portraying them. Lately Mr. Kingsley has been so busy as to seem indiscriminate, taking oddball roles in movies big and small, decent and dreadful — “BloodRayne”? “The Love Guru”? Sir Ben, really!  Even in the lamest vehicle, however, he is almost always a delight to watch. Dr. Squires, by turns squirrelly reckless, with a less than firm grip on his marriage (to a dazed and tragic Famke Janssen), reality and the will to live, is perhaps the most preposterous character in “The Wackness,” and for just that reason the most intriguingly plausible. The doctor is, for his young patient and pot supplier, both a mentor and mascot. His evident untrustworthiness makes him the only grown-up in whom Luke has any faith.  As gossip-minded readers may already know, Mr. Kingsley makes out with Mary-Kate Olsen, who in 1994, at the age of 8, was nearing the end of her run in “Full House.”  Her character here, a stoner named Union, is part of a supporting cast of eccentrics and urban curiosities — Method Man and Jane Adams are two more — who pleasantly divert “The Wackness” from its main narrative purpose.  Not that the tentative, transient romance between Luke and Stephanie is without interest. Mr. Levine is careful not to overstate the melodrama of young love, allowing Luke’s own longing and confusion to set the tone. Mr. Peck, formerly a star of the Nickelodeon tweener sitcom “Drake and Josh,” works a little too hard to convey the tension between Luke’s outward affectlessness and the riot of feeling inside. He shows great seriousness and potential as an actor, but he also shows too much of what he has learned in acting class.  Ms. Thirlby, meanwhile, who had a few nice scenes in “Juno,” does a fine job, as she did in “Snow Angels,” of playing the smart adolescent seductress of a teenage loner. I hope the angst mongers of the independent film world can find a leading role that will test her talents and show the full extent of her dopeness.  “The Wackness” is rated R (Under 17 requires parent or adult guardian). Back in the ’90s New York teenagers swore, had sex and smoked pot. Thank goodness that’s all over.</text>
      <date>July 3, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>