<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Waist Deep," directed by Vondie Curtis Hall, is unapologetically a B movie, its narrative premise whittled down to a mean little nub and placed carefully on the borderline between the wildly implausible and the completely absurd. Its hero, a former gangster known as O2 (Tyrese Gibson), is knocked off his post-prison commitment to the straight and narrow by the kidnapping of his young son (H. Hunter Hall).  With the occasional help of his unpredictable cousin Lucky (Larenz Tate) and the more steadfast though initially reluctant assistance of a beautiful hustler named Coco (Meagan Good), O2 does what any father would. He incites a gang war in the streets of Los Angeles and hits a few banks while he's at it, before finally collecting the payback he is owed by the machete-wielding one-eyed villain, an uber-criminal named Big Meat (the hip-hop star the Game).  Mr. Hall, an actor whose other directorial efforts include the Mariah Carey vehicle "Glitter" and "Redemption," which starred Jamie Foxx as the former gang leader Tookie Williams, transacts this bit of genre business with an aggressive sense of style and a surprising dose of sentiment. The swiveling, jittery camera movements, the extreme, off-center close-ups and the attention to urban geography recall "Collateral," Michael Mann's recent exercise in nocturnal Los Angeles noir.  It may be that "Waist Deep," beautifully shot by Shane Hurlbut, looks better than it is. There is plenty here to make you roll your eyes or glance at your watch. But hovering over the fistfights, gun battles and car chases is an aura of melancholy: a blend of frustration, fatigue and paternal guilt that is interesting and unusual.  Yes, this strain of feeling culminates in one of the most audaciously maudlin endings this side of "Beaches."  But the film's first scene, in which O2 rushes from his job as a department store security guard to pick up Junior, stopping to buy him a toy on the way out, has an emotional impact that may prove hard to shake.  Mr. Gibson's sheer physical presence — he has the gravity of a carved and polished block of stone — can sometimes overshadow his skill as an actor, and can sometimes bring it into high relief. You might not expect flashes of sweetness, anxiety or deadpan humor from someone so muscular and imposing, but there they are. Ms. Good, for her part, is less convincing when the script (by Mr. Hall and Darin Scott) calls for deep maternal feeling than when it requires theatrical displays of seductiveness or brass.  There is some wit in the movie as well, an undercurrent of the tart social insight that distinguished the best of the early blaxploitation pictures. O2 and Coco's lightning crime spree — three banks in a single day, plus a few scams and home invasions — takes place while the streets are full of angry citizens protesting gang violence. The social critic and scholar Michael Eric Dyson is heard on the radio, and the current police chief and mayor of Los Angeles are called out by name. For a time the two fugitives — "a modern-day Bonnie and Clyde," according to an admiring convenience store clerk — hole up in an elegant Modernist house in the Hollywood Hills, a retreat that emphasizes the chasms of racial and class inequality that define the Southern California landscape.  Whatever its throwaway title is supposed to mean, "Waist Deep" is not as shallow as you might expect.  "Waist Deep" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has pervasive violence and profanity.</text>
      <date>June 23, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>