<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>he director Eytan Fox had an unexpected international success in 2002 with "Yossi and Jagger," a gay love story set against the unlikely backdrop of the Israel Defense Forces. With "Walk on Water," his third feature-length film, Mr. Fox takes on the even more controversial subject of Israeli nationalism in the aftermath of the Holocaust. In fact, there isn't much that "Walk on Water" doesn't take on, from global terrorism and Israeli-Palestinian relations to homophobia in the Mossad, the Israeli security service. Eyal (Lior Ashkenazi) is a Mossad special agent with a brusque, sardonic manner and a marked lack of sentiment for the terrorists he targets for assassination; asked to speculate on their motivations, he barks, "What's to think? They're animals." After an unexpected tragedy in Eyal's personal life, his supervisor (Gidon Shemer) sends him on an unusual assignment: to track down a Nazi war criminal in hiding, Eyal must pose as a tour guide to spy on the old man's adult grandchildren. This brother-and-sister pair, Axel and Pia (wonderfully played by Knut Berger and Carolina Peters), are just the sort of well-meaning bourgeois liberals that grate on Eyal's nerves, but as he drives Axel around the historical sites of Israel, he begins to feel an affinity for the gentle, soft-spoken boy. When Axel drags his host to a gay bar (and adds insult to injury by flirting with a Palestinian Arab), the macho Eyal withdraws abruptly, asking to be removed from the case. But later Eyal makes a trip to Germany that forces both men to reconsider their political and erotic allegiances. "Walk on Water" is an odd bird, a slight-feeling indie film that slowly builds into a substantial meditation on contemporary politics, sexual and otherwise. Though it is marred by an implausible climax and a cloying conclusion, this movie's quiet intelligence sneaks up on you, marking the director as a talent to watch.</text>
      <date>March 4, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>