<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Nothing in Paul Schrader’s film “The Walker” can quite match its delicious opening scene of sniping repartee over canasta among three Washington grandes dames and their pet gay playmate. Lynn (Kristin Scott Thomas), Natalie (Lauren Bacall) and Abigail (Lily Tomlin) constitute what may be the screen’s most formidable threesome of jaded, dirt-dishing socialites since “The Women.”  Ms. Bacall’s Natalie has the film’s toughest bons mots.  Marrying for money, she cracks in her brandied baritone, is the hardest job:  “You don’t get the money; you get to look at it.” Ms. Scott Thomas’s Lynn seethes with the chilled rage of a neglected wife. Ms. Tomlin’s gaunt, hollow-eyed Abigail personifies the political spouse as ferocious watchdog.  As the fourth card player, Carter Page III, the scion of a Virginia political dynasty that reached a pinnacle of respectability during the Watergate hearings, Woody Harrelson executes a spectacular pirouette away from his usual hot-wired renegades. Playing a bewigged, forked-tongue charmer drooling gossip inside this viper’s nest, he drops nuggets like his signature line, “I’m not naïve, I’m superficial,” in the languid, insinuating tone of a Southern courtier. Carter, who dabbles in real estate and decorating and favors too-tight double-breasted suits, relishes his role of “walker,” a platonic escort to the wives of boorish Washington power players who can’t be bothered to attend cultural and social functions.  If it is all overdone, that’s how Mr. Schrader likes his decadence; ripe and toxic, it seeps through the gold-trimmed furniture and into the water supply. Without being overtly political or naming names, “The Walker” portrays contemporary Washington as a cesspool of soullessness, hypocrisy, greed and antiquated social attitudes. Its brutal realpolitik is personified by Abigail’s husband, Jack Delorean (Ned Beatty), a greasy-haired fat cat and behind-the-scenes manipulator who will do whatever it takes to do whatever is necessary.  “The Walker” is the third part of Mr. Schrader’s so-called lonely man trilogy, which began in 1980 with “American Gigolo” and continued 12 years later with “Light Sleeper.” Carter is the spiritual descendant of Julian Kaye, the Hollywood stallion for hire played as a noble fool by Richard Gere in “Gigolo.” Both are innocents who fancy themselves sophisticates.  When scandal threatens to ruin the party at which their services come in handy, they are sacrificed to the wolves by their fancy, fair-weather friends. Carter’s self-defining slogan should be reversed to read: “I’m not superficial. I’m naïve.”  Like “American Gigolo,” “The Walker” unfortunately finds it necessary to attach a juicy social microcosm to a clunky mystery thriller whose antihero finds himself the chief suspect in a murder. Carter’s troubles begin when he chauffeurs Lynn, his closest friend among the card players and the wife of a senator, to the home of her lover (Steven Hartley), a financial wheeler-dealer.  While Carter loyally waits in the car to take her home, Lynn returns in great agitation, having found her boyfriend’s dead body on the living room floor. Fearful of a scandal, she refuses to report the crime and begs Carter to cover for her. He agrees and returns later to “discover” the body and contact the police.  Immediately he is the chief suspect, and already the film’s machinery has begun to creak. Carter is hounded by an ambitious district attorney (William Hope) and by a detective (Geff Francis) speaking tin-eared dialogue. A meeting between Carter and Lynn’s husband (an ill-used Willem Dafoe) is laughably sketchy.  The awkward scenes between Carter, who begins investigating the murder, and his German-Turkish lover Emek Yoglu (Moritz Bleibtreu), generate no emotional heat. A tabloid paparazzo who wants Carter to use his connections to help him break into art photography, Emek sleuths on his computer and unearths enough information to get himself followed to a gay bar and beaten up as a warning. The ominous gay-bar ambience feels about 30 years out of date, as do the  songs featuring the shivery voice of Bryan Ferry.  By the end of “The Walker” a movie that begins as a dazzling round of charades has deteriorated into a plodding game of Clue.  “The Walker” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity.</text>
      <date>December 7, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>