<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> I hope you will forgive me for saying so - and I hope the filmmakers will forgive me, too - but "Wallace and Gromit: The Curse of the Were-Rabbit" has forced me to ponder the deepest mysteries of cinema. Why, for instance, do certain faces haunt and move us as they do?  I am thinking of Gromit, the mute and loyal animated dog whose selflessness and intelligence can be counted on, when things get really crazy, to save the day. Gromit has no mouth, and yet his face is one of the most expressive ever committed to the screen. In particular, his brow - a protuberance overhanging his spherical, googly eyes - is an almost unmatched register of emotion. Resignation, worry, tenderness and disgust all come alive in that plasticine nub. To keep matters within the DreamWorks menagerie, you might compare Gromit to Shrek, who has the genetic advantages of Mike Myers's Scots burr, a bevy of celebrity-voiced sidekicks and rivals, and state-of-the-art computer-animation technology. Good for him. But Gromit, made by hand and animated by a painstaking stop-motion process, has something Shrek will never acquire in a hundred sequels: a soul.  And this unassuming pooch's feature film debut, after appearances in three sublime half-hour shorts, is thus a solemn occasion (even if the movie itself is utterly silly). His face now enters the pantheon of stars whose charisma transcends speech. Keaton, Chaplin, Garbo - let them now make room for Gromit. Which is in no way to slight Wallace, his entrepreneurial owner, who speaks in the voice of Peter Sallis and who personifies all the traditional virtues of the provincial English middle class. (His shortcomings are entirely his own, of course.)  Anyway, "The Curse of the Were-Rabbit" finds master and hound running a pest-control company specializing in the humane disposal of rabbits. These creatures are infesting the local gardens on the eve of an important vegetable competition, imperiling giant pumpkins and carrots as well as Gromit's prize melon.  Sheltering the bunnies threatens to overwhelm Wallace and Gromit's modest household, and so Wallace invents a device that will cure their craving for fresh produce, with predictably disastrous results. What I mean is that it is predictable that the results will be disastrous, but the particular shape of the disaster springs with delightful surprise from the imaginations of Nick Park and Steve Box, who directed the film, and Mark Burton and Bob Baker, with whom they wrote it. They have also assembled a fine supporting cast of bounders, ninnies and local biddies, notably a pompadoured villain named Victor (voiced by Ralph Fiennes) and his aristocratic would-be fiancée, the flame-haired, green-thumbed Lady Tottington (trilled by Helena Bonham Carter), otherwise known as Totty.  That nickname is mildly naughty British slang, and there are a few other hints of bawdiness in the movie, adding a dash of Benny Hill vulgarity that is entirely appropriate to its sensibility. The animation is a marvel - all the more so because the most demanding sequences seem almost casually tossed off. The world of Wallace and Gromit is one of the few genuinely eccentric places left in the movies, a place where lumpy, doughy characters achieve a peculiar dignity in spite of their grotesque features and the ridiculousness of their circumstances.  It is a world I have been longing to revisit ever since my children wore out the tapes of "A Close Shave" (formerly known in our house as "the one with the mean dog"), "The Wrong Trousers" ("the one with the mean bird") and "A Grand Day Out" ("the one when they go to the moon"). I was a bit worried that more superficially sophisticated pleasures - "Lizzie Maguire" or whatever tweener sitcoms the kids are into these days - had eroded the appeal of Wallace and Gromit, but I need not have. We all had a marvelous time. Perhaps it was the giant furry were-rabbit, or maybe the twinkle of romance between Wallace and Totty, or even the uplifting and nutritious pro-vegetable message (which resonates with the implicit vegetarianism of Mr. Park and Peter Lord's "Chicken Run"). All of that and more, I'm sure. But for me, most of all, it was Gromit's forehead, which gave me renewed appreciation for the magic of movies. If only I had a dog like that.</text>
      <date>October 5, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>