<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> In 2002, the Israeli government began constructing what it calls a security fence. Located some eight miles east of the Mediterranean, this barrier runs more or less - how much more and how much less is a matter of intense dispute - along the 1949 armistice line (or Green Line)  that divides Israel from the West Bank. That this more than 400-mile proposed stretch of asphalt, wire, trenches and concrete summons up the Berlin Wall is just one of its many wrenching paradoxes. More wrenching still is that it effectively drives yet another wedge between Israelis and Palestinians.  The French filmmaker Simone Bitton takes a measured look at the barrier in her documentary "Wall,"  a film that considers hard-core political realities alongside agonizing personal truths. A self-described Arab Jew, Ms. Bitton was born in Morocco, educated at a French school and partly brought up in Israel. She has said that she completed her military service during the Yom Kippur War in 1973, and the experience turned her into a lifelong pacifist. She attended a prestigious French film school  and now lives in Paris and Jerusalem, returning to Morocco when she can and making documentaries about Middle Eastern subjects. One such film, "The Bombing," traces the effects of a Palestinian suicide bombing in Jerusalem on the families of both the perpetrators and their victims.  The very name of her latest  film indicates that Ms. Bitton isn't interested in playing the familiar documentary game of feigned impartiality. The Israeli Defense Ministry calls the barrier a security fence (and an antiterrorist fence),  but it is usually called a wall by its detractors. Everyone in the world seems to have an opinion: it has also been called an "apartheid wall" (Al Jazeera), "a racial separation wall" (the Arab League)  and "unlawful" (Britain's foreign secretary, Jack Straw).  As might be expected, given both its impact on the surrounding populations and the history of the Jewish state, discussions about the barrier tend to be contentious, extremely partisan and, on occasion,  fraught with ugly undertones, as one 2004 headline in The Guardian made abundantly clear: "Israelis Hasten Land Grab in Shadow of Wall."  The barrier fills Ms. Bitton with anguish, but perhaps because she straddles two identities and speaks from both sides of the divide (or perhaps because she studied in France), she tempers her despair with cool intellect and appreciable irony. Laying her cards on the table, she opens the film with a traveling shot of a concrete section of the barrier covered in bright, Matisse-like figures and doves. Initially, the only sounds are laughing children and chirping birds. "What's this?" an unseen woman suddenly says. "The wall," answers a young girl, also off-camera." "What for?" asks the woman. "They shoot Arabs from here," says the girl. "No," says a second girl, "Arabs shoot at us." The woman, whom we will later recognize as Ms. Bitton, then asks, "Who shoots at who?"  This last question reverberates throughout the film as Ms. Bitton speaks with Israelis and Palestinians grappling with and occasionally breaching the barrier. All the discussions are eye-opening  - the Iraqi who longs to return home because life is easier there; the Israeli who struck up a friendship with a Palestinian, whom, because of the barrier, he has never met. The most startling interviews, however, are those with  Amos Yaron, the director general of  Israel's Defense Ministry, who makes the government's case for the fence, and with a kibbutz dweller named Shuli Dichter. As he drives inside the West Bank gesturing at the fruit trees and dusty hills, Mr. Dichter speaks of the "mad love" Israelis have for the land and how those who survived the shtetls and ghettos of Lodz settled a country defined by "closure and enclosure."  Ms. Bitton does not respond to Mr. Dichter's comments, at least not directly. Instead, in a powerful series of images that close her film, she points her camera at the barrier and waits for it to reveal truths that cannot be measured in kilometers and policy. What she shows us, simply, are people talking with one another through gaps in the barrier and clambering over the concrete and barbed wire, while a (presumably Israeli) helicopter hovers above. Whatever you believe about the barrier, its effectiveness and its meaning, the images of these men and women contravening this costly, ostensibly secure edifice  - including the couple who pass their baby from one side to the other  -  underscore that there are few things in the world stronger than the human will.</text>
      <date>August 26, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>