<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>Set during an unspecified ancient time in the seldom-captured picturesque locales of India's northwestern desertland and the western Himalayas, Asif Kapadia's feature debut, "The Warrior," which sat on Miramax's overstocked shelves for close to four years, is a minimalist but strikingly beautiful tale of renounced violence told with uncommon precision and depth. The title warrior, Lafcadia (Irfan Khan), is a longtime indentured servant and executioner whose livelihood consists of ravaging small villages - and their women - with his menacing gang of brutes. During a routine pillaging, he experiences a flash of clarity and resolves to never again pick up a sword. But his vicious warlord master immediately retaliates by calling for the head of Lafcadia and the death of his disloyal servant's only son. Instead of becoming a typical revenge-driven killfest like many of the westerns that were clear inspirations for this film, it develops into a rich journey of repentance, redemption and acceptance of fate. Accompanying the warrior on a meditative trek to his birthplace is an intuitive elderly blind woman (Damayanti Marfatia) and a young thief (Noor Mani), a lost though spirited teenage boy whose family has been murdered (perhaps by the hand of the warrior himself). They come to embody hope and a newfound familial presence for the grieving warrior who at first can barely muster the strength to continue. The themes explored in "The Warrior" are less than groundbreaking,  but the mesmerizing portrayal of a beaten man - and a true victim of his times - by Mr. Khan, one of the few professional actors in the cast, makes it all somehow fresh. His worn, gruffly handsome face, with big bags under the eyes, oozes pain and remorse. But because his barbaric acts are never shown, Lafcadia is probably more sympathetic than he deserves to be. Despite a measured pace, "The Warrior," with its lush imagery and sweeping score, is powerful and gripping, without ever resorting to easy spectacle. In fact, the most extensive swordplay occurs during the gracefully choreographed opening credits, featuring only Lafcadia and his blade. When the warrior grasps the full magnitude of his sins, while passing through a recently plundered town, he stares dejectedly as if seeing the ghosts of everyone he has killed. It's an incredibly moving scene, one that reminds audiences that an expression can be more eloquent than words - and a contemplative movie more hard-hitting than numbing depictions of violence. "The Warrior" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes adult themes and some violence.</text>
      <date>July 15, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>