<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> More than a decade after Larry Clark's "Kids" scandalized the movie world with its quasi-documentary portrait of New York skateboarders and the virgins they deflower, he is still pushing buttons with his lubricious insider's view of teenage life.  A filmmaker, photographer and besotted observer of sex and death on the adolescent fringe, Mr. Clark  pointedly photographs young flesh with the  drooling concentration  of a chicken hawk. Although he might say his purpose isn't to turn viewers on but to capture the intense physical reality of adolescent experience, there is more erotic energy floating through his films than in a hundred laboriously obtained  orgasms from a pornographic loop. Watching his films can make anyone over 30 feel like a dirty old whatever.  In "Wassup Rockers," his camera caresses the wet lips and smooth torsos of a pack of Hispanic skateboarders from South Central Los Angeles as they cruise the city looking for the perfect slope. Deliberately blurring the line between fiction and documentary, this handsomely photographed film leads off with an interview with its teenage star, Jonathan Velasquez, who mumbles about his life and early sexual experiences.  Mr. Velasquez, who plays a character named Jonathan, is the prettiest and most prominently featured of the movie's untrained actors, all playing versions of themselves. As the group's seven members   travel from their ravaged graffiti-scarred neighborhood of gangbangers and drive-by shootings to Beverly Hills, the story's romantic conceit is that they are only exchanging one hell for another.  Because these lollipop angels with dirty faces are pointedly different from the adolescent nihilists Mr. Clark normally tracks, "Wassup Rockers" has an upbeat lilt; it might almost be called a comedy. As they dash down boulevards and leap over walls and fences, tossing their skateboards ahead of them, the movie recalls such antic frolics as "A Hard Day's Night;" no one stands still for long.  For all the horrors they have seen in South Central, Mr. Clark's magnificent seven are holy innocents whose passion for skateboarding and group solidarity has kept them immune to the decay and corruption around them. With their mops of hippie-length hair and tight pants, they are outsiders in their own community, taunted and menaced by their gun-toting African-American peers who carry guns inside their baggy hip-hop uniforms.  Jonathan, who idolizes the Ramones, sings lead in a punk-rock band. Kico (Francisco Pedrasa), the most endearing of the seven, when asked where he's from, guilelessly replies, "I'm from the ghetto."  Their 24-hour journey from one jungle to another and back begins when they drive a borrowed car to Beverly Hills to skate the "nine steps," a famous local challenge that involves leaping over a concrete stairway and remaining vertical upon landing. But on the way, the boys, who have neither licenses nor registration, are stopped and intimidated by a stereotypically menacing and racist Los Angeles policeman, who arrests one of them.  Undeterred, they take the bus to their destination, where they are lustfully ogled by two sleek, high-school-age babes, one of whom invites Jonathan to visit her mansion. Scary policemen,  girls with dirty minds and their arrogant, hateful boyfriends  are only the first in a series of increasingly grotesque monsters encountered by visitors whom the movie   wants to portray as incorruptible.  Chased from one fancy house to the next, they crash a party whose flamboyantly gay host, a physique photographer, follows Jonathan to the bathroom and peeks through the keyhole, then leeringly offers "career" advice. A gaunt, drunken housewife drags Kico into a hot tub for sudsy horseplay. As the boys retreat, a high-powered film director who suggests a Clint Eastwood-Charlton Heston hybrid pulls out a gun and casually shoots one of them.  By now there are only five of the original seven.   They are rescued from hell by a sympathetic group of Hispanic maids from the neighborhood who enlist a friend to spirit them back to South Central in his pickup truck.  However you respond to "Wassup Rockers," it is completely alive, unlike any number of teenage Hollywood movies with their stale formulas and second-hand puerility. And that's mostly to the good.  "Wassup Rockers" is rated R (under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has violence, sexual situations and profanity.</text>
      <date>June 23, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>