<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> After watching the documentary “We Live in Public,” a hyperventilated account of the rise and weird fall of the dot-com millionaire turned self-declared artist Josh Harris, you might want to run home, lower all the shades and unplug yourself from the Internet. Certainly Mr. Harris, who earned a sizable fortune from different Internet ventures only to become increasingly consumed with issues of privacy, control and surveillance — a complex of obsessions that helped him lose much of  that fortune — could have used some alone time.  Mr. Harris is now apparently living in Ethiopia,   where he runs  an outfit called African Entertainment Network and remains, as he says in the movie, far from the reach of his creditors.  In 1986 he founded Jupiter  Communications, an early Internet analysis and consulting firm. In 1994, after making a tidy profit from the sale of that company, he created  Pseudo Programs, an online television company that, because broadband was still years away, was the right idea with the wrong technology. That company filed for bankruptcy   when the dot-com bubble burst in 2000, but by then Mr. Harris was  suffering his own meltdown, at times while made up like a clown called Luvvy, named after a character on “Gilligan’s Island.”  “Gilligan’s Island” wasn’t just Mr. Harris’s favorite show when he was a child: it also turns out to have been a guidepost for his life. Yet while Gilligan and the rest of the castaways ran accidentally aground during a storm, Mr. Harris appears to have in part steered his life into the shoals through ruinously expensive follies. In the first he sealed some 100  volunteers in a bunker in Manhattan wired with cameras and outfitted with guns. He called this 1999 project “Quiet: We Live in Public,” though it was anything but. Over their month of confinement these pod people turned progressively rowdier, letting it all hang out, sometimes while weeping and screaming, for the viewing pleasure of the other inhabitants.  Mr. Harris invited Ondi Timoner, the director and writer of “We Live in Public,” to shoot the experiment, which explains the wealth of images in this movie. Some of the more disturbing ones invoke the bullying techniques of discredited self-help groups like EST. The bunker itself suggests a wired version of a model prison designed by the 18th-century British philosopher Jeremy Bentham that he called the Panopticon, which allows a guardian to watch inmates who, because of the structure’s design, can never see that they’re being observed. This constant surveillance would become an instrument of control because the prisoners, not knowing if they were being watched, would, out of uncertainty, behave as if they were. Not surprisingly, Bentham’s design has become a favorite metaphor for life in the surveillance age.  Although the men and women in “Quiet” knew they were being observed, the ubiquity of the cameras and monitors meant that their actions were part of a visual stream that blurred their individual actions, turning them into an undifferentiated mass. It’s no wonder that some of the participants Ms. Timoner later interviewed likened the experience to fascism. Mr. Harris wasn’t a fascist, of course, just a manipulator of sizable economic means whose motivations,  ethics  and sanity were all in question. He compared himself to  Warhol, an analogy some journalists ignorantly parroted, but he comes off as a rich bully who enjoyed buying other people’s time and even their tears. (In the movie’s production notes he is described as a “professional artist.”)  Mr. Harris continued his experimentation on a more intimate level with his girlfriend, Tanya Corrin, with whom he lived online  in constant view of anyone with a computer. There were cameras in the bedroom, the litter box and even the toilet bowl, a vantage point that offered viewers images that perhaps more than most revealed how Mr. Harris felt about other people. The happy couple soon soured, turning to the project’s chat room for company and later relationship solace. As she does with the “Quiet”  project, Ms. Timoner weaves in chunks of this increasingly unpleasant second endeavor, weliveinpublic.com, with a cacophony of music and colorful graphics along with witnesses who, against the odds, try to wring sense from Mr. Harris’s mess.  Ms. Timoner questions his mental health, but she doesn’t seriously engage with the issues her documentary raises, including whether the right to privacy will survive given how eagerly so many now surrender themselves to the camera. At one point she describes “Quiet”  as a metaphor for how Mr. Harris believed we would live in the Internet age. Later, citing the example of how online sites mine our data, she asserts: “We all willingly share this information. We enjoy the attention, the feedback, the comments.”  We do and we don’t, but she doesn’t explore the nuances. From the ample evidence, Mr. Harris’s own life in public was a bust. Ms. Timoner  sees him as a cautionary tale as well as a visionary; what I see is that, as with many things, too much “Gilligan’s Island” can be bad for you.</text>
      <date>August 28, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>