<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Venture capitalist: that’s the misleading job description preferred by the title character of the slight and silly “Wendell Baker Story.” Wendell (Luke Wilson), a cheerful Texan slacker, runs a profitable operation on the Tex-Mex border selling fake driver’s licenses to illegal  migrant workers.  Wendell, who works with a partner, Reyes (Jacob Vargas), out of an Airstream trailer he calls the Ellis Island of the Southwest, means no harm. A Panglossian eternal teenager at heart, he is madly in love with his girlfriend, Doreen (Eva Mendes). She, however, is running out of patience with his protracted adolescence.  This shambling, good-natured comedy is a Wilson family affair. Written by Luke Wilson, who directed with his older brother Andrew, it also stars a third brother, Owen, as Wendell’s nemesis. The appeal of “The Wendell Baker Story” depends on how charming you find the Wilson brothers, with their chipmunk grins and hip smart-aleck attitude. For my taste, a little goes a long way. But if you like Lyle Lovett songs, Thomas McGuane novels and sardonic country yarns sung by grizzled Texan “outlaws,” you’ll have no trouble slipping into its easygoing groove, fortified by its country-rock soundtrack. Smirks are to be had, but no belly laughs.  Wendell knows how to make the best of a dicey situation. Caught by the Border Patrol and sent to prison, he negotiates peace between the Crips and the Aryan Brotherhood while studying hotel management, an ideal occupation for someone with his obvious people skills.  Love, though, is another matter. Doreen has had enough. She deserts him, only to reappear much later, when Wendell spots her photo at a supermarket whose manager (an uncredited, very funny Will Ferrell) is her possessive new boyfriend. The Shady Grove retirement hotel, where Wendell begins his postprison career, isn’t exactly the Austin Hilton or even a Holiday Inn. It is a decrepit palace whose head nurse, Neil King (Owen Wilson), runs a Medicare fraud scam in which he and his partner, McTeague (Eddie Griffin), bilk selected residents of their benefits by giving them what they call “the Greyhound treatment.”  It isn’t clear how it works, except that those chosen are dispatched to his mother’s farm in the middle of nowhere where they do heaven knows what. There are intimations that it is a slave labor camp from which there is no exit. Neil’s fearsome mother, Wanda (Jo Harvey Allen), a glaring, trigger-happy termagant, patrols the place with a rifle. To delve deeper into the scheme would break the prevailing tongue-in-cheekiness.  ”The Wendell Baker Story” is also a salute to grumpy old men, but with a transgressive twist. In Texas at least, grumpy old men appears to mean dirty old men who trumpet their undiminished virility in gravelly Willie Nelson voices, flicks of the tongue and beady-eyed babe-ogling. At Shady Grove, Wendell befriends two such roués, Skip Summers (Harry Dean Stanton) and Boyd Fullbright (Seymour Cassel), lifelong best friends champing at the bit for some action. The scenes of these sly silver foxes drooling over two 16-year-old girls behind the counter of a convenience store celebrate rakish seniority with unabashed glee.  When gaunt, hawk-eyed Skip boasts about his prowess, the girls’ ears perk up.  Under Wendell’s tutelage, Summer and Boyd team up with Nasher (Kris Kristofferson), a mysterious Shady Grove resident who suggests a benign Howard Hughes, to liberate the farm and engineer Neil’s downfall. As the movie winds down, it softens into an earthbound, feel-good answer to “Cocoon.”    “The Wendell Baker Story” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual situations and off-color humor. </text>
      <date>May 18, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>