<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> On a show like “The Wire,” policemen and criminals belong to competitive organizations locked in uneasy, permanent coexistence. In “We Own the Night,”  James Gray’s operatic new film, the police and drug dealers are imagined as warring tribes in a fight to the death. The Russian gangsters on one side appear ready to take out the entire N.Y.P.D. (“We get them all!”) And some of the cops are just as eager to forgo the legal niceties and do some righteous killing of their own (“Wipe ’em out. No survivors.”).  In other words, “We Own the Night” is not a procedural, in which the narrative is threaded through details of the job and close observations of big-city life. It is, rather, a bloody, passionate melodrama, self-consciously Shakespearean — or Biblical, or Greek, take your pick of atavisms — in its intentions. At the center are two brothers: Joseph Grusinsky (Mark Wahlberg), a clean-cut, ambitious family man rising quickly through the ranks of the department, and Bobby Green (Joaquin Phoenix), who has forsaken the family surname and who manages a raucous nightclub in Brooklyn.  Cain and Abel; the ant and the grasshopper. Bobby and Joseph present, at least at first, wildly contrasting temperaments as well as divergent career choices. Joseph takes after their father, Burt (Robert Duvall), a high-ranking officer who can barely contain his disappointment and disgust when Bobby is in the room. But Bobby, while he may be as irresponsible as his father and brother think he is, also has a sweet, impulsive, hedonistic side. He shows it in an early scene of sexual bliss with his girlfriend, Amada (Eva Mendes), and in the way he bounces through his cavernous club and into the apartment of its owner, a grandfatherly Russian named Buzhayev. Bobby is loving, and also lovable.  But he is also, within the film’s fatalistic universe, a traitor, or at least a prodigal who must be brought back into the fold. Much as he may revel in the company of his surrogate family — the Buzhayev clan is warm and welcoming, and Bobby’s sidekick Jumbo (Danny Hoch) is a bubbly fountain of brotherly affection — the claims of blood are always stronger. And once Mr. Buzhayev’s gangster nephew Vadim (Alex Veadov) causes Joseph to be hurt, Bobby puts away his childish sense of fun and gets down to the grim business of settling scores.  As this happens, the life begins to leak out of “We Own the Night,” and especially out of Mr. Phoenix’s performance. In the actor’s case, this seems deliberate, as if he had chosen to interpret grief as a form of petrifaction. His elbows and shoulders stiffen, and he lumbers across the sets like a Frankenstein monster. Even his tongue seems paralyzed. Mr. Gray, meanwhile, strides manfully into a thicket of clichés and heavy grandiosity.  When it works, though — especially in those earlier scenes, when Bobby and Joseph are at each other’s throats (and Bobby and Amada are in each other’s pants), and in a brilliantly executed car chase later on —  “We Own the Night” demonstrates a rough, lived-in authority and an unpretentious sense of craft. In his previous films, “Little Odessa” (another grim story involving the Russian mob) and “The Yards” (an unjustly neglected tale of political corruption), Mr. Gray evoked the urban crime dramas of earlier eras without being showy or self-conscious about it. And there is certainly nothing fancy or gimmicky about this movie.  But there is nothing especially interesting or new, either. “We Own the Night,” which takes its title from the slogan of the N.Y.P.D.’s street crime unit, is set in 1988, a wilder and more dangerous time in the city’s history (though perhaps not quite so wild and dangerous as Mr. Gray makes it seem). But in spite of a few historically apt musical selections and a digitally enhanced cameo appearance by former Mayor Ed Koch, this is less a period movie than an exercise in free-floating nostalgia.  It’s not nostalgia for any particular time or place, but rather for a mythical, tribal America where the obligations of clan trump individual desires. Authority in this world is patriarchal: Women are always being told to leave the room, mind the children or wait in the car. An index of Bobby’s betrayal is that he has adopted his mother’s maiden name, and his attempt to escape into a life of easy pleasure, social mobility and self-invention is doomed from the start. Where he ends up is where he always belonged.  This is a profoundly sentimental idea, one that flourishes in the collective fantasy life fed by television and the movies. The problem with “We Own the Night” is that it mistakes sentiment for profundity, and takes its ideas about character and fate more seriously than it takes its characters and their particular fates. “I feel light as a feather,” Bobby says in a crucial scene, at which point the movie starts to sink like a stone.  “We Own the Night” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sex, drug use and abundant profanity. </text>
      <date>October 12, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>