<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> There’s some nice filmmaking tucked inside “What Goes Up,” a muddle of moods and intentions. The British comic actor Steve Coogan plays Campbell Babbitt, a flailing, depressed journalist who’s sent to New Hampshire in the mid-1980s  to write an article pegged to the imminent liftoff of Christa McAuliffe, the high school teacher who was part of the Challenger space mission.  There he has close encounters with a group of adolescent outsiders mourning the death of another teacher, who happened to be one of Campbell’s old college friends. Although largely indifferent to the teenagers other than as potential story material, he does take notice of two beauties, Lucy (Hilary Duff) and Tess (Olivia Thirlby), who wear their angst as unsuccessfully as their black New Wave clothes.  As Campbell and the teenagers wander about in the moodily lighted winter (with British Columbia standing in for New England), it becomes increasingly unclear what story the first-time feature director Jonathan Glatzer is trying to tell, and whose. Based on a play he wrote with  Robert Lawson,  the movie lurches from melodramatic pathos (Campbell has a tragic back story) to broad satire (the high school is putting on an absurd space-theme musical) to unproductive end, as each new tonal shift erodes whatever narrative coherence and momentum Mr. Glatzer has managed to establish. At times he seems to be trying to say something critical about America and heroism (the cartoonish musical suggests as much); at other times he appears to be embracing the very values he previously lampooned.  Although the performances don’t stick  (Ms. Duff makes no sense in her role), the antagonism that comes to a boil between Campbell and Tess gives the film some bristling tension. Mr. Coogan doesn’t seem altogether comfortable with his part, which, like the story, undergoes a number of unconvincing changes. And it’s painful to watch him try to feign interest in Ms. Duff, miscast as a misfit object of desire. (Ms. Thirlby, meanwhile, assumes that unscripted role by virtue of her smoky eyes and glower.) Yet even when Mr. Coogan  can’t  make his scenes work, his prickly  presence keeps you watching, as does the eerie scenes of winter that Mr. Glatzer captures with the camera.  “What Goes Up” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Adults and teenagers talking like adults and teenagers.</text>
      <date>May 29, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>