<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> Plumbing the secrets of celebrity, its furtive ups and dirtiest downs, has been a favorite human endeavor for so long (psst, I hear Alexander swings both ways), it's a wonder that anyone can work up indignation about it, much less an interesting story line. We dish the dirt partly because it's a social lubricant but mostly because it's pleasurable, a quality largely absent from Atom Egoyan's period drama about a fictional comedy team, Collins and Morris, who conquered America, in particular anything in and out of a skirt, and popped more pills than Judy and Marilyn combined.  Set principally in the 1970's, with an occasional flashback to the 1950's, "Where the Truth Lies"  takes the shape of a  mystery, or rather one of those self-atomizing mysteries that play with genre. Mr. Egoyan, who has had his own ups ("The Sweet Hereafter") and downs ("Felicia's Journey"), tends to stray from the storytelling straight and narrow, taking a generally metafictional approach to narrative. Here, he seems to want to deconstruct celebrity through the familiar mechanics of a murder mystery. Yet because he also doesn't want to be imprisoned by genre, he tries to shake loose its rules, much as Robert Altman did in 1973 with his laid-back take on Raymond Chandler's "Long Goodbye." It almost works, at least in part.  When we first see Lanny Morris (Kevin Bacon) and Vince Collins (Colin Firth) waiting in the wings and staring at each other across a television stage, they look to be the bitterest of enemies and the closest of friends; in truth, they're both. The two are about to enter laughing and clowning for one of their annual polio telethons during which, through songs, patter and ingratiation, they will wring donations from the viewing audience. Whether mugging on the big screen or the little, plying their shtick in the Palisades or Miami, the pair are as seemingly inseparable as the team upon which they are loosely patterned, Jerry Lewis and Dean Martin, who together cut a lucrative swath through nightclubs, television and the movies in the late 1940's and early 1950's.  The film is based on the first novel by Rupert Holmes, who in 1986 won Tony Awards for  the score and the book of his first Broadway musical, "The Mystery of Edwin Drood," and earned earlier success for his vilely catchy pop song "Escape" ("If you like piña coladas ..."). In a review of Mr. Holmes's cabaret show in The New York Times, Stephen Holden noted that the songwriter was fond of "songs that present teasing little puzzles and games" and showing "how systems designed to facilitate communication between people can play tricks on them." Both approaches are at work in this novel, a puzzle of a story about the games played by a pair of faded entertainers and the hungry young journalist mucking about in their midst.  As far as I know, Martin and Lewis, as they were headlined in their heyday, never discovered a dead blonde sprawled in one of their bathtubs when they played the Latin Casino, the 500 Club or any of the other nightspots in which they polished their act and built their renown. In Mr. Holmes's very busy novel, which Mr. Egoyan has vainly attempted to wrestle into a coherent screenplay, Vince  and Lanny, along with some shady club types and a conveniently placed law enforcement officer, do find a blonde (a very good Rachel Blanchard) submerged unclothed in a tub. How that blonde ended up in such compromising circumstances is the central why in this whodunit, which is narrated in the main by another comely young blonde, Karen O'Connor (Alison Lohman).  As the hub of the story, Ms. Lohman guides us through what, at least on screen, evolves into an almost comically distorted labyrinth. Hired to pen a book about Vince, Karen, an ambitious reporter from the 1970's cut closer along the lines of Jessica Savitch than Oriana Fallaci, meets first one member of the long-disbanded comedy team, then the other. Slowly, through documents, interviews and one trippy  tumble down the rabbit hole in the company of yet a third blonde (Kristin Adams), Karen unlocks the secrets of Lanny  and Vince's collaboration. However tortuously engineered, these forays into the men's wonderland past succeed nicely because they usher the story back to that moment when the two worked their mojo in front of their most devoted audience: each other.  There is another big why swirling through this mystery, namely the calamitous miscasting of Ms. Lohman - as in why Mr. Egoyan chose to hang a story of sex and scandal on an actress whose ingénue looks and uncontrolled voice are wildly out of sync with the film's other performances and self-consciously lurid atmosphere. Ms. Lohman has done fine work in films like "White Oleander," but she has neither the chops nor the core mystery that might have made Mr. Egoyan's pseudo-David Lynch ambitions for his film fly. When Mr. Lynch unleashes the actress Naomi Watts in "Mulholland Drive," a film that surely was running through Mr. Egoyan's head when he directed this one, you see the allure of beauty as well as its dangers, not just a pretty face.  In the end, it is Mr. Egoyan's fealty to the novel, its feints and dodges, that proves the film's undoing. This becomes clear every time Lanny, a string bean soaked in hair grease and flop sweat, and Vince, a smooth operator and possible psychopath, turn their sights on each other. Mr. Bacon's excellent performance doesn't convey Jerry Lewis's manic neediness or genius for slapstick; even at Lanny's most aggressive and desperate, when he all but licks a television camera lens grubbing for attention, the imitation pales. Even so, the actors make a persuasive case for how love sometimes feeds a deep hate. Too bad their director, distracted by all that plot and his own narrative ambitions, couldn't see that two kings trump three blondes, dead or alive, every time.</text>
      <date>October 14, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>