<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> With Ralph Fiennes and three Redgraves aboard, you couldn't ask for a tonier cast than the one that gamely tries to pump oxygen into the thin, filtered air of "The White Countess."  The final collaboration between the director James Ivory and his longtime partner, the producer Ismail Merchant, who died during post-production, the movie, set in Shanghai in 1936 and 1937, is one of their most ambitious projects. But with its tentative pace, fussy, pieced-together structure and stuffy emotional climate, "The White Countess" never develops any narrative stamina.  With an original screenplay by Kazuo Ishiguro, whose novel "The Remains of the Day" (adapted by Ruth Prawer Jhabvala) became one of the team's biggest successes in 1993, "The White Countess" has the familiar Merchant-Ivory trademarks: cultivated dialogue, a keen eye for the nuances of upscale society and a sophisticated, internationalist view of class and ethnicity. What is missing from a film that wants to be an Asian "Casablanca" crossed with "The English Patient" is a racing, dramatic pulse. Its sedate tone is simply too refined for the story it has to tell.  Mr. Ishiguro's prim, anemic screenplay is so lacking in drive and emotional gravitas that the actors are left with only scraps of lean dramatic meat to tear into. Mr. Fiennes brings his usual multilayered subtlety to the character of Todd Jackson, an American businessman and diplomat disillusioned with the world since the failure of the League of Nations, which he helped to set up. Jackson is literally and metaphorically blind. And Mr. Fiennes, who affects a flat, neutral American accent, disconcertingly seems to forget his character's affliction much of the time and to act as if he can see. How he became blind isn't explained until the second of two crucial flashbacks hurriedly shoehorned into the movie that reveal the family tragedies that drove him into his shell.  Natasha Richardson is Sofia Belinsky, a spirited Russian émigrée countess who becomes the bruised apple of his unseeing eye, but the warmth generated between Ms. Richardson and Mr. Fiennes barely reaches room temperature. That coolness is due in part to the fact that their repressed romantic attraction is stifled by a mutual agreement not to share the details of their personal lives. But even after those barriers have begun to crumble, there are few signs of heat.  The film takes its name from the Shanghai nightclub that Jackson buys when he bets his life savings on a horse and wins. His club, the ultimate cosmopolitan melting pot of his dreams, suggests a fancy Far Eastern answer to Rick's place, from "Casablanca," peopled with a richer, more volatile mix of colliding social forces. Its patrons include Maoists, anti-Communists, Japanese, rogue Western capitalists and dancing girls.  Sofia, the film's bravest and most sympathetic character, is a widowed  countess who has fled to Shanghai with her family, which she supports and scandalizes by working as a taxi dancer and sometime prostitute. Her relatives include her Aunt Sara (Vanessa Redgrave) and Uncle Peter (John Wood); her vicious, sniping mother-in-law, Olga (Lynn Redgrave); her sister-in-law, Greshenka (Madeleine Potter); and her 10-year-old daughter, Katya (Madeleine Daly), whom Sofia's prudish in-laws believe is in imminent danger of being corrupted by her mother.  The women, who sleep three in a bed in a dingy Shanghai slum, spend their days sewing, complaining and dreaming of scraping together enough money to move to Hong Kong, where they imagine their noble lineage will be recognized. Sofia's fortunes take an upswing when she meets Jackson, who invites her to be the hostess, centerpiece and real-life namesake of his new club, the White Countess.  Jackson is befriended by Matsuda (Hiroyuki Sanada), an enigmatic, well-connected Japanese wheeler-dealer who volunteers to fill the club with the missing ingredient from Jackson's recipe for nightclub perfection: political tension. Matsuda is the film's answer to Claude Rains's cynical, all-knowing Captain Renault in "Casablanca."  What makes "The White Countess" so frustrating is that enough ingredients are in place to imagine how they might have been rearranged to create a thrilling drama of lives swept forward on a historical floodtide. But not until the last half-hour, when the Japanese bomb the city on Aug. 14, 1937, precipitating a panicked mass exodus, do the elements begin to gel. By then, it's far too late for this polite, meandering epic-manqué to rouse itself to glory.  "The White Countess" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language and mild violence.</text>
      <date>December 21, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>