<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> It's unclear what exactly Peter Rosen's documentary "Who Gets to Call It Art?" is about, much less why it was made. Clocking in at 80 minutes, this glib, largely uninformative and poorly organized précis of the post-World War II art scene, with its emphasis on New York in the 1960's and the curator Henry Geldzahler, succeeds neither as history nor as art history. If you want to know about Geldzahler, who in 1960 became a curatorial assistant in the department of American painting and sculpture at the Metropolitan Museum of Art (he died in 1994), you would do better if you typed his name into your favorite search engine. If you want to know about art in the 1960's, well, the art critic Arthur Danto is a good place to start.  A jumble of contemporary and, frustratingly, undated talking-head interviews, undated archival film material and still photographs, the film opens promisingly. The sculptor John Chamberlain growls about the public in what appears to be a fairly recent interview. ("What will the public think?" he asks, answering, "It's their job to catch up.") The painters Jasper Johns and Willem de Kooning offer up words of wit, wisdom and obfuscation from times past. The words "The Legend of Henry Geldzahler, 1935-1994" soon appears, as does the man himself, his full-moon face rising. Frank Stella attests to Geldzahler's importance, which isn't very surprising, since the curator included nine of the artist's works in his landmark 1969 show at the Metropolitan, "New York Painting and Sculpture: 1940-1970."  The importance of that controversial blockbuster show  —  408 works by 43 artists in 35 galleries  —  is forcibly repeated in the documentary, but not satisfyingly explained. Such is the case with every idea and artist that rushes past. We learn that artists liked to drink at the Cedar Tavern, and we see Jackson Pollock (or is it Ed Harris?) executing some of his drip paintings. Times change, faces too: enter Pop Art and Andy Warhol, who befriended Geldzahler and once said (though not in this film) that the curator "gave me all of my ideas." David Hockney and Mark di Suvero also make appearances; oddly, the only female artist name- checked is Helen Frankenthaler. Eva Hesse, Lynda Benglis, Anne Ryan and Louise Nevelson, among others, remain missing in action, which certainly adds another layer of meaning to the documentary's title question.</text>
      <date>February 1, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>