<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The extravagantly titled “Vince Vaughn’s Wild West Comedy Show: 30 Days and 30 Nights — Hollywood to the Heartland” imagines itself a contemporary equivalent of rootin’- tootin’ traveling entertainments like Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show. That’s a tall comparison to draw.  Nothing, not even Cirque du Soleil’s high-tech spectacles, could live up to the reputation of William Cody’s 19th-century touring circus, which involved as many as 1,200 performers and living legends like Sitting Bull and Annie Oakley.  On this not-so-rowdy 6,000-mile tour of one-night stands in 2005, Mr. Vaughn and four rising young male comedians (and  drop-in guests) traveled from Los Angeles across the southern tier of states and ultimately wound up in Chicago, Mr. Vaughn’s hometown.  Though it includes some moderately funny snippets of actual performances, “Wild West Comedy Show” is not a concert film. We never see a complete performance or even a quarter of one. The recipe for Mr. Vaughn’s variety show is left to the imagination. More of a backstage documentary, the movie explores the lives of his guests, handpicked comedians from the Comedy Store, a Los Angeles club.  John Caparulo, Bret Ernst, Sebastian Maniscalco and Ahmed Ahmed are observant, likable comics, but their humor never approaches the scabrous, cutting-edge extremes of someone like Sarah Silverman. All are youngish, ambitious professionals who are not about to blow an important career opportunity.  Among the tamest tours ever filmed, this one appears to have involved no drugs, and the only alcohol in sight is an occasional beer or glass of wine. Despite the abundance of beautiful women in every city, the sexual temperature remains below normal.  Early in the film we are reminded that the golden age of comedy has passed. In the 1980s, when leading comedy clubs franchised themselves and stand-up humor was wishfully called the rock music of the day, instant riches beckoned aspiring comics by the thousand. When “Wild West Comedy Show” was filmed, Mr. Maniscalco still had a day job as a waiter.  Mr. Vaughn, the tour’s mastermind and M.C., exudes the same amiable, guy’s-guy brashness he displays in movies like “Wedding Crashers.” But none of his protégés kill, to use stand-up comedy lingo. Most of Mr. Ahmed’s humor revolves around his paranoia as an Egyptian-born Arab-American having to endure humiliating waits in airport security checkpoints after 9/11. We meet his parents, who immigrated to the United States when he was a baby and hoped their son would become a doctor or a lawyer.  Mr. Ernst, the most physical of the four, does a funny bit as an inferior skater in a roller rink. Mr. Caparulo plays a geeky, self-mocking loner from Ohio. Much of Mr. Maniscalco’s humor deals with the contrasting behavior of men and women in nightclubs.  As the tour proceeds from city to city, fragments of country music provide regional flavors. In Bakersfield, Calif., the tour makes a pilgrimage to a museum celebrating Buck Owens with accompanying music and television clips from “Hee Haw.” Dwight Yoakam, an Owens disciple, joins Mr. Vaughn onstage and cajoles him into singing.  Because the tour came after Hurricane Katrina struck the Gulf Coast, it had to be rerouted. In the most revealing scene Mr. Vaughn and his crew visit an Alabama trailer camp to give free tickets to the residents, many of them New Orleans evacuees who lost everything. In a collective moment of insight, the performers realize that sleeping in bunk beds in close quarters on a tour bus isn’t the worst thing in the world.  “Vince Vaughn’s Wild West Comedy Show” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language and raunchy humor.</text>
      <date>February 8, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>