<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>t would have been easy for a filmmaker in search of novelty to treat the bird-fancying "St. Francis of Telegraph Hill" - as a passer-by calls the subject of Judy Irving's documentary "The Wild Parrots of Telegraph Hill" - like a sitting duck. Just aim the camera, fire and assemble the torn feathers into the portrait of a bohemian crank. That subject, Mark Bittner, is a shaggy-haired, ponytailed, redheaded, 50-ish San Franciscan who tends a flock of around four dozen wild parrots that live in his neighborhood. Mr. Bittner subsists with no visible means of support in a rent-free cottage on luxury real estate. One scene shows this affable, well-spoken man, who moved to San Francisco from Seattle more than 25 years ago to be a professional musician, accepting free food at a North Beach bakery. But in Ms. Irving's affectionate film, Mr. Bittner is more of a sage than a deadbeat. A dreamer who has spent half his life discovering his calling as an avian observer, he refuses to think of himself as an eccentric. Neither does Ms. Irving, who takes him at his word and documents his unusual life with barely the hint of a raised eyebrow. By the end of the movie,  you might even begin reconsidering your relationship with the animal kingdom and questioning the distance you put between yourself and nonhuman species. As Mr. Bittner introduces you to the noisy parrots he observes and nurtures and whose lives he chronicles in photographs and journals, he convincingly demonstrates that individual birds have distinct personalities. They also form personal attachments that may have an emotional dimension. Even as Mr. Bittner suggests this idea, he warns himself and us not to go too far in anthropomorphizing our relationships with animals. The close-ups of the blinking parrots, with their bright green backs, red or blue heads and imperious beaks, are gorgeous. We meet Mr. Bittner's favorite, Connor, a standoffish blue-crowned conure who lives among a flock made up mostly of cherry-headed conures with names like Mingus, Picasso, Sophie, Pushkin and Tupelo. Ms. Irving's camera observes the birds eating out of Mr. Bittner's hands, as well as squabbling and nuzzling among themselves and signaling the danger of hawks that circle the sky, perpetually on the lookout for prey. Rest assured that Mr. Bittner's birdland is no Disney-softened peaceable kingdom. The parrots themselves are vicious to those in their flock who are sick or injured. How did these South American species, originally from Ecuador and Peru, end up in San Francisco? In the weakest segment of the movie, assorted urban legends are trotted out as possible explanations, from escaped pets to transportation accidents. Mr. Bittner's experiences with birds have turned him into a metaphysician. Near the end of the movie, in which a real estate renovation uproots him and separates him from his flock, he relates a parable told to him by a Zen master after observing a waterfall in Yosemite National Park. When a river spills from the top of a cliff, it disperses into individual drops, which cohere back into the river once they reach the bottom. Those drops are our lives and the river something much larger: the stream of life itself.</text>
      <date>February 11, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>