<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "Why not be silent?" a filmmaker asks himself in the opening voiceover to the sublimely bleak documentary "William Eggleston in the Real World." After a few minutes of narration, that filmmaker, Michael Almereyda, establishes that being quiet is key to getting intimate with the hard-to-know pioneer of color photography. Mr. Eggleston is mostly mute while prowling for images of the Deep South's luxurious decay. But  his mutterings become clear, in this look at tattered glory.  Mr. Eggleston is now 65 and nearly three decades past his exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art, which some critics reviled because of its ordinary subject matter. Throughout his celebrated career, he searched for bright but sad scenes in and around his Memphis home, when he wasn't flashing some light on the dark places. The documentary includes a slideshow of his iconic images: a dark-suited white man standing with his back to a white-jacketed African-American man; a metal chain wrapped in a tornado-like swirl around a parking-lot pole; a bare-bulb fixture on a sinfully red ceiling.  Mr. Almereyda confesses his own difficulty in putting such images and their meanings into words, and when he asks Mr. Eggleston for help, the artist declines. Instead, Mr. Eggleston allows the video camera to follow him on a shoot in Mayfield, Ky., a project commissioned by the native son Gus Van Sant. There, Mr. Eggleston takes long, careful looks at a bright chicken statue on top of a restaurant; the piñatas in a taco joint; the labels on boxes in a CVS pharmacy, where Elvis Presley is asking on the loudspeaker never to be let go.  On this trip, Mr. Eggleston has a leg wound to tend to, the origin and severity of which are unclear, except that it requires a "complicated bandage." Eventually a strip of gauze slips out of his creased pant leg and twirls down the street, evoking the plastic bag that was caught in a wind eddy and captured by the teenage videographer in "American Beauty." The documentary is entirely in tune with the grace of such rubbish, the eerie motions of a ghost world.  The still-hobbled American South is thoroughly reflected in Mr. Eggleston's work and persona. His habits match his habitat. He is crisply dressed but slyly decadent. With his grown son Winston in tow, he patiently tromps through abandoned houses and strip malls, proving he can be industrious. Then he plays creepy organ chords for languid sessions that suggest the "paralysis of will" so often applied to geniuses in repose. He is outwardly respectful to his devoted, curatorial wife, his teenage sweetheart who came from a similar background of dwindling plantation wealth. But he also allows the camera along for a late-night, boozy visit to the home of a female companion, who writhes on a couch, sucks a lollipop and delivers a soul-crushing, foreshadowing monologue.  Viewers are invited to rest with Mr. Eggleston in a haze of cigarette smoke and alcohol, to give in to "Grey  Gardens"-esque torpor. Only then does his visionary style seem best understood. He assiduously collects shards that suggest a broken past, a tormented present, a weird future. He is the obvious forefather of the digital age's explosion of oddball quotidian snapshots. He is perhaps the first "fotologger," telling a personal history with copious images that don't include him. (By Mr. Eggleston's count, he has taken 450,000 pictures and never snaps several of the same.) In a lesser-known artistic feat, he turned an early video camera on an inebriated underworld where this son of the South and dad to three was no stranger.  By now, pop culture is sorting out suburban oddity on many frontiers, and Mr. Eggleston proves the polished granddaddy who, early on, recognized beauty in a garish wasteland.  In this accomplished look at a storied career, he instructs - without words -  how to see all that is hauntingly familiar.</text>
      <date>August 31, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>