<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text>inter Solstice" is the kind of ambling, event-free family drama that will either draw audiences in with its gentle, understated power or quietly bore them out of their skulls. Like its protagonist, a taciturn New Jersey widower named Jim Winters (Anthony LaPaglia), the film plays its cards close to its vest. As a measure of the movie's restraint, it's not until two-thirds of the way through its running time that we learn how and when Jim's wife died (in a car accident, five years before the film begins). By that point, though, an attentive viewer will have gathered everything he needs to know from the movie's richly detailed context. A moderately successful landscape gardener in an idyllic suburb, Jim has two teenage sons, Gabe (Aaron Stanford) and Pete (Mark Webber). The younger of the two, Pete, is a rebellious underachiever, desultorily attending summer school and picking fights in convenience-store parking lots. Gabe has a steady job and a devoted girlfriend (Michelle Monaghan), but his apparent calm masks a bone-deep sadness. The father sips coffee and broods at the kitchen table; the boys shoot hoops and scuffle in front of the television. And that's pretty much it - until a newly arrived neighbor named Molly Ripken (Allison Janney) invites the Winters family over for dinner, upsetting the fragile equilibrium of their bachelor household. The boys, particularly Mr. Webber as Pete, are astonishingly good, and Ms. Monaghan, who looks like a slightly more tomboyish Liv Tyler, makes a deep impression in a minor role. Mr. LaPaglia, of the television series "Without a Trace," brings a tender gravity to the shell-shocked Jim. But Ms. Janney is an actress so indelibly associated with her role on "The West Wing" that she may never be able to escape its shadow. I don't even watch "The West Wing," and I kept expecting her to stride in with a white paper on defense spending and slam it down on Mr. LaPaglia's desk. It doesn't help that Ms. Janney's character is the least developed in the movie; though her back story is briefly sketched in, she serves mainly as a plot device in what is ultimately a film about masculinity and its discontents. "Winter Solstice" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language and some mild violence.</text>
      <date>April 8, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>