<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The pall of depression that hangs over "Winter Passing," the first film written and directed by the promising New York playwright Adam Rapp, never really lifts, even after its wanly upbeat ending.  This glum family drama is so scrupulously written that its information-packed screenplay suggests the major characters emerged from exhaustive outlines listing their traits and personal histories.  Although this degree of care is laudable, so many details are packed into the dialogue that "Winter Passing" often feels like a well-wrought classroom exercise hovering uncertainly between the stage and the screen. Its familiar story of an embittered child's homecoming and confrontation with a parent throws off dramatic sparks, but they never flare into a blaze.  The central character, Reese Holdin (Zooey Deschanel), is an aspiring New York stage actress and the daughter of two famous novelists who returns to the Michigan home of the reclusive, alcoholic father she hasn't seen in six years. Reese wants to retrieve a box of her parents' love letters, written in happier times, that was willed to her by her mother, who recently strangled herself with a necktie. A book editor has offered her $100,000 for their publication and advanced her the money for the bus trip.  Reese, who ekes out a living as a bartender and has a cocaine habit, carries a boulder-size chip on her shoulder. Ms. Deschanel's brave, unsympathetic performance doesn't shy away from making her a total pill. She delivers almost every line in the sullen, affectless murmur of a resentful child asking to be smacked across the face.  Those famous parents suggest a fictionalized mix-and-match stew of J. D. Salinger, Ken Kesey, Ted Hughes and Sylvia Plath, with dollops of Jack Kerouac and Ernest Hemingway thrown into the pot. Reese's father, Don Holdin (Ed Harris), once a flaming neo-Marxist radical, is a literary legend whose 1960's novel "People's Park" became a modern classic. Starry-eyed admirers still show up on his doorstep toting backpacks and panting to pay their respects. Her mother wrote high-toned literary romances.  Don, who is deeply depressed and afflicted with writer's block, is a brooding, stringy-haired eccentric tended by two semipermanent houseguests. Corbit (Will Ferrell), a former guitarist in a Christian rock band, is his live-in handyman, partner in an indoor golfing ritual and human guard dog, trained to shoo away visitors. Shelly (Amelia Warner), a former student, is Don's cook, housekeeper and literary manager, who, to Reese's disgust, has become a sort of surrogate daughter.  In the movie's early scenes, the camera trails around after Reese as she ambles through Lower Manhattan being mean to people. The story begins in earnest when she arrives in Michigan and has to prove her identity to Corbit before gaining entry to the house. Switching out of comedy, Mr. Ferrell offers a credible portrayal of a musician with a pathological streak of shyness that prevents him from playing the guitar and singing at the same time. Coaxed to perform at an open mike in the local bar, he freezes and pulls out a recorded accompaniment for his own wobbly performance of the Eagles' hit "I Can't Tell You Why."  Mr. Harris may be boxed in by his clichéd role of a bourbon-swilling, burnt-out novelist who is himself suicidally inclined, but he gives it his best shot. How deep he is willing to go inside a character is revealed in a scene where Reese comes upon him weeping uncontrollably.  It isn't Mr. Harris's fault that the drama of Don's decline has so little dimension. The screenplay, for all its small details, refuses to tackle the big stuff about art, writing and Don's legendary marriage, and the movie is much the worse for this reticence.  Beyond that, isn't one clinically depressed, self-destructive writer enough for a movie? Must we have two? And must they be married? Any work of art that subscribes this wholeheartedly to the myth of the cursed artist has an obligation to come to grips with such a despairing vision.  "Winter Passing" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and sexual situations.</text>
      <date>February 17, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>