<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> I took my daughter, who recently turned 10, to see “Race to Witch Mountain.” Yes, this is one of those Dad-goes-to-the-movies reviews, but surely you didn’t think I was going to see it alone. When the movie was over, as my own impressions buzzed distractingly around in my head, I asked her what she thought. “It was O.K.,” she said. “It was pretty noisy, though.”  Really, what more can I add? And also, what else did she expect? When I was around her age,  there was “Escape to Witch Mountain,” which starred Donald Pleasance, Eddie Albert and Ray Milland; it was based on a popular kiddie-sci-fi novel by Alexander Key and was followed a few years later  by “Return From Witch Mountain,” with, of all people, Bette Davis and Christopher Lee.  As I recall, they were O.K., but in those days Disney live-action juvenile pictures had less competition and were thus less compelled to be loud and dazzling. They were, in fact, kind of strange and spooky. This one, which stars Dwayne Johnson as Jack Bruno, a Las Vegas taxi driver who becomes the unwitting protector of two towheaded aliens, is modest and diverting, rough and bland, with some good (if not quite Bette Davis caliber) actors and so-so special effects.  Mr. Johnson  belongs in the latter category, though his range improves with every role and his natural, lapidary charisma takes him a long way. He is best when he expresses an agitated annoyance amusingly at odds with his solid, muscular presence. He doesn’t really have much to do in “Race to Witch Mountain” (which was directed with reasonable competence by Andy Fickman) — throw some punches, react with incredulity and, well, race to Witch Mountain — but it’s not painful to watch him do it.  Nor to see Carla Gugino pretend to be an astrophysicist whose research is ignored until it’s almost too late, or Ciaran Hinds scowl and bark as a government heavy intent on hunting down the cute little extraterrestrials. They are Seth (Alexander Ludwig) and Sara (AnnaSophia Robb) and, like many others of their kind, their English is impeccable, though they are unable to use contractions or slang, or to refer to people by first names alone.  Their powers are impressive — Sara can read Jack’s mind and also talk to dogs; Seth can reach through metal and create force fields — but erratic enough that they need Jack to smack around their pursuers. These include not only the terrestrial government heavy but also his counterpart from Seth and Sarah’s home planet, an assassin with a mask and plated armor.  Jack also has some hoodlums on his tail, apparently because the movie needed a few more black S.U.V.’s driven by guys with shaved heads. It benefits more from the half-clever, sort of obvious conceit of staging a big action set piece in the middle of a science fiction convention full of costumed fans and geeks.  Such folks will not find much to groove on in “Race to Witch Mountain” — the threat of Earth’s destruction or colonization is so perfunctory that it doesn’t rise to the level of allegory — but it will amuse some of their young counterparts until summertime. Provided they don’t mind the noise.  “Race to Witch Mountain” is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some rough action sequences.</text>
      <date>March 13, 2009</date>
   </review>
</reviews>