<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> “What is this, some 1930s movie?” asks a character in “The Women.” If only! Of course, the line pays winking homage to a specific ’30s movie, directed by George Cukor and based on a notorious play by Clare Boothe Luce, that starred Norma Shearer and Joan Crawford and was also called “The Women.”  Further comparison would only serve to demean that sleek and waspish artifact of a bygone era, and also to humiliate the remake, a witless, straining mess written and directed by Diane English, the creator of “Murphy Brown.” Watching it, you wait in vain for a moment of snappy repartee, of fresh emotion, of grace or charm or pathos. You wait, by the way, for a very long time — two hours that pass like the whole 13-episode jump-the-shark season of a series on basic cable — and what you get is Meg Ryan munching on a stick of butter dipped in cocoa powder as she rants and raves to her au pair (Tilly Scott Pedersen) and her maid (Cloris Leachman) about the sorry state of her life.  And that’s the best scene in the movie. At least it gives Ms. Ryan, who otherwise has to oscillate between ditzy and mopey, a chance to remind us that she is still the spitfire who won America’s heart when she faked an orgasm at Katz’s Deli. In “The Women,” she certainly works at faking something — pluck? distress? belief in the script? — but table-pounding ecstasy, or even simple, modest pleasure, is beyond this movie’s range.  Ms. Ryan plays Mary Haines, part of a circle of friends that includes Edie (Debra Messing), Alex (Jada Pinkett Smith) and, supremely, Annette Bening as Sylvie. One of the film’s clever conceits, borrowed from the original, is that it entirely banishes men. And yet, far from liberating the women from male domination, this trick serves only to emphasize their dependence on the caprices of patriarchal authority. The invisible men in “The Women” wield an almost mystical power.  Only Alex, a lesbian and a celebrated essayist, is immune, but she disappears for much of the movie (lucky her). Edie, meanwhile, is pregnant for the fifth time, while the never-married Sylvie, a magazine editor with crisp suits and a posture of easy, confident command, lives in constant fear of being fired by her male publisher. Mary, in spite of the energy with which she devotes herself to work, family, cooking, gardening and everything else, is employed by her father and, it turns out, at the mercy of her philandering stockbroker husband.  “Sex and the City,” where plenty of men hang around and have speaking parts, was able, on the big screen but especially on television, to create and maintain an autonomous space of female friendship. However big they might have been, the dudes knew their place, which was at the margin of the charmed circle of Carrie, Samantha, Miranda and Charlotte. Here, the fathers and husbands cast a longer, darker shadow. While it’s possible that this is Ms. English’s point, it’s one that contradicts and ultimately makes incoherent her celebration of female self-sufficiency and solidarity.  Really, though, muddled sexual politics are not the main problem. If “The Women” had managed to give its various impulses some kind of coherent shape or tone, it might be worth arguing about. As it is, the movie wanders and wallows, stumbling toward screwball before veering in the direction of weepiness and grasping at satirical urbanity along the way.  At the heart of the hectic story is Mary’s discovery that her husband is having an affair with Crystal (Eva Mendes), a gold-digging vixen who works at the perfume counter at Saks Fifth Avenue. The strain of top-down class resentment in the way her character is portrayed — mean, selfish, cheap and vulgar — is perhaps the most shocking thing about the movie, and also, perhaps, the most honest. At bottom, this is less a movie about defending a marriage or battling for a man than it is about the protection of social privilege. Out in the suburbs, the loyal servants stand by their mistress (and seem to have no private lives or desires of their own), while in the city the lower orders scheme and gossip and connive to steal what can never be rightfully theirs.  And of course, the heroic women of “The Women” will not concede without a fight. But rarely has class struggle, or catfighting, for that matter, been so tediously waged. And rarely have so many fine actresses been enlisted in such a futile cause. They all deserved better, and it hurts especially to watch Ms. Bening and Candice Bergen (who plays Mary’s mother) lend their wit and dignity to a project that has so little of its own.  “The Women” is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual references and some strong language.</text>
      <date>September 12, 2008</date>
   </review>
</reviews>