<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The idea of a documentary about crossword puzzle fanciers may not immediately cause everyone's pulse to race. Those of us addicted to doing the crossword puzzles in this newspaper should find the spectacle of similar fetishists compulsively watchable. Nonaddicts may need more convincing. In "Wordplay" the director, Patrick Creadon, a veteran cameraman, employs playful strategies to keep both sets of viewers engrossed. With rapid editing style, he shuffles between crossword composers and solvers, feeding in a steady stream of entertaining cameos by notables like the comedian Jon Stewart, the New York Yankees pitcher Mike Mussina and the ever-charismatic Bill Clinton, all confessing to an inner nerd.  In one enlightening episode the crossword composer Merl Reagle shares his thought processes while putting together a new puzzle, affording an insight into the deep linguistic structures that inform this seemingly trivial hobby. Mathematicians and musicians, we are told, are best at solving crosswords quickly, being able to glimpse the underlying orthographic patterns and puns like a system of numbers or notes.  Following a mite too slavishly the successful formula of "Spellbound,"  "Wordplay" is built around the 28th annual American Crossword Puzzle Tournament, which attracts the  top competitors. The movie presents them with affection as a proudly geeky tribe of isolates, coming together each year to revel in family feeling and competitiveness. Many of the players emerge as colorfully rabid characters; others seem robotic and washed-out, obsession having the curious property of heightening some personalities, flattening others.  Will Shortz, crossword editor of The New York Times and a National Public Radio host, who has organized the tournament from its inception, comes off as a genial ringmaster, gracious if somewhat bland. The failure to bring us closer to this ostensible anchoring figure leaves a gray hole at the film's center. And the documentary lapses, at times, into an overly fawning tribute to Mr. Shortz, with a tone of excessive self-congratulation and apologetic insistence that everyone is "having fun." On the contrary: finishing crossword puzzles is a serious matter. Whatever  the documentary's flaws, the filmmakers should be saluted for giving us a rare glimpse of life in these trenches.  "Wordplay" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested) for some language and mild thematic elements.</text>
      <date>June 16, 2006</date>
   </review>
</reviews>