<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> "The World" was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Manohla Dargis's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 11, 2004. The unrated film, in Mandarin with English subtitles, opens today in Manhattan at Cinema Village, 22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village.    Globalization and its discontents form the molten core of "The World," the new film from the prodigiously talented Chinese director Jia Zhangke. Set in a sprawling Disney-like entertainment park in a Beijing suburb, the film centers on a young female dancer, Tao (Zhao Tao), whose entire universe seems to begin and end at the complex. Along with her boyfriend, a security guard named Taisheng (Chen Taishen),  Tao yearns for a better life but can barely articulate much less envision what a life beyond this peculiarly conceived simulacrum might look like.  As he did with his last feature, "Unknown Pleasures," Mr. Jia has fashioned a quietly despairing vision of contemporary China with an almost ethnographic attention to detail and a somewhat cavalier attitude toward narrative momentum. The film opens with Tao tramping through the backstage corridors and warrenlike dressing rooms where she and the other young performers spend so much of their time. Dressed like a Las Vegas version of a Hindu princess and insistently, rather hilariously bellowing for a bandage, she makes for a gaudy and curiously poignant spectacle. By the time she finally finds her Band-Aid, the credits have rolled and the dressing rooms have emptied out of the other performers, leaving her to tend to the first of many such wounds.  Loosely constructed, "The World" drifts along pleasantly for much of its two-and-a-half-hour running time. Mr. Jia has a terrific eye and an almost sculptural sense of film space (especially in close quarters), and he brings texture and density to even the most nondescript rooms. And while he's too in love with the film's overarching metaphor, he nonetheless gracefully incorporates the theme park into the everyday lives of its workers. In one scene, we pass by a miniature Leaning Tower of Pisa with the nonchalance of an Italian citizen; in another scene, the pyramids of Egypt, complete with drifts of sand and a masticating camel, make a suitably dramatic backdrop to a fight between friends.  Something of a story gradually emerges, built on incident, mood and the amorphous desires of the film's characters. Tao befriends a Russian woman whose melancholic smile, crumpled family photograph and horribly bruised shoulders speak volumes about her plight. The scenes of the two women trying to communicate despite their language differences at times veer dangerously close to melodramatic excess, in particular when the Russian starts to drunkenly serenade Tao, but Mr. Jia manages, for the most part, to keep sentimentality at bay. In the end, what makes Tao herself a figure of great pathos isn't that she understands the other woman's tragedy; it's that because, locked inside this false world, Tao does not and, suggests Mr. Jia, cannot see her.  In a sense this miniaturized world creates a prison for the filmmaker, as well. Mr. Jia isn't just enamored with his metaphor; he's mesmerized by it. As he wanders around the amusement park, repeatedly cutting away to the phony Eiffel Tower jutting into the China sky, the pyramids and even the Manhattan skyline, he increasingly comes across less like a filmmaker who knows what he's after and more like a besotted tourist. Even when he occasionally takes us outside the park, for a glimpse of the whirring Beijing street life, with its teeming humanity and a shocking glimpse of Chairman Mao beatifically smiling over the city, you get the sense that Mr. Jia is, as much as any of the film's other caged birds, eager to return to his manufactured world. </text>
      <date>July 1, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>