<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The afterlife can be a difficult place to set a movie, especially a comedy. Apart from the inevitable lighting and labor issues, there is the risk of alienating viewers with sentimentality, implausibility or questionable metaphysics. Then again, when the conceit works, you may wind up with “It’s a Wonderful Life,” “Defending Your Life” or the various iterations of “Heaven Can Wait.”  “Wristcutters: A Love Story” is not quite at that level; it’s more likely to live on as a cult favorite than as a consensus classic. But this movie, written and directed by Goran Dukic, a graduate of the Academy of Dramatic Arts in Zagreb, Croatia, and based on a  novella by the Israeli writer Etgar Keret, has an offbeat, absurdist charm that turns a potentially creepy conceit into an odd, touching adventure. The Sundance Film Festival (where “Wristcutters” first popped up in 2006, before vanishing into indie limbo) can be a breeding ground for studiously whimsical, willfully quirky films. “Wristcutters” belongs to a rarer species: it is genuinely eccentric.  At the beginning a mopey young man named Zia (Patrick Fugit) puts on a Tom Waits record — Mr. Waits himself will show up later — cleans his apartment, and commits suicide by the method suggested in the title. As a consequence of this act, apparently provoked by love trouble, he is plunged into a purgatory reserved for those unfortunate or impulsive souls who chose a similar exit.  It’s not a terrible existence, or nonexistence, as the case may be. For Zia, it’s a lot like the life he  quit, but “a little bit worse.” This netherworld, which looks like a shabby corner of the American Southwest, is a place of broken-down cars, hand-lettered signs and unflattering fluorescent lights. No one is able to smile and the stars are invisible. Still, a desultory society has taken shape. People compare notes on how, as they put it, they “offed”   (the title notwithstanding, some used nooses, guns or gas).  And since everyone is already dead, there’s no reason not to smoke a cigarette or drink a beer first thing in the morning.  Zia befriends Eugene (Shea Whigham), a failed musician and semi-successful ladies’ man whose loving Russian family has, oddly enough, accompanied him into this afterlife. Zia and Eugene, in the course of a road trip, meet up with Mikal (Shannyn Sossamon), a lovely young woman who is trying to convince whoever is in charge of this world that she was sent there by mistake. Zia’s attraction to her is complicated by his search for his old girlfriend,  Desiree, who caused his self-destruction and seems to have followed it with her own.  And this is only the beginning. Mr. Waits shows up as a broken-down guru named Kneller (Mr. Keret’s story is called “Kneller’s Happy Campers”) and his appearance precipitates a swerve from dark comedy into wild spiritual allegory. One of the chief virtues of Mr. Dukic’s film — as well as a potential obstacle for nervous moviegoers — is that it conforms to no familiar pattern or genre. It seems to invent its own rules as it goes along, but with such low-key self-confidence that it takes a while to appreciate the full measure of its originality.  What makes it work is that the performers, trapped in a weird movie about a weird place, underplay their astonishment. Mr. Fugit, such a perfect, quiet witness to the rock ’n’ roll craziness of “Almost Famous,” shows a remarkable range of emotions against a ground bass of morose bewilderment, and Ms. Sossamon, moody and mercurial, is his perfect foil. Mr. Whigham seems to have drifted in from a Gogol short story by way of an Iggy Pop song, and Mr. Waits gives the whole strange, irresistible confection his scruffy, soulful blessing.  “Wristcutters: A Love Story” is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for language and disturbing content involving suicide.</text>
      <date>October 19, 2007</date>
   </review>
</reviews>