<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The first thing to say about Sally Potter's "Yes" is that it is written in verse - rhymed iambic pentameter, to be precise. This curious feature may not, however, be the first thing you notice about the movie, given Ms. Potter's knack for enjambment and her cast's impressive ability to make highly artificial language sound like natural speech. The rhythms of their dialogue are at once odd and familiar, and the meter gives the picture a brisk momentum, making it feel like the expression of single, sustained impulse. "Yes" is not just a movie, in other words, it's a poem.  A bad poem. There is no denying Ms. Potter's skill at versifying - or for that matter, at composing clear, striking visual images - but her intricate, measured lines amount to doggerel, not art. Her formal ingenuity (also on display in "Orlando" and "The Man Who Cried"), which it would be unkind to dismiss as mere pretension, is yoked to ideas of almost staggering banality, and she sacrifices the seriousness of a group of superb actors on the altar of her own intellectual vanity. Her ambitions could hardly be larger - this wants to be a movie about love, hate, class, religion, ethnicity, science and the fractious state of the modern world - but rather than expanding our sense of what it all means, Ms. Potter shrinks it down to a single syllable. Tempting as it is to contradict her yes with a simple no, other responses also come to mind. And? So? What?  The two main characters are themselves monosyllabic generalities: an adulterous couple known only as He and She. He is a Lebanese refugee living in London, a surgeon in his home country and a restaurant cook in his city of exile. She is an American scientist who spent her childhood in Northern Ireland and who now endures a cold marriage with a stuffy British  diplomat. He (the cook, not the diplomat) is played by a gifted Armenian-Lebanese actor named Simon Abkarian,  whose work  has mainly been in French movies and on the Paris stage. She is the incomparable Joan Allen, whose bearing grows at once more supple and more regal with every film. Sam Neill, as the husband, joins the list of eminent actors (Anthony Hopkins and Kevin Kline are at the top) who have portrayed Ms. Allen's worse half, and he gallantly plays along in a game that is rigged against him from the start. Ms. Allen suffers not just nobly, but intelligently, and briskly pockets  the audience's sympathy and its admiration.  Sympathy is in order, not necessarily for the overblown tristesse of the characters, but for the valiant actors, who do their best to give subtle, vivid, human performances, only to find themselves banging against the bars of the allegorical cage Ms. Potter has built for them. He and She after batting eyes and exchanging pleasantries at a stuffy formal dinner, begin a love affair that before long becomes a geopolitical crisis in microcosm. The differences between them - of religion, culture and circumstance - drive them apart, as all the complex hatreds of the modern world press down on their simple desire to be in love.  Or so Ms. Potter would have us believe. But really, the main obstacle facing them is the director's dogmatic belief that human beings exist mainly, if not solely,  as accretions of identity. Another way to say this is to observe that "Yes," a movie that proudly (if lazily) flies the flag of tolerance and cosmopolitanism, consists of nothing but stereotypes. He, with his long mustache and expressive hands, is a figure out of a threadbare Orientalist carpet: florid of speech, emotionally volatile, oscillating wildly between pride and self-pity. She is the embodiment of chilly Western rationality, and the twain can only meet in bed. Or on the beach in Cuba, which turns out to be the only place in the world free from the frigid materialism of the developed world and the blood hatreds of the Middle East. (Well, maybe North Korea too, but the climate there is not as pleasant.)  The secondary characters are also cartoonishly drawn, from the thin-lipped, deceiving husband to the best friend whose motherly sentimentality is a challenge to the heroine's childless reserve. The hero's co-workers in the kitchen include a black West Indian whose promiscuous love of women has given way to a beaming affection for Jesus, and a white Briton with spiky hair and a foul mouth who reveals himself in the heat of argument to be an anti-immigrant bigot. The only figure capable of any mischief or surprise, or any humor, -is a house cleaner (Shirley Henderson) who functions as tour guide, Greek chorus and voice of the otherwise silent working class.  Meanwhile, He and She, having recoiled from their initial sexual bliss, start arguing politics. Since She spent part of her childhood in Belfast, she is excused from bearing a full measure of imperialist guilt. Like her lover, she can claim a homeland riven by religious hatred. But his sympathy wears thin after a confrontation with his racist co-worker, and He assails She with rhetoric about honor and shame, blood and oil, and the poverty of Western civilization, which apparently consists of "Elvis and Eminem and Warhol's Art." "I have read the Bible -  have you read the Koran?" He demands.  "The things that they have done have not been in my name," She says,  speaking not of Elvis or Warhol but of the unnameable Voldemorts in the American government. "I feel no pride. I feel a deepening shame." The shame is that this sentiment has the psychological weight and ideological nuance of a bumper sticker, which is pretty much what "Yes" amounts to. Ms. Potter has made much of the fact that she began writing the screenplay shortly after the Sept. 11 attacks, but her film is strikingly the work of somebody whose view of the world has not been significantly altered by that event or any other recent catastrophe. "Yes" offers a case study in the moral complacency of the creative class, and its verbal cleverness cannot disguise the vacuous self-affirmation summed up in the title. For all her intellectual posing, Ms. Potter does not want you to think, but rather to nod your head in agreement. Please.  "Yes" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian.) It has some sexual content and strong language.</text>
      <date>June 24, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>