<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <text> The kiddie wars have commenced. The popularity of "Cheaper by the Dozen" two years ago has sparked the resuscitation of a rival litter of cute-as-a-button rugrats wreaking havoc in the lives of two caring parents. "Yours, Mine &amp; Ours," a remake of the 1968 comedy starring Lucille Ball and Henry Fonda, ratchets up the juvenile population from a dozen to 18, enough to fill a medium-size school bus.  The keepers of the New London, Conn., lighthouse and attached home in which two combined families settle are now Dennis Quaid and Rene Russo. Their characters, Adm. Frank Beardsley, a United States Coast Guard officer, and Helen North, a handbag designer, are former high school sweethearts, both widowed, who reconnect at their 30th high school reunion and marry before consulting their children. Because Helen has 10 kids, including 6 adopted children, and Frank has 8, their sudden marriage is like a merger made without approval from two critical boards of directors.  The movie, which has a one-month window of commercial opportunity before the arrival in theaters of "Cheaper by the Dozen 2," poses a marketing question: is there room for two movies and 30 squabbling children in one holiday season?  To use one of Frank's favorite words, "Yours, Mine &amp; Ours" is a "shipshape" family movie that won't disturb the sleep of the very young audience at which it is directed. To describe the film as so squeaky clean that it makes the Baker family of "Cheaper by the Dozen" look like the Sopranos would be a gross exaggeration. But "Yours, Mine &amp; Ours" is so snug, airtight and insulated from reality that the nice, well-scrubbed "Cheaper by the Dozen" seems almost rambunctious by comparison.  If you scrape away its triple-frosted glaze, "Yours, Mine &amp; Ours" is about opposing styles of child-rearing: one militaristic, the other bohemian, fighting for supremacy under the same roof. After an hour of waffling, the movie comes down very cautiously on the side of militarism. When Frank admits to Helen that  he's not averse to giving an unruly child a gentle swat on the behind occasionally, you can hardly blame him after what he's been through.  Frank has organized his eight into an efficient sailing crew who talk in nautical language as they march around discharging their duties like good little sailors, chirping,  "Aye, aye sir!" when Daddy gives them orders. Helen, who keeps a messy home office and wouldn't touch a hair on her dear ones' heads, is the movie's idea of a hippie mom. Frank mocks her style of child rearing as "free to be you and me"; she flings the term "anal retentive" in his face.  Once the combined families move in together, disharmony reigns. A sailing expedition organized by Frank to achieve unity collapses in chaos. The two clans of children instantly loathe each other. Helen's more sophisticated brood refuses to follow Frank's minutely computed schedules for everything from chores to bathroom privileges. Unanimity is achieved only when the two sides collaborate to break up their parents' marriage.  "Yours, Mine &amp; Ours" is a straight farce in which Frank, a neat freak, becomes the butt of redundant pranks that find him slipping and sliding and landing in buckets of paint and waking up in bed nuzzled by the family's pet pig.  As in "Cheaper by the Dozen," parental responsibilities go head to head with career opportunities. Frank, the heir apparent of the retiring Coast Guard commandant (Rip Torn), is offered a job that would take him away from home. Helen's new line of handbags is a winner.  The movie's population explosion exceeds its capacity to take a thorough census. Among the 18, the only 3 to stand out from the pack are squabbling teenage girls (Katija Pevec and Danielle Panabaker), and Frank's oldest son (Sean Faris). Linda Hunt, as a tart-tongued, martini-swilling housekeeper, flutters around the edges of the movie, her role obviously cut to the bone. Mr. Quaid and Ms. Russo comfortably hold their own amid the madness, and Mr. Quaid accomplishes the unenviable task of making his dictatorial control freak reasonably likable. Think of him as a younger, more macho Steve Martin, a shipshape 50-something hunk with perfect abs.  The movie is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has some strong language. </text>
      <date>November 23, 2005</date>
   </review>
</reviews>