<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Oct 22, 2008</date>
      <text>When you go into a new movie directed by Clint Eastwood, you can more or less count on the pleasure of his calm classicism &#151; the deftly angled shots, the story that unfolds with well-carpentered precision, no matter how many surprise corners it bends around. In Changeling , which is based on events that took place in Los Angeles in 1928, the stately formality of Eastwood's style is even more pronounced than usual; the whole film has a slightly remote period-piece gravity. When we first meet Christine Collins (Angelina Jolie), who oversees a floor of telephone operators, she looks as stylized as a doll, with white makeup, ruby lipstick, and a flapperish hat.
The torment of Christine's situation, and also the dastardliness of the cops (who turn a corrupt lie into media hype), gets rubbed in our faces. When Christine tries to fight back, egged on by the community activist Rev. Gustav Briegleb (John Malkovich), she is branded as crazy. Yet there's little mystery, and therefore very little drama, to any of this. Jolie, who brought a tremulous power to her portrayal of Mariane Pearl in A Mighty Heart  &#151; another woman distraught over a lost loved one &#151; isn't given enough notes to play here. She's brave, despairing, defiant, and monotonous. Changeling  is a muckraker that crushes the audience under the dull weight of injustice. And when the film starts to show you what really happened to Walter, it grows even more oppressive. The trouble with Changeling  is that it plays less like reality than like a bare-bones, moralistic rehash of other, better movies, such as L.A. Confidential  or Frances . The oldfangled deliberateness of Eastwood's style has backfired this time, only adding to the sense that though you may not have heard this particular story before, you already know everything that's coming.
Changeling : See an exclusive clip:
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>