<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep 12, 2007</date>
      <text>It can be a film-buff parlor game to try to decipher David Cronenberg's ideas, but in movies as diverse as A History of Violence , Crash , Spider , Dead Ringers , and The Fly , it's aggressively apparent that they are  films of ideas. That's what makes his new one, Eastern Promises , so intriguing. It's an academic meditation in underworld-thriller drag &#151; a movie that looks about as close to a straight-ahead, down-and-dirty genre entertainment as anything the director has made since his exploding-head horror days. Just give it a while, though. In London, a dazed 14-year-old, with purple track marks on her arm, collapses in a bloody heap. Anna (Naomi Watts), a hospital midwife &#151; she's English, but of Russian descent &#151; watches helplessly as the girl dies in childbirth, then attempts to locate the baby's relatives.
Her one clue is a diary, written in Russian. It leads her to an elegant restaurant, in the city's Russian demimonde, run by Semyon, a grandfatherly gent played by the great sly dog Armin Mueller-Stahl with such soft-spoken benevolence that from the moment he volunteers to translate the diary, you just know he's bad to the bone. A thriller can lead us into the fascinating intricacy of a criminal subculture, and Eastern Promises  does that with the globalized Russian Mob. The whackings have their own brazen operatic flavor, and so does the ritual of becoming a ''made'' man (it involves special tattoos). A prostitute den is stocked with morose Slavic Valkyries &#151; a relevant setting, since the film explores sex trafficking.
Even more vivid, though, are Semyon's son, the sneery, hotheaded Kirill (Vincent Cassel), and his driver, poker-faced Nikolai (Viggo Mortensen), who is angling to move up in the family business. (Semyon treats him like a second son.) Both carry a beyond-cool mystique of solemnly heartless old-world machismo. Nikolai, toughened by his time in Soviet prisons, is a particular enigma: a dashing statue of a man, at once calculating hard case and noble knight. He woos Anna, who has no idea that he's a gangster, and begins to win her over with his frosty-eyed reticence.
Eastern Promises  unpeels like an onion of corruption, with double crosses and deceptions, and ordinary do-gooders (like Anna's crusty old uncle) in way over their heads. Cronenberg's craftsmanship is seductive, yet anyone waiting for a conventional resolution, or even a coherent one, will be soundly disappointed. The film's key sequence is an amazingly vicious fight in which Nikolai, naked, fends off two dagger-wielding assassins in a steam bath, grabbing their weapons and plunging them again and again. And again. Cronenberg, riffing on the strategy of A History of Violence , wants us to gaze at Viggo Mortensen and see not just a man but a paradox, a walking deconstruction of humanity's dual nature: good and  bad, immersed in a violence so brutal it can only have come from evil, even if it's being used for justice. But this is all a bit much to pile onto a conventional heart-of-darkness thriller. Eastern Promises  is a decent night out, but in delivering ''more'' than it promises, it also delivers less.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>