<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Sep 02, 2009</date>
      <text>The mass of men, wrote Henry David Thoreau, lead lives of quiet desperation. You could debate whether that statement is still true &#151; or maybe more  true &#151; in the age of cozy fat armchairs and giant-screen TVs. But it's certainly true this year in one breed of late-summer movie: the masochistic comedy of everyday jerkdom, in which we behold the flailing of losers who are really us. Extract  and Big Fan  both feature small-fry heroes who don't act so much as they get acted upon . True, neither one of these men is particularly quiet. But that hardly makes them any less desperate.
Couldn't Mike Judge, with his acid wit, have come up with a better title for a suburban-schlub comedy than &#8232;Extract ? The title refers to the company owned by Joel (Jason Bateman), who bottles ''natural'' food sweetener on a mini-factory assembly line that he's on the verge of selling to General Mills. The plan gets squashed when one of his workers (Clifton Collins Jr.) loses a testicle &#8232;in a freak industrial accident. The worker decides to sue, mostly at the prompting of Cindy (Mila Kunis), a sociopathic hottie. The weirdest thing about Extract  is that the small-business chicanery isn't even Joel's main problem. That would be his wife (Kristen Wiig), who draws her sweatpants tight with chastity-belt precision. Joel plans to relieve his sexual frustration by sleeping with Cindy, but he must first absolve his guilt by hiring a dumb gigolo (Dustin Milligan) to seduce his wife, a plan that ends up working a little too well.
I love Mike Judge's cartoons (King of the Hill , Beavis and Butt-Head ), and Idiocracy  (2006), his unfairly dumped future-shock satire, had flashes of demented brilliance. But didn't Judge realize that Extract , with its plastic setups and one-dimensional harpies, plays like Kevin Smith remaking a bad George Segal comedy from 1978? There are a handful of fun moments. Judge has Joel take one of the longest bong hits in movie history, and he casts Ben Affleck, in terrifying hair, as a pill-popping medicine chest of a bartender. (Affleck is the one actor on screen who looks like he's having fun.) But there's something didactic, overly programmed , about the middle-class misery of Extract . It's not just the characters' lives that are stifled &#151; so is Judge's spontaneity as a filmmaker.
Big Fan , the first movie directed as well &#8232;as written by Robert Siegel (who wrote The &#8232;Wrestler ), stars Patton Oswalt as a 35-year-old Staten Island parking-garage attendant who has no life apart from his fervid devotion to the New York Giants. The movie is an unblinking look at the hidden (or perhaps not so &#8232; hidden) pathology of American sports mania, in which the power and victory of your team becomes the sole conduit for your self-worth.
Oswalt's Paul sits in his parking booth, then arrives back at the house he shares with his mother to call the Sports Dog radio phone-in show. There, he spouts the ''spontaneous'' Go Giants! Eagles suck!  rant he has already scrawled on a legal pad. Oswalt, looking like a mild, dwarfish Michael Moore, makes &#8232;Paul an unnervingly rational nut, a spokesman for the ''wholesome'' addiction our all-sports-all-the-time culture has become. After Paul spots the Giants' superstar linebacker, he tails him to a strip club and ends up getting beaten up by his idol &#151; an event that you'd think would leave him furious. But it only heightens the cultishness of his worship; Paul, it turns out, loves the Giants more than he loves himself. Big Fan , while it holds us right up to the suspenseful simmer of its nerd–Taxi Driver  climax, doesn't go where you'd expect. That's what makes Siegel, more than Judge, a born filmmaker.

</text>
   </review>
</reviews>