<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews>
   <review>
      <date>Nov 04, 2008</date>
      <text>Role Models  is a comedy about two loser-slacker- underachievers (they hawk energy drinks at public schools &#151; 'nuff said) who get arrested for crashing a truck and then sentenced to 150 hours of community service. Each of them has to play big brother to a kid with major adjustment problems, and if you hear that and think, ''Isn't this a remake of some maximally dumb comedy from the 1980s?'' you’d be justified. The fun of Role Models  is that it's a high-concept movie executed with speed and finesse and the kind of brusquely tossed-off obscene banter that can get you laughing before you know what hit you. The fish-out-of-water setup may be claptrap, but the movie feels loose, shaggy, and improv-y. Especially after Danny (Paul Rudd), a 35-year-old mope who sounds as if his soul has been burnt to a crisp, and Wheeler (Seann William Scott), a skirt chaser without a single mean bone in his body, arrive at the Sturdy Wings mentorship center and discover that trying to actually, you know, relate  to a kid is their own special brand of hell.
Wheeler is assigned to a pint-size pottymouth (Bobb'e J. Thompson) as mentally agile as he is misbehaved, while Danny gets stuck with Augie, a myopic nasal teenage dork who devotes his afternoons to organized medieval role-play. Christopher Mintz-Plasse plays this super-dweeb with such conviction that you're not sure if you want to laugh at him, give him a pep talk, or slap him silly. The director, David Wain, had devious fun putting bad youth movies through the wringer in Wet Hot American Summer , and here he shows a corkscrew affection for the kind of studio comedy that's far too by-the-numbers to be mistaken for reality. What makes Role Models  a kick is that its heroes act as if they can't quite believe their predicament is real either. Rudd delivers put-downs like a toxic avenger, while Scott, in his freshest star turn since American Pie , uses his disarming sweetness to make Wheeler the most nuttily likable of sleazebags. They're matched by Jane Lynch, who plays the Sturdy Wings overseer as an ex-addict who couldn't be prouder of those addictions; she's hooked on overdoses of ego. The big medieval battle of the cardboard swords, with our heroes done up like the Knights of a certain rock band, is an event the movie pays tribute to by seeing through every gloriously geeky minute of it.
</text>
   </review>
</reviews>