<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>13 Tzameti</name>
   <company>Palm Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Géla Babluani</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Géla Babluani</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>FranceGeorgia</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>George Babluani</actor>
      <actor>Philippe Passon</actor>
      <actor>Aurélien Recoing</actor>
      <actor>Pascal Bongard</actor>
      <actor>Vania Vilers</actor>
      <actor>Nicolas Pignon</actor>
      <actor>Olga Legr</actor>
      <actor>Christophe Van de Velde</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>93</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The language and the landscape is French, but the sensibility and style is unmistakably Eastern European.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/286856_limited29.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Starts slowly but builds, Hitchcock-style, to a terrifying crescendo. And don't fool yourself into thinking you know what's going to happen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/well_done_noirish_number_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>13 Tzameti is cut from the same cloth as the humans-hunted-for-sport classic "The Most Dangerous Game" - and from that early talkie's many subsequent remakes and rip-offs, including John Woo's "Hard Target."</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=694715&amp;reviewId=21398</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A stylish and unnerving thriller that sucks you into surreal scenes of horror with the chilly confidence of a nightmare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1163040928254140.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Take 13 Tzameti for what it is: a tightly screwed shocker, a suspense tour de force that proceeds through a harrowing chain of events with alarming confidence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070119.wtzameti19/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's simplicity and intensity are aided by the crisp black-and-white photography of Tariel Meliava. Director Babluani's greenness shows itself in the ending, which is weak, but the film nevertheless stays with you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/13/DDGV9LNKB61.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Creating a mood that suggests an unholy mix of Czech novelist Franz Kafka, American pulp fictionist Jim Thompson and French heist moviemaker Jean-Pierre Melville, Babluani's story is about the perils of get-rich-quick schemes.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060908-movies-review-13,0,6870917.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shot in neorealist black-and-white, it opens like a gritty slice of social drama, then takes a sharp turn into bleak, existential horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=47218&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The resulting jolts add up to one unforgettably surreal nightmare. Just be sure your heart can handle any surprises headed your way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/438842p-369482c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Géla Babluani is unmistakably a first-timer, and his debut project is raw and rough-edged. But he aces the way simple images can make the most of a simple story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/50968</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The work of both Babluani brothers is weirdly stilled and mature, already devoid of the need to show off--serves only to thicken the horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060807crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shot like the grunge version of a '50s noir thriller from France (or Soviet Georgia), the black-and-white 13 (Tzameti) turns into a shocker of Tarantino proportions in protracted sequences of explosive violence that leave viewers quaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928145?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although it's likely too stark for everyone, 13 Tzameti offers a mind-blowing experience for anyone willing to go along for the ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-tzameti11aug11,0,1785714.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One wonders what its objective is other than the cynical obliteration of all hope.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A415694</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>13 (Tzameti) is an existential horror film, a violent prank, a metaphor for modern Europe, and a first-time director's startling calling card.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9333</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>13 Tzameti is certainly nightmarish, but it's the kind of nightmare that fades instead of lingering on in the memory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2988</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The artiest entry in the ever growing torture-movie genre, this playfully wicked French thriller from twentysomething provocateur Gela Babluani blasts its way into your brainpan with the help of black-and-white widescreen cinematography whose striking but smooth textures better suit the upwardly mobile auteur than his poor protagonist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0630,nelson,73966,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its icy cynicism and desolate settings, the film evokes the work of the young Roman Polanski in his sadistic trickster mode.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/07/28/movies/28tzam.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For me, the meticulous style, the fascination with ritualized (and ludicrous) violence and the film-geek self-referentiality all seem like markers of a film made by a young man, for other young men. If I were 23, and full to the brim with dark-hearted existentialism, I might love it too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/07/20/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not for the faint-hearted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002423882</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We are meant to think about a society that revels in this moral pit. But all that puzzled me was why an audience would need a film to immerse it in wanton, speciously motivated death when the television news provides so much of it every day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060828&amp;s=kauffmann082806</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>French art thriller 13 Tzameti has a literal hair-trigger premise, yet it's so lacking in human dimensions that it creates virtually no suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1222165_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's so easy to be seduced by technique... What a disappointment, then, to find the technique pressed into the service of little substance and lots of fashionable cynicism.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>These actors move with the labored blocking of a high school play.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118018&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Adriane Quinlan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>13 (Tzameti) might seem allegorical, but it’s too cynically concerned with what works as entertainment to offer larger truths about human existence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/060908/</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$121,390</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,805</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>