<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>27 Dresses</name>
   <company>20th Century Fox</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Aline Brosh Mc</author>
      <author>Kenna</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Anne Fletcher</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Katherine Heigl</actor>
      <actor>James Marsden</actor>
      <actor>Malin Akerman</actor>
      <actor>Ed Burns</actor>
      <actor>Melora Hardin</actor>
      <actor>Judy Greer</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 18, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>107</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Predictable but utterly engaging, 27 Dresses will likely be remembered as the film that made Katherine Heigl an A-list star.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.dresses18jan18,0,6912730.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mostly silly and always frothy, as sugary at times as wedding-cake frosting but tempered with a welcome strain of sour grapes, mostly doled out by the peerless Judy Greer as Jane's cynical, slutty best friend.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/382753.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frothy, funny and formulaic, 27 Dresses is a pleasantly predictable romantic comedy that sees Katherine Heigl following “Knocked Up” with smooth moves at the wheel of her first starring vehicle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935723.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It delivers everything you expect on a timetable you can predict to the minute. It's filmmaking as a cross between a carefully choreographed dance and an elaborate pageant.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/347755_27dresses18q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's not a surprising moment in the movie yet it works in spite of the stale, insipid storyline. That has a lot to do with lead actress Katherine Heigl and a little to do with the glowing embers between her and her co-star, James Marsden.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/t/27_dresses.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sporadically entertaining cupcake of a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10356</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>27 Dresses is like one of the many bridesmaid dresses featured in the film: frothy, predictable and over the top.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-01-17-27-dresses_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cute, cute, cute. No bouquets for originality, but it pushes all the buttons of this mini-genre, and Heigl and Marsden ring dem bells.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135244</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The romantic comedy 27 Dresses will work best for people who have never seen a romantic comedy. If you have, you might find it amusing to tally up the steals – I mean, homages.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0118/p12s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>27 Dresses is a movie geared to a pitch of high matrimonial-princess fever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20170199,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The jokes hit about half the time – the best bits have an off-the-cuff feel – and it’s pocked with the kind of rom-com clichés that are practically written in stone (screenwriter Aline Brosh McKenna's script for "The Devil Wears Prada" was far sharper).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A581464</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The eerily precise Heigl, who provided confident back-court support as the exile in Guyville also known as “Knocked Up,” has no trouble filling a leading lady’s shoes. She’s just snarky enough to be interesting, and she knows how to take a fall.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-27-dresses/286250/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a tangle unknotted in the most predictable fashion by Aline McKenna's script, and with little flair from choreographer-turned-director Anne Fletcher.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/27_dresses</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A chick-flick on a sugar high, so giggly-bouncy and nostalgic for the fantasy-girlhood of its audience that the DVD, which should follow relatively quickly, should come packaged in big pink bows and include a coupon for a free pony ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4357/27-dresses.html</url>
         <critic>Ryan Stewart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Katherine Heigl makes an official bid for America's Sweetheart in her sophomore effort, 27 Dresses, a romantic comedy that -- despite her undeniable, apple-cheeked appeal -- sags like a day-old bouquet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145383&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almost everything about this starring vehicle for Katharine Heigl feels borrowed from some previous romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080117.wdresses18/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No worse and no better than the majority of chick flicks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01182008/entertainment/movies/she_wears_it_well_215484.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the director, Anne Fletcher, methodically cuts back and forth between two weddings, she makes the reasonably insightful, moderately funny point that modern American weddings, however they may strain for individuality and specialness, are all pretty much alike. The problem is that much the same could be said about modern American romantic comedies.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/01/18/movies/18dres.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For most of this romantic comedy, fatuous contrivances run neck and neck with what seem to be authentic observations about repressed sibling rivalry; some of the latter are too painful to be funny, and eventually the contrivances win out, but the cast keeps it all watchable.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32604_TWENTY_SEVEN_DRESSES.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>27 Dresses dutifully privileges its formulaic plot over its stick-figure characters, slapping a happy ending on a setup that, say, "Happiness" director Todd Solondz could have gone to town on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-dresses18jan18,0,3625328.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Heigl is terrific, this uninspired romantic comedy is considerably less so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=10393&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Light, formulaic and soft around the middle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/27-dresses/review/291861</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are glimpses of the wit McKenna displayed in “Prada,” but these brief gasps of life are quickly suffocated by the inevitable schmaltz.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10707</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So flimsy it gives froth a bad name.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15481326/review/18048506/27_dresses</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Marsden's natural charisma is totally wasted in an unlikable role, while Burns doesn't even try to hide his boredom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/01/18/2008-01-18_katherine_heigls_radiant_but_27_dresses_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Much as I gnashed my teeth during 27 Dresses, I genuinely enjoyed the warmth of Heigl's and Marsden's confident ease. While both might be a few minutes past their star-is-born moment, these troupers with more than 30 years of professional work between them have never shone so brightly. It may sound contradictory, but loved them, hated IT.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080118_A_marriage_easy_on_the_eyes.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only bright spot is Marsden, a great actor who's always stuck playing the less-desirable romantic rival (see: "The Notebook," "X-Men," "Superman Returns"). He finally gets the fun-guy role for a change and does everything he can to rip it up. He can only do so much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1200533115315440.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The biggest disappointment of 27 Dresses is that it inhabits a Harlequin romance New York City, one remarkably short on homosexuals and divorce.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/01/18/27_dresses/</url>
         <critic>Mary Elizabeth Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A forgettable, formulaic comedy so predictable that seeing it and skipping it are the exact same thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0803,wilonsky,78852,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Katherine Heigl carries 27 Dresses when all else fails, which it does with great regularity.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120061149390499007.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It gets worse and worse as it goes along and finally ends just as it's becoming unbearable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/18/DDS0UF2V1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$76,808,654</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$23,007,725</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,057</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>