<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>3:10 to Yuma</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Western</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Elmore Leonard</author>
      <author>Derek Haas</author>
      <author>Michael Brandt</author>
      <author>Halsted Welles</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>James Mangold</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Christian Bale</actor>
      <actor>Russell Crowe</actor>
      <actor>Ben Foster</actor>
      <actor>Alan Tudyk</actor>
      <actor>Gretchen Mol</actor>
      <actor>Peter Fonda</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 7, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>James Mangold's 3:10 to Yuma restores the wounded heart of the Western and rescues it from the morass of pointless violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070906/REVIEWS/709060305</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The new version is a glorious, thrilling throwback that never sacrifices its solid roots in the western genre despite a sharp modern update that actually improves on the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/story/227367.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The finest American Westerns have a characteristic that 3:10 to Yuma shares. In a way that's almost mystical, they suggest a truth beyond the specifics of the tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/09/07/DDBQRR59R.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The rousing new Western 3:10 to Yuma has the sweep of an epic and the economy of a stopwatch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.yuma07sep07,0,559174.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mangold has time to build sensational, studied characterizations, brilliant pacing (courtesy Mike McCuster, who also edited the director’s previous effort, the Johnny Cash biopic “Walk the Line”), and blistering action.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10271</url>
         <critic>KJ Doughton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>James Mangold directs it with such energy and passion that it's as if he didn't know it's all been done before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-yuma7sep07,0,1382051.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike Glenn Ford, a soft-spoken studio star who was cast against type as Wade 50 years ago, Crowe is a perfect fit. Not because of his bad boy behavior offscreen, but because he can blend charm and menace better than anyone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/09/07/2007-09-07_russell_crowes_on_track_in_310_to_yuma_r-1.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The nerve-racking wait at the Contention hotel is no longer the film's centerpiece, but the deeper characterization gives Bale an opportunity to once again sink his teeth into a complex role, and offers a reminder as to why the notoriously difficult Crowe is sometimes worth the trouble.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/310-yuma/review/290231</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both actors are among the best, most intuitively creative we have, and whatever transpires offscreen in Crowe’s case, onscreen they only serve their characters. Neither man showboats here, and it’s a thrill to watch them work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9716</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A riveting remake of a pretty terrific 1957 western about manhood, fatherhood and honor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20070907_Good_vs__Evil__finely_drawn.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fine and sturdy picture, capable of standing alongside the many such films made when Westerns were one of our chief entertainments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1188951924242820.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Alfred Hitchcock once said about thrillers also applies to Westerns: The stronger the bad guy, the better the film. By that measure, 3:10 to Yuma is excellent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0907/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mangold delivers a taut modern take on a lesser classic, preserving the "High Noon" themes about doing the right thing against all odds, and injecting a more modern pacing and urgency without going overboard. His film isn't Leonard's classic, but it's a solid, genre-respecting Western in its own right.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/3_10_to_yuma</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A largely compelling ride on the strength of a powerful cast led by Russell Crowe and Christian Bale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9637&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this movie, Fonda really is iconic. 3:10 to Yuma may be familiar, but, at its best, it has a rapt quality, even an aura of wonder.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/09/03/070903crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>James Mangold's remake walks a fine line in retaining many of the original's qualities while smartly shaking things up a bit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934435.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Period westerns are so unfashionable and costly that they usually require a top-drawer script to get off the ground -- and this one, adapted from an Elmore Leonard story and its 1957 movie version, travels with an arrow's clean arc.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#32035</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who says remakes are always inferior to the original film? And who says the western is dead? Especially when a movie is as entertaining as this one, you begin to think this formerly beloved genre is due for a revival.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1659969,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film is an example of a Western that ought to appeal to a healthy-sized contemporary audience, and is also a remake of the 1957 film of the same name, which is a hallmark of the type of psychological Western.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A530437</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Captures a potent sense of the Old West with its multidimensional raw performances and captivating final shootout sequence. But with its emphasis on emotional truths, it transcends the confines of a cowboy movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-09-06-yuma-review_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The 30-minute finale, which includes a tense stand-off with Ben's gang, is masterfully executed. It's perfectly paced, suspenseful, and ends in a way that's both appropriate and satisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/t/310_yuma.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is how a Western today tries to give us more bang for the buck. By working this hard to be a crowd-pleaser, though, it may please fewer crowds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20053547,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe this redo didn’t need so many bells and whistles, but Mangold brings it home.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/14539861/review/16255501/310_to_yuma</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the newer version's darker ending lends a more contemporary twist, overall 3:10 to Yuma is reverent to the original – a few more bullets and more spilled blood notwithstanding.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070907.wyuma07/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extremely well-acted and well-directed remake of a 1957 oater.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09072007/entertainment/movies/best_western.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mangold has been smart or fortunate in casting, and personalities sustain interest even when the narrative flags.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=941072&amp;reviewId=22656&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the battle of the leading men, Crowe's character has a slight edge, and the actor really makes the most of it, showing us how boyishly mischievous charm and utter venality can exist without seeming contradiction in the same being. But Bale builds to a pretty impressive boil himself after laying back for about three quarters of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4050/310-to-yuma.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, the picture is accomplished, intelligent and, in places, a little dull. Mangold isn't an economical filmmaker, and parts of 3:10 to Yuma suffer from needless bloat. The new version doesn't use the same kind of blunt, visually arresting shorthand as Daves' original...And yet somehow, maybe just barely, Mangold -- succeeds on his own terms, largely because the actors he's working with here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/09/07/yuma/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As Ben Wade, gang leader and murderer, he gives an ironic performance, but Crowe’s irony is more intense than other actors’ obsession. He turns the idea of having so few emotions--of being beyond caring--into a bloody joke. He upstages everyone with his laughing eyes.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/37248/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's best performance belongs to Peter Fonda. Tough, terrific, and totally unrecognizable as a bounty hunter, this cantankerous old hippie is so leathery he deserves his own line of rawhide apparel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0736,hoberman,77661,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What this version offers is the chance to watch Russell Crowe and Christian Bale—two of the more charismatic, macho leading men around--duke it out psychologically, while another fine but less well-known intensity artist, Ben Foster, steals</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20534717/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More likely to be recalled as a moderately satisfying entertainment than remembered as a classic.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/09/07/movies/07yuma.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Under Mangold’s sure if uninspired hand, the new Yuma is reasonably exciting and terse, and, like its predecessor, built around a memorable villain of ambiguous villainy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-310-to-yuma-exiled-hatchet/17173/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result bears so little resemblance to the original that you have to wonder what happened. It seems more a remake of "How the West Was Won" than 3:10 to Yuma.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/330593_310yuma07q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The acting is its chief strength. Russell Crowe brings a cocky charisma to Ben Wade.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070907-movies-review-yuma,0,4138162.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The strengths of the first "3:10 To Yuma" were enhanced by its proportionality -- an intimate story told in 92 minutes. The story is no bigger in the new version, which goes on for 117 minutes. And it's certainly not better.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118911720903119886.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The remake adds 24 minutes and subtracts most of the suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1109519&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$53,606,916</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$48,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$14,035,033</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,652</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>russell crowe</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>