<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>49 UP</name>
   <company>First Run Features</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Apted</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Bruce Balden</actor>
      <actor>Jacqueline Bassett</actor>
      <actor>Symon Basterfield</actor>
      <actor>Andrew Brackfield</actor>
      <actor>John Brisby</actor>
      <actor>Suzanne Dewey</actor>
      <actor>Charles Furneaux</actor>
      <actor>Nicholas Hitchon</actor>
      <actor>Neil Hughes</actor>
      <actor>Lynn Johnson</actor>
      <actor>Paul Kligerman</actor>
      <actor>Susan Sullivan</actor>
      <actor>Tony Walker</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 6, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>135</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>49 Up is a precious document, and must viewing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1542496_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The latest riveting, heartbreaking chapter to one of the supreme creations of documentary filmmaking, the "7 Up" series.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/10/05/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dropping by on the same people every seven years like an old friend - or an unwelcome relative - Apted has constructed a peerless, suspenseful work that develops character to a depth that would make Tolstoy jealous. If you have any interest in documentaries, watch the DVD of the first film, "7 Up" (49 Up hits DVD Nov. 14). You won't be able to stop.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10062006/entertainment/movies/looking_up_yet_again_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No matter their wealth or social status, these people share disappointments and elations and a sense that life, in the end, may be what life is about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9198</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How 49 Up differs from its precursors for the better is that it's the first to have its participants interact with Apted the filmmaker, no longer a one-sided interviewer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/feature/3168/new-york-film-festival-2006-update-3.html</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you haven't gotten hooked already on Michael Apted's series--collectively, one of the great documentaries in the history of the cinema--you should prepare yourself for the latest installment, 49 Up.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061103-movies-review-49,0,649595.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This seventh installment is utterly fascinating.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/nextweek/30577_FORTY_NINE_UP.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I am not British, was born 14 years before the subjects, and yet by now identify intensely with them, because some kinds of human experience -- teenage, work, marriage, illness are universal. You could make this series in any society.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20061102/REVIEWS/611020304</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Apted's landmark films documenting the lives of a disparate group of Brits in seven-year intervals have always been fascinating from a sociological perspective. But the latest installment proves that they are undeniably brilliant cinematically as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003221257</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the best things about Michael Apted's uniquely ambitious and continuing documentary series on the lives of a group of British schoolchildren is that you don't have to have seen the last one to enjoy the next.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/459031p-386039c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A solid starting point for those unfamiliar with Apted's greatest work, and a must-see for those who have been down this road before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/f/49_up.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While all the "Up" films hold a fascination akin to a Christmas letter from an almost-forgotten friend, 42 Up didn't show much progress from "35 Up." Even fans of the series had to wonder whether the faces of England were going to remain permanently frozen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/53753</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The passage of time has rarely been more forcefully conveyed in a movie, as we see clips of the interviewees not only from today but also at seven-year intervals from the past.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1006/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>49 Up is more than a deeply satisfying movie; it's a reminder of the wonder contained in ordinary lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-up6oct06,0,1344262.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Suzy's marriage, Nick's divorce, Paul's work history: none of it is my or anyone else's business. But these things -- these people -- have become, through Mr. Apted's films, a vital part of modern life, which seems to grow richer every seven years, when the new "Up" movie comes out.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/10/05/movies/05fort.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Their pain is our pleasure, for though occasionally Apted's bluntness makes you want to take a bite out of his neck, there's something immensely satisfying about watching the playing out of ordinary lives we've become attached to over time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14706/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The segments are so cleverly arranged--Apted includes past pictorial references for each of the people we revisit--that now there is something almost mystical involved. It is as if a wizard were giving us an overview of forty-two years that mortals were possibly not meant to see.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20061016&amp;s=kauffmann101606</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the series means in the long run is anybody's guess; I just know I sleep better at night knowing it's out there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A407487</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Taken as a whole, these films constitute one of the greatest uses of cinema a documentary filmmaker has ever devised. Like the other films in the series, 49 Up is alternately touching and mundane, part soap opera, part reality show and part anthropological study.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/10/06/DDGURLIC1L1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because the subjects are all mellowing into grandparenthood and their abrasive, wilder days are behind them, this particular "scrapbook" isn't as heavy hitting and hard-edged as its predecessors.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/288484_limited13.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Profoundly different from the others. On the cusp of their half-century mark, Apted's British subjects have accommodated themselves to what they were, what they are, and what they will be.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/22318/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Moving and ambitious in scale like nothing else in cinema, Michael Apted's Up films began in 1964 as a BBC news program exploring an old Jesuit maxim: "Give me the child until he is seven, and I will show you the man."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0640,atkinson,74635,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The more you watch, the more you are committing yourself to watching "56 Up" and beyond.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1124069&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For Americans, the film may be best taken as fodder for debate, especially for individuals interested in sociology. You wonder why those people stuck to the commitment. You may also wonder how different a parallel American film would've been.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=714814&amp;reviewId=21572</url>
         <critic>Marta Barber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It doesn't make for involving drama, unless the audience is already invested in the subjects' fortunes. Thus, 49 Up will have more appeal for long-time followers than newcomers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930878?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Eddie Cockrell</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$241,772</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$120,207</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>18</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>