<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>9 Songs</name>
   <company>Tartan USA</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Winterbottom</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Winterbottom</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Kieran O&amp;#039;Brien</actor>
      <actor>Margo Stilley</actor>
      <actor>Black Rebel Motorcycle Club</actor>
      <actor>The Dy Warhols</actor>
      <actor>Elbow</actor>
      <actor>Franz Ferdin</actor>
      <actor>Michael Nyman</actor>
      <actor>Primal Scream</actor>
      <actor>Super Furry Animals</actor>
      <actor>The Von Bondies</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 22, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>71</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A touching, often poetic, sometimes achingly real snapshot of a brief encounter related almost entirely through the bedroom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117923908&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>9 Songs, for all its failed ambitions and its tinge of sexism, is lovely to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/22/movies/22song.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While 9 Songs is sexually explicit in the basic sense, its DIRECTNESS is what's most fascinating, and ultimately most moving, about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/07/22/9_songs/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Winterbottom nakedly goes where no "respectable" director has gone before - to sex and beyond! His provocative 9 Songs is the first movie by a director of Winterbottom's standing to depict real, uncensored sex between its lead actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/07-22-2005/entertainment/movies/story/330355p-282318c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film accurately reminds you, if you need reminding, what it's like to have your mind hijacked by somebody's body.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/50154.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ingenious with his use of music and hypnotic pacing, Winterbottom keeps us in his world as usual. But this time that world feels ever more gratuitous, meandering and puzzling, with sex that's less and less authentic even though it's real.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050825-movies-review-ninesongs,0,3394455.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the emotional equivalent of a big shrug.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=391352&amp;reviewId=19209</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie is, essentially, porn, and whether it's a turn-on is likely to be subjective to each viewer. Those who find traditional porn too artificial should be pleased.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Members of what used to be referred to euphemistically as the "raincoat crowd," will probably enjoy Winterbottom's experiment more than most.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46327</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Winterbottom never provides the empathic connective tissue we expect. Love it or not, 9 Songs amounts to a common human rite fastidiously caught in amber, giving off no heat or joy but crystallized for the future.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0529,atkinson1,66017,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nobody will go to see Michael Winterbottom's sexually explicit, novelty-act drama - a naughty peep show for sobersides, disguised as a nature documentary - to hear the songs; everyone will go to see the shagging, which occupies the majority of the screen time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1084830_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neither lurid nor especially compelling. This is the triumph, and the limitation, of 9 Songs: it makes explicit movie sex ordinary--as ordinary as the sexual activities of most of the folks watching it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1086158,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's always hard to predict what Winterbottom will try next, but this experiment isn't worth repeating, the lively concert scenes notwithstanding. Be forewarned that the sexual scenes aren't simulated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0729/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As an idea, the film is fascinating, but as an experience it grows tedious; the concerts lack closeups, the sex lacks context, and Antarctica could use a few penguins.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050825/REVIEWS/50822001/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a movie that consists almost entirely of real sex and real rock 'n' roll, 9 Songs feels remarkably conventional.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/movies/archives/2005/0805/050826.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Winterbottom's erotic drama isn't so much a story of a love affair as an anatomy of a sexual relationship.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/237144_limited19.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a smart, provocative idea for a movie. I wish 9 Songs was that movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7554</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It works best as a spank-it movie you don’t have to feel guilty about and that you can dance to. And there’s nothing wrong with that.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A287215</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With no previous acting experience, she's (Stilley) a natural between the sheets but a rank amateur between the vowels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050923/NINE23/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As 9 Songs played out for sixty-nine (count ‘em!) minutes, I started to find myself wishing they would just end the interminable, deliberately underlit, sex scenes and get back to those really hot pics of Antarctica.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=6849</url>
         <critic>Bob Westal</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A stultifying bore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1129200951284690.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An examination of a sexual relationship that's about as viscerally explicit as hardcore can get...But as satisfying viewing experiences go, the film comes up mighty short in terms of story, interesting characters and technical prowess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000629711</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Between the performances in the bedroom and on stage, 9 Songs gives off plenty of heat, but the whole project seems half-thought-out and hastily arranged, hampered by butt-ugly DV photography that turn skin tones grimy and make the Brixton scenes look as high-grain as a bowl of Mueslix.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8719</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yet for all its ballyhooed candor about sexual matters, it's a surprisingly baffling and opaque film, too artistic to be standard pornography and too zealously focused on being graphic to the exclusion of all else to succeed as drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-songs29jul29,0,7766599.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>9 Songs could have been "Last Rock Show in London." Unfortunately, it's stupefyingly dull, even with good music and at the short but resonant length of 69 minutes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2123555/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never did sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll seem more shopworn and routine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081101123.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>9 Songs inadvertently proves just how limited experimentation for its own sake can be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081101851.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a fine film to be made about the retreat from worldly obligation into erotic rite, and Brando and Bertolucci made it in 1972. But what “Last Tango in Paris” proved was that our skin-grazing view of a body makes us more, not less, enthusiastic to grasp the shape of the soul that it enshrines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050801crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This disappointing new film from director Michael Winterbottom ("24 Hour Party People") suffers from a similar malaise: It's poetic and pretty, strives for profundity without attaining it, and finally ends up saying nothing.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/08/12/DDGQAE60TG1.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$49,835</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,457</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>