<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Adam</name>
   <company>Fox Searchlight Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Max Mayer</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Max Mayer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Hugh Dancy</actor>
      <actor>Rose Byrne</actor>
      <actor>Peter Gallagher</actor>
      <actor>Amy Irving</actor>
      <actor>Frankie Faison</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 29, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>99</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Subtlety and nuance mark both the film's dialogue and performances. It's hard to see how Dancy and Byrne could be any better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-adam29-2009jul29,0,2699739.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tendency for an actor in a role like this is to overact. The result is often disastrous, reducing a character into a caricature. Hugh Dancy, adopting an American accent as effectively as the mannerisms of someone on the moderate portion of the Asperger's spectrum, makes Adam believable and generally sympathetic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1734</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The beautifully crafted Adam offers no pat or easy answers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/07292009/entertainment/movies/adam_shows_autistic_merit_181911.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the speed of love, not the speed of light, that occupies Adam, a small, sweet movie about one man's widening cosmos.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/08/06/MVF4194F1T.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Amy Biancolli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may not be original, but Adam could leave a lump in your throat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/3965A0837CC9BBE08625761700716782?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When it's not lapsing into disease-of-the-week prose, Adam presents a credible account of the challenges inherent in this misunderstood and often-ridiculed condition.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/08/my_lover_my_astronomer_adam.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best, Adam makes the viewer understand the frustration of living in a world in which everyone is a stranger -- not least by making us work as hard to understand its hero's feelings as Adam himself must work to understand Beth's.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/adam,1156449/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Dan Kois</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sensitive but not sentimental story about a romance involving a mentally challenged young man never makes a misstep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-adam-1003931866.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Emotionally potent performances, gently offbeat humor and writer-helmer Max Mayer's assured touch guide this tender New York love story to a quietly hopeful conclusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939413.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Adam</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The humor is delicate, and the performances sweet and sure; the script (by the director, Max Mayer) is not entirely predictable, and the Manhattan locations (lovingly photographed by Seamus Tierney) have a starry-eyed glaze.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/07/29/movies/29adam.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to buy this relationship even for a moment. Adam is sweet, meticulous, and, at times, sort of clever, but it's also a not-quite-surprising-enough heartwarming trifle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20294563,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adam is a cut above most romances and boasts a intriguing conclusion. One comes away with a sense of hope, leavened by realism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-07-28-adam_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adam wraps up their story in too tidy a package, insisting on finding the upbeat in the murky, and missing the chance to be more thoughtful about this challenging situation.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090805/REVIEWS/908059993</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most daring thing about Adam, the story of a young man with Asperger's syndrome, is that there isn't a scene in which someone stops to explain exactly what Asperger's IS.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1194628.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The climax and epilogue are the juiciest, most tough-minded bits in the movie. Too bad Mayer didn't work his way backward from the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/bal-ae.mo.adam21aug21,0,2713555.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It can be argued that Adam uses Asperger's as a kind of metaphor for the barriers that people erect to fend off strangers, to guard against intimacy. It can also be argued that writer/director Mayer is shamelessly manipulative.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090807_It_s_a_sweet_love_story__and_not_so_neuro-typical.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A very superficial look at what it may be like trying to romance someone on the autistic scale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136484</url>
         <critic>Anna Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adam succeeds at getting inside its hero's mind and, more impressively still, gives us entrée to his singular soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dancy’s character has difficulty processing information and dealing with emotion, but even he could probably see through this schmaltz.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/adam,31084/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beyond that educational element and the delicate performances of Dancy and Byrne, I found Adam dramatically limp, predictable and in a curious way even retrograde.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/07/29/adam/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Is a man with Asperger’s boyfriend material? It’s difficult to determine how we wind up here, but it’s strange that a movie ostensibly about a man and his lack of social options left me depressed about a woman and hers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/08/07/romantic_drama_adam_fails_to_take_a_chance/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Other than Rose Byrne's on-screen radiance and a soothingly warm palette lit by cinematographer Seamus Tierney, there's not much to get passionate about in this amiable chamberpiece from theater director Max Mayer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-07-28/film/pieces-lock-snugly-in-amiable-chamberpiece-adam/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Were it not for the fine engaging performances of both Dancy and Byrne, Adam would be sickly sweet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/adam/article1243609/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As predictable as the alphabet but should hold particular appeal to women whose maternal impulses inflect their mating instincts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?film=977550</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As well-intended as it is, writer-director Max Mayer's film lacks focus.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/08/touching_adam_has_heart_but_la.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I find nearly every film about mentally challenged characters excruciating to watch...None of these movies ever come close to accurately depicting what it’s like to live with mental challenges.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11783</url>
         <critic>Jessica Baxter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the kind of movie in which every other line of dialogue feels like a metaphor – and from there on, the film seesaws between the uncomfortable extremes of glum and twee: an overwrought dirge keyed to a xylophonic ping.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A820684</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,277,396</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$96,888</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>