<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Aeon Flux</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Phil Hay</author>
      <author>Peter Chung</author>
      <author>Matt Manfredi</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Karyn Kusama</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Charlize Theron</actor>
      <actor>Marton Csokas</actor>
      <actor>Jonny Lee Miller</actor>
      <actor>Sophie Okonedo</actor>
      <actor>Frances McDorm</actor>
      <actor>Pete Postlethwaite</actor>
      <actor>Amelia Warner</actor>
      <actor>Caroline Chikezie</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 2, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all so geekily gorgeous, it hardly matters that the narrative lapses in and out of incoherence and the dialogue is functional at best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051203/AEON03/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ideas underlying Aeon Flux's plot are the film's strength, and the filmmakers deserve some credit for doing more than paying lip service to them.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/a/aeon_flux.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aeon Flux is not that terrible. It's certainly more fun than a lot of films that get lovingly showcased.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2130909/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The futuristic thriller is overly familiar and never especially gripping -- and too somber and cerebral for the young action crowd -- but it looks terrific and is in no way an embarrassment.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/250650_aeon03q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By forcing definition on Flux, the filmmakers rob her of any allure. What do they offer instead? Clumsy exposition, bland PG-13 gunfights and subpar computer animation.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501201-movies-review-flux,0,4626801.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Robert K. Elder</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot frequently resets/realigns itself in the fashion of "Lost" or "Alias," as good guys become bad guys, friends become enemies, and combatants become lovers. To portray confusion and uncertainty is one thing; to make a film this unsure of itself, wracked by its own faulty footing and reticence, is quite another.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3684&amp;Sumbit.x=41&amp;Sumbit.y=16</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What made Aeon Flux compelling and special as an animated series had everything to do with the medium and the freedom Chung was given to shape the story as he pleased. Take away those elements, and Aeon Flux becomes nothing more than middling science fiction, which is unfortunately what the film is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2120</url>
         <critic>Ryan Devlin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Theron is an arresting image, but, like everything else in Aeon Flux, she's stranded in a trashy and derivative glum zone of fashion-runway fascism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1137463_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With the exception of a few enjoyable action scenes, such as when Aeon and fellow operative Sithandra (Sophie Okonedo) flip and backflip their way across a lethal garden of bullet-spewing trees and spikes disguised as blades of grass, Aeon Flux is surprisingly draggy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106103&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kusama offers moments of inspiration, but it frustrates like hell that she couldn't nail it completely.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While its heart is in the right place, Aeon Flux's head is just a little too high to make much sense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A315023</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gone are Chung's willfully irrational non sequitur surrealisms, vertiginous designs, dry humor, and physiological weirdness; now we have Charlize Theron trying to look icy, leaping about in resistance to a future dystopia that looks a lot like an overlandscaped European Union industrial park.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0550,atkinson,70895,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a movie best appreciated for the costumes, the sets and Ms. Theron's haughty athleticism.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/12/03/movies/03aeon.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The future looks alternately grim and hysterical in Aeon Flux, a spectacularly silly sci-fier that plays like "The Matrix" crossed with "The Island" and reinterpreted as a long-lost Michael Jackson video.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929028?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This live-action cartoon tries to walk the line between pleasing the faithful and appealing to a broad-based action audience. It fails on both fronts: It's too lifeless and watered-down to stand on its own high heels, but commits the cardinal sin of messing with the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46514</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The wordless six-minute animé shorts - at the end of which our double-jointed heroine would always die - don't lend themselves to a 95-minute action movie where viewers might rightfully expect something to make sense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/12-03-2005/entertainment/col/story/371118p-315725c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smultaneously silly, ostentatious and terribly boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001613908</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aeon Flux is the sophomore picture from Karyn Kusama, who's first movie was a modest boxing film called "Girlfight." Here she's in over her head. The movie's sexual and scientific ideas never come through, and the characters would be fun only if they came with a joystick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8307</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to sit all the way through Aeon Flux while fully awake.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/12/05/DDG73G23CA1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Aeon Flux is what Charlize Theron does to pay the bills while otherwise being engaged in "Monster" and "North Country," it's probably a reasonable price to pay. For her.
For us? No, no, no.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-flux5dec05,0,3536367.story</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Depressing and trivial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=9970</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Every rumor you’ve heard about this film is true; it’s an absolute wreck.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8230</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aeon Flux is by far the year's worst movie, a most dubious achievement.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/58769.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$25,857,987</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$55,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$12,661,112</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,608</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>charlize theron</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>