<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Amreeka</name>
   <company>National Geographic Cinema Ventures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Cherien Dabis</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Cherien Dabis</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
      <origin>Canada</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Nisreen Faour</actor>
      <actor>Melkar Muallem</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 4, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amreeka is strategically inviting and carefully mild even when making unsubtle points about Palestinian suffering and American insensitivity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20301957,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amreeka is anything but a depressing digression on American wartime paranoia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A876296</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This slice of American life, as seen through the eyes of Palestinian immigrants, is nuanced, engaging and authentically observed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-09-03-amreeka-review_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A heartwarming film, not a political dirge. Much of this warmth comes from the actress Nisreen Faour.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090916/REVIEWS/909169987</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's one of the funniest and most perceptive films of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/95539A63ACC9D9248625767200694E77?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Calvin Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a pointed, emotional story of a divorced Palestinian woman and her son who immigrate to the U.S. just after the invasion of Iraq, a story that benefits from Dabis' background as a child growing up in the Midwest during the Gulf War as the daughter of a Palestinian father and a Jordanian mother.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-amreeka4-2009sep04,0,1312069.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Abetted by an observant cast, she (Dabis) navigates across politically and emotionally fraught terrain with a warming inflection of humor and a mother-hen's attention to the needs of all of her characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/amreeka,1158182/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dabis, a Palestinian-American, has thoroughly re-energized the genre with refreshing wit, honest emotions, incisive observations and a perfect cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-amreeka-1003931653.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A culture-clash dramedy whose background in Middle-East conflict is leavened with vibrant energy, balanced politics and droll humor by first-time feature director Cherien Dabis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939387.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=amreeka</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing bitter or cynical about Amreeka, which is directed with impish wit, an observant visual competence, and an open, conciliatory spirit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-09-01/film/displacement-dramedy-gets-a-spin-with-amreeka/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A kind of stealth political film that confronts issues of ethnic tension and American xenophobia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/amreeka/article1344120/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The acting is good, particularly by Faour, who plays the naive, zaftig heroine as warm and appealing despite her troubles. It's also nice to see veteran Palestinian actress Hiam Abbass ("Lemon Tree"), who plays Muna's sister.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/09/17/MV4E19NF4O.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s one of the richer movies you’re likely to see about average Arabs in America.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/09/25/amreeka_explores_the_recent_arab_immigrant_experience_in_the_united_states/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filmmaker Dabis based Amreeka on her own family's experiences in the rural Midwest during the first Gulf War. Although the drama heads on a predictable course, Faour brings intelligence and humor to her performance and Muallem, as the smart adolescent turned surly and scared, is likewise sharp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090925_A_tale_of_immigrants__struggles_and_successes.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This small gem takes a basically optimistic view about the struggles that generations of immigrants have endured.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09042009/entertainment/movies/immigrant_tale_with_mideast_spices_188057.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only one of a number of recent immigrant tales to hit theaters, but with its blend of sweet humor and topical relevance, it's one of the more compelling -- and surprising -- in some time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/11/amreeka_a_pleasant_surprise_of.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When most filmmakers want to say something important about cultural conflicts, they labor to bring tears to our eyes. Dabis, by contrast, makes us laugh at ourselves and, in turn, each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/2009-06-25/film-tv/coming-to-amreeka/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most accomplished recent films about a non-European immigrant coming to the United States.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/09/04/movies/04amreeka.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Cherien Dabis shot Amreeka in a gritty documentary style that reflects the often grim reality of the characters' situation. But he also knows how to mine the comic situations that are often part of the immigrant experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joanne Kaufman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the story were more arresting, and the filmmaking more original, then the notions of post-9/11 assimilation might be more compelling. As it stands, the movie just serves up another warmed-over Ellis Island rehash.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/78203/amreeka-film-review</url>
         <critic>Stephen Garrett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With her large, expressive eyes, abundant warmth, and radiant energy, Faour commands our sympathy, even through some weak dialogue and even weaker plot points.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?oid=1010805</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amreeka lacks the sense of humor that set "Aliens In America" apart--and frankly, it’s rarely as insightful about the biases and strengths either of Arab émigrés or of sheltered Midwesterners.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/amreeka,32505/</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Faour and Muallen give solid performances, but there are a few too many by-the-numbers moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/09/04/2009-09-04_short_film_reviews_unmade_beds_american_casino_and_more.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$627,436</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$71,548</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>true</labor_release>
</movie>