<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>When Did You Last See Your Father?</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Blake Morrison</author>
      <author>David Nicholls</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Anand Tucker</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
      <origin>Ireland</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Gina McKee</actor>
      <actor>Jim Broadbent</actor>
      <actor>Juliet Stevenson</actor>
      <actor>Gina Mckee</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Lancashire</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 6, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Superbly acted, intelligently written.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-05-last-see-your-father_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jim Broadbent and Colin Firth demonstrate once again the magic and majesty of finely etched British acting. Backed by a solid support cast, their performances are deeply felt and cagily detailed.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-when-did/454245/content</url>
         <critic>Sid Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Broadbent's picture to steal and, playing the father through several decades, he takes full advantage; his theft is effortlessly skilled.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080613.wfather13/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Taps into the conflicting feelings so many of us can have about parents who haunt us because they're difficult, which is part of what makes them irreplaceable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20204728,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Loss and mourning are hard emotions to make real on film. Go one way, and they easily come off tear-jerky; go the other, and they end up aloof. Usually the first approach wins out, but When Did You Last See Your Father? lands right in the middle, one man's cool-headed but still warm account of his dying dad's impact on him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/06/2008-06-06_broadbents_old_rascal_is_the_life_of_fat.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kind of superior middlebrow filmmaking at which the Brits excel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0823,when-did-you-last-see-your-father,458821,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The acting is top-notch. With a series of character roles in recent years, Colin Firth has managed to put the iconic Mr. Darcy behind him. Jim Broadbent, now the proud owner of an Oscar, creates a motion picture rarity: a father who is neither a saint nor a demon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1004</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nicely balances moments of childhood trauma with a full appreciation of the man whose enthusiasm for high spirits sometimes came at considerable cost to those around him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/when_did_you_last_see_your</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A classy tearjerker.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/12/DDEP117HG2.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film did not provide me with fulfillment or a catharsis. Apparently the memoir wouldn't have, either. That's fair enough. How many unanswered questions are we all left with? I have some. This is a film of regret, and judging by what we see of the characters, it deserves to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080612/REVIEWS/889247886</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directed by Anand Tucker, who brings the same knack for restrained but observant storytelling that marked both his "Shopgirl" and "Hilary and Jackie," the film is a memory piece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080704_Memories_of_father__surfacing_painfully.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An eloquent and affecting evocation of a man who remains bigger than life even as he approaches death.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121271272126950681.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The whole thing might have been improved with a bit of messiness, a little vulgarity to leaven its tastefulness and tact.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/06/movies/06fath.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Firth can be an engaging actor, he doesn't seem to be having any fun here and saps the life out of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/368544_when27q.html</url>
         <critic>Andy Spletzer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film winds up with some meaningful things to say about balancing the desire to clear the familial air and the need to let some things be, but never gets deep enough into its character's psyches to dig up anything more revelatory than that.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/06/movie_review_when_did_you_last.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may be powerful in direct proportion to the emotions and memories each viewer brings to the table, but on its own the film's upper lip remains much too stiff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11355</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film ends on a lovely, graceful, simple moment, one that will stick with you, especially if you've had occasion to give the title question some thought.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/575616.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One would only hope that a film about death and dying wouldn't have to feel quite so lifeless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-father6-2008jun06,0,4601383.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An unashamed tearjerker that’s all wrapping and no center.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934468.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=when+did+you+last+see+your+father</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A stylishly appointed but monotonous relationship drama that keeps going around in the same, indulgent circles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9885</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performances are marvelous, and little moments ring all too true, making Tucker's film rewarding if not illuminating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A641267</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretty good, for a movie about death isn't really good enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06062008/entertainment/movies/last_respects_un_urned_114163.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adapted from a memoir by British writer Blake Morrison, this father-son drama never rises above the archetypal: its conflict will be familiar to all, its resolution a surprise to none.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33209_WHEN_DID_YOU_LAST_SEE_YOUR_FATHER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is slick (the director loves mirrors!) and treacly and goes nowhere that hasn't been gone before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1142463&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,071,240</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$8,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$39,210</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>