<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Aqua Teen Hunger Force Colon Movie Film for Theaters</name>
   <company>First Look International</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Animation</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Matt Maiellaro and Dave Willis</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Matt Maiellaro</director>
      <director>Dave Willis</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Dana Snyder</actor>
      <actor>Dave Willis</actor>
      <actor>Carey Means</actor>
      <actor>Andy Merrill</actor>
      <actor>Mike Schatz</actor>
      <actor>Matt Maiellaro</actor>
      <actor>Fred Armisen</actor>
      <actor>Bruce Campbell</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 13, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>86</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the stuff of not quite dreams, and it's rendered with such accuracy and hilarity that I am tempted to call Aqua Teen Hunger Force Colon Movie Film For Theaters the most successful full-on surrealist film since Bunuel and Dali's 1930 "L'Age d'Or."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3712/aqua-teen-hunger-force.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Begins by living up to its fans' rabid expectations, and ends by justifying skeptics' doubts. In between lie roughly equivalent levels of tedium and hilarity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/aqua_teen_hunger_force_colon</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You either get it or you don't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9952</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a cinematic landscape where truly original ideas are rarer than floating food, recklessness like this deserves to be appreciated. Not understood, but appreciated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.aqua13apr13,0,4529196.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's ragged, and at times it scrapes your comedy ganglia like a cheese grater. But 15 minutes or half an hour is an ideal chunk of time to set aside for truly inspired absurdism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04132007/entertainment/movies/hey__its_a_bunch_of_wisefries_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers a diverting package of surreal, rude stoner and pop culture-based humor that will delight youthful viewers while bewildering stray elders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933337.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At best, it's an inspired piece of free-association pop art held together by sheer momentum, at worst a noisy mess of juvenile nonsense passing itself off as a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/311387_aquateen13q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot can't be summarized: Let's just say that crazy s--- happens, and occasionally, you laugh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20034461,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To call the animation crude would be high praise. But they succeed enough of the time to make a perversely entertaining movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/13133883/review/14030426/aqua_teen_hunger_force_the_movie</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has an even amount of hilarious individual ideas and moments as well as stretches that just seem gratuitously out-there.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=855724&amp;reviewId=22398</url>
         <critic>Christy Lemire</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing here for kids, or, for that matter, anyone who claims to be an adult. But if the title makes perfect sense to you, the movie probably will, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/04/13/2007-04-13_short_takes.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is intended for the target audience of arrested-development stoners who stay up late being thrilled rather than confused by the show's non-sequiturial humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20070413_An_adventure_not_everyone_can_appreciate.html</url>
         <critic>Dan DeLuca</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No doubt about it, the show's certifiably bizarro, stream-of-consciousness sensibility has made the transition notably intact, which should please its young male fan base.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9041</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>ATHF can seem brilliantly deconstructive one moment and stupefyingly boring the next--or to provide a more accurate ratio, it can follow five brilliant seconds with five straight minutes of boredom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2164057/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Difficult to recommend, without first knowing the sobriety of the viewer.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/04/13/DDGKPP738L1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Narrative's beside the point in a movie created by two guys who gorge on pop culture's high-fat diet and regurgitate it into something approaching . . . art? Close enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0715,wilonsky,76352,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A work of either a profoundly transgressive genius or a goofball high on Pez and patio sealant. It could come from no normal collection of brain cells.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1134022&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its infectious, go-for-broke wackiness ATHFCMFFT never quite surpasses its opening sequence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-disturbia-perfect-stranger-and-more/16117/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's nowhere near as funny or incisive as the South Park movies, and it has a much crazier style. Imagine Abraham Lincoln chatting up a giant milkshake and discussing slavery, and you get the picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-04-12-aqua-teen_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pre-credits sequence, featuring a variety of old-school snack treats performing a speed-metal number about courteous movie-theater behavior, is flat-out hilarious and deserves to be played before all R-rated films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/aqua-teen-hunger/review/286993</url>
         <critic>Angel Cohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strictly for cultists, and even they might find less than 90 bongless minutes hard to sit through.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/movies/13aqua.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It gives me no pleasure to report that Aqua Teen Hunger Force Colon Movie Film for Theaters is fairly excruciating to sit through -- because I'm writing this as a fan of the TV series that spawned the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1176247527295690.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Feels deeply calculated rather than genuinely crazy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/04/13/aqua_teen/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A little of this junk-drawer fusillade goes a long way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-aqua13apr13,0,870595.story</url>
         <critic>Sam Adams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Count it as one of the great Hollywood mysteries – right up there with the death of Natalie Wood and the career of Vin Diesel – that we've had to wait this long for a movie starring a talking milkshake, a floating box of french fries, and a ball of ground beef.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A464278</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The TV episodes invariably embed a character or a bit of dialogue in your brain that you continuously describe or repeat to your friends. No such find in the movie, though the offbeat soundtrack is very gettable.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070413-movies-review-force,0,7403478.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Eric Gwinn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tends toward arch silliness more than actual humor, a formula that's tolerable enough in 15-minute tube installments but deadly dull in this 86-minute feature.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31414_AQUA_TEEN_HUNGER_FORCE_COLON_MOVIE_FILM_FOR_THEATERS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Essentially, an act of terrorism against entertainment. It's inconsequential, potty - mouthed, extremely silly, and -- the worst sin of all -- dead boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10020</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$5,520,368</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$750,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,005,175</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>877</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>