<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ask the Dust</name>
   <company>Paramount Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robert Towne</author>
      <author>John Fante</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert Towne</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Colin Farrell</actor>
      <actor>Salma Hayek</actor>
      <actor>Donald Sutherl</actor>
      <actor>Eileen Atkins</actor>
      <actor>Idina Menzel</actor>
      <actor>William Mapother</actor>
      <actor>Tamara Craig Thomas</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask the Dust is more than an amorous period piece. It's a strongly bitter, strongly sweet poem in prose and motion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.dust07apr07,0,3340376.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More than anything else, Ask the Dust feels like a compendium of desires - for a city, for a woman, for youth.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/movies/10dust.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask The Dust may find Towne a little past his prime, but after so much time in the Hollywood wilderness, it's good to see him trying again.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46106</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Occasionally overrated as a writer but consistently underrated as a director, Towne does a marvelous job resurrecting all the seedy jumble of the long-gone Bunker Hill neighborhood.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46785</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At a time when juvenile movies often dominate theaters, this is an adult movie through-and-through, and evidence that there are filmmakers who care about entertaining a more mature audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/a/ask_dust.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its portrait of an artist hungry for experience is as timely today as when it was written.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=549668&amp;reviewId=20359&amp;startDate=03%2F17%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask the Dust does manage to cast a spell. The film is not only an evocation of a bygone era but an emanation of it as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0310/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask the Dust requires an audience with a special love for film noir, with a feeling for the loneliness and misery of the writer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060316/REVIEWS/60314003/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eccentric, miscast (though stimulatingly so), not for all tastes but far from flavorless.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060317-movies-review-dust,0,7817378.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To Towne's credit, he's a thoughtful and conscientious romantic. He skillfully makes the two main characters a hot, volatile couple, deftly staging their courtship as if it were an erotic grudge match.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/movies/archives/2006/0306/060317.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What seduces most about Ask the Dust isn't its verisimilitude, but its gloriously old-fashioned backlot sheen - the L.A. of old Hollywood movies and of our collective fantasies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/12854/gone-with-the-wind/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is faithful to the book's tone of dark ache and much of its detail and for the most part terrifically cast. But Towne can't overcome an essential challenge of the material: Arturo and Camilla are constructs and ciphers as much as they are vivid characters -- difficult roles, to be sure. Neither the screenplay nor the actors manage to get far under their skin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001956879</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thirty years of gestation have produced a film of great beauty with unfulfilled promise - a disappointment, but with much to recommend and be glad about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-dust10mar10,0,6799646.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film, which is literary to a fault, includes an earthquake, but if the earth moves at all, thank Hayek, who gives the tale a smoldering life that finally lifts it from the page.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6137397/rid/9440861/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sepia-tinted palette of Ask the Dust drips, reeks and creaks of the seamy side of a city that takes more often than it gives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-10-2006/entertainment/col/story/398524p-337570c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After an hour or so, Ask the Dust seems to have said everything, and the air starts to seep out of its hermetic atmosphere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8651</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A curiously resistable drama, despite several strong elements - the most notable being newcomer Idina Menzel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=10105</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Something is missing, though. The themes are all there, but the movie doesn't cross the blood-brain barrier and rev you up.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16312/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Farrell's performance possesses a touch too many mannerisms on loan from Tyrone Power and Clark Gable; you can almost hear the gears turning in his brain each time he cocks his head or raises an eyebrow in homage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-03-16/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Highlighted by a strong and sensual performance from Salma Hayek as the doomed heroine, elegant pic's muted quality and the central character's vexingly contrary behavior will keep auds from connecting with characters who themselves have trouble establishing bonds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929461?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Miscast, constricted, loose in tone and meandering in intent, it has far fewer moments of inspiration than unintended laughter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1142454308181720.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Farrell and Hayek are two beautiful people with absolutely no chemistry. Even when they're lying in bed together, they're so far apart that they might as well be in different movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2668</url>
         <critic>John Migliore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It would seem Towne is too much in love with the book to recognize its fundamental limitations as a film.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=549668&amp;reviewId=20367</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask the Dust is the ghost of a cult novel; it can't bring itself to life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1169890,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask the Dust is beautifully shot -- sepia becomes the ravishing, affecting Ms. Hayek. Unfortunately the images of the heaving waves of the Pacific in the moonlight, of mountains rising over scrub and cactus in the sunlight here, serve only to emphasize the emptiness of the drama unfolding in the foreground.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the film offers a meticulously rendered Depression-era L.A., it's not in the same league as "Chinatown," for which Towne wrote an Oscar-winning script. Here, the characters seem shallow, their motivations murky.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-03-09-ask-the-dust_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching it is like being in a restaurant where the waiter brings out a luscious platter of food, then keeps walking right past you. All night long.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64962.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Farrell is badly miscast as an ethnic Italian with an inferiority complex, the star-crossed love story has very little emotional pull, and even the (heavily CGI-enhanced) period atmosphere ultimately seems rather forced and self-conscious.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/263254_dust17q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Alternately grandiose and abject, Bandini is a sort of underground man, and if no more miscast than usual, heartthrob Colin Farrell miserably fails to convincingly render Bandini's neurosis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,hoberman,72462,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most eagerly awaited cinematic projects of 2006, which may be why it lands with such a curious thud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118432&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This story, like many of Towne's own, does not come with a happy ending. Or beginning, for that matter, because it's almost immediately clear that Ask the Dust bites the dust -- his dream movie is stillborn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060317.DUST17/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is a particular disappointment considering its pedigree.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/17/DDGERHOU541.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie lacks even the misplaced fervor of obsession. It's lifeless kitsch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1171080_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$742,614</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$68,779</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>7</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>