<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Baby Mama</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Mc</author>
      <author>Cullers</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Mc</director>
      <director>Cullers</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tina Fey</actor>
      <actor>Amy Poehler</actor>
      <actor>Greg Kinnear</actor>
      <actor>Dax Shepard</actor>
      <actor>Romany Malco</actor>
      <actor>Maura Tierney</actor>
      <actor>Holl Taylor</actor>
      <actor>Sigourney Weaver</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 25, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the chemistry between the stars that makes the film stand out in a drab spring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/594472.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even though Kinnear is meant to be obvious love interest, it's the relationship between Kate and Angie that becomes the film's central story, making this comedy sweeter -- and more honest in its depiction of class difference -- than one might otherwise expect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/baby-mama/review/293099</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the competition hasn't exactly been stiff, Fey and Poehler may well be the best female comedy duo since Lucy and Ethel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-04-24-baby-mama_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Best when skewering New Age entrepreneurs for what might be called Compassionate Capitalism. Steve Martin is sublime as Kate's boss, Barry, purveyor of organic food and Zen koans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080425_Winning_pair_in__Baby_Mama_.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this era of Apatow and Ferrell and Rogen and Wilson, of men monopolizing movie comedy, Baby Mama feels absurdly momentous, and even political. Fey and Poehler aren't just taking back control of their bodies. They're taking back control of their profession.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10726</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the big picture itself gets mushy, the small moments, especially involving Fey, are sharp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20195624,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a comedy with the old-time blend of wit and sentiment. Years from now, when you stumble across it on TV, you could persuade yourself that, back in the two-thousand-oughts, they made pretty good movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1735059,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An essentially sweet-natured picture that doesn't go as far as it could.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/04/23/baby_mama/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fey is a delight to watch throughout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936841.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surely, if Fey herself had written Baby Mama, this mild cross between "Baby Boom" and "The Odd Couple" would not be so crushingly predictable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04232008/entertainment/movies/film_fest_tribeckons_107690.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing terribly wrong with Baby Mama but it's probably better suited for viewing on television, where many of the participants cut their teeth. This is small screen stuff masquerading as something bigger.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/baby_mama.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are gags and scraps of action that give the movie fits of buoyancy, and these tend to come not so much from the younger, eager performers as from the old hands.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/04/28/080428crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a pleasing contrast to Fey's sharpness, Poehler keeps her performance unpredictable and fuzzy. In this just-add-water comedy, a very funny movie star is born.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/04/25/2008-04-25_amy_poehler_delivers_star_comic_performa.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie hardly allows itself any sharp moments at all -- it's much too sweet-natured to be cruel, and much too cheerful to be angry. It probably could have pushed a few more buttons, but Baby Mama aims to please and succeeds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-baby25apr25,0,6317912.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baby Boom serves up plenty of smart, knowing laughs early on, but by the time it hits the third act (or would that be trimester?), it barely crawls to the finish line.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=cRhnLL2Jz57QBThHTMVcSnvbxysyJ1F63BTvcPq5h2dV5fJTFdFX!-1792468288&amp;&amp;rid=10987</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not without laughs--Poehler and Fey, as ever, have strong chemistry, and there's a truly bizarre scene in which Martin offers Fey a strange "reward" for a job well done--but there's a lot of arid space between them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/baby_mama</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer/director Michael McCullers sprinkles the film with sight gags and comic characters (the lisping birth coach becomes funny out of sheer doggedness), but his pacing is poor and doesn't know how to showcase the small-screen chemistry of Fey and Poehler on the big screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/360476_babymama25q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You could blast for it, and you still won't find 30 uninterrupted seconds of truth in Baby Mama. The characters are lies. Their emotional workings are lies. The jokes are based on lies about human behavior.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/04/24/DD8K10AL3A.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sporadically funny, bland, talent-wasting junk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/04/review_tina_fay_births_baby_ma.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There’s a lot of talent up there on the screen, and some authentic laughs, but too much of it is comedy territory that was claimed long ago.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10935</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For those who crave mannerisms and shtick and like their jokes set up and knocked out with plenty of arrows and quote marks, Baby Mama may fall flat. But audiences alive to the modest charms of its take on female friendship will be rewarded with at least a few quiet chuckles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1142935&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film never comes fully to term, as it were: the visual style is sitcom functional, and even the zippiest jokes fall flat because of poor timing. But, much like the prickly, talented Ms. Fey, it pulls you in with a provocative and, at least in current American movies, unusual mix of female intelligence, awkwardness and chilled-to-the-bone mean.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/04/25/movies/25baby.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Poehler is the life of the party and steals just about every scene, although there's not much to steal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0425/p13s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, that's all this shrugging disappointment is: a "Saturday Night Live" sketch stretched a good hour past its breaking point of no return.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0817,tina-fey-and-amy-poehler-s-surrogate-mommy-comedy,422568,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Midway through I started wondering why I wasn't laughing more. "Baby Mama" was not written by Fey and/or Poehler, which may be the reason.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-baby-mama/388170/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baby Mama is the most disappointing movie of the year so far--which, granted, isn't saying a lot in mid-April.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2189886/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baby Mama is rescued by two scene-stealing veterans: Sigourney Weaver as the smug, patrician owner of the surrogate company, and a priceless, ponytailed Steve Martin as the self-infatuated New Age owner of Round Earth. These two aren't onscreen a lot, but the movie seems most fully alive when they are.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/133797</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The show is redeemed by its co-stars, up to a point. They struggle womanfully, and sometimes successfully, to find truth in the script's silly symphony of false notes.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120908724598943787.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script favors routine "Odd Couple" gags over the sort of comic contemplation of motherhood a writer like Fey might have brought to the subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33071_BABY_MAMA.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just amusing enough to provoke a few chuckles and just short enough to keep you from glancing at your watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/507645.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A painfully predictable movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080425.wmama25/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time it reaches its supposedly crowd-pleasing finale, Baby Mama may have self-respecting comedy fans (and even Tina Fey fans) crying uncle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.baby25apr25,0,6606855.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just like it is in the world of "SNL" that Fey, Poehler, and McCullers sprang from, the choice gets made time and again to aim not for the high road but for the great, big, fat, juicy, unchallenging, uncontroversial middle ground, where everybody’s laughing but nothing is all that funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A614764</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exhausting 90 minutes of SNL-centric mediocrity that gives one the nagging feeling that Tina Fey's inability to cut the cord is going to quickly start to cool interest in her upcoming projects.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4546/baby-mama.html</url>
         <critic>Ryan Stewart</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$60,494,212</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$17,407,110</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,543</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>