<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Balzac and the Little Chinese Seamstress</name>
   <company>Empire Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sijie Dai</author>
      <author>Nadine Perront</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sijie Dai</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>FranceChina</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Xun Zhou</actor>
      <actor>Kun Chen</actor>
      <actor>Ye Liu</actor>
      <actor>Shuangbao Wang</actor>
      <actor>Zhijun Cong</actor>
      <actor>Hong Wei Wang</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 29, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>111</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sweet, funny, sad and profound -- the sort of film that becomes more remarkable when you realize it's based on someone's real life.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/02/DDGPTEGBRL1.DTL#flick2</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Curiel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An oddity: an adaptation of a popular novel co-written and directed by the novelist himself. It's also a fine, gentle film love story and a cinematic tribute to the power and manifold benefits of communications between different cultures and nations.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050930-movies-review-balzac,0,1016619.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A funny, sad and absolutely lovely film.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=405265&amp;reviewId=19272</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For an exquisitely melancholy story steeped in a sense of the past as a succession of great waves of political, ideological and economic change, it's fitting that the movie should end with an underwater sequence. It looks like a dream of a memory of a place about to be wiped out by the next great flood of history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-balzac26aug26,0,616328.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the movie is straightforward and predictable in its attitude, it also exudes a sort of documentary lyricism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081100598.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Enlightenment is good, Dai acknowledges. But the movie's more provocative assertion is the notion that ignorance was also a kind of bliss.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1095006_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, it's a lovely little movie about very big things, and the smallness both illuminates it and keeps it from greatness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8170</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A meditation on literature, love and remembrance that is able to find humor and hope in the dark days of the Cultural Revolution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/50522.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fanciful tale, but the message is sweet - that the higher arts speak a universal language that transcends politics and ignorance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/332479p-283981c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It makes for an unusual angle on the era, and a passionate paean to the power of books, ideas and art.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/242771_balzac30q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dai Sijie's tender, touching adaptation of his own novel of the same title.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/29/movies/29balz.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A visually lush and very Westernized vision of life in a remote Chinese village in the early 1970s.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2003&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117917766&amp;categoryid=1273&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>David Stratton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the film lacks some of the paper incarnation's subtlety, Dai's infidelity to his own text keeps things interesting. He busts the book's brief time frame, tweaks countless plot points, and tops it all off with a titanic metaphor not found in his own pages.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0530,tracking1,66241,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ed Park</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By turns merry, tough-minded and sweetly nostalgic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3517&amp;Sumbit.x=41&amp;Sumbit.y=8</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Artfully designed to appeal to lovers of romance and books, but by the end of the film I was not convinced it knew much about either.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050929/REVIEWS/509290301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sure, Balzac meanders at too leisurely a pace. But the actors are charming; the story sweet</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081101855.html</url>
         <critic>Teresa Wiltz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ethereal private moments and inspired passages are beautifully shot by Jean-Marie Dreujou, but Dai never quite organizes the material dramatically, and the tone is too often jagged and disruptive.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/23153_BALZAC_AND_THE_LITTLE_CHINESE_SEAMSTRESS</url>
         <critic>Patrick Z. McGavin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sijie mostly adapts his own work dryly and literally—the footage of the Chinese mountainside is breathtaking, but it's the only thing in the film with much depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://redesign.theonion.com/avclub/node/25081</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story is winning but the telling, with Dai adapting and directing from his own novel, is too sentimental in the long run.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0729/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is beautifully shot and well-acted, but, like the book, it never achieves anything like the import of the stories that inspired it. Balzac is even a little dull, especially toward the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cute and toothless as a kitten, Seamstress doesn't inspire the same kind of fervent devotion its principals feel when confronted with art, but it does make a pleasant enough diversion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A317145</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Demonstrating just how different literature and filmmaking can be, filmmaker-turned-writer-turned filmmaker Dai Sijie botches an adaptation of his own best-selling short novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46350</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$665,260</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$16,694</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>