<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Bank Job, The</name>
   <company>Lionsgate</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dick Clement</author>
      <author>Ian La Frenais</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Roger Donaldson</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jason Statham</actor>
      <actor>Saffron Burrows</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Campbell Moore</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Mays</actor>
      <actor>James Faulkner</actor>
      <actor>Alki David</actor>
      <actor>Michael Jibson</actor>
      <actor>Richard Lintern</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 7, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the pleasures of The Bank Job is that it returns us to the days when robbing a bank was a gritty, hole-in-the-wall affair.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20182344,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The gritty heist picture The Bank Job has everything adult action fans could want, starting with a grand, fact-inspired gimmick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.bankjob07mar07,0,1890591.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Entertaining and subtle at once, it doesn't just dazzle us with the hows and whys of a particularly wily brand of thievery; it transports us to a specific time and place that often seems to fall between significant eras. The Bank Job is set in a country that's in transition, an extended metaphor for the way its characters are in transition, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/03/07/bank_job/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jason Statham, possibly the greatest B-movie leading man of this era, stars in a complicated and clever imagining of what might have happened in the mysterious 1971 London bank heist dubbed the "Walkie-Talkie Robbery" - in other words, it was unbelievably high-tech.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03072008/entertainment/movies/accrues_interest_100743.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brisk, entertaining crime thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/03/07/DDPRVEUJ5.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Steve Winn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nothing more than an efficient time-killer with the added bonus of being based on a real misadventure. But, unlike its benighted cast of characters, it gets the job done without a hitch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0307/p15s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Feels both absolutely of the 1970s and absolutely fresh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080307_A_heist_turns_to_hush-up_as_a_bank_vault_spills_secrets.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A heist movie in the classic tradition - it details every aspect of the caper, from its genesis to its aftermath. The fact that there's political intrigue and espionage swirling around the edges only makes it more fascinating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/bank_job.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The suspense aspect works like mad, but what's also noteworthy is the character component, which at times evokes a "Smash Palace"-era Donaldson.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4437/the-bank-job.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slick, ice-cold and enjoyable, The Bank Job is a bit of all right.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-bank/326524/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dull title for a juicy, fact-based caper movie that's full of surprises I have no intention of spoiling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18159737/review/18947923/bank_job</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Based more on rumor and supposition than fact. It's a highly entertaining set of hypotheses.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/354001_bank07q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprisingly tight, clever, twisty heist tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/bank-job/review/292654</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Statham fans weaned on the adrenaline flowing through "The Transporter" and "Crank" may feel short-changed, but the rest of us can appreciate the unassuming, old-fashioned craftsmanship of The Bank Job, which is based on a true-life heist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/525203.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Imagine a blend of "Snatch," "Ocean's 11" and "The Italian Job." Then juxtapose the staples of the caper genre with real events involving national security and high-level corruption, and the result is The Bank Job.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-03-06-bank-heist_N.htm?loc=interstitialskip</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Bank Job engages us fully with a tale that's well-fashioned more than anything else, a fascinating study of morality at several levels of English society, and of honor, or the lack of it, among implausibly likable thieves.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120485307946918309.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Statham's totally believable. He might yet become Bruce Willis.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/2008-03-06/film/heist-flick-the-bank-job-is-too-fun-to-fact-check/</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes director Roger Donaldson's movie greater than zany heist fare is that this particular robbery really happened and that this episode illuminated an almost moral clash between the haves and the have-nots of Great Britain.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145391&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The actual robbery that the picture is based on is shrouded in mystery, and the screenwriters, Dick Clement and Ian La Fresnais, have engaged in a fair amount of entertaining invention.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/03/10/080310crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film dawdles at times. but for the most part Donaldson keeps just the right amount of tension present in each scene.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-bank7mar07,0,1002598.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is not a lot of scintillating dialogue in The Bank Job, but there are plenty of kinky sexual allusions and it includes a torture sequence about as brutal as anything you're likely to see in the movies these days.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1720472,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fascinating: supposedly the crooks kept all the cash and jewelry, but their sponsors in the MI5 were really after sexually explicit blackmail photos of Princess Margaret and other aristocrats that were being held by the revolutionary Michael X.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#32865</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One doesn't want to oversell the film; you could catch it on DVD and regret nothing. But, frankly, in a marketplace that tends toward cranked-up action thrills, it's just nice to watch a level-headed crime movie aimed at actual grown-ups.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/03/movie_review_the_bank_job_grow.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike the other great caper films of the last 10 years, like "Ocean’s 11" and "The Italian Job" – stylish affairs in which punishment is close enough to give the audience a sense of lingering danger but never so close that it gets in the way of the technological fetishism and love of tailored shirts that apparently make grand larceny such a kick – the blowback in The Bank Job is real and ugly and involves some sort of pneumatic paint-stripping machine that would freak out the Coen Brothers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A598529</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Semi-decent, somewhat okay, not-half-bad.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080306.bank07nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The workmanlike title The Bank Job is a nice fit for this wham-bam caper flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/03/07/movies/07bank.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An engrossing if underwhelming period thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936345.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Leslie Felperin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A slow-paced and often confusingly plotted crime drama that never lives up to the delicious potential of its premise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=3jddHNbTNyZNLkBy4p97B1yzj15X2ZBWC1JlLKs0RhjQ1hvFX4Tp!1158789824&amp;&amp;rid=10747</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Bank Job secures the viewer’s attention pretty quickly and does not relinquish that hold for a second.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10818</url>
         <critic>Stina Chyn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Donaldson also misses the chance to score some easy laughs from his petty criminals, who are infinitely more audacious than they are competent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_bank_job</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What The Bank Job ends up stealing is all your precious time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/445840.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie doesn't hang together as a thriller, and the characters don't hang together as interesting people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11356</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$30,060,660</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$5,935,256</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,603</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>