<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Basic Instinct 2</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Leora Barish</author>
      <author>Henry Bean</author>
      <author>Joe Eszterhas</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Caton-Jones</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>GermanySpainUKUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sharon Stone</actor>
      <actor>David Morrissey</actor>
      <actor>Charlotte Rampling</actor>
      <actor>David Thewlis</actor>
      <actor>Hugh Dancy</actor>
      <actor>Anne Caillon</actor>
      <actor>Iain Robertson</actor>
      <actor>Stan Collymore</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 31, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>114</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basic Instinct 2 isn't bad, exactly, but it lacks the entertaining vulgarity of the first film; it's Basic Instinct redone with more ''class'' and less thrust.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1178144_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>BI2 is packed with as much lust, nudity and sexual depravity as the first. So, why isn't it as much fun? What's lost in any sequel is the freshness of the first film, and was "BI1" ever fresh!</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-31-2006/entertainment/col/story/404638p-342509c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Those hoping for either a sizzling -- or an unintentionally hilarious -- good time will be disappointed by this inexplicably dull sequel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930078?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn't boring, exactly. It's too nutty for that.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0331/p16s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like many sequels this is actually a remake, and it suffers from the law of diminishing returns.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29527_BASIC_INSTINCT_TWO.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's turned Stone's Catherine Tramell from a warning sign for the dangers of wanton sex into the last thing you'd figure - a bore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.basic31mar31,0,7565709.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A few bodies pile up. Surprisingly little sex is had. And given that Catherine's true nature was revealed at the end of the first "Basic," the mystery seems superfluous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1143678339219550.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're trying to reinvigorate the art of the stylish thriller, the movie you come up with needs to be stylish and it needs to be thrilling. Basic Instinct 2,  is neither.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/03/31/basic_instinct_2/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fails as a sequel because we’re not in the 90s anymore. Gone are the days when characters could answer questions with questions and hypothetical situations and still sound clever and cool.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8884</url>
         <critic>Stina Chyn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Morrissey gives a stiff, awkward performance, while Stone moves dangerously close to overplaying the femme fatale. There is little if any intrigue in the story or the characters. Even the murders don't even seem to matter much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002275142</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basic Instinct 2 pushes diligently along in a murder-and-mayhem-stuffed effort to demonstrate that (a) a sillier and more hackneyed movie than "Basic Instinct" is possible and (b) that shrinks have ids too, by golly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film-reviews/13010/film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once the credits are done rolling it's a dour, enervated mystery, selling the old cat-and-mouse games.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060331-movies-review-basic,0,260039.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basic Instinct 2 is supposed to help Stone show it's possible for a woman to be sexy in her late 40s. But it's Rampling - who is 60 - who comes off as the more provocative and alluring. Stone's purring, snarling, bedroom kink is embarrassing.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=569464&amp;reviewId=20450</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basic Instinct 2 is double trouble -- the femme is to die for, the film is to die from.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060331.BASIC31/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the sex and slicing, the most shocking thing about it is how dreary it is.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46665</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a lot of things, but boring is not one of them. I cannot recommend the movie, but ... why the hell can't I? Just because it's godawful? What kind of reason is that for staying away from a movie? Godawful and boring, that would be a reason.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060330/REVIEWS/60323008/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What we may very well be looking at here is another "Showgirls," a drag camp-fest for the "Baby Jane" crowd, fabulous fodder for future cabaret acts, and a pleasure probably best enjoyed in a crowd -- preferably a vocal one. Dead serious and stone idiotic, the only basic instinct in evidence here is desperation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-basic31mar31,0,4241457.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not content simply to examine the relationship between sex and death, BI2 ponderously blurs the boundaries between art and life, and the plot, already mired in nonsensical backstory, collapses with the late-inning introduction of a tired metafictional device (not to mention a wildly lunging "Usual Suspects" twist).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0614,lim,72753,20.html</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basic Instinct 2 is pretty awful. Rarely has a meaningless thriller had so many meaningful glances, or such arch acting by good actors who know better.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where is the suspense part? There is no suspense part. Suspense demands clarity of motive and action, and this screenplay never provides it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1107102&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fortunately, as a showcase for Sharon Stone's physique, Basic Instinct 2 is a rousing success. In every other respect, it's a colossal failure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46925</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Few expected Basic Instinct 2 to be very good, but no one expected it to be this boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=569464&amp;reviewId=20434</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The 1992 phenomenon was creepy, tense and sexually charged in a bold yet tawdry way. This sequel lacks even a shred of those elements.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-03-30-basic-instinct-2_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a better movie, this grand-dame performance might have been fun, but it's surrounded here by an impossibly dull and unsatisfying whodunit plot, unintentionally funny dialogue and such absurdities as having Catherine stay up late one night and whip out an entire novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/264941_basic31q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film is unable to involve, entertain, or titillate. Basically, it stinks.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/b/basic_instinct2.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sequel is one big tease.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/31/DDG6TI0A8V1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The accidental comedy sensation of the year to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8006</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stupefyingly lackluster.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16561/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At this point, there are inflatable toys that are livelier than Stone, but how can you tell the difference? Basic Instinct 2 is not an erotic thriller. It's taxidermy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/66285.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This script by the husband-and-wife team of Leora Barish and Henry Bean is hopelessly contrived and takes forever to get to the point. (I warn you: The film does not absolutely identify the killer.)</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=569464&amp;reviewId=20430&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A disaster of the highest or perhaps lowest order.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/31/movies/31inst.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The laughs to be had in this deliciously awful sequel are all unintentional. A bummer for film buffs, but a ball for fans of the misbegotten.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/7276417/rid/9549574/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stone still dazzles the eye, but this wholly unwarranted sequel is so outrageously preposterous (and so very chockablock with quotable examples of the fine art of bad dialogue) that the end result achieves a basement grandeur of near-epic proportions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A350483</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$5,946,136</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$70,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,201,420</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,453</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>