<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Battle in Heaven</name>
   <company>Tartan USA</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Carlos Reygadas</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Carlos Reygadas</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>MexicoBelgiumFranceGermany</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Marcos Hernández</actor>
      <actor>Anapola Mushkadiz</actor>
      <actor>Bertha Ruiz</actor>
      <actor>David Bornstien</actor>
      <actor>Rosalinda Ramirez</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 17, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Promiscuously inhabiting several planes at once, Reygadas's restless inquisition may already be this year's movie to beat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0607,atkinson,72188,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reygadas asks audiences to plunge headlong into his chaotic vision of the world, no questions asked but complete trust required. Not everyone is going to be willing or able to take this leap of faith, but those who do go along with Reygadas may well feel they have come away having undergone a stunning revelatory experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-battle17feb17,0,6412265.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reyadas' radical rejection of filmmaking conventions is at first off-putting, but he's able to elicit remarkable performances from the cast of non-professionals while building tension that will hold viewers' attention. Love it or loathe it, you won't soon forget Battle in Heaven.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/63686.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some audiences will find it an endurance test and Reygadas doesn't make it easy with his confrontational imagery, but he provokes emotions not often explored on screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/264086_limited24.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simultaneously shocking and deeply religious, Carlos Reygadas' follow-up to his acclaimed 2002 debut, "Japon," tells the story of one man's battle for spiritual redemption through a series of explicit images rarely seen by even the most jaded art-house audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46742</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Working again with Diego Martínez Vignatti, the cinematographer for "Japón," the director doesn't just seize our attention; he commands it - forcing us into a world of terror and beauty.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/17/movies/17heav.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Battle In Heaven is like a serious of artful photographs, except that Reygadas also moves the camera in astonishing and unusual ways, swooping around the conventional x- and y-axes while teasing the audience with what he's about to show. He's got an astonishing technique. Here's hoping that someday he'll use it to make a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45424</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With relentless and ruminative deliberateness, Reygadas shows us a Mexico City that seems to be decaying from the inside out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8405</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reygadas is clearly out to shock us, to shake us and show us a host of furious ideas about class, gender, religion, nationality, love - really, there's very little he doesn't throw into this thickly ambiguous stew. If only he hadn't made his deliberately confusing, heavily symbolic story quite so difficult to digest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/392186p-332413c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reygadas is an undeniably important artist hewing his own path, but who is also self-consciously playing to the tastes of a tiny elite audience that craves obscurantism, confrontation and heavy-handed symbolism. Still, I really want you to see this. Then I'll have somebody to talk about it with.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/16/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both intensely exciting for its cinematic inventions and terribly uninvolving on emotional and dramatic levels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927119?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is an interesting set-up here for something great but Battle In Heaven never lives up to the expectations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8444</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We may indeed yawn a bit from time to time, but we know that we are yawning in the presence of a director who is intelligently disturbed by the moral inertia he sees around him and whose future is worth watching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060313&amp;s=kauffmann031306</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is really Reygadas' show all the way. And what he's delivered is a sad, tawdry picture in which all hope for salvation lies with God.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A352620</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proves to be a disappointing turn-off. The film deliberately works against most cinematic expectations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000922290</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Battle in Heaven cannot be so easily dismissed - indeed, it is that rare failed film that leaves you as eager to see what its maker will do next as you were when you walked in the door.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12675&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A notorious opinion divider last year at Cannes, Battle in Heaven is less about heaven or battle, or hell on earth, or the soul of Mexico, and all too much about gawking. And so, for all the ''shock'' of the movie's clinical carnality, this battle is lost.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1159767_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A spectacular failure, despite further evidence of the director's keen eye and bold cinematic ideas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/31/DDG9AI0F5L1.DTL#flick5</url>
         <critic>G. Allen Johnson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$70,899</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$20,351</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>