<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Baxter, The</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Showalter</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Showalter</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael Showalter</actor>
      <actor>Elizabeth Banks</actor>
      <actor>Michelle Williams</actor>
      <actor>Justin Theroux</actor>
      <actor>Zak Orth</actor>
      <actor>Michael Ian Black</actor>
      <actor>Catherine Lloyd Burns</actor>
      <actor>Abby Wathen</actor>
      <actor>Peter Dinklage</actor>
      <actor>Melisa McGregor</actor>
      <actor>Paul Rudd</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 26, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>No great shakes, The Baxter nonetheless has a quiet loopiness going for it. And it has the absence of a laugh track going for it, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=419401&amp;reviewId=19039</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Baxter is just an OK movie, but Showalter's performance is the gem to take from it.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/16/DDGDFENOO41.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performers are fresh and offbeat, with the diminutive Peter Dinklage (Elf, The Station Agent) especially funny as a gay wedding planner named Benson Hedges.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28394_BAXTER_SHOWALTER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sign of The Baxter's charm is that it's essentially spoiler-proof: We know from the get-go which couples will pair off, and the pleasures lie in the spring-stepped vibe, the natty throwback wardrobe, and the intricate goofball patter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0534,fpark,67106,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ed Park</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Modest and polite. That's not a ringing endorsement of Michael Showalter's good-natured comedy, but there are enough laughs in it if you're willing to settle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/08-26-2005/entertainment/col/story/340683p-290709c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A self-consciously arch work of hipsterism that's more styled than funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7802</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A tender love story and a dead-on lampoon of the genre, but its main drawback is that Showalter is egregiously miscast in the title role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-baxter2sep02,0,6643372.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, The Baxter is a Baxter of a movie: well meaning and mildly likable, but unlikely to sweep you off your feet.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/08/26/movies/26baxt.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Van Gelder</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This wry, low-key comedy, crafted by members of the sketch-comedy group The State, swims defiantly against the stream of contemporary comedy, eschewing bodily-function jokes and obvious gags in favor of laughs so sly and self-effacing you could almost overlook them.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46172</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That's ultimately the film's fatal flaw: it bumps Showalter's Baxter up to the role of the romantic lead without giving him an equivalent increase in complexity or depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/39560</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"The Station Agent's" Peter Dinklage provides diversion as a gay wedding planner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1097727_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>May find a following among those who stand in awe of the names Sandler, Ferrell and Spade. But Showalter pushes too far: Nerdiness, after all, can be only so attractive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926987?categoryid=1929&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Showalter is a funny man, but … how to put this gently … not a funny movie star.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050909-movies-review-baxter,0,4944209.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with The Baxter is right there at the center of the movie, and maybe it is unavoidable: Showalter makes too good of a baxter. He deserves to be dumped.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050908/REVIEWS/509080301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A wheel-spinner. The more the film stresses and strains to be funny, the unfunnier it gets.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001050065</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie filled with cardboard cutouts where the interesting characters ought to be. As a result, The Baxter is less engaging than the '40s screwball comedies (like The Philadelphia Story) that it's supposedly sending up, and not nearly as effervescent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3528&amp;Sumbit.x=42&amp;Sumbit.y=14</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no comic spark under Showalter's drab direction, and no good argument in the film why we should ever wonder about the guy left at the altar.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/240887_limited16.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film never recovers its initial fizzy-pop charms, owing largely to pacing that turns positively molasses-slow in the second act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A290068</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With The Baxter, Showalter's begging his way into the ranks of the safe and the mediocre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/15/AR2005091502237.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As coincidence would have it, Steve Carell's "The 40-Year-Old Virgin" spun comedy gold from a similar idea just last week. Virgin shares not only The Baxter's basic premise, but also two of its key cast members (Paul Rudd and the beautiful Ms. Banks), allowing audiences to see just how much better The Baxter might have been if Showalter had given us some reason to identify with his socially awkward protagonist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2248</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A zero-joke romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/51642.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Baxter is so ineptly conceived, staged, written and played that you suspect it's part of a psychology experiment to see if people will laugh at anything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/112669580156010.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$181,872</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$37,437</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>47</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>