<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Beauty Academy of Kabul, The</name>
   <company>Shadow Distribution Inc.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Liz Mermin</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors/>
   <release_date>March 24, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>74</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The teachers have moxie. The students have courage. Mermin's warm, funny, beautiful and deeply humane documentary certainly honors the latter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/115819354431350.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So laugh all you want at the proud haircutters of Beauty Without Borders - but don't underestimate what a basic cut and color can mean for a country's future.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46848</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mermin presents all this without editorial comment, and her film would be worth watching if only for its look at a profound culture-clash. But it goes one better, and delves into one of those clashing cultures, capturing it in a moment of change that goes far beyond one beauty academy's superficial concerns.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47089</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, Mermin's film is a profound reminder of the things that make us human. Things that don't matter much, in the scheme of things, but loom large when taken away. Things we all have in common.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-beauty28apr28,0,1065917.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A spiny, puzzling and highly entertaining film, and whatever you go into it thinking, you're likely to come out thinking something else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/03/23/btm/index4.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Liz Mermin documents the hilarious, moving and sometimes fractious meeting of diametrically different cultures, one that has suffered unimaginable horrors and one that believes a good perm is the answer to everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/24/movies/24beau.html</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary takes on its own engaging shape - one of edgy editorial and political ambivalence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1175642_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As they talk between classes about oppressive husbands, abusive brothers and arranged marriages, it becomes clear that the frivolities Americans take for granted can be their lifeline. In this tentatively hopeful setting, a single lipstick becomes leverage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/402448p-340791c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An often touching and always intriguing look at the fall and rebirth of a nation and the resilient spirit of its women.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/268262_limited28.html</url>
         <critic>Winda Benedetti</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Queen Latifah, the star of Barbershop 2 and Beauty Shop, and thus our reigning monarch of big-screen beauty stylists, should fund and narrate a sequel. Because The Beauty Academy of Kabul is good enough to make you want to know how they do.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.beauty28apr28,0,5795153.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's that gulf between earnest idealism and beaten-down realism that's the unexpected drama of Beauty Academy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8857</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Without editorializing, Mermin raises fascinating questions about the cultural impact of globalization, the allure of the West, and the troubled history of an ancient land.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=285331&amp;reviewId=20824</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's great charm, and also discomfort, in watching these highly motivated, excited women learn the tricks of a trade practiced very differently from their own, and casually swap horror stories of life under the Taliban.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13307/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The questionably good news put forth in this documentary is that vanity apparently survives everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A234652</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Democracy might not really come from a bottle of shampoo, but "Beauty Academy" teaches us that, sometimes, mascara really matters.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060414-movies-review-kabul,0,4782038.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's unforgettable stars are the beauty academy's students, women who have survived tribal warfare, Soviet invasion, Muslim tyranny, American bombs, patriarchal families and even Western good intentions with extraordinary grace and fortitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106873&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In an act of "selfless service," a group of American women, backed by industry giants like Clairol and Vogue, open a beauty school in war-ravaged Afghanistan. The anomalies are manifold: Gun-toting soldiers patrolling the streets are visible through the windows as rookie beauticians busily snip, perm and tweeze.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117923749?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The idea isn't as odd as it might first appear, since running a salon is one of the few socially acceptable means for a woman in Afghanistan to earn an income. The execution, however, evokes a particularly outlandish Christopher Guest mockumentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0612,winter,72605,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Winter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This quirky documentary about a group of American hairdressers who establish exactly that shows that the power of hair salons should never be underestimated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002385344</url>
         <critic>Richard James Havis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Debbie, for better or for worse, is the high point of the entertaining but lightweight film, which is better suited to public TV than the big screen. Oh, yes. If anybody should decide to open another beauty school in Kabul, be sure to leave Debbie in Indiana.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/65899.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How ironic that one form of beauty would be returned to battle-scarred Afghanistan by ugly Americans, but that's just what director Liz Mermin caught in her slim 2004 documentary for the BBC.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29600_BEAUTY_ACADEMY_OF_KABUL.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best, Mermin -- who used an all-female crew -- conveys the sense of an entirely feminine world being created under the beauty school roof, and it's refreshing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/05/05/DDGAQIKAHQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$225,448</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$14,489</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>