<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Because I Said So</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Karen Leigh Hopkins</author>
      <author>Jessie Nelson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Lehmann</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Diane Keaton</actor>
      <actor>My Moore</actor>
      <actor>Gabriel Macht</actor>
      <actor>Tom Everett Scott</actor>
      <actor>Lauren Graham</actor>
      <actor>Piper Perabo</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Collins</actor>
      <actor>Ty Panitz</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 2, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>102</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite being rooted firmly in "chick flick" territory (with a high "cuteness" index), it has the capacity to please to viewers of both genders who appreciate the genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/because_i.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amongst the cardboard-cutout supporting characters, Lauren Graham brings a welcome deadpan sensibility to the overeager proceedings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8741</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any relationship between the world of Because I Said So and actual human behavior is purely coincidental.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/58173</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Keaton is so over-the-top, so loud and so physically animated that when
Daphne develops a case of laryngitis mid-way through the movie, it's as if a
neighbor's car alarm has finally been shut down. However, in those silent moments, when Daphne is communicating with notes, you realize how much you like this actress.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-02-2007/entertainment/movies/story/493879p-415994c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mild exercise in deliberate mediocrity, with chuckles and heartwarming moments distributed as carefully as nuts in a factory-made brownie. The movie's lack of ambition is hardly surprising, but both Ms. Moore and Ms. Keaton, who can wring flustered comedy out of the mildest provocation, deserve better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/02/movies/02beca.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because I Said So might have been sharper if it had focused on the mother/daughter relationship and didn't blunt its story with romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=798660&amp;reviewId=22153</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with Because I Said So isn't that it's formulaic and predictable; fans of romantic comedy can get around those qualities, and even appreciate them. It's that the film keeps missing out on its own opportunities for comic gold.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2158865/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exercise in canned cuteness, Because I Said So pushes its normally appealing stars, Diane Keaton and Mandy Moore, over the edge of sitcom hysteria.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932649.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like nearly all of Lehmann's post- "Heathers" work, it's lazy and disinterested--a hack-for-hire job any number of film-school grads could have put through its uninspired paces.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0705,foundas,75687,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Formulaic romantic junk.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070202-movies-review-because,0,6107767.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, Graham and Perabo have so little to do that it's hard to imagine why Maggie has three daughters instead of one; they just clutter up her screen time. As to Perabo, she seems to exist for the sole purpose of making risque remarks, and the family dog has more memorable moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=285617&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Angel Cohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This slapdash, charmless, baldly boomer-chasing romantic comedy, directed by Michael Lehmann (Heathers) from a clunky, orgasm-obsessed script by Karen Leigh Hopkins and Jessie Nelson, is the lazy studio's answer to a call for more age-appropriate entertainment for "More" magazine readers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20010408,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a lazy, cliché, rabid plot and paper-thin character development, Because I Said So might as well have been directed by a trained chimpanzee.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A440603</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the filmmakers try to play for laughs -- a mom and her daughters chatting about orgasms while shoe shopping -- isn't funny, it's creepy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1125852&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Throughout most of her career Diane Keaton has shown sound instincts, so it's a mystery why she failed to sniff this false, brittle comedy out as a waste of her gifts.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31062_BECAUSE_I_SAID_SO.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's so derivative, unfunny and thuddingly bad that it's one of the more cringe-inducing movies of a genre chock-full of clunkers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-02-01-because-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A 105-minute cringe-a-thon that reduces the Katharine Hepburn of her generation to a sitcom harpy presiding over a brood of Valley Girl chicks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070202.BECAU02/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching this movie, with Diane Keaton cast as the ne plus ultra of irritating, overbearing mothers, is roughly the equivalent of listening to fingernails on a chalkboard for nearly two hours.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.because02feb02,0,7717507.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sloppily made bowl of reheated chick-flick cliches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9187</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As close to perfectly unwatchable as it can be.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=798660&amp;reviewId=22154&amp;startDate=02%2F02%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The search for true love is the backbone of romantic comedy as well as the lifeblood of match.com, but this film's clumsy, completely inauthentic portrayal of it is handled in a shockingly tedious fashion.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=5A292396AD8394B63F2A3E7DA86B3660.prodapp15_ae_01?id=798660&amp;reviewId=22151&amp;startDate=02%2F02%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film drags by, charmlessly, endlessly. Shrieking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3488/because-i-said-so.html</url>
         <critic>Sara Brady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I hope Keaton doesn't begin to make a specialty of these roles. They play into what is least attractive in her repertoire – the loosey-goosey, knockabout side of her that all too swiftly devolves into hysterics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0202/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thirty years after "Annie Hall," the beloved actress is scraping below the bottom of the barrel with this desperately unfunny farce, in which she mugs and pratfalls in the worst performance of her entire career.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02022007/entertainment/movies/its_annie_hell_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a dreadful exercise, tin-eared and sincere, bereft of any truth or inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/02/02/DDGJTNT2TR1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to imagine how the movie year could possibly produce a more annoyingly stupid movie. It's so witless, broadly played and insulting to anyone's intelligence that it's almost as offensive, in its own way, as "Jackass: The Movie."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/302079_because02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not so much phoned in as it is auto-dialed with a text-to-speech prerecorded message in one of those creepy robotic voices.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-because2feb02,0,2220484.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's tempting to write off Because I Said So as just another dumb, bad comedy, made yesterday and forgotten tomorrow. But no matter how negligible this particular picture is, it's time to look a little deeper. If these are the only kinds of roles we can conceive for actresses who have grown into their faces, as Keaton has, it's no wonder so many younger performers are seeking the knife.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/02/02/because/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By far the most appallingly cretinous picture in which Keaton has ever appeared.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9738</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film bespeaks a truly startling mistrust of the movie audience, and, what's more, a disrespect for the feature film medium. Yes, of course it was conceived as an unpretentious entertainment pitched mainly to girls and young women. Yet that doesn't explain the nightmarish quality of the finished product.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$42,674,040</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,122,865</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,526</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>diane keaton</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>