<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Beerfest</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jay Chandrasekhar, Kevin Heffernan, Steve Lemme, Paul Soter &amp; Erik Stolhanske</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jay Chandrasekhar</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Erik Stolhanske</actor>
      <actor>Paul Soter</actor>
      <actor>Jay Chrasekhar</actor>
      <actor>Steve Lemme</actor>
      <actor>Kevin Heffernan</actor>
      <actor>Philippe Brenninkmeyer</actor>
      <actor>Will Forte</actor>
      <actor>Ralf Moeller</actor>
      <actor>Cloris Leachman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 25, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beerfest panders shamelessly to the 15-year-old in this 30-year-old... without assuming he is a 15-year-old. It's R-rated puerility for actual immature grown-ups.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1328532_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fun-dumb and definitely not everyone's cup of tea -- I don't want to oversell it -- but Broken Lizard keeps it interesting by refusing to color inside the lines, creating their own silly little universe.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1156377354113280.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Random silliness rules the day, but the gags are frequently surprising.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/52053</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The guys of the Broken Lizard comedy troupe (of "Super Troopers" fame) are neither subtle nor especially ingenious. But in the age of gross-out gags and high-concept gimmicks, they throw themselves into the raucous, rude style of '70s film comedy with shameless glee.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/282459_beerfest25q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funnier than you might imagine.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=282082&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ach, Klaus, das ist funny! But Beerfest goes on too long. Take out 20 minutes of nonfunctioning jokes, and it would have given you a comedy buzz like four tankards of Lowenbrau.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/schlitz__giggles_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fans of Broken Lizard's previous work will enjoy this beer-fuddled effort; for anyone else it has its moments, but is best watched through beer-goggles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133829</url>
         <critic>James Swanwick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Granted, you'e going to enjoy it a lot more if you spent a healthy chunk of your late teens/early 20s playing Bullshit and doing keg stands, but it's far from the worst comedy of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9264</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Among the cast, Chandrasekhar is easily the funniest of the Lizards, though in fairness, each has his moments. The movie does, too; just expect them to shrink exponentially depending on your level of sobriety.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/08-25-2006/entertainment/col/story/446549p-375834c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This gets off to a pretty good start, with most of the laughs coming from beefy Kevin Heffernan and nerdy Steve Lemme. But at 111 minutes, the movie is too slackly paced to build up enough momentum; like the characters they play, these guys don't know when to call it a night.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30222_BEERFEST.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ok, so maybe you don't absolutely have to have a Y chromosome and be 14 years old (or have the mind of a 14-year-old) to appreciate the freshmanic humor that is Beerfest. But, oh, does it help.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joanne Kaufman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The five comedians known collectively as Broken Lizard have created a frat-house staple for the ages.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/08/25/movies/25beer.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beerfest is one sloppy comedy, but the lads of the comedy troupe Broken Lizard don't know when to say when in their pursuit of the idiotic laugh, and persistence certainly counts for something.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060825-movies-review-beerfest,0,226826.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Such fare plays better on DVD, where the best moments can be absorbed in bite-sized bits and the debris easily bypassed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931383?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mediocre raunchy comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/08/25/beerfest/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To enjoy it you almost have to be stoned on marijuana.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/08/25/DDGBAKO49P1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beerfest bubbles with the cheeky irreverence of early John Landis and David Zucker. Yet, like just about every other American screen comedy of the moment, it's far too long in the tooth, with a scattershot final half-hour that seems the work of an editor battling a bad hangover.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14328/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's funny to Broken Lizard? Let's try: What's not funny? The answers are, everything and nothing. They'll do anything for a laugh, no matter how puerile, silly or offensive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1120677&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, Beerfest plays like a party that's gone on too long, when the buzz has worn off and the hangover starts to set in.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-08-24-beerfest-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Scott Bowles</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beerfest is safety-by-numbers comedy. A troupe, as opposed to a single comic star like Adam Sandler, shares the comic load and, well, at least the film is funnier than "Click."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060825.BEER25/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beerfest is tedious and, at 112 minutes, too long to sustain a sophomoric, one-joke comedy even for the presumed target audience of older male teens and the college-age crowd.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003053009</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sober, this kind of material is an acquired taste at best and downright unbearable in stretches. And yet, the movie has the makings of an instant cult classic, sure to grow funnier among its devoted fans with each successive viewing.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=683222&amp;reviewId=21352</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script is a stupid mix of Teutonic tongue twisters (say hello to Herr Schniedelwichsen), hoary German cliches (from phallic sausages to U-boat spoofs), and bad slapstick.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=86715F42A1F84934269DB09DFDF39734.prodapp12_ae_01?id=683222&amp;reviewId=21356&amp;startDate=08%2F25%2F2006</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Making a comedy that celebrates binge drinking and cretinous behavior isn't a crime against nature. Making one that's as brutally unfunny as Beerfest is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8866</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The vulgarity is so over-the-top and the decent jokes too few and far between.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A396795</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$19,185,184</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$7,031,228</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,964</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>