<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Before the Devil Knows You&amp;#039;re Dead</name>
   <company>THINKFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Kelly Masterson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sidney Lumet</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Philip Seymour Hoffman</actor>
      <actor>Ethan Hawke</actor>
      <actor>Albert Finney</actor>
      <actor>Marisa Tomei</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 26, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie grabs hold and runs you through the wringer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0743,hoberman,78117,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mesmerizing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20153695,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the great American films of the past decade, and the crowning masterpiece of Lumet's long career.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1026/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This flick is fast and ferocious, his (Sidney Lumet) sharpest and best since "Prince of the City" (1980) - and surely one of the year's finest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10262007/entertainment/movies/el_sid.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers the rare pleasure of watching a major director return to his own material and rework it 30 years later. This story of a pitiful jewel heist gone so profoundly wrong that it approaches the scope of Greek tragedy isn't quite a remake of "Dog Day Afternoon."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2176631/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In addition to being a study in great acting, this is a study in great directing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141012&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A superb crime melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071101/REVIEWS/711010302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A wicked deconstruction of a dysfunctional clan: brothers at each other's throats; a father whose legacy is anger and betrayal; an unfaithful wife; a history of deceit. It's a horror show of hatred and festering psychic wounds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20071102_All_the_deadly_sins__sinfully_fine.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its virtues are velocity, energy, innovative storytelling - and something that seems even more the province of young directors: a certain heartlessness and ironic distance in the tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/02/DDJRT42TO.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Compact, nasty, and altogether wonderful, a tale of brotherly greed and New York comeuppance that shows an old dog dusting off old tricks using new technology.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10716</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Emotionally brutal, ferociously acted, crafted with unflagging expertise and relentlessly locked in its vision of human darkness, Before the Devil Knows You're Dead is as grim and despairing as any tragedy by Sophocles or Shakespeare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1195088363209160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bleak, weirdly witty at times and unrelentingly suspenseful, Before the Devil Knows You’re Dead is the cinematic equivalent of a perfect storm.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10473</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is no nostalgia trip taken by an 83-year-old director. It's a fierce, hot slap of a movie, a shameless melodrama with bite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-devil2nov02,0,3542471.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is, like quite a few Lumet pictures, rather small in scale, easy to overlook. But I think it is time to gather around a director who has embraced his octogenarian bleakness and sing his praises. Ultimately, I think you'll laugh a lot at what he has wrought here -- but only well after the movie is over and the full scale of its perversity settles into your bones.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1676634,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>His (Sidney Lumet) touch in Before the Devil is so sure, so perfectly weighted, that it’s hard to imagine him capable of making a bad movie. The thing is just enthralling.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/39587/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pungently atmospheric, brilliantly textured and featuring superb performances from every performer in parts big and small.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9735&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The wrenching tale has something for anyone who likes their melodrama spiked with palpable tension and genuine suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934641.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Lisa Nesselson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the evil that men do to one another in this film may well be rooted in the Cain-like enabling of original sin from one doomed brother to another, the final familial tragedy feels exactly like classic Lumet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A558319</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One bad idea can unravel and ruin lives in unimaginably horrific ways.That's the concept underlying the riveting Before the Devil Knows You're Dead, a sharply acted and highly entertaining morality play.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-11-01-devil_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A dynamite film that ranks with the year's best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15797370/review/16971675/before_the_devil_knows_youre_dead</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The true star of this nerve-racking family crime drama, shot with a minimum of fuss by Ron Fortunato, is playwright and first-time screenwriter Kelly Masterson's deft script, which carefully develops each fatally flawed character and tells their stories in achronological flashbacks that seamlessly fit together like a jigsaw puzzle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/devil-knows-youre/review/290750</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Arguably Lumet's best film in 20 years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/10/26/2007-10-26_before_the_devil_knows_youre_dead_a_winn.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The action is violent, messy, and threaded through with dark humor. This is a movie for grownups, for sure, but it has a mulish kick that most such pictures consider themselves to tasteful to aspire to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4199/before-the-devil-knows-youre-dead.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, the film is just a smart caper picture with some good performances, but at times it's VERY smart, and Hoffman's performance in particular is one of the most natural and unexpectedly affecting that he's given in years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/before_the_devil_knows_youre</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Curiously exhilarating. Some of this comes from the simple thrill of witnessing something, or rather everything, done well.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/10/26/movies/26devi.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Furious and entertaining little morality play.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/10/29/071029crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is not a drama of shadings, but of ever-increasing intensity.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119456479096187232.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bleak, brutal and quite possibly brilliant, this is a triumphant return to form for Lumet and further proof that Hoffman is on an incredible winning streak.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134215</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Atmosphere is the main virtue with which this "Devil" can tempt us.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=982766&amp;reviewId=22779&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is an adrenaline-pumping, devilishly well-made thriller set against the downfall of an American family.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/337722_before02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Philip Seymour Hoffman is in fine form as a man teetering on the edge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/before_devil.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What you’re left with, finally, is the pleasure of a wily director’s company. In much the same way John Huston defied convention and predictability in the third act of his directorial career, with films as odd and fresh as “Wise Blood” and “Prizzi’s Honor,” Lumet is doing the same, right now.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-before-the/243068/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only player in this tawdry round-robin game who moved or seduced me in any way was Andy’s poor, hapless Gina. Tomei’s an ordinary beauty...  But she has real screen presence and range, and her neglected wife is an artful inversion of her Oscar-winning role as Danny DeVito’s pert squeeze in "My Cousin Vinny."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/the-lower-depths/17608/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is not a first-class film noir but a top-grade acting class. You admire it without enjoying it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.freddead09nov09,0,810899.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem is not that the director is working but that his latest film is working too hard. Way too hard – this thing is melodrama running a marathon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071116.wdevil16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even though it's scripted by a woman (Kelly Masterson), this tale of buried family resentments rising to the surface as the brothers plot to rob their parents' jewelry store is concerned only with the guys, and it's marred by an uncharacteristically mannered performance by Albert Finney as the father.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32372_BEFORE_THE_DEVIL_KNOWS_YOU&amp;#039;RE_DEAD.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The evident strengths and laudable intentions of Before the Devil Knows You're Dead (and even the appeal of Marisa Tomei in her undies) are overwhelmed by an implausible plot verging on unintentional comedy and a panoply of Noo Yawk dirt-bag supporting characters who might've seemed awkward on a 1993 episode of "NYPD Blue."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/10/25/btm/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,085,511</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$73,837</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>