<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Beowulf</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Animation</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Anonymous</author>
      <author>Roger Avary</author>
      <author>Neil Gaiman</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert Zemeckis</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ray Winstone</actor>
      <actor>Angelina Jolie</actor>
      <actor>Anthony Hopkins</actor>
      <actor>Crispin Glover</actor>
      <actor>John Malkovich</actor>
      <actor>Robin Wright Penn</actor>
      <actor>Brendan Gleeson</actor>
      <actor>Alison Lohman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 16, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>113</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zemeckis springs so many pow 3-D surprises you'll think Beowulf is your own private fun house.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/7667721/review/17335234/beowulf</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf is a solemnly gorgeous, at times borderline stolid piece of Tolkien-with-a-joystick mythology.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20160207,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the record, it's truly puzzling that this film has been rated PG-13; it's much stronger than that. The monsters of "Beowulf" have haunted human imagination for more than a millennium; the ones in this film will easily provoke a few nightmares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1195079132279160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's got power and depth, and two kings whose greatness is diluted by hubris, and a thrilling dragon fight, and the demon Grendel as a tortured outcast, and a naked monster who looks a lot like Angelina Jolie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1684839,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s not a reinvention of the wheel, but in 3D this is an astonishing experience that borders on ‘must-see’, and raises the bar for what James Cameron is planning with Avatar. And you’ll be glad to know that the creepy dead eyes thing has been fixed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=11012</url>
         <critic>Tom Ambrose</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Highly entertaining - but far from classic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11152007/entertainment/movies/beowatch_386299.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zemeckis has converted the epic poem about the warrior who slays the monster Grendel into a species of computer game. He employs the same motion-capture technology that he first used in "The Polar Express," to slightly better effect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1116/p15s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We are not looking at flesh-and-blood actors but special effects that look uncannily convincing, even though I am reasonably certain that Angelina Jolie does not have spike-heeled feet. That's right: feet, not shoes.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071114/REVIEWS/71115001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not all of it works - and not all of it works the way the target audience of jacked-up young males might want it to - but the movie is hugely provocative fun, and I'm pretty sure that's on purpose.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8510</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf couldn't be less faithful to the original epic poem, and that's actually a good thing for moviegoers. It's a lot more fun than the mythic adventure most of us read in school.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-11-15-beowulf-review_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Regardless of the medium, this is an effectively brutal story of swords, sorcery, demons, and heroes, with an Oedipal hint or two thrown in for flavor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/beowulf.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The bolder stroke comes from screenwriters Roger Avary (Pulp Fiction) and Neil Gaiman (the graphic novel Sandman), who’ve turned the arthritic legend into sort of an Arthur Miller play in chain mail.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32396_BEOWULF.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Could call Zemeckis subtle; but his style
Well suits the poem's crude and earthy brawn.
Comic-Con geeks and cinephiles alike
Will gape at the resplendent imagery
(But don ye specs, and see it in 3-D).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2178072/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story works, but I wish they'd teach these avatars to act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1115910&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf deserves to be taken semiseriously; its eye candy is mixed with narrative fiber and dramatic protein. But it begs to be taken frivolously. Effects have grown so exciting in the realm of the third dimension that you just sit there all agog behind your polarizing glasses.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119517337319395051.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf may ultimately be viewed as a failure, but it’s a fascinating one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-smiley-face-beowulf-confessions-of-a-superhero-om-shanti-om/17696/</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Robert Zemeckis not only deploys 21st century movie technology at its finest to turn the heroic poem into a vibrant, nerve-tingling piece of pop culture, but his film actually makes sense of Beowulf. In Zemeckis' hands, it's an intriguing look at a hero as a flawed human being.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=10190&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although this version of Beowulf (the script, ricocheting between thrilling, heroic, and hilarious, is by Neil Gaiman and Roger Avary) does take some liberties with certain heretofore undreamed of aspects of parentage, it's as faithful to the extant version as it needs to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A560352</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As dazzling a feast for the eyes as the hungriest eyes can take.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/16/2007-11-16_a_big_bad_beowulf.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>People's eyes still look as glassy and dull as a taxidermized possum's. But if you're going to Beowulf to experience the sweeping passions that only real eyes can convey, you're missing the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=A2D3B3335E2375749A9697F110605000.prodapp02_ae_01?id=977651&amp;reviewId=22756&amp;startDate=11%2F15%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the arrival of Beowulf is any indication, movie actors will soon all be replaced by lifelike, digitally animated facsimiles. The good news is that some of them might still sound like John Malkovich.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071116.wbeowulf16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf is many things, but boring isn't one of them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/308579.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its visual sweep and propulsively violent action, this bloodthirsty rendition of the Old English epic can't overcome the disadvantage of being enacted by digital waxworks rather than flesh-and-blood Danes and demons.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935372.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf is all right as far as it goes, and it goes pretty far for a PG-13 rating: Dismemberment, “300”-style blood globules comin’ atcha, and a digitally futzed and, for all practical purposes, completely naked!!!</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-beowulf/251935/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>First and foremost a showcase for the latest developments in motion-capture and 3-D technology.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/beowulf/review/291213</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I like a good flying, fire-breathing dragon as much as the next fellow. Beowulf's excesses, though, are such that the film ought to carry the subtitle …But This Is Ridiculous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4245/beowulf.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zemeckis, who blazed trails mixing live-action with animation in "Who Framed Roger Rabbit," blazes not even a footpath here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071116_Beowulf_an_epic_exercise_in_silliness.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The 3-D is necessary to the film only in so far as it keeps your eyes engaged when your mind starts to wander. Stripped of much of the original poem’s language, its cadences, deep history and context, this film version of Beowulf doesn’t offer much beyond 3-D oohs and ahs, sword clanging and a nicely conceived dragon, which probably explains why Mr. Zemeckis and his collaborators have tried to sex it up with Ms. Jolie, among other comic-book flourishes.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/16/movies/16beow.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As for Beowulf itself, it's all about the visuals, which means that as soon as the novelty of 3-D wears off, the experience has been had.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/16/DDIITCC2D.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ten years from now, Beowulf may look like the groundbreaking project that helped kill live-action movies, but for the moment, its uncomfortable jokes and fakey rendering of life leave it wedged firmly in the uncanny valley. (Insert your own joke about Jolie's astonishing animated anatomy here.)</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/beowulf</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Owing more to the sword-and-sex-play fantasies of 12-year-olds than the traditions of Old English poetry, Robert Zemeckis' Beowulf will allow adolescents to have their cheesecake - and beefcake - and eat it, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.beowulf16nov16,0,1009906.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most interesting thing about Beowulf, alas, is its technology. It's the work of a man who has fallen in love with his toys, but I miss the wicked satirist who made "Used Cars." And the truth is the motion capture in Beowulf comes across as an unsatisfying compromise between animation and live action.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/70660</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Certainly, modern interpretations should add their own spin to an ancient tale, but in the hands of director Robert Zemeckis, Beowulf becomes... silly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10417</url>
         <critic>Jamie Tipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beowulf appears so cartoony, in fact, that the academy just put it on the short list of films to be considered for the Oscar in feature animation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-beowulf16nov16,0,5722497.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ambitious, overbearing and hollow; it goes overboard to impress, yet it never feels truly inventive or imaginative. At best, it achieves a level of clumsy camp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/11/16/beowulf/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$82,195,215</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$150,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$27,515,871</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,153</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>anthony hopkins</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>robert zemeckis</oscar_winning_director>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>