<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Beyond the Gates</name>
   <company>IFC Films / Renaissance Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Wolstencroft</author>
      <author>Richard Alwyn</author>
      <author>David Belton</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Caton-Jones</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKGermany</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>John Hurt</actor>
      <actor>Hugh Dancy</actor>
      <actor>Dominique Horwitz</actor>
      <actor>Louis Mahoney</actor>
      <actor>Nicola Walker</actor>
      <actor>Steve Toussaint</actor>
      <actor>David Gyasi</actor>
      <actor>Susan Nalwoga</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 9, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>115</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caton-Jones' refusal to pull back on showing exactly what happened to the 800,000 Rwandans who were murdered that spring means that strong stomachs and even stronger nerves are required, but the film demands to be seen by anyone attempting to grasp how -- and just how quickly -- genocide can occur.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=285091&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In some ways the movie's straightforward style is more appropriate to the horror than a more souped-up approach would have been. With material this strong, sometimes the best thing a filmmaker can do is to stay out of the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0316/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tense and gut-wrenching, Beyond the Gates is a horrifying story told with grace and compassion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-beyond16mar16,0,5764019.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Critics have faulted this 2005 British feature about the Rwandan genocide for focusing on a couple of white characters instead of the 800,000 Tutsis who were slaughtered, but such easy judgments miss the point entirely: this is a spiritual drama, not a political one, drawing a thick line between our good intentions and the selfish choices we ultimately make.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#31321</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Beyond the Gates were merely a well-intentioned bore, the reality might seem jarring. As is, the coda fits and feels like the only possible ending--proof that surviving to help tell the story of a genocidal nightmare is the best revenge.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070330-movies-review-gates,0,2881497.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gripping, terrifying, profoundly touching human drama that's definitely worth seeing.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/309536_gates30q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>John Hurt is magnetic as a Catholic priest running a school where terrified Tutsi have taken refuge, while Hugh Dancy, as a naive teacher, represents white commitment to black Africa at its most impotent and unreliable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20014258,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hurt steals scenes with a brilliantly nuanced character, a man bitter enough to make every line delivered to his peers a challenge or an accusation, yet experienced enough to present those challenges with an ingratiating politesse that only cracks in extremis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/beyond_the_gates</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hurt and Dancy are terrific in these roles, but the power of the movie is in the tension created by Caton-Jones on the same sites where this historical event unfolded.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/503692p-424763c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Powerful and moving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/03/23/DDGGDOPE3R1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film may employ the well-worn tradition of filtering African stories through the experiences of Europeans, but they use the conceit for some penetrating revelations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1132678&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is occasionally heavy-handed, and the priest character is almost absurdly saintly, but there is an awful power to scenes such as one in which the Europeans are evacuated on trucks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03092007/entertainment/movies/help_me__rwanda_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though less reassuring and not as dramatically coherent as "Hotel Rwanda," it still packs a hard punch.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/09/movies/09gate.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although in many respects a more stylish, authentic, tougher-minded film than "Hotel Rwanda," director Michael Caton-Jones' respectable and well-intentioned Beyond the Gates (aka Shooting Dogs) still falls into the trap of filtering an inherently African story through the eyes of a noble white protagonist -- in this case, two of them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928369.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though hobbled by its anxious impulse to teach history to an audience that by now surely knows the basic contours of Rwanda's tragedy, the script apportions blame where it belongs (on high), while leaving smaller fry--including an admirably un-cute BBC journalist--dangling, however sympathetically, on the hook.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0710,film,75994,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The greatest failure of the film, written by David Wolstencroft, is its inability to enter into the lives of the Rwandans, Tutsi and Hutu alike. The movie never moves beyond the tragic facts to show us the human face of either victims or perpetrators. All we get are white people shaking their heads and cursing Western governments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8883</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sadly, this is the sort of movie in which the white Europeans do all the talking and worrying with each other. The Africans, for the most part, are either terrified, cowering, wincing masses or corpses strewn in the dirt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9799</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beyond the Gates bears witness to the worst of the worst, but these days, and far more importantly, so does YouTube.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A479262</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$40,848</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$6,374</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>