<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Black Snake Moan</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Craig Brewer</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Craig Brewer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Samuel L. Jackson</actor>
      <actor>Christina Ricci</actor>
      <actor>Justin Timberlake</actor>
      <actor>S. Epatha Merkerson</actor>
      <actor>John Cothran Jr.</actor>
      <actor>David Banner</actor>
      <actor>Michael Raymond-James</actor>
      <actor>Adriane Lenox</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 2, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>115</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gorgeous, life-affirming movie. On paper, it sounds lurid bordering on ridiculous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1172697913183990.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a filmmaker, Brewer doesn't just yank your chain: He forges a bond with his characters and his audience that produces ecstasy and healing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.black02mar02,0,3043716.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ricci's performance is brave and effective - the most provocative in a career that has rejected Hollywood norms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/black_snake.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story is as humorous and raunchy as a good blues refrain, and the way Lazarus and Rae react to each other almost resembles the classic call-and-response structure of the blues.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A450682</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perpetually wide-eyed and mega-snarly bedraggled, Christina Ricci prowls through Black Snake Moan looking like something the cat dragged in. If you're anything like me, you'll be very grateful to the cat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3532/black-snake-moan.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Black Snake Moan' is a trip to that unfamiliar territory well worth tagging along on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/03/02/DDGOAOD1LD1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's beautifully shot -- the sweat-drenched jukejoint scenes are particularly evocative -- and features a terrific performance by Ricci, one that deserves to be seen by a wider audience than the one certain to be reeled in by those torrid ads.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286020&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Hustle &amp; Flow," Moan succeeds on languid atmosphere and the conviction of its leads. But it'd be nice if the execution matched the startling audacity of its premise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/59210</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brewer, who romanticized the world of pimps and ho's in "Hustle &amp; Flow," is obviously out to push some politically incorrect buttons with this ludicrous - yet, in the end, sweetly involving - Southern Gothic pulp yarn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03022007/entertainment/movies/blues_blazes_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I knew blues music can make you feel you're not alone when your woman has gone, and rock your soul when you're on top of the world. But until I saw Black Snake Moan, I didn't know it could also cure nymphomania.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=813099&amp;reviewId=22292</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A wild and sweet little picture about sex, redemption and music, though perhaps not necessarily in that order.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/03/02/black_snake/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's outlandish, hilariously overripe, and possibly sexist: You'd expect no less from Craig Brewer, the writer and director who made the passionate case for how hard it is out there for a pimp. But I loved the picture's tabloid energy and heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/28516/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's easy to work up a good head of feminist steam over the misogyny and downright idiocy of a story that suggests that the tyranny of a righteous man can prevent an abused girl from making poor and whorish fashion choices. But it's hard to dismiss completely this atmospheric and persistently intriguing film.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=25F503A203C7E473EE93E8F480791B2D.prodapp12_ae_01?id=813099&amp;reviewId=22305&amp;startDate=03%2F02%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A roiling, boiling mix of blaxploitation, sexploitation, Tennessee Williams and the Tennessee outback.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=813099&amp;reviewId=22302</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie is crazy, but the insanity is electric.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9119</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sam Jackson delivers the electric blues in a not-so-blue movie that promises more Deep South sin than it actually delivers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134220</url>
         <critic>Damon Wise</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to know what to make of the thing, though it has a sleazy charm, it's never boring and it goes a certain distance on Samuel L. Jackson's conviction.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/305703_snake02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best thing about Black Snake Moan, a song title, is the blues soundtrack. The movie is an absurdly jarring collection of archetypal characters in miserable circumstances with a resolution that feels forced and tacked on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-03-01-black-snake-moan_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mix Brigitte Bardot in "And God Created Woman" with Carroll Baker in "Baby Doll," sex it up times 10 and you have a notion of the effect of Christina Ricci in Black Snake Moan.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2007&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=berlin&amp;nav=RBerlin&amp;articleid=VE1117932596&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Black Snake Moan sho-nuff ain't no "Sweetback." Indeed, long stretches of Brewer's Suthun-fried sophomore slump come down the country road lookin' as haggard as a workaholic ho on a Sunday morning.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0709,nelson,75919,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is one of those ludicrous, semi-offensive, semi-entertaining potboilers that feels as if the script were dragged out from someone's naughty-book stash.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070301.wmoan02/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Black Snake Moan morphs into a wacky intergenerational bonding movie, something closer to "Harold and Maude" or "The Karate Kid" with a dusting of Southern grit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2160961/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brewer knows how to guide his leads through this improbable story, and he kept me interested in spite of everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31134_BLACK_SNAKE_MOAN.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In spite of Amelia Vincent's toothsome cinematography and the down-home locations, the movie often has the lumbering, literal-minded rhythms of a second-rate stage play -- not a moan or a howl, but a slow, anxious groan.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/02/movies/02blac.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Be prepared to collapse into a hoot and a howl of hilarity at all the wrong moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20013555,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The blues music in "Moan" is superfine, but my oh my, what to make of the ripe Southern cliches and this absurd story. The film is so jaw-dropping awful that it just might become a boxoffice hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8704&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Black Snake Moan is unadulterated deep-fried silliness from "Hustle &amp; Flow" filmmaker Craig Brewer, Jackson makes it indisputably more palatable. It's still not a very good movie, but it's intermittently entertaining (and sometimes unintentionally funny).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-black2mar02,0,5584616.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Parading through most of the movie in a cutoff T-shirt and bikini briefs, Ricci takes the stereotype of the oversexed farmer's daughter to gothic extremes; Jackson's character, named Lazarus, is similarly drawn with oversize strokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1123266&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Black Snake Moan strikes me as hogwash. It fundamentally does not work; its consciously far-fetched, out-there notions of the things damaged people do in the name of love are reductive and go only so far. It's as if the premise were tethered to a radiator or something.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070302-movies-review-snake,0,4782038.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offensive on multiple levels -- if only the plot had any levels at all -- Black Snake Moan leaves no "Tobacco Road" cliche unsmoked. Ricci gives it her all, and then some, but even her body and Jackson's blues can't heal a movie that rockets plum off its nut.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/6172585/review/13544757/black_snake_moan</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Black Snake Moan is, at its core, a fairly straightforward variation on George Bernard Shaw -- "Pigsfeetmalion," if you will. One day, when he outgrows his terminal adolescence, Brewer might be the perfect filmmaker to tackle Faulkner or Tennessee Williams.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-black-snake-moan-wild-hogs-and-more/15806/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the preposterous clichés of the plot, which clanks as loudly as Laz's chain, and for all the inertness of Justin Timberlake's performance as Rae's brooding squeeze, Black Snake Moan finds unchained energy in its foolishness, and gives Mr. Jackson a chance to pluck a guitar and sing. He's really good at it, too. The music almost redeems the movie.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe Jackson should avoid any more movies with "snake" in the title.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0302/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At heart, "BSM" is no different from the midnight movies of the '60s and '70s that reveled in a head-spinning blend of blatant exploitation, provocative racial commentary and overwrought performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/501864p-423219c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$9,396,870</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$4,143,199</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,252</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>samuel l. jackson</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>