<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Borat: Cultural Learnings of America for Make Benefit Glorious Nation of Kazakhstan</name>
   <company>Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sacha Baron Cohen,Anthony Hines, Peter Baynham,Dan Mazer,Todd Phillips</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Larry Charles</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sacha Baron Cohen</actor>
      <actor>Pamela Anderson</actor>
      <actor>Ken Davitian</actor>
      <actor>Pat Haggerty</actor>
      <actor>Alan Keyes</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 3, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>82</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>You won't know what outrageous fun is until you see Borat. High-five!</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/9544561/review/12221746/borat_cultural_learnings_of_america_for_make_benefit_glorious_nation_of_kazakhstan</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Absurd, outrageous, gross, disturbing, insightful, and so funny it’ll burst half the blood vessels in your face.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134345</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat is a rarity: a comedy whose middle name is danger, or as the Kazakhs say, kauwip-kater.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061103-movies-review-borat,0,784347.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a perfect combination of slapstick and satire, a Platonic ideal of high-and lowbrow that manages to appeal to our basest common denominators while brilliantly skewering racism, anti-Semitism, sexism and that peculiarly American affliction: we're-number-one-ism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1122144&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wildly funny. Its best jokes approach some savage, atavistic core of cultural taboo and make the viewer wonder: Is it really possible to laugh at this? But by the time you formulate that question, it's too late: You're already laughing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2152790</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat isn't just one of the funniest movies of the year, it might be one of the funniest movies of all time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9401</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As clever as he is crude, Cohen alchemizes bad-taste comedy into Strangelovean satire.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html?week=nextweek#15258</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I can't wait to see Borat, which has twice as many laughs as all of this year's other movie comedies combined, for a fourth time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11022006/entertainment/movies/kazakh_it_to_me__movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I hate to sound blurby, but Borat is the funniest comedy I've seen since I don't know when.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1103/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Borat has been likened to "Jackass," there's a huge difference. The "Jackass" movies are about extreme stunts. Borat is about interaction and gullibility, and its success is unique to both Cohen and to this one-time-only movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/11-03-2006/entertainment/col/story/467915p-393526c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat is a terrific, risky comic creation: a village idiot for the global village.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.borat03nov03,0,1129417.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A comic put-on of awe-inspiring crudity and death-defying satire and by a long shot the funniest film of the year. It is "Jackass" with a brain and Mark Twain with full frontal male nudity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8982</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's screamingly, hysterically, laugh-through-the-next-joke, laugh-for-the-next-week funny. It's so inventive…This is a film by an original and significant comic intelligence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/11/03/DDGRCM45V31.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is comedy from the danger zone, and it will genuinely offend some folks who feel certain subjects are not to be laughed at. They'd best stay at home. Fans should be warned as well: Borat can make you laugh so hard it hurts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15560971/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Very nice. I like Borat very much. I think it is, as everybody has been saying, the funniest movie in years.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20061102/REVIEWS/611020302/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When Baron Cohen works without a net, he flies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1553310_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed, the man who invented Borat is a masterful improviser, brilliant comedian, courageous political satirist, and genuinely experimental film artist. Borat makes you laugh but Baron Cohen forces you to think.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0644,hoberman,74897,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Uproariously funny mockumentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931533.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Leslie Felperin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The brilliance of Borat is that its comedy is as pitiless as its social satire, and as brainy.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/11/03/movies/03bora.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since the halcyon days of Archie Bunker and "All in the Family" has so sharp a wit punctured so many balloons.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat is an astonishingly entertaining picture, and it's a testament to Cohen's gifts that he can pull off a feat as extravagant and as fully realized as this one is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/11/03/borat/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This feature-length expansion of Cohen's deliciously ridiculous character accomplishes what decades of Soviet propaganda failed to do: It points out and underscores issues of race, religious intolerance, classism, and all manner of very American social ills by giving the culprits just enough rope to hang themselves by their own petards (and then some).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A415224</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat is most gloriously funny moving picture for to make people see their stupidness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-11-02-review-borat_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It takes some exceptionally intelligent and witty people to make a dumb comedy this funny and perceptive: Borat may be offensive (to some), infantile, low-brow or even just a stunt, but you won't hate yourself in the morning for loving it.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=13F248C819D69B384AD32C6BEE8B8844.prodapp15_ae_02?id=733168&amp;reviewId=21728</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baron Cohen brings scary conviction to the performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=733168&amp;reviewId=21721</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As slapstick, as satire, as sheer gut-busting comedy, Borat is top notch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1162349747324810.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In choosing cheap gags over incisive cultural commentary, Borat scores more as scatology than satire, but it's easy to overlook its ramshackle nature in light of the explosive laughter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/54822</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is equipped, like an F-15 Eagle, to engage multiple targets at once.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?061106crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The gimmick is simple but devastatingly effective: Never once breaking character or acknowledging that he’s in on the joke, the Jew-fearing, grammatically challenged reporter ingratiates himself with his unsuspecting, average-American victims before uproariously turning the tables on them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14926/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With his corrosive brand of take-no-prisoners humor that scalds on contact, Cohen is the most intentionally provocative comedian since Lenny Bruce and early Richard Pryor, with a difference. For unlike those predecessors, there is a mean-spiritedness, an every-man-for-himself coldness about his humor. The one kind of laughter you won't find in Borat is that which acknowledges shared humanity. Instead, there is that pitiless staple of reality TV, watching others humiliate themselves for our viewing pleasure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-borat3nov03,0,6047507.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The weapon wielded by Cohen and Charles is crudeness. People today, especially those in public life, can disguise prejudice in coded language and soft tones. Bigotry is ever so polite now. So the filmmakers mean to drag the beast out into the sunlight of brilliant satire and let everyone see the rotting, stinking, foul thing for what it is. When you laugh at something that is bad, it loses much of its power.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The variation keeps things fresh and the relatively short running length (less than 90 minutes) ensures that Borat doesn't overstay its welcome - even though when it's all done, we wish this absurd man might have lingered a little longer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/borat.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat is, in many ways, an heir to the same kind of subversion of American norms that the transvestite Divine perfected in John Waters’ early films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3082/borat.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Letkemann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fearless performance and yields some squirm-inducingly funny moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=283879&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cohen and his gang are smart enough to know when to quit. Like a loud but amusing guest at a dinner party, Borat collects his coat and goes home just as his hosts are starting to fidget.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=733168&amp;reviewId=21718&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Borat at its best is pure satiric genius, the Swiftian kind that has you busting a gut with laughter even while checking your conscience for implicating flaws.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20061103.wborat03/BNStory/Entertainment/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Except for a screamingly funny climax in which he attempts to kidnap Pamela Anderson (who reportedly wasn't in on the joke), I found the Borat feature (directed by Larry Charles, who does similar duties on "Curb Your Enthusiasm") depressing; and the paroxysms of the audience reinforced the feeling that I was watching a bearbaiting or pigsticking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorkmetro.com/movies/features/23476/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie itself cannot begin to match its delicious high concept. It's offensively funny in places but it can't sustain itself for a feature length running time and it's not nearly as clever or as fun as it should be.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/290918_borat03q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$128,505,958</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$18,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$26,455,463</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>837</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>