<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Boy in the Striped Pajamas, The</name>
   <company>Miramax Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Herman</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Mark Herman</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>David Thewlis</actor>
      <actor>Vera Farmiga</actor>
      <actor>Rupert Friend</actor>
      <actor>Asa Butterfield</actor>
      <actor>Jack Scalon</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 7, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>93</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>And yet the great conundrum of the Holocaust is that it was perpetrated by human beings, not monsters. Few movies have rendered this puzzle so powerfully.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1108/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even though it unfolds almost entirely through a child's eyes, and contains no onscreen violence, The Boy in the Striped Pajamas packs as devastating a punch as an adult-oriented drama about the subject. Its concluding five minutes are almost impossible to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/758896.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Boy in the Striped Pajamas is not only about Germany during the war, although the story it tells is heartbreaking in more than one way. It is about a value system that survives like a virus.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081105/REVIEWS/811059987</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Viewers should know that the film's resolution, though admirably restrained and unsentimental, is devastatingly sad. Parents should take this into account. This beautifully rendered family film is told in a classic and old-fashioned style, in the best sense, providing poignant and powerful teachable moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-11-06-boy-in-striped-pajamas_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film has any number of chances to exploit the setting and Butterfield's wide-eyed innocence, but instead, it mines a vast, eerie tension by keeping both boys in the dark.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_boy_in_the_striped_pajamas</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Turns out this is a thoughtful, well-acted film that manages to view this most inconceivable of travesties through the eyes of child without being childish itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/11/movie_review_making_friends_wi.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boyne's tale is starkly cautionary, and writer-director Herman handles a difficult topic with great sensitivity, drawing splendid performances from his young actors with David Thewlis and Vera Farmiga and the other grown-ups reliably efficient.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11672</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Opening half-hour has some of the best stuff in the movie, walking a precarious line between black irony and showing the war from a totally German viewpoint, without tipping over into gallows humor or parody.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938323.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=boy+in+the+striped+pajamas</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In adapting Irishman John Boyne's acclaimed young-adult novel, writer-director Mark Herman (Little Voice) draws beautifully modulated performances from his two child actors, who navigate a full range of emotions from wonder to betrayal to guilt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-11-05/film/the-boy-in-the-striped-pajamas/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In key ways, The Boy in the Striped Pajamas is like Guillermo del Toro's "Pan's Labyrinth": a child, caught in the waking nightmare of one of history's ugliest times, confronting the horrors of a grown-up world, and dealing with them as best he, or she, can.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20081107_Two_boys__one_always_in_striped_pajamas.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The power of this Holocaust tale sneaks up and floors you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15481268/review/24014316/the_boy_in_the_striped_pajamas</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Told from a different angle than any other Holocaust film I've seen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/11/06/DDHE13TQSJ.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because its gaze is so level and so unyielding, it stands as one of the better dramatic films made on this subject (although it's not nearly as fine as Louis Malle's "Au Revoir les Enfants."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12435</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result isn't meant to be an historical document transmuted into fiction; instead, it's fiction turned into a fable, a dark fable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081107.wboy07/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's two levels -- metaphoric and nitty-gritty -- don't mesh until the devastation of the closing sequence, which both indulges in and transcends melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-pajamas7-2008nov07,0,2239957.story</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Boy in the Striped Pajamas should be heartbreaking, but it isn't. The muted quality of its impact is the result of narrative shortcuts and a desire to keep the images from being too startling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1385</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herman's intentions are admirable, but his results are unsettling in the worst ways.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/386716_stripedpajamas07q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The bulk of the movie consists of scene after scene coyly setting up the same ironic juxtaposition, in the exact same way, about innocence vs. Nazism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11072008/entertainment/movies/peering_innocently_into_a_nazi_death_cam_137484.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film succeeds to the degree that it does -- partially, but honorably and sometimes affectingly -- because it was made as well as it was.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122601401498306659.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>True artists will risk sacrificing audience goodwill for truth and sentimentality for cold historical reality, but Herman doesn't want your respect; he just wants your tears.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A704551</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I found the movie impossibly basic and sanitized as a "never again" parable of the Final Solution - and simply wrongheaded as a story about children.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.boy21nov21,0,3069070.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although it's a far less objectionable Holocaust revision than, say, Roberto Benigni's "Life Is Beautiful," Herman's The Boy in the Striped Pajamas is yet another attempt to revisit a sorrowful event in history that should never be forgotten or used for entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/the-boy-in-the-striped-pajamas,1153047.html</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The faux-naive point of view probably worked better in the novel; the literalness of film renders certain of the story's conceits overly precious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=96526153</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herman fails to journey beyond the surface-level realities of his central perspective, which makes his film feel half-developed and poorly conceived, and drives it into sensationalism.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/boy-striped-pajamas/review/295835</url>
         <critic>Nathan Southern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching The Boy in the Striped Pajamas, it struck me that weaving a touching little tale about a death-camp friendship is actually a pretty bad way to teach kids about the Holocaust.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/11/07/boy/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An appalling, jaw-dropping movie that will cause serious nightmares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20237773,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>See the Holocaust trivialized, glossed over, kitsched up, commercially exploited and hijacked for a tragedy about a Nazi family. Better yet and in all sincerity: don't.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/11/07/movies/07paja.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This might have had some potential as a German exercise in self-examination, but as a tony BBC Films production, with the actors all speaking British-accented English (including Jersey girl Farmiga), it reeks of self-righteousness.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33688_BOY_IN_THE_STRIPED_PAJAMAS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$9,030,581</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$12,500,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$253,085</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>17</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>