<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Broken Embraces</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Pedro Almodóvar</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Pedro Almodóvar</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Spain</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Penelope Cruz</actor>
      <actor>Lluis Homar</actor>
      <actor>Blanca Portilla</actor>
      <actor>Rossy de Palma</actor>
      <actor>Kiti Manver</actor>
      <actor>Chus Lampreave</actor>
      <actor>Lola Duenas</actor>
      <actor>Angela Molina</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 20, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>127</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A voluptuary of a film, drunk on primary colors, caressing Penelope Cruz, using the devices of a Hitchcock to distract us with surfaces while the sinister uncoils beneath. As it ravished me, I longed for a freeze frame to allow me to savor a shot.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20091216/REVIEWS/912169993</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Many of the characters go by two different names. So best advice for optimum viewing is, see Broken Embraces...twice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20320744,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Broken Embraces welds Douglas Sirk melodrama to the most gracefully unsettling elements of Alfred Hitchcock, wrapping both in the stylish, hushed elegance that’s become Almodóvar’s trademark since his mid-’90s reinvention.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/broken-embraces,35587/</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Almodóvar and Cruz we have a real collaboration of artist and inspiration that only seems to improve and deepen over time.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/12/review_--_the_dynamic_duo_of_a.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This really is Cruz's movie: Almodóvar is her North Star -- following his lead, she's always found her surest and most graceful footing as an actress.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/11/18/broken_embraces/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie is utterly irresistible.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/62253/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Broken Embraces leaves the viewer in a contradictory state, a mixture of devastation and euphoria, amusement and dismay that deserves its own clinical designation. Call it Almodóvaria, a syndrome from which some of us are more than happy to suffer.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/11/20/movies/20broken.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cruz exudes a sensual aura of mystery that holds you spellbound. And Almodóvar, a true poet of cinema, creates images -- horrifying and healing -- that live inside your head like a waking dream. You want to miss a movie like that? I didn’t think so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/26274654/review/30842704/broken_embraces</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That still makes Broken Embraces superior to at least 99 percent of the movies released in 2009. Run, don't walk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/movies/broken_from_page_xGbVcdQYNvzVtI7H1aKYHM</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie putters near the end, but it's a film lover's delight.</snippet>
         <url>http://featuresblogs.chicagotribune.com/talking_pictures/</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gorgeous and seductive, if pitched at Almodóvar fans and perhaps a touch long. Those drawn by Cruz’s divadom will wonder why it takes so long to get to her -- though she is wholly dazzling when it does.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136507</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Almodóvar's love of movies informs every frame of this beautiful film.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The writer-director is up to his old tricks, creating an onion of an experience -- a movie within a movie within a movie, irony in each layer, poignancy that stings and whimsy that bites.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-broken11-2009dec11,0,5922525.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This melancholy romance is the first Almodovar feature I’ve ever really liked, an expertly fashioned melodrama that steers mercifully clear of his usual puckishness and star-mongering.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?oid=1020354</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At times, it looks as though Broken Embraces might be the love child of Douglas Sirk and Alfred Hitchcock, with its dramatic broad strokes, iconic reds, and teasing narrative clues.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A934988</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Broken Embraces is stylish and sly, an engaging exercise that gives us less than meets the eye.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/4239580B17608EC8862576A400036035?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amid all this dazzling artifice, the film's most authentic source of power comes from its star.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/broken-embraces-los-abrazos-rotos,1158783/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At 128 minutes – Almodovar's longest film to date – Broken Embraces is an easy film to bid farewell to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/broken-embraces/article1403919/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s both ridiculous and ridiculously romantic, which is an apt description of a work shaped like a heart and structured like a pretzel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/12/25/almodvars_embraces_has_plenty_of_heart/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A melodrama painted in the saffron-and-turmeric hues of a Bollywood musical, Broken Embraces is the Spanish filmmaker's homage to Hitchcock's "Vertigo," that moody account of obsessional love and double lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20091224_broken_embraces.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>During vast sections of Broken Embraces, I wished I was watching the actual old-time noirs instead of the miasmic concoction that Almodóvar has made from them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/The-Culture/Movies/2009/1212/Broken-Embraces-movie-review</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a film that pays tribute to vintage '50s Hollywood, Broken Embraces is a visual delight.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-11-20-broken20_ST_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a pretty minor film from the filmmaker. It feels like more of an exercise in plotting and movie nostalgia than a story about real people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-broken-embraces-1003974325.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A restless, rangy and frankly enjoyable genre-juggler that combines melodrama, comedy and more noir-hued darkness than ever before, the picture is held together by the extraordinary force of Almodovar’s cinematic personality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939885.html?u=IMDB&amp;p=H2BE&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Holland</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The final half-hour of Broken Embraces is littered with facile contrivances and plot turns worthy of a soap opera. It's almost mystifying, and more than a little frustrating, to watch a movie cruising at such a high level suddenly suffer a complete breakdown and lose too much altitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1970</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With this gorgeously melodramatic ode to cinema, the filmmaker comes dangerously close to losing himself inside his celluloid dreams -- and leaving the audience behind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1396983.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed, three decades into his career as a name-brand fashioner of zesty soapers, Spanish cinema's most beloved export could direct un film de Almodóvar with his eyes shut and still get a rise out of his fans. So who could blame the matador for letting the bull run the show this time?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-11-17/film/for-broken-embraces-almod-oacute-var-still-believes-in-almod-oacute-var-trade/</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching the new film is like getting upsettingly full on insubstantial tapas: You would never say no to just one more, but there’s better.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/80765/broken-embraces-film-review</url>
         <critic>Joshua Rothkopf</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The notable lack of chemistry between Cruz and Homar is a crucial absence in a film about all-consuming romance. And though each part is great fun to watch, the whole feels unfinished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/11/20/2009-11-20_short_movie_reviews_penelope_cruz_in_broken_embraces_planet_51_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seems a touch too long, too airless, and too content with its own contrivances to stir the heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/11/23/091123crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It all adds up to an entertaining combination of suspense and melodrama, a movie that doesn't cohere too well - and veers toward the silly in its more-obvious plot mechanics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/12/17/MVG81B58FE.DTL</url>
         <critic>Amy Biancolli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almodovar lets his movie become boring, and insufferably so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2010/01/almodovars_broken_embraces_nev.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$4,726,606</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$107,111</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>