<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Brothers</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Anders Thomas Jensen</author>
      <author>Susanne Bier</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Susanne Bier</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Denmark</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Connie Nielsen</actor>
      <actor>Ulrich Thomsen</actor>
      <actor>Nikolaj Lie Kaas</actor>
      <actor>Bent Mejding</actor>
      <actor>Solbjørg Højfeldt</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Juel Werner</actor>
      <actor>Rebecca Løgstrup</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 6, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A triumph of psychological drama, owing as much to Ms. Bier's sensitive style as to Anders Thomas Jensen's smart screenplay, based on Bier's own story idea.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0506/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brothers takes a scenario as old as Genesis – two jealous siblings spar over the affections of the same woman – and renders it fresh and immediate, by virtue of the warm, almost maternal, generosity director Susanne Bier shows her characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?article_id=2144</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Imaginative and immensely engrossing film.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/05/20/DDG1NCRBHN1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We do live in a fraught world of interconnections, Bier makes clear, and what happens far away matters, in unexpected ways, close to home.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1060091_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everyone involved -- actors, crew, director Susanne Bier and screenwriter Anders Thomas Jensen in their second collaboration -- are in peak form in this unflinching look at repressed feelings and emotional devastation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000911687</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A drama of uncommon moral complexity, unexpected humor, convincing transformations (for good and bad) and, best of all, vibrant, unpredictable energy. In a movie landscape littered with dead souls, here's a live one.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gripping from start to finish.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/7833729/site/newsweek/page/2/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The central performance in Brothers is by Connie Nielsen, who is strong, deep and true.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050519/REVIEWS/50510001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A powerful, brutal, funny, tragic, vibrant, very human movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050603/BROTHERS03/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The two male leads, bulwarks of the Danish film industry for more than a decade, play off each other like the veterans they are.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=312039&amp;reviewId=18772&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brothers is about how people change, how they can rise to an occasion, or sink to one. It's a tale of love and allegiance, of truth and the cruelties that men can bring to bear on one another.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=312039&amp;reviewId=18076</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>These three central performances, and a solid script by Anders Thomas Jensen and director Susanne Bier, ground a potentially overwrought story in genuine feeling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/111770639462262.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a quiet anti-war film full of lovely, heartbreakingly assured performances and real situations and responses.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/224999_siff20.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The end result was that the performances reached a remarkable level of intimacy and intensity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-brothers13may13,0,6805517.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filmed in the unadorned Dogme style and acted with a ferocious intensity.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/05/06/movies/06brot.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The second collaboration between helmer Susanne Bier and scriptwriter Anders Thomas Jensen once again shows what skilled artists can do with a story that might have ended up filled with cliches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117924690&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Gunnar Rehlin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A beautifully acted, graceful, and intelligent film that usefully dramatizes the gulf between Fortress Bush and the relativist politics of Western Europe.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's such a sense of overall intensity, you know you have been though something powerful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/02/AR2005060200804.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its core, Susanne Bier's wrenching portrayal of the shifting dynamics within a Danish family is really about survival, about how we cope in the face of shattering grief and what we'll do -- anything, really -- to save ourselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miami.com/mld/miamiherald/entertainment/movies/11850747.htm</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Piercingly co-written and directed by Susanne Bier, the movie dramatizes one man's collapse and the other's surprising maturation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7761</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Susanne Bier is helped by a well-chosen cast, especially the glowing Nielsen, a Danish-born actress best known for American films like "Gladiator."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/43478.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tapping into the basest fears of war while subverting all expectations, director Susanne Bier deftly reads between the headlines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/306850p-262494c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the film's strength lies in an ensemble effort, it's really Sarah and Jannik who provide the film with its most compelling characters, its momentum and, ultimately, its heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050519-movies-review-rke-brothers,0,2355115.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Robert K. Elder</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Danish director Susanne Bier elicits wonderfully intimate performances from her actors, and this 2004 drama has so many genuine, low-key encounters it manages to overcome a contrived and familiar plot.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/27573_BROTHERS_BIER_BRODRE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie so nice she made it twice, Susanne Bier's Dogme-certified feature "Open Hearts" gets a slight makeover in her follow-up Brothers, another raw melodrama about three lives recalibrated by sudden tragedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8456</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What sets Bier's film apart from similar fare are the consistently fine performances and powerful scenes of surprising ferocity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7000</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's interesting and well-performed, but it's no Cain and Abel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A273063</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sounds rather soapy and melodramatic, but director Susanne Bier, assisted by an able cast, ensures the traumas are painfully realistic and subtly observed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=11106</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brothers emerges as no less or more than Bier's claustrophobic compositions and unimaginative choices.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0518,tracking1,63623,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bier's portrayal of the brothers' interplay holds few surprises, and the exploitation of the war between East and West is vulgar, contrived and borderline racist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3393&amp;Sumbit.x=47&amp;Sumbit.y=16</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$384,982</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$8,161</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>