<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Bubble</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Coleman Hough</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Steven Soderbergh</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Debbie Doebereiner</actor>
      <actor>Dustin James Ashley</actor>
      <actor>Misty Dawn Wilkins</actor>
      <actor>Omar Cowan</actor>
      <actor>Laurie Lee</actor>
      <actor>David Hubbard</actor>
      <actor>Kyle Smith</actor>
      <actor>Decker Moody</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 27, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of the idiosyncratic ''little'' movies that Soderbergh has made to clear his head (Full Frontal, Schizopolis), this is the first that truly connects.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1152877_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everything about the film -- its casting, its filming, its release -- is daring and innovative.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060126/REVIEWS/60117006/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Soderbergh and screenwriter Coleman Hough aren't interested in creating a coy whodunit so much as evoking the deeper, less romantic mysteries of people -- and it's riveting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1116774&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bubble is a strong film with a gorgeously minimal script by Coleman Hough. Soderbergh has directed his actors to perfection, rendering them indistinguishable from their roles. And, though the story resorts to sensationalism for its conflict, the film is eloquent in its portrayal of silence, depression, repression, denial and the woes of the Midwestern white working class.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-01-26/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A potent and provocative look at life unhinged. Bubble is said to be the first in a series of six low-budget films from Soderbergh. If they all rock the boat like this one, bring 'em on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/8647433/rid/9176172/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Soderbergh does overemphasize the "little-people" dreariness of it all. But there is much low-key humor here, too, albeit on the dark side.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0127/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Easier to admire than love, Bubble is a fascinating exercise that seems calculated to repel most audiences, which probably suits Mr. Soderbergh just fine.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/movies/27bubb.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film doesn't judge or prod its characters, just watches the long fuse of the plot dwindle, then explode.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1149380,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Starting off as a low-key psychological drama, this suddenly turns into a murder mystery that's resolved awkwardly and ambiguously, but the fascination of the characters and milieu remains.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#29214</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's reassuring to see Steven Soderbergh return to riveting down-and-dirty filmmaking with Bubble.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/01/27/DDG96GT2ER1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film manages to be an intriguing, grimly entertaining, strangely haunting little slice of heartland noir very much in the experimental tradition of such previous Soderbergh oddities as "Schizopolis" and "Full Frontal."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/257166_limited27.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bubble is a haunting film, made all the more intriguing by the use of ordinary people, not actors, in all the roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-01-26-bubble_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simply too odd and unconventional to ever appeal to a broad audience, either at the multiplex or on home video.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=528236&amp;reviewId=20010</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In movies this deliberately paced, the line between fascination and boredom is a fine one, easily crossed. Fortunately, Bubble stays on the right side of that line.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/b/bubble.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An odd little movie and a good one, worthy for what it is and potentially groundbreaking for how it's being made available.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060127-movies-review-bubble,0,7509282.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its refreshingly straightforward style and compelling performers, the movie feels encased in an invisible, filmy membrane of its own. Soderbergh keeps his characters on one side of the wall and his audience on the other. As to which is living in the real world, I guess that's open to discussion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-bubble27jan27,0,485253.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strange and off-putting, and hard-nosed types in the film business will no doubt dismiss it as a nothing. But, even if Bubble hasn't brought down the Bastille, the movie is far from nothing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060213crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's almost condescending, as though Soderbergh were challenging himself to make Middle America interesting. And yet the movie IS interesting, almost in spite of itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/44719</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bubble is a stunt in search of a movie, and it almost finds one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8468</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, Bubble is less important as a film than as an experiment in simultaneous cross-platform film distribution.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46677</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the more interesting low-budget experiments Steven Soderbergh has indulged in between flashy Hollywood entertainments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/62335.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bubble is the moviemaking equivalent of the worst narrative journalism. Every bit of "human interest" is so painstakingly planted, so determined to be applauded for its observation and sensitivity, it ends up seeming as slick and bogus as the worst Hollywood blockbuster.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.bubble27jan27,1,4852242.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Worth seeing, even if you're as ambivalent about it as I am. Its strength is in the way the drama creeps up on you.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/15702/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The experience is interesting, in a flattened way.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Likeable if unexciting little tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928057?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story is so flat and transparent in the telling, so empty of psychological mystery and depth, it skates dangerously close to condescension.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12509&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The three stars are all perfectly naturalistic, but their roles are too bloodless and their patter too dry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0604,atkinson,71903,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'd rate Bubble at no better than a C-plus for artistic achievement and a D-minus for audience appeal. In one sense, it accomplishes its goals efficiently by making you feel, in less than 80 minutes, as if you've gotten permanently trapped in the dead-end, trailer-park lives of its working-class characters. I've never been so grateful to get out of a theater, turn my cellphone back on and plug myself into a $4 Starbucks latte.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/01/26/btm/index4.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Likely to be remembered more for its method of manufacture and release than for any inherent qualities of its own. It will also become one of the many fascinating footnotes in the always provocative career of Steven Soderbergh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A327997</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bubble is among his (Soderbergh) worst films. What in the world was he thinking with this?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8002</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An embarrassment to all concerned, the film was written, directed and produced by Soderbergh for reasons that are not readily apparent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001054604</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So brutal a negation of the popcorn aesthetic is liable to be mistaken for artistic courage. A grindingly slow pace, a quarter-baked plot, a semidocumentary focus on the lives of the working poor: It's enough to make you whimper "Matt Damon" in defeat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2134933/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>Stephen Metcalf</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$145,382</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$1,600,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$70,664</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>32</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>steven soderbergh</oscar_winning_director>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>