<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Bucket List, The</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Justin Zackham</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rob Reiner</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jack Nicholson</actor>
      <actor>Morgan Freeman</actor>
      <actor>Sean Hayes</actor>
      <actor>Rob Morrow</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 25, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>97</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Actors tell us that dying is easy, comedy is hard. But comedies about dying are hardest of all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12252007/entertainment/movies/two_good_men_381861.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's sincerity helps it get over some of the most difficult hurdles and the feeling after leaving theater is one of having experienced something worthwhile albeit unremarkable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/b/bucket_list.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The leads, who were born six weeks apart in 1937, have remarkable hare-and-tortoise chemistry.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=1005032&amp;reviewId=22836&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are certainly worse ways to spend the holiday season than in the company of two charming old actors, being reminded that human companionship makes life worth living, even as it makes dying a little tougher.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_bucket_list</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite some emotional dips and a see-it-to-believe-it load of schmaltz at the end, The Bucket List is mostly a joy ride with good company, and the actors obviously were having a high time on their traveling boondoggle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/25/2007-12-25_jack_nicholson_morgan_freeman_connect_in.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script is weak and obvious and the direction disappointingly unimaginative. But stars are stars, and the old boys are terrific - enough to make this a funny and sometimes moving buddy picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135410</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A feel-good film about death, a sitcom about mortality, "Ikiru" for meatheads. It's also a picture about two cancer patients confronting reality, and deciding how they want to spend their presumed last days, that has not an ounce of reality about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935622.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Turns out The Bucket List is a meta-film, mostly about how these two legendary actors interact and what it means to be an actor in your own life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0751,wallace,78653,20.html</url>
         <critic>Julia Wallace</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has its moments, and some are undeniably affecting. But even those seem artificial, relying far too much on our familiarity with and fondness for the film's stars.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.bucket11jan11,0,664940.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Emotionally false.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/11/DDMLUAMLV.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Freeman and Nicholson make the most of Justin Zackham's script, but there just isn't enough substance behind their characters to prop up the carpe diem platitudes. The result is a semi-comedic, geriatric "Brokeback Mountain" minus the sex and with a Himalayan summit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-bucket25dec25,0,6936552.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Freeman and Nicholson mostly stand in front of special-effects green screens and have the locales projected, like they're in a "Road" picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/119993190518390.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In The Bucket List, Nicholson is human-ish. And Freeman is so human.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10804</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Feels every bit as cheap and flimsy as Edward's hospital.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/373713.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nothing wrong about a movie that says, Stop and smell the roses. Now, if only director Rob Reiner hadn't rubbed our noses in a bouquet of plastic blooms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080111_Just_going_through_the_emotions.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Rob Reiner is betting that their star power alone will blind us to the holes in this cheesecloth of a script. It proves a fool's bet – no star shines that brightly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071223.bucket24gta/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You'd think the team of Rob Reiner, Jack Nicholson and Morgan Freeman might have had the right stuff. Alas, their labored efforts fail to lift The Bucket List out of its flatlining state.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=3DfgHfzCvSwJGqYtBvn4WzfWQqJc6b8Y1L71YQkJkh269JDv9x8h!1606043844&amp;&amp;rid=10328</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fails its stars in fundamental ways. Mr. Nicholson has played wealthy rogues before (most recently in “Something’s Gotta Give”), but this particular bon vivant is unsalvageably repellent.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/25/movies/25buck.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Bucket List will quickly be kicked into oblivion, but, at a lifetime-achievement-award ceremony, Nicholson’s tempest will fit nicely into a montage of Crazy Jack moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/01/07/080107crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie exists wholly in the realm of metaphor, whose messages stick out like placards: Find joy through pain. Reunite with estranged loved ones. Keep hope alive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1698307,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first thing to say about The Bucket List is that Rob Reiner is the rare director who can take all the wonder out of one of the seven wonders of the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20170203,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A manipulative look at dying with dignity and a lame yarn about as realistic as the fantasy in “The Princess Bride.”</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-bucket/281639/content</url>
         <critic>Sid Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The entire undertaking feels like a waste of time and talent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-23-bucket-list_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Bucket List is a movie for oldsters that, paradoxically, looks as if it was made for 15-year-olds. If this is what is meant in Hollywood as "thinking outside the box," then it's time to get a new box.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0111/p12s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>White-bread storytelling made by, for, and about people who think joy and meaning can be acquired by simply taking a step or two out of life’s comfort zones and into African-safari packages and skydiving excursions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A578846</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Edward and Carter are like the original Odd Couple, except nobody’s laughing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10471</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The overall sense, however, is of a movie coasting on an obvious and somewhat flimsy premise, to which no one thought to bring much else besides Nicholson and Freeman.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141755&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Rob Reiner’s atrocious cancer “comedy” marks a new low in Hollywood’s self-flagellating “things to be thankful for” tradition.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/movie-reviews-the-bucket-list-persepolis-the-great-debaters/17936/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This terminally ill, terminally awful dramedy marks a sad cinematic milestone: The Bucket List is the first film in history to feature a truly wretched Nicholson performance -- and we're not talking about the character he plays.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4338/the-bucket-list.html</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie about two old codgers who are nothing like people, both suffering from cancer that is nothing like cancer, and setting off on adventures that are nothing like possible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080110/REVIEWS/801100301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rob Reiner's feel-good tear-jerker, in which dying well is the best revenge, wants to be heartwarming. But first-timer Justin Zackham's screenplay is so stridently formulaic and disingenuous that the film falls flat at every inspirational turn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/bucket-list/review/291165</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most insipidly innocuous film ever made about facing mortality and living it up before passing away, The Bucket List has as much poetry and poise as its clumsy, clunky title.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/346871_bucket11q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any moron can make a bad movie. But it takes a special breed of schemer to make a picture as shameless as The Bucket List.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/12/25/bucket_list/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I don't know if Rob Reiner is the one to blame for this atrocity, but he directed and coproduced.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32578_BUCKET_LIST.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$93,466,502</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$631,725</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>16</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jack nicholson</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>2</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>morgan freeman</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>jack nicholson</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>true</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>