<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Cache (Hidden)</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Haneke</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Haneke</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>FranceAustriaGermanyItaly</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Daniel Auteuil</actor>
      <actor>Juliette Binoche</actor>
      <actor>Maurice Bénichou</actor>
      <actor>Annie Girardot</actor>
      <actor>Lester Makedonsky</actor>
      <actor>Bernard Le Coq</actor>
      <actor>Walid Afkir</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Duval</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 23, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This brilliantly disturbing movie is constructed with surgical precision. Haneke lets no one off the hook least of all the viewer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/10416135/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We the viewers are its beneficiaries, watching and waiting for something awful to happen. Here it does, first subtly, then spectacularly. The twist is not revealed until the last shot--if you keep your avid eyes open.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1139824-2,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The picture moves with stealth, enjoying its own thriller-ness as hints are laid and mislaid. There's a sense that Hitchcock is hovering in the background and cheering for Auteuil, who musters all his French superstardom to play a man having his mask of blandness torn off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1140767_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A perplexing and disturbing film of great effect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060112/REVIEWS/51220007/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this movie, Auteuil ("Jean de Florette") and Binoche ("Chocolat") are such marvelous actors, they can shift us in almost any emotional direction with a speech or a glance.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060113-movies-review-cache,0,2296240.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maurice Bénichou does the most heartbreaking work in the movie, playing a friend of Georges's. It's a character and a performance I'll have a tough time getting out of my dreams.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8349</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Hitchcock, only creepier, Haneke slowly cranks up the suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=528238&amp;reviewId=19996</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most vital and strangely gripping films in recent years, a thriller more opaque, involving and realistic than just about anything that Hollywood is capable of.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1138677951136310.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Laurent's crime is really the crime of being European and conquering people of color. That understood, Cache is brilliant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1114471&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Haneke echoes the theme of Hitchcock's "Rear Window": Moviemaking is basically an act of voyeurism. We secretly examine people's lives in every movie. But in this one, there is a hidden camera, a movie within the movie as it were, forcing us to observe a character along side a mysterious stranger.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000922119</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Binoche and Auteuil are both quietly sensational in their fracturing personae, but the film is Haneke's premier postmodern assault--less visceral, perhaps, than "Code Unknown" and the criminally underappreciated "Time of the Wolf," but more thoughtful and, in the end, deeper in the afterplay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0551,atkinson,71157,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A psychological suspense drama of the utmost rigor and originality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-cache23dec23,0,5899130.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caché seems at first glance like a straightforward thriller - about a talk-show host being stalked by a technologically savvy blackmailer. But it's really a sly, subversive commentary on conscience, race, class and inequity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/377280p-320283c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deliciously elusive mystery.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/58768.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caché is unsettling and tense, even shocking. And its story of enduring tensions between an Algerian immigrant and a well-off French family is particularly timely.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-12-22-cache-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Casts a spell that grips you and won't let go. The film works as a provocation, on a personal and a political level.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/7539498/rid/9118182/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Haneke peels back the layers of Georges Laurent as slowly and dispassionately as a scientist dissecting a diseased mouse. The ending arrives with the power and inevitability of Greek drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=528238&amp;reviewId=20291&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Haneke is best known for "The Piano Teacher." His latest, Caché (or Hidden) is a quieter but equally provocative attack. It's less in your face, more in your head and under your skin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20060127/CACHE27/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extraordinarily taunt and suspenseful psychological thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/257168_cache27q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the most Hitchcockian of Haneke's films. A seemingly well-adjusted man in a well ordered universe is brought to the brink.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0113/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether viewed as a political allegory or a domestic drama, this is the most accessible film yet from one of Europe’s very finest filmmakers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=132303</url>
         <critic>David Parkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A tightly constructed drama that will keep you on the edge of your seat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/12/22/btm/index.html?sid=1420262</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This brilliant if unpleasant puzzle without a solution about surveillance and various kinds of denial finds writer-director Michael Haneke near the top of his game, though it's not a game everyone will want to play.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/28776_CACHE</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On a deeper level, Haneke tries to reach for political allegory on the French-Algerian War, but the film functions best as a perfectly calibrated thriller, perhaps his most accessible to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/40722</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A tightly plotted and paced thriller whose not-so-hidden agenda is to expose the bad conscience of the world's haves toward its have-nots, "Hidden" is one of Austrian helmer Michael Haneke's most watchable and pungent works.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927103?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The eerily timely subject of Haneke's film is France's unwilling encounter with the disenfranchised minorities it has tried to sweep under the rug. As one who giggled through his widely admired, irredeemably silly "The Piano Teacher," I wasn't prepared to be easily won over by Caché, but it turns out to be his most human and affecting movie to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/06/04/holiday-taylor.php</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To some degree, “Hidden” is a cat-and-mouse thriller, the only problem being that mouse and cat insist on swapping roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?051226crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While this film can seem politically simplistic, it is nonetheless psychologically astute, and more complicated than it at first appears.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/12/23/movies/23cach.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Demanding, quietly breathtaking film.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's compelling about Caché is not the answer to the whodunit but Haneke's exacting invocation of palpable tension.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A338807</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What really makes Hidden so involving is Haneke's sometimes maddening insistence on keeping things vague.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=528238&amp;reviewId=20061</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone looking for the comfort in a tense thriller ending in a satisfying restoration of order and psychological security will be bitterly disappointed, but Haneke isn't in the business of encouraging comforting illusions.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46616</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It isn't your typical scary movie--there are no "boo!" moments--but it may gradually creep you out and perhaps even more after you've seen it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-01-26/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As with much art of our time--music, painting, sculpture, theater--Caché in a certain way affronts us. Its deliberate contravention of our expectations, and not necessarily stodgy expectations, is part of its intent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060206&amp;s=kauffmann020606</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Caché offers food for thought, the last third is muddled.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/c/cache.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cache is the feel-guilty movie of the new millennium.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.cache17feb17,0,3507053.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the important things, in all the ways that really count, Caché is a handsome fraud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/01/27/DDG96GT2ET1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,647,381</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$8,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$57,010</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>