<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Cadillac Records</name>
   <company>TriStar Pictures (Sony)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Darnell Martin</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Darnell Martin</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Adrien Brody</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Wright</actor>
      <actor>Beyonce Knowles</actor>
      <actor>Gabrielle Union</actor>
      <actor>Columbus Short</actor>
      <actor>Cedric the Entertainer</actor>
      <actor>Emmanuelle Chriqui</actor>
      <actor>Eamonn Walker</actor>
      <actor>Mos Def</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 5, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ensemble is stupendous--howlingly great--and the music goes deep.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/52586/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie is crowded and sprawling, and if it rambles sometimes, that's just fine. Like those big, boxy Caddies (and like Howlin’ Wolf, if he did say so himself), it's built for comfort, not for speed. It hums, it purrs and it roars.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/12/05/movies/05cadi.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's biopic aspect is multiplied by the sheer number of players who made Chess the first family of Chicago blues, R&amp;B and rock 'n' roll...That all of them were later inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame attests to their enormous influence on popular music and culture.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/390614_cadillac05q.html</url>
         <critic>Gene Stout</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an enjoyable ramble, with a feel for what made the early days of rock as wild as any that followed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20243936,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film suffers at times from biopic-itis – the narrative unfolds with the requisite heartbreak carefully apportioned – but it's always eye-catching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1206/p25s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the strengths of Cadillac Records, written and directed by Darnell Martin, is that it's a movie about music by someone who genuinely seems to enjoy listening to music.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2206030/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Such an exhilarating, spirited piece of work that its embellishments and omissions cease to matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/12/05/cadillac_records/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In watching this film, it's best not to worry much about the film's fidelity to history but rather simply lean back and enjoy one great jam session on film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=gDY5J0PNnj2Qv3Rvh3y28y1rzb6P1G9cZmpGNd54vhD1PLFJ1JKP!1446314594&amp;&amp;rid=11988</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cadillac Records is an account of the Chess story that depends more on music than history, which is perhaps as it should be. The film is a fascinating record of the evolution of a black musical style, and the tangled motives of the white men who had an instinct for it.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081203/REVIEWS/812039993</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mos Def makes a terrific Berry, all flash and confidence, and Wright offers a memorably soulful take on Waters, whether he's strutting, singing, suffering or all three. Walker's Howlin' Wolf is a deep-throated, pride-filled bear of a man who dominates the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-cadillac-records-1205_dec05,0,3020654.story</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A satisfying combination of great songs and strong dramatic performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/12/04/DDGB14GFCC.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's most memorable performance is by Eamonn Walker, who is scarily good as the singer known as Howlin' Wolf.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12052008/entertainment/movies/cant_lose_with_these_blues_142665.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has buoyancy to spare. It's filled with bumps and scratches. But in the manner of a nicked old LP, its gnarly surface and warps-and-all sound evokes real life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.cadillac05dec05,0,5611167.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone who likes pop music or wonders how bands like the Rolling Stones got rolling will enjoy the ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090219.wcadillac0220/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The electrifying music helps camouflage the screenplay's hyperbole.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33921_CADILLAC_RECORDS.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cadillac Records may be a mess dramatically, but it's a wonderful mess, and not just because of the great music. The people who made it must have harbored the notion, almost subversive in a season of so many depressing films, that going out to the movies should be fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122842792010280755.html?mod=article-outset-box</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cadillac Records bobs and weaves, strides and duckwalks, samples and smiles on the sounds that made urban Chicago such a blues melting pot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A708744</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a hell of a story, and Cadillac Records wants to tell it so badly that it threatens to warp the narrative out of recognition.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12597</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brody plays Chess as a slightly crooked but well-meaning musical cheerleader without fully emerging as a character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20081205_Music_drives__Cadillac_Records_.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film features too little about Berry (an engaging Mos Def), who crosses over to great fame.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-12-04-cadillac-records_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are plenty of small pleasures to be found throughout Darnell Martin's feature, but a compelling storyline featuring three-dimensional characters is not among them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1412</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Darnell Martin (I Like it Like That) races through the script's bullet points with a brisk superficiality that leaves crucial plot points underdeveloped and unresolved, and refuses to engage the dark side of Leonard Chess’ paternalism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/2008-12-04/film-tv/web-hed-required/</url>
         <critic>Ernest Hardy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most of the details are right-on in Cadillac Records, though the director's efforts to sell it sometimes steers the film into mawkish or hokey territory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939110.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are certain films - let's call them Road Map Movies - that drive you directly from point A to point B to point C, with barely a stop for gas. Cadillac Records is such a film: You see all the major landmarks, but how enlightening can a road trip be if you never even get off the highway?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/12/05/2008-12-05_cadillac_records_takes_a_greatesthits_ap.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beyoncé proves her Dreamgirls turn was no fluke in this so-so Blues melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135903</url>
         <critic>William Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all a blur, except for the music. That's workin'.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/23318547/review/24762047/cadillac_records</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a rousing, fast-paced tale, told with a modicum of verve and packed with colorfully flawed, occasionally heroic and even tragic characters. It also feels disappointingly bloated and too fast-paced by half.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/cadillac-records,1154623.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Martin attempts to present the whole oversized Chess story, but instead winds up reducing the lives and art that give it shape.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/cadillac_records</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We never get a real sense of what made these recordings so different or revolutionary. Part of the problem is that re-recorded versions of songs by the actors were used in the film, with vastly mixed results that never match the ferocity and excitement of the original tracks.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/cadillac-records/review/296049</url>
         <critic>Matt Collar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With everything so wrong, how can there be anything right about Cadillac Records?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-12-03/film/cadillac-records-turns-the-label-s-history-into-another-downer-soap-opera/</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$8,138,000</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$12,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,445,559</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>687</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>adrien brody</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>