<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Candy</name>
   <company>ThinkFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Neil Armfield</author>
      <author>Luke Davies</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Neil Armfield</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Australia</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Abbie Cornish</actor>
      <actor>Heath Ledger</actor>
      <actor>Geoffrey Rush</actor>
      <actor>Tony Martin</actor>
      <actor>Tom Budge</actor>
      <actor>Noni Hazlehurst</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 17, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>108</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neil Armfield's film hits hard because it sensitively shows how life on drugs can never be about anything else, and how the real horror of addiction is not what users do to themselves, but what they do to each other out of loneliness and despair.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=283660&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Told in a serenely observational fashion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9147</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite being well made and supremely acted, Candy is a true feel-bad experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/candy.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its depiction of a descent into drug addiction, Candy is filled with surprisingly sweet moments and goes down more easily than seems possible given the subject matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/12/15/DDGNRMVNUM1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its intelligence, compassion, human terror and sheer loveliness, Candy is a winner despite the well-worn path it treads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/11/16/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Doesn’t add anything substantively new, though it has been nicely directed by Neil Armfield, known in his country for his theater work, and features striking performances from Heath Ledger and Geoffrey Rush.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/11/17/movies/17cand.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a druggie movie, Candy is surprisingly dynamic and involving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-candy1dec01,0,402667.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it's a well-worn story, Candy does touch on a universal anxiety. For two people basking in the heat of an all-consuming love, what happens when the power gets cut off?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/55382</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because although there are some very striking moments in Neil Armfield's debut, there are simply not enough to keep us absorbed the way a movie should.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/11-17-2006/entertainment/col/story/472157p-397223c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The way director and co-adapter Armfield shoots it, the film's awfully pretty in its grimness, in the way "Leaving Las Vegas" managed to make train-wreck alcoholism more fake-lyrical than grungy.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061201-movies-review-candy,0,4131274.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cornish provides a counterbalance for Ledger's authoritative presence, turning what could have been just another heroin movie into a flawed but engrossing parable on love and sacrifice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1105445&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the characters' lives fall apart, Ledger fails to bring the necessary gravitas to the role, and he looks a bit too healthy throughout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=275</url>
         <critic>Richard James Havis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Life, love and addiction make a mostly bitter, but occasionally sweet, concoction in Oz drama Candy, which is sometimes hard to swallow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;head=berlin&amp;nav=RBerlin&amp;articleid=VE1117929639&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Russell Edwards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ledger mumbles his entire performance (some of it barely legible) as a fuzzy, friendly, happily passive heroin addict and sometime poet, as if he's too blissed out to even open his mouth as he simply drifts along with his addiction.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/295123_candy08q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What we see, though, is the same old same old - beautiful faces turning gaunt and haunted, strung-out hero and heroine, stupid parents, de-tox worse than tox, descent to and return from the depths. Candy could be seen, I suppose, as a cautionary tale; take this as a cautionary review.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There has to be a good reason to put yourself through yet another junkie odyssey and Candy flunks the test.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1201/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ledger turns in another stellar performance and Cornish is heartbreakingly good also in this well-crafted film. But once that first plunger is pushed, the surprises are few.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3273/candy.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Warren</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Geoffrey Rush is fine as a gay drug dealer who serves as an enabling Santa Claus to the doomed couple. But in the end, Candy is a little too sweet and not quite harmful enough to the audience's health.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2153941</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any drug movie's effectiveness can be measured by the strength of its detox, and Candy doesn't sweeten the cold turkey. Still, it's a downward spiral from there in more ways than one. Never mind the neo-psychedelic-pop soundtrack and occasional double-vision cinematography: Dope just can't account for the film's fried brain cells.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0646,nelson,75049,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A wildly romanticized Australian druggie drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1559786_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the movie's feet get stuck in its own misery, it made me appreciate "Trainspotting" all over again - its wit, how it moved, the way any outcome for its characters seemed possible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11172006/entertainment/movies/drug_story_all_needles_but_no_pins_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A story that's reminiscent of the seminal "Panic in Needle Park."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/30511_CANDY</url>
         <critic>Meredith Brody</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Decent performances aside, the only interesting bits involve Geoffrey Rush as a chemistry professor who enables their self-abuse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1166662531195380.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's neither utterly real nor utterly romantic (heroin, like alcohol, manages to be awfully and unremittingly both).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A428779</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$45,128</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$3,646</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>geoffrey rush</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>