<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Cars</name>
   <company>Buena Vista Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Animation</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dan Fogelman</author>
      <author>John Lasseter</author>
      <author>Dan Gerson</author>
      <author>Jorgen Klubien, Philip Loren, Kiel Murray and Joe Ranft</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>John Lasseter</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Owen Wilson</actor>
      <actor>Bonnie Hunt</actor>
      <actor>Paul Newman</actor>
      <actor>Larry The Cable Guy</actor>
      <actor>Cheech Marin</actor>
      <actor>George Carlin</actor>
      <actor>Richard Petty</actor>
      <actor>Michael Keaton</actor>
      <actor>Tony Shalhoub</actor>
      <actor>John Ratzenberger</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 9, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>G</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first great movie of the summer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1194022,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether the movie will make you believe a shocking-orange stock car has a future with a lavender Carrera, it's more fun to follow than a televised freeway chase.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/424977p-358436c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All told, Cars is a knockout.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/273246_cars09q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lasseter's inclusive, utterly distinctive sensibility makes Cars all that it can be. His embrace of the comic-dramatic friction between innovation and tradition infiltrates every aspect of the movie - the look, the characters, the story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.cars09jun09,0,789064.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A work of American art as classic as it is modern. Note to tourists: Leave before the very end of the credits and you'll miss some of the best and funniest roadside sights.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1201791_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's surprising about this supremely engaging film is the source of its curb appeal: It has heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-cars9jun09,0,1373698.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who's this movie for, again? No matter: It's impossible to find more joy in the dark at the moment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2143311/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>Michael Agger</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Cars teaches is how to blend brash comedy with technical astonishments so that each enhances the other. I can't imagine who wouldn't want to test-drive this one. Like the promos say, "It's got that new-movie smell."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6149674/rid/10025028/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the most basic level, Cars is an old-fashioned fable about an egotistical, talented loner who learns humility and redeems himself by helping unfortunates.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=618328&amp;reviewId=20943&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the film lacks in freshness, it makes up for in great characters, fun vocal performances, and a script with some genuine emotional heft.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2877</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the one movie so far this summer that demands to be seen on the big screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46895&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cars leaves the animated competition in the dust, even if it is a tad slower and more predictable than Pixar at full throttle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/69857.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cars is a fine example of the formula, with pleasant chemistry, the patented Pixar cleverness, and the usual sweetly melancholy nostalgia courtesy of songwriter Randy Newman.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/49268</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's so much to impress and delight you that the time flies by.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1149553509162570.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Exciting though the car-racing scenes are, with their millions of fan-cars swaying fluidly around the stadium, it's the drives through the canyons and passes, and the quiet old ruin of a town (which recalls the abandoned mall in Miyazaki’s "Spirited Away"), that truly quicken the pulse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/zoom-zoom/13721/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As eye-popping as anything Pixar has done. But Cars inspires more admiration than elation. It dazzles even as it disappoints. This time around, John Lasseter and his codirector, the late Joe Ranft, seem more interested in dispensing Life Lessons than showing us a roaring good time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/13121950/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It might not be way up there in "The Incredibles"/"Finding Nemo"/"Toy Story" stratosphere, but the charming Cars is nevertheless a thoroughly pleasant way to mark Pixar Animation Studios' 20th anniversary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002613444</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Pixar people have an extreme talent for conjuring imagery that is both soaring in its majesty but also resonant -- it's a stylization but acute enough to carry emotional meaning.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1093735&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By relying too much on snappy dialogue and by adhering to the philosophy that "steel should feel like steel and glass should feel like glass," the filmmakers have bridled their imaginations and created a movie about toys that are too blubbery and not rubbery enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0609/p12s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, if the film is not as funny as its predecessors, that's probably part and parcel of why it doesn't seem as enchanting. Emotionally, despite the character arc, Cars doesn't resonate in the same way "The Incredibles" or "Toy Story" did.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/c/cars.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wouldn't have thought that even in animation a 1951 Hudson Hornet could look simultaneously like itself and like Paul Newman, but you will witness that feat, and others, in Cars.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060608/REVIEWS/60606002/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cars is a classic American tale firing on all cylinders and fueled by organic emotion and a lively sense of adventure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-06-08-cars-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie wins you over through crack comic timing and an awareness that the point of driving isn't how fast you get there but what you see on the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2006/06/09/revved_up/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Periodic bursts of cleverness brighten the festivities, but they're too few and far between, and the trademark humor that appeals to adults and kids often misfires.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930716?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Cars is something of a letdown, that is not because of the moral messages that it delivers but because of the heavy hand with which it cranks them out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060619crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never really quite great, it's still a good enough diversion for the family and should please adult fans of racing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A372691</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever you do, don't leave before watching the snippets that run during the closing credits--the self-referential, tongue in cheek "outtakes" are quite possibly the funniest part of this movie--a visual stunner that seems to have misplaced its heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060609-movies-review-cars,0,997014.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cars is certainly watchable, and there's always some amusing bit of business happening at the edges of the frame.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=618328&amp;reviewId=20950</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Warning: Cars comes unequipped with two essential options -- charm and a good muffler.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060609.CARS09/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This one is dully conventional even by family-uplift standards. The details are sweated, all right: It's a triumph of perspiration over inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/17247/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Judged against previous form, this is not Pixar firing on all cylinders, lacking the sophisticated comedy we've come to expect. Judged against fare from other studios, however, it's a triumph.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=9827</url>
         <critic>Olly Richards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At 116 minutes, it's a test not of speed but endurance.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29910_CARS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cars is an elaborate concoction all right. But it feels soldered together from a scrap heap of tired ideas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/06/09/cars/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ultimately redeems Cars from turning out a total lemon is its soul. Lasseter loves these animated inanimate objects as though they were kin, and it shows in every beautifully rendered frame.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0623,wilonsky,73448,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It doesn't make Cars a bad picture -- the visual inventions are worth the price of admission -- but it constitutes conduct unbecoming to a maker of magic.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>And did I mention that it's long? It's long.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=618328&amp;reviewId=20956</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Curiously and unexpectedly, the movie brings on a suffocating feeling of constraint. It's a consequence of seeing characters with such terribly limited mobility.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/09/DDGEAJ9FD91.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both in its ingratiating vibe and bland execution, Cars is nothing if not totally, disappointingly new-age Disney.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/06/09/movies/09cars.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Cars is indicative of the kind of movie we can expect from Pixar post-Disney merger, well, there's always Miyazaki.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9053</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$244,082,982</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$70,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$60,119,509</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,985</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>paul newman</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>owen wilson</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>