<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Casino Royale</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Neal Purvis</author>
      <author>Robert Wade</author>
      <author>Paul Haggis</author>
      <author>Ian Fleming</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Martin Campbell</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUKCzechRepublic</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Daniel Craig</actor>
      <actor>Eva Green</actor>
      <actor>Mads Mikkelsen</actor>
      <actor>Judi Dench</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Wright</actor>
      <actor>Giancarlo Giannini</actor>
      <actor>Caterina Murino</actor>
      <actor>Simon Abkarian</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 17, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>144</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Relaunches the series by doing something I wouldn't have thought possible: It turns Bond into a human being again -- a gruffly charming yet volatile chap who may be the swank king stud of the Western world, but who still has room for rage, fear, vulnerability, love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1559753_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Casino Royale is fresh, actually fresh.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/11/16/DDGEQMDOHU7.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie is NEW  from the get-go. It could be your first Bond. In fact, it was the first Bond; it was Ian Fleming's first 007 novel, and he was still discovering who the character was.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070816/REVIEWS/708160301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flat-out one of the best Bonds ever.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/292430_casino16q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script updates Ian Fleming's first Bond novel to a post-9/11 world and scales back the silliness that always seems to creep into the series; director Martin Campbell (The Mask of Zorro) contributes some superior action set pieces but keeps the camp and gadgetry to a minimum.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30720_CASINO_ROYALE_CAMPBELL.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's appealing about Bond is precisely its unhip classicism -- its promise of clean, crisp excitement delivered without the interference of whiplash-inducing camera pyrotechnics, attention-deficient editing patterns, gratuitous color tinting and/or ear-splitting rock ballads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/betting-on-bond/15025/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig, excellent in both art house endeavors (The Mother, Enduring Love) and blockbuster think pieces (Munich), has both a nasty streak and a soft side never before seen in the series; Fleming would recognize him as most like his literary creation: damaged goods in a tailored tux.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0646,wilonsky,75033,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Bond as we've never seen him, more naked, alive and mysterious than ever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/11/17/casino/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Casino Royale is quite possibly the best action movie of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9435</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is no longer the James Bond we know from the '60s, '70s, '80s, and '90s. Welcome to the new world of MI6's most storied agent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/casino_royale2006.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fans of anyone other than Sean Connery who has played James Bond may want to look away, because admirers of Ian Fleming's 007 novels are almost bound to agree that Daniel Craig is the best Bond since Sean.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/471897p-397074c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig gives us James Bond in the fascinating act of inventing himself. This you do not want to miss.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/7349978/review/12450444/casino_royale</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eleven years ago director Campbell made "GoldenEye," the first of the Brosnan Bond pictures. Casino Royale trumps it every which way.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061117-movies-review-casino,0,230202.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig makes you aware of something that the Bond series, in its pursuit of steamy sex and cartoon action, quickly lost sight of: 007 is a killer. That's what he's licensed to do.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1117/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The latest James Bond vehicle -- call him Bond, Bond 6.0 -- finds the British spy leaner, meaner and a whole lot darker.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/11/17/movies/17roya.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Turns out to be cracking good entertainment, as well as a fresh start for the perdurable 21-picture franchise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1092406&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Daniel Craig isn't merely acceptable, but formidable. His Bond is at least the equal of the best ones before him, and beats all of them in sheer intensity.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Martin Campbell (who also directed Pierce Brosnan's first outing as Bond in "Goldeneye"), has chosen to give us a Bond who's both metaphorically and literally stripped bare. Let me take this opportunity to thank him for both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2153940</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Contrary to pre-release nay-sayers, Daniel Craig has done more with James Bond in one film than some previous stars have in multiple reprises. This is terrific stuff, again positioning 007 as the action franchise to beat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=10199</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a relief to escape the series' increasing bondage to high-tech gimmicks in favor of intrigue and suspense featuring richly nuanced characters and women who think the body's sexiest organ is the brain.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8223</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig comes closer to the author's original conception of this exceptionally long-lived male fantasy figure than anyone since early Sean Connery.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117932077.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This Bond is haunted, not yet housebroken, still figuring out the persona. In Casino Royale, the reset button has been pressed in the manner of "Batman Begins."</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/24089/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The good news is Craig, who was riveting as a London pharmaceutical salesman in the recent Brit import "Layer Cake," is equally mesmerizing here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A420106</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Casino Royale marks a shrewd relaunching of a franchise. But Campbell and company show too much of their sweat. If these movies continue to follow Fleming's profane pilgrim's progress, the next Bond movies should be more emotional and funny, with a bit of brass-knuckled charm.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.casino16nov16,0,3108174.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eva Green...Gaspingly beautiful, wouldn't you say?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11162006/entertainment/movies/platinum_bond_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As M, Dench knows she has a tiger by the tail and isn't fazed in the slightest. Reservations aside, the film marks the beginning of a new phase in James Bond's history, and it promises to be a gripping one.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284443&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you miss the old cliches, consider whether, after 21 Bond films and countless parodies, your response is simply Pavlovian.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8094</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>See Casino Royale for a Bond you've never seen before, and then imagine him in a film two-thirds the size. Here's hoping the writers of the next Bond movie employ the same personal trainer that Craig did to keep the script tight and lean.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/116346570388900.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The payoff is the revitalization of Bond by making him closer to what Fleming envisaged: a sociopath who, fortunately, is on our side.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061117.CASINO17/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is about a half hour too long. The third act drags and an extended high-stakes poker game doesn't always keep our attention. But this is a superior Bond.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-11-16-review-casino-royale_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Connery - but in different proportions - Craig is earthy and erotic, holding himself like a smoking gun.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=759777&amp;reviewId=21811</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the first time in memory, the film ends not just with the promise of more Bonds but without a firm conclusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=759777&amp;reviewId=21812&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In its overt attempts to balance high-spirited spy adventure with more realistic acting and actio--conveying the realities of government-sponsored murde--Casino Royale is a step in the right direction for the Bond franchise. But it's a small, tentative step.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/55373</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly light on fab gadgets, there are, of course, double crosses, fast cars, and lots of gunplay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3269/casino-royale.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Letkemann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the film's final break-the-bank action sequence in Venice is worth waiting for, Casino Royale's 2-hour, 24-minute running time is long enough to exhaust all but the series' biggest fans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-casino17nov17,0,6222788.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig has the courage to present a hollow man, flooding the empty rooms where his better nature should be with brutality and threat. His smile is more frightening than his straight face, and he doesn’t bother with the throwaway quips that were meant to endear us to the other Bonds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?061120crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is simply too long for its own good.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=F1C78624FC0585043FFF817783AFBBB0.prodapp12_ae_01?id=759777&amp;reviewId=21802</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a Bond with great body but no soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1558307,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$167,365,000</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$102,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$40,833,156</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,434</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>