<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Cassandra&amp;#039;s Dream</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Woody Allen</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Woody Allen</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ewan McGregor</actor>
      <actor>Colin Farrell</actor>
      <actor>Tom Wilkinson</actor>
      <actor>Sally Hawkins</actor>
      <actor>Hayley Atwell</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 18, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>108</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a pulp story pinned to the screen with an ice pick of conscience in a manner that would have pleased Allen's idol, Ingmar Bergman.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01182008/entertainment/movies/lost_in_a_dark_woody_312365.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen's latest, Cassandra's Dream, is one of his debonair ''small'' entertainments, the closest that he has come to doing a tidy, no-frills, down-and-dirty genre thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20172127,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In thematic terms, Cassandra's Dream could be looked at as a rebuttal to "Crimes and Misdemeanors."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/18/DDPJTU7CE.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is actually a softer treatment of the similar sibling anguish in Sidney Lumet's "Before the Devil Knows You're Dead." Allen isn't enough of a great dark artist to pull off a full-scale tragedy the way Lumet does.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10586</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a talkative film, rather earnest in its tonalities, not at all a deft, witty or well-paced. On the other hand, it is, for Allen, a comparatively rare excursion into lower-class life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1704952,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Woody Allen’s latest excursion to the dark side of human nature, is good enough that you may wonder why he doesn’t just stop making comedies once and for all.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/01/18/movies/18cass.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ewan McGregor’s bright-eyed Ian, following in the footsteps of characters in Allen’s “Crimes and Misdemeanors” and “Match Point,” is a study in guilt-free violence. But Colin Farrell’s Terry is something new. Terry is a decent guy with many weaknesses, and, after the crime is committed, Farrell gives him a piteous self-loathing that is very touching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/01/21/080121crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This 38th Allen film (and third in a row to be set in London) is a drama about two brothers that's so heavy in tone it seems inspired by Greek tragedy and the grimmest '40s film noir.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/347752_cassandra18q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not Allen's weakest work, not by far. But its impact is shockingly superficial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1200531324272730.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What we get are themes and variations on previous good work, to lessening effect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0118/p15s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen, who stays behind the camera, brings too little wit and too much contrivance to material that quickly dissolves into warmed-over Dostoevski.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/14721473/review/18048463/cassandras_dream</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like so many late-period Allens, it leaves behind the feeling that he's made this movie before, but better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/cassandras_dream</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The identical premise is used in Sidney Lumet's "Before the Devil Knows You're Dead," which is like a master class in how Allen goes wrong.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080117/REVIEWS/801170301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Feels like one of Allen's laziest pieces of writing and direction, leaden with heavy metaphor and characters who rarely make it beyond the archetype--marionettes in a miserablist puppet theater.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0803,foundas,78843,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like a tragic overture played at the wrong tempo and slightly off-key, Woody Allen's London-set Cassandra's Dream sends out more mixed signals than an inebriated telegraphist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934555.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a lame psychological thriller with an obvious story trajectory. It's a wannabe film noir with no atmosphere whatsoever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/cassandras_dream.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen is obsessed with the notion of getting away with murder, mulling over which personalities can shoulder the psychological burden of killing without remorse, while others crumble under the pressure. The problem is, you don’t feel the human sweat and strain in Cassandra’s Dream, despite game work from Farrell and McGregor.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-cassandras-dream/286087/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An uninspired if perfectly watchable drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-cassandra18jan18,0,6594044.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A psychological thriller in serious need of both psychology and thrills, Cassandra's Dream is a wan, exceedingly minor drama by Woody Allen, who has started to recycle himself in London the way he had long been recycling his New York City pictures.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/382752.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Coen brothers might have pulled this off, but it's out of Allen's faltering reach.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/01/18/2008-01-18_woody_allens_murder_caper_cassandras_dre.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's not a believable character, nor line of convincing dialogue to be found.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080118_An_improbable_murder_plot_that_seems__well__improbable.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen's latest, his 42nd effort as a director, is the work of an artist devoid of ideas and energy. Perfunctorily staged and lazily written, it comes to life in only the briefest of spurts, usually when the ever-reliable Tom Wilkinson is on-screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.cassandra18jan18,0,4843178.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After making his best and smoothest drama (Match Point) in England, Woody Allen returns there for one of his most clueless and awkward, outfitted with a standard-issue Philip Glass score.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32651_CASSANDRAS_DREAM.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cassandra's Dream is not unredeemably bad. MacGregor and Farrell hack away at their implausible dialogue with admirable intensity (though when Terry starts to descend into mental illness, Farrell touches his limits as an actor).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2182350</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As writer, Allen offers lazy plotting, poor characterization, dull scenes and flat dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=VbkKHTkbwP0nyd1sRCthKxJ1J6rpjWpl277QFvdmjhlpVz1CWmpL!-1562314872&amp;&amp;rid=10477</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The thrills are few and the expository dialogue tediously overwhelming in this preachy cautionary tale about getting too big for one's britches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/cassandras-dream/review/291844</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Farrell is quite good, though it's hard to buy the Scottish McGregor and the Irish Farrell as brothers. But mostly, the film feels rudderless, almost as if it's been directed on autopilot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-01-17-cassandras-dream_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of offering a perspective that, at the very least, laments a world where the flow of money hurts otherwise good people, Allen simply pushes the movie into an uncertain sinkhole between morality play and black comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139672&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At this point, I guess we should just applaud Allen for his work ethic. Even at the ripe, old age of 72, he’s still making movies at the rate of one a year, come rain or come shine. The problem, of course, is that he doesn’t make good movies at the rate of one a year. In fact, by my count, he hasn’t made a good movie for almost a decade (1999’s "Sweet &amp; Lowdown").</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A581510</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cassandra's Dream, an earnest meditation on greed, desire, murder and class struggle, is one of Woody Allen's funniest movies in years -- except Allen doesn't know it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/01/18/cassandras_dream/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Takes a long time to say nothing new, which is a shame because it wastes fine performances across the board (it's a nice reminder that Farrell, can, in fact, act), and, well, a really effective score by Philip Glass.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4370/cassandras-dream.html</url>
         <critic>Eric Alt</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$973,018</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$361,901</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>107</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>woody allen</oscar_winning_director>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>ewan mcgregor</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>