<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Changing Times</name>
   <company>Koch Lorber Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>André TéchinéLaurent Guyot</author>
      <author>Pascal Bonitzer</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>André Téchiné</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>France</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Catherine Deneuve</actor>
      <actor>Gérard Depardieu</actor>
      <actor>Gilbert Melki</actor>
      <actor>Malik Zidi</actor>
      <actor>Lubna Azabal</actor>
      <actor>Tanya Lopert</actor>
      <actor>Nabila Baraka</actor>
      <actor>Idir Elomri</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 14, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This magnificent pair are the heart of Techine's film, and the sense of frayed, aging beauty and handsomeness they now carry helps project the picture's main theme: the imperishability of true love.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060811-movies-review-times,0,4253169.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Volatile and sometimes daring performances by Catherine Deneuve, Gerard Depardieu, Gilbert Melki, Malik Zidi, and Lubna Azabal (as twins) contribute to the highly charged and novelistic experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#30116</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Changing Times, Mr. Téchiné, the great French director, is near the peak of his form. Weaving a half dozen subplots, he creates a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/07/14/movies/14chan.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Another gorgeous and immensely satisfying reminder that there are few better directors than Téchiné when it comes to capturing the vagaries of the heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8233</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Full of last-minute surprises, this willfully slippery movie seems to make the case both for mixing it up and sticking to your own kind. Which is all of a piece with the sensibility of this wonderfully ambiguous filmmaker, a visionary of our changing times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/there-goes-the-neighborhood/14153/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its weaknesses, Changing Times ("Les Temps Qui Changent" in French) is always watchable and even poignant from time to time. What it is never going to be is the grand passion of anyone's moviegoing life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-changing4aug04,0,3035520.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoughtful and reflective love story about the impact of time on true love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000799431</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A Cathererine Deneuve-Gerard Depardieu vehicle that leaves ample room for interesting supporting characters, this moody, more-bitter-than-sweet ode to anxiety is intense adult fare reinforced by effective no frills lensing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117925754?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Lisa Nesselson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something uniquely pleasurable about watching a director in total command of his craft, even when that craft is in service of a scattershot melodrama with pale intimations of social relevance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/50425</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There isn't a flicker of chemistry between these old pros in Andre Techine's peculiar melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/435056p-366391c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While incontrovertibly light compared to contemporary master of melodrama Andre Techine's best work, this 2005 romance is best enjoyed as the welcome reunion of two of French cinema's most beloved stars.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=281258&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strangely inert drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1216706_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Techine doesn't have much of a story to tell, so instead of moving the narrative forward, he expands it laterally.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/07/21/DDGA8K275Q1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the title, knee-jerk cast, pop-song intro, and schmaltzy plotline of his new film Changing Times is any indication, he's (André Téchiné) now the French mainstream, the premier Gallic pilot of high-toned soap opera.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0628,atkinson,73809,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's kind of a mess. An agreeable, even lovable mess, but still a mess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/07/13/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's always enjoyable watching Depardieu and Deneuve, but they deserve better material than they've been given by Techine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/times_they_are_a_wastin_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$545,255</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$31,702</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>