<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Charlie Wilson&amp;#039;s War</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>George Crile</author>
      <author>Aaron Sorkin</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Mike Nichols</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tom Hanks</actor>
      <actor>Julia Roberts</actor>
      <actor>Phillip Seymour Hoffman</actor>
      <actor>Amy Adams</actor>
      <actor>Ned Beatty</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 21, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>97</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>More of a hoot than any picture dealing with the bloody, protracted fight between the Soviet Army and the Afghan mujahedeen has any right to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/21/movies/21char.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A picture about war and politics that has manages to be both rational and inspirational. It is also the year's funniest smart movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1697661,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The two actors (Hanks/Seymour Hoffman) have terrific chemistry and riff off one another like partners in a veteran comedy team.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10467</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its rapid pace, smart screenplay, and top-notch acting, this is one of the 2007 Oscar season's most appealing and compelling adult motion pictures.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/charlie_wilsons.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hanks has a good time, romping around with the assurance of a holy fool. He and Roberts seem "actorish," putting on accents and mannerisms, but they're entertaining. Hoffman is something more, a scenery-devouring force of nature irresistible as a cyclone and irreverent as a stand-up comedian at a midnight show.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=996551&amp;reviewId=22805&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all about a likable scoundrel who discovers what it means to act out of conviction. The film's underlying twist, though, is tartly ironic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20165793,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A witty, literate, wryly sophisticated parable of American politics: just the kind of movie that Hollywood, in its search for the global audience, supposedly doesn't make anymore.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/344341_charlie21q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You don't often hear critics gripe that a movie isn't long or explicit enough, but Sorkin and Nichols could have gone the extra lap or so to show that Wilson's saga is more than just a story of a good ol' boy accidentally pulling off a remarkable coup; it's a sobering account of the geopolitical hijinks that gave shape to our current world.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2007/12/review_charlie_wilsons_war.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Philip Seymour Hoffman steals the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.charlie21dec21,0,4516605.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Philip Seymour Hoffman utters one of the year's most refreshing lines in this terrific tale of political wheeling and dealing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/12/21/charlie/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Extremely enjoyable. Although it’s a little tonally unsure, whenever Hanks and Hoffman are on screen, any misgivings are forgiven.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=11302</url>
         <critic>Chris Hewitt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie probably gets the Washington process better than any since Otto Preminger's underrated "Advise &amp; Consent" in 1962. It's not about men of virtue doing the impossible, but men of flaws doing the doable, but just barely.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139735&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Charlie Wilson's War is that rare Hollywood commodity these days: a smart, sophisticated entertainment for grownups.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935536.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dark and funny and mean and sexy, damned near pitch-black-perfect considering that at the end of this boozy comedy you wind up with, oh, Osama bin Laden.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0751,wilonsky,78654,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rude, crude and hilarious, whether he's hitting on Joanne or brokering the sale of Soviet weapons through Israel and Islamic Pakistan, Hoffman is the film's sparking live wire.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15086826/review/17652584/charlie_wilsons_war</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is definitely the year of Philip Seymour Hoffman.In Charlie Wilson's War, he and Tom Hanks make a particularly sharp and engaging duo, bouncing clever lines off each other as if it were a verbal ping-pong match.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-20-charlie-wilsons-war_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You might think Tom Hanks is miscast as the lovable sinner. Dennis Quaid, maybe, or Woody Harrelson. But Hanks brings something unique to the role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071220/REVIEWS/712200303/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With 20/20 9/11 hindsight, it's clear that covertly arming the Mujahedeen wasn’t such a good idea after all, but neither Nichols nor Sorkin wants to spoil the fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=291843&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a crackling, almost farcical pace, even though its subject matter could not be more serious or complex.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/351362.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Sorkin's D.C.-set TV series, "West Wing," his script for Charlie Wilson's War is full of rapid-fire badinage, with movers and shakers moving smart and shaking snappy as a squad of aides trot along behind, briefcases and coffee cups in tow. A decade - not to mention a war - never went by so quickly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071221_Brisk_political_comedy_of_intrigue_and_audacity.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's nice to watch a political movie that, for a change, isn't trying to save our souls. It's possible to have a good time with this movie while, at the same time, regretting all that it isn't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1221/p12s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of all the Middle East-theme movies this season, Mike Nichols' Charlie Wilson's War is the least political and most entertaining. That doesn't mean it's great, just that it's unimportant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/21/2007-12-21_charlie_wilson_puts_the_fun_in_war_fundi.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Clever and enjoyable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/12/21/DDMMU02LC.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is first and foremost a farce, not unlike Nichols' "The Birdcage."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12212007/entertainment/movies/afghanistand_up_483878.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Takes a kernel of truth and roasts it into a popcorn movie. There's terrific fun to be had, and much wry comedy too. What's missing, surprisingly given the subject matter, is any real sense of gravity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071220.charlie21nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Julia Roberts has never played a dowager before, but heaven knows she makes a good, and funny, one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4331/charlie-wilsons-war.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this film, directed by Mike Nichols in one of his most satirical moods and scripted by Hollywood's most politically astute writer Aaron Sorkin, a womanizing, alcoholic, easily tempted bachelor gets elected in a Texas district that doesn't care what he does as long as he brings home the bacon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=10248&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Philip Seymour Hoffman carries the movie. As the CIA operative who hates Communists and his myopic superiors in equal measure, he has a wily, don’t-give-a-shit drive that makes you wish he’d been in Baghdad in 2003.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/42087/index2.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It packs political machination, helicopter gunships, single-malt whiskey, Las Vegas, Islamabad, naked butts, and eight years of war. The film, adapted from George Crile’s book, doesn’t always work, but it sure offers value for money.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/12/24/071224crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of course, hanging over this ironic tale is the deeper historical irony--that many of the "good guy" rebels Charlie is funding (and we're cheering) will become our mortal enemies...It's as if "Titanic" ended with a celebratory shipboard banquet, followed by a postscript: by the way, it sank.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/74399</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching Charlie Wilson’s War is like sitting through a very long episode of "The West Wing."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/charlie-wilsons-war-go-mujahedeen-go/17911/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A funny, sprightly tribute to the American can-do spirit, with a bleak ending that suggests that our plucky protagonist may have just dug his own (or, in this case, his country's) grave.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2180433</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nichols succeeds in spinning an entertaining yarn, but the cautionary aspects feel fatally undernourished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/charlie_wilsons_war</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is well made as far as it goes. I wish it went beyond its own carefully prescribed limits of the commercially acceptable.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-charlie-wilsons/271198/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Is, in its way, an apolitical comedy about politics. Or at least a naïve one, since those weapons likely eventually made their way into the hands of Al Qaeda.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9692</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps there was some confusion – should we play this as a lark or a lesson in geopolitical unrest? – or maybe there was some studio involvement to defang the politics; whatever the case, the noncommittal Charlie Wilson's War treads a good-natured but yawning in-between.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A573025</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, Charlie Wilson's War is glib rather than witty, one of those films that comes off as being more pleased with itself than it has a right to be. It also suffers from being not all of a piece, with mismatched elements struggling to cohere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-wilsonwar21dec21,0,5653564.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fascinating story, but Mr. Nichols and his actors never stop reminding us how fascinating it is. With the exception of Mr. Hoffman, a master of understatement, everyone acts up a storm, yet context is lacking.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As creator and head writer of "The West Wing," Aaron Sorkin had a gift for making policy debate seem sexy, but what worked in the context of that liberal fantasy founders badly amid the realpolitik of this cold war drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32603_CHARLIE_WILSONS_WAR.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$66,661,095</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$75,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,656,250</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,575</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>2</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>julia roberts</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_actor>tom hanks</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>mike nichols</oscar_winning_director>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>2</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>julia roberts</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>tom hanks</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>