<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>City of Men</name>
   <company>Miramax Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Elena Soarez</author>
      <author>Paulo Morelli</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paulo Morelli</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Brazil</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Douglas Silva</actor>
      <actor>Darlan Cunha</actor>
      <actor>Rodrigo dos Santos</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 29, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>In many ways, City of Men is like a Portuguese-language version of David Simon's "The Wire."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080229_Young_men_trying_to_survive_on_Rios_Dead-End_Hill.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's energetic and occasionally inspired. Its gritty, sweaty, shiny feel deepens the case that there's a vital new essence to Brazilian cinema.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1204156509213390.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A compelling and visually arresting drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/02/29/DD0QV9PQ8.DTL</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Morelli and editor Daniel Rezende know how to set up complex lines of action and keep the screws tight.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-city-of/320148/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The three leads all played these characters over multiple seasons on the TV show; they're comfortable in these skins, and they show that. (Confusingly, all three appeared in "City of God" under other characters' names.)</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/145/story/514317.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cunha and Silva, both featured in 2002's similarly themed "City of God," have been playing these roles since they were 13, and the rapport between them is electrifying. Much of the sweetness of the film comes from what they bring to their roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/353075_city29q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A poignant look at the legacies of fathers who abdicate their responsibilities.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-02-28-city-of-men_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's lighter, funnier and violent, and it's not entirely without hope, making this tale of survival under horrendous conditions far more suitable for younger, more impressionable audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/city-men/review/292022</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story might have been lifted from an old Warner Brothers melodrama, though it's smartly paced, sincerely delivered, and consistently absorbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32840_CITY_OF_MEN.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its sudsy storyline, this second tour through the punk-infested Rio slums could attract more mature arthouse auds, drawn by character rather than the minutiae of guns 'n' drugs, though it's unlikely to match "God's" muscular $7.5 million U.S. take.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2478&amp;reviewid=VE1117935222&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So much emotional traffic streams through this City of Men that it's easy to miss a narrative turnoff. You won't get lost, but your sense of direction might be profoundly changed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1142425&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some might perceive City of Men as a slow film, while others could reasonably argue that Morelli is taking more time to develop characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10834</url>
         <critic>K.J. Doughton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>City Of Men has its share of problems, but being too entertaining isn't one of them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/city_of_men</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Intriguing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A415014</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As heavy with message as any Hollywood delinquent drama of the late '50s.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20180598,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's power comes less from its contrived story than everything else: the stark setting, chaotic energy and authentic cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/02/29/2008-02-29_short_takes_more_movies_out_this_week.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mix of credible sociology and tired melodrama, along with a palpable sense of déjà vu. Because the plight of boyz 'n' the hood is a global tragedy, its depiction on the screen has become a global commonplace with its own attendant danger – the tragedy is starting to feel trite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080228.wmen29/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>City of Men is clunky and often contrived, but there’s something haunting about fatherless boys in a blighted place fumbling to teach themselves what it means to be a man.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/44475/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paulo Morelli directs capably, with a heavy dash of MTV-generation flair: hyper-saturated colors, close-ups of skin glittering with sweat, and a constant patter of gunfire that undergirds the soundtrack like a steady heartbeat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0809,313322,313322,20.html</url>
         <critic>Julia Wallace</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>City of Men has a more humane, you might say bleeding-heart, perspective on this anarchic culture than “City of God.”</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/02/29/movies/29men.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Morelli uses plentiful flashbacks drawn from the earlier movie and television series that are at times intrusive to the narrative but eventually serve to deepen the relationship of Ace and Laranjinha.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-city29feb29,0,4342643.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's doubly disappointing that all the subplots about Ace and Wallace and their fathers intertwine in increasingly predictable ways.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.city29feb29,0,4631586.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has a dramatic thinness, breezy tone, and unconvincing happy-ish ending that make it feel more inconsequential than anything about killers and imperiled children probably should.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10918</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Performances are up to par, but the story unfolds conventionally - it lacks the fragmented fury of its predecessor. You might call it "City of God Lite."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02292008/entertainment/movies/city_of_men_99720.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Six years after its release, "City of God" is still electrifying and fresh: It hasn't aged a bit. City of Men, though, already feels strangely stale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/436781.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$307,076</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$130,579</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>75</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>