<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Coco Before Chanel</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Anne Fontaine</author>
      <author>Camille Fontaine</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Anne Fontaine</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Audrey Tautou</actor>
      <actor>Benoit Poelvoorde</actor>
      <actor>Alessro Nivola</actor>
      <actor>Marie Gillain</actor>
      <actor>Emmanuelle Devos</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 25, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The naturalism of Anne Fontaine's film would be at home in a novel by Dreiser. Her star Audrey Tautou, who could make lovability into a career, avoids any effort to make Coco Chanel nice, or soft, or particularly sympathetic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20091007/REVIEWS/910079994/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wish Fontaine would follow up with a sequel: "Coco After Chanel." Tautou's performance cries out for a second act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/1016/p17s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This refreshing alternative to the usual potted biopic provides an absorbing look at a singular, steely determination as it was forged and annealed, long before it made itself known to the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/coco-before-chanel,1158482/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anne Fontaine’s biopic transforms the designer’s early life into highbrow guilty-pleasure gold.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/78885/coco-before-chanel</url>
         <critic>Karina Longworth</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Coco is played by Audrey Tautou, and she's phenomenal--self-contained, tightly focused, sparing with her smiles, miserly with her joy, often guarded to the point of severity, yet giving off a grave radiance at every moment she's in front of the camera.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A superior filmed biography that brings intelligence, restraint and style to what could have been a more standard treatment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-coco25-2009sep25,0,7544808.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not an expansive biopic but a fascinating snapshot of a pivotal chapter for Chanel, her formative fashionista years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-09-24-coco-before-chanel_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tautou is a fascinating, unsmiling, petite presence with a severe brow and an androgynous appeal, so much so that I wish Alessandro Nivola (Junebug) were a more robust beau as Arthur ''Boy'' Capel, the love of Chanel's life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20307597,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe it's just the subtitles, but it would seem that Fontaine has a keener eye for the elements that made Chanel's style than she has an ear for dialogue. But she gets a splendid performance from Tautou.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20091009_Young_rebel_of_an_overdecorated_gilded_age.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Through Tautou's performance, Coco Before Chanel reveals the formation of an artist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1294353.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the story of the diminutive Coco before she became the fashionable Chanel – in other words, the whole movie is one long first act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/coco-avant-chanel/article1308479/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Coco Chanel is not the most lovable of heroines, but it's a strength of the film that director Anne Fontaine allows Tautou to make Coco as cold and ungiving as she does.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/10/01/MVEJ19UHMP.DTL</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is most fascinating when it shows how Chanel communicated her enlightened sense of womanhood through her innovative designs, which in turn helped women feel differently about themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?film=1020361</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A hard luck, true life fairy tale story told with poignant humility, embellished with solid acting and determined direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11924</url>
         <critic>Elias Savada</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly intimate and nuanced.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/59250/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spectacle, a love triangle, heritage settings, bravura acting, witty dialogue, a bittersweet finale: There's something for everyone in Anne Fontaine's Coco Before Chanel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/coco-before-chanel-film-review-1003964789.story</url>
         <critic>Bernard Besserglik</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The blossoming of her ambition, as much as her love life, drives the story forward, and turns Coco Before Chanel into a costume drama worthy of the name.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/09/25/movies/25coco.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tautou is, as ever, radiant and deep and affecting, but a film about such an extraordinary personage as Chanel shouldn’t feel so ordinary and wan.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/10/review_--_taking_measure_of_co.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The thread connecting the ambitious girl to the acclaimed woman is enough to make us wish for a sequel titled "Chanel No. 2."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/0789BA238B31944C862576640071D8C5?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Technically, it's superbly made; dramatically, it fails to achieve escape velocity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1820</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I could have watched this woman rip a piece fabric and turn it into a dress all day. I haven’t seen a lot of that. I have seen movies about a woman caught between two men, as Chanel is here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/10/02/coco_has_fashion_but_lacks_real_passion/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are a select few artists who can take the same materials used by everyone else and create a masterpiece. Coco Chanel was one of them. Director Anne Fontaine is not.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/09/25/2009-09-25_coco_before_chanel_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More a snapshot of a moment than conventional biography, and while less complex than it might want to be, still a quietly thoughtful look at one of the 20th century’s most influential characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136490</url>
         <critic>Liz Beardsworth</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More sentimental than chic, Gallic biopic Coco Before Chanel nonetheless knits a convincing portrait of the designer's journey from her humble beginnings as a provincial seamstress to the halls of Parisian haute couture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940098.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=coco+before+chanel</url>
         <critic>Jordan Mintzer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too much of the film feels like one of Balsan’s house parties: undriven, indulgent, quite at ease.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/09/28/090928crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are indications scattered throughout Coco Before Chanel of a major designer quietly and persistently honing her craft, but most of the film could exist without the Chanel name and still smell like the same perfume.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/coco-before-chanel,33305/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Coco of Fontaine's project--which she co-wrote with her sister, Camille, freely adapting Edmonde Charles-Roux's book L'Irrégulière: ou, Mon itinéraire Chanel--can be described as courtesan before couturiere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-09-22/film/chanel-hagiography-is-so-last-season-in-coco-before-chanel/</url>
         <critic>Melissa Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A better title: "Coco Before She Was Interesting."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/11/coco_before_chanel_never_reall.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s a perfectly nice period piece and biographical backgrounder, but the film feels as though it’s a meal of tasty side dishes that lacks a main course.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A893723</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is neither an affecting romance (Coco even considers marrying Balsan because "I'd achieve social status") nor an inspiring success story. Chanel sold herself to one guy, happened to get customers through him, and took a start-up loan from another lover.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/movies/lift_skirt_raise_dynasty_t22uHczsa8kARID7Wk3QGM</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$6,095,004</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$23,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$177,339</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>