<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Conversations with Other Women</name>
   <company>Fabrication Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Gabrielle Zevin</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Hans Canosa</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Helena Bonham Carter</actor>
      <actor>Aaron Eckhart</actor>
      <actor>Nora Zehetner</actor>
      <actor>Erik Eidem</actor>
      <actor>Olivia Wilde</actor>
      <actor>Thomas Lennon</actor>
      <actor>Cerina Vincent</actor>
      <actor>Brianna Brown</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 11, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>84</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's brilliant work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/this_talk_isnt_cheap_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The entire film is shot in split screen. Each of the unnamed characters is photographed separately in their own slice of space, the images sutured together with a purposeful imperfection, with occasional overlap and rare moments of union. It gives them the appearance of dancing around one another, almost touching but never getting past the years of emotional scar tissue, even as they work their way to her hotel room.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/282467_women25q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I found the film powerfully erotic, although it has minimal nudity and no explicit sex.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/08/10/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fine acting and sexy chemistry between Bonham Carter and Eckhart make it work.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=281314&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Conversations is well-calculated and well-ordered, and it manages an equilibrium that a science lab would envy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/52163</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A smart, sexy romantic drama, directed within an inch of its life by Hans Canosa.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/08/11/DDGRSKESO01.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The charm of Conversations With Other Women, a gimmicky but oddly moving two-character drama that flies in from who knows where, is its intelligentknowingness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9279</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For once, the gimmick is a perfect reflection of the characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060811.WOMEN11/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film ultimately becomes too contrived to be anything but a fleeting diversion, but kudos to these emerging filmmakers for daring to make something a little bit different and, for the most part, intriguing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106920&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An intimate movie in every sense, Conversations With Other Women sets out to explore well-trammeled yet at the same time uncharted territory without grinding any axes. What it offers is a modest fantasy that will be familiar to contemporaries of Bonham Carter and Eckhart especially. It's sad and funny, satisfying and frustrating, totally familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-conversations11aug11,0,1682452.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the movie is occasionally too clever-talky for its own good, it has the authentic ring of an elegy for love lost when one partner grows up while the other runs in place.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0632,taylor,74128,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The actors, who portray a reunion that is more sparring match than love fest, strike occasional sparks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0811/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This minor relationship picture comes and goes, but her (Carter's) performance lingers.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060825-movies-review-women,0,5428225.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Witty and articulate but the continual editing devices can distract from the momentum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135015</url>
         <critic>Anna Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>None of it is quite believable -- the film is too studied, too forward in its conceits to be entirely satisfying -- but Mr. Eckhart and Ms. Bonham Carter approach their roles with intelligence and conviction.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/08/11/movies/11conv.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The battle of the sexes is restaged to clever but inconsequential effect in Conversations With Other Women. Very much a case of old wine in a new bottle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928090?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That the movie holds viewers' attention despite its contrivances is a testament to the script and acting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002274412</url>
         <critic>John DeFore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, the problem with Conversations with Other Women is not that it pulls an ordinary romance into unfamiliar shapes but that it doesn't pull far enough. It may be dotted with fine observations, yet somehow the charm of its novelty grows stale, and the airless feeling of a closed set begins to fester.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060807crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Theirs is an affair not worth remembering.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/442494p-372587c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the resourcefulness of the two leads, the movie finally registers as much ado about very little.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30219_CONVERSATIONS_WITH_OTHER_WOMEN.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$379,418</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$66,157</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>13</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>