<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Counterfeiters, The</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Stefan Ruzowitzky</author>
      <author>Adolf Burger</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Stefan Ruzowitzky</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>German</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Karl Markovics</actor>
      <actor>August Diehl</actor>
      <actor>Devid Striesow</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 22, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters is in its own smart, trim fashion "The Bridge on the River Kwai" of concentration-camp sagas. Also based (like Kwai) on a real-life story, this movie starts small but becomes a miniature epic of overreach and moral drift.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.counterfeiters28mar28,0,113057.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Without doing anything so divisive as taking sides, The Counterfeiters pays sympathetic attention to those who play their cards to win even when the rules are terrible, not least because the remarkable Markovics, an Austrian TV actor with a pugnacious anvil of a head, is so riveting as an unsaintly survivor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20180583,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This poses some tricky moral questions, and its troubling ambiguities rank a cut above the dubious uplift of "Schindler's List."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#32823</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters differs from most Holocaust movies in that the emphasis is on the personal moral choices that are made rather than the overall horror and despair.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A610245</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Swift and compelling, winner of this year’s Oscar for best foreign-language picture, The Counterfeiters may not be destined for the large international audience that embraced last year’s winner, “The Lives of Others.” But it’s the better, tougher film, with a more provocative moral dilemma at its center.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-counterfeiters/320209/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some movies rest on an actor's face, and The Counterfeiters has a great one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10833</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Quiet, watchful, out for himself, Sorowitsch is a complicated figure - neither hero nor villain, and certainly no fool. The Austrian actor Markovics is riveting in the role; he is wiry, anticipatory, his eyes darting with intelligence and worry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080314_Interned_by_Hitler__and_forging_for_him.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters is a testament to guile. Ruzowitzky scored the picture with tangos, and the tangos are meant to be Sally’s music--seductive, insolent, triumphant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/03/03/080303crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While terrific entertainment, The Counterfeiters fails to stir the soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/03/review_counterfeiters_strange.html</url>
         <critic>Stan Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is always intriguing as it follows the arrest and captivity of Salomon Sorowitsch (the terrific Karl Markovics), one of Germany's leading counterfeiters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/445839.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A conventional mixture of thriller and moral drama, the film is unsettling in both intentional and unintentional ways.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080228.wcounter29/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well made, provocative and compelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/02/29/DD9VV8V9H.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>David Wiegand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gripping, unusual and suitably harrowing -- if, in the final analysis, not particularly satisfying -- concentration camp drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/354003_count07q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From an historical perspective, the story is interesting because it shows a different side of the war than what we're used to observing in motion pictures.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/counterfeiters.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Based on the true story of the world's largest counterfeiting operation, The Counterfeiters is full of the weird details that, though unsurprising on one level, are so jarringly wrong that they seem fresh: As a reward for producing 134 million pounds sterling, the prisoners get a pingpong table.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02222008/entertainment/movies/odd_currency_of_desperation_98700.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though extensively fictionalized -- Sorowitch is loosely based on the notorious, larger-than-life forger Salomon Smolianoff; Herzog on SS officer Bernhard Krueger, after whom the operation was named.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/counterfeiters/review/292306</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The moral quandary of Nazi complicity is revisited in taut drama The Counterfeiters, which tells the true story of a disparate group of imprisoned artists, financiers and swindlers secretly assembled in a concentration camp to forge millions of pound and dollar notes to support the German war effort.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2478&amp;reviewid=VE1117932752&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Eddie Cockrell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters demonstrates that no matter how many Holocaust stories the movies tell, there are always new and unexpected ones waiting to be revealed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-counterfeiters22feb22,0,2748285.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best--and queasiest--The Counterfeiters asks disturbing questions more commonly found in the survivor literature of Primo Levi or Bruno Bettelheim than at the movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0808,302384,302384,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters is inevitably serious, even austere, and full of chilling, ironic details.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120363729689184347.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Counterfeiters is a swift and suspenseful thriller, and perhaps a little too entertaining for its own good.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/02/22/movies/22coun.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though swiftly paced, The Counterfeiters convincingly examines the complex nature of humanity under inhuman conditions</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1140326&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Adam Bernstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Markovics largely rescues the film with his mesmerizingly layered, steady performance as a man who solves the problem of compromise by refusing to admit that he's compromising.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_counterfeiters</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$5,488,570</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$6,250,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$87,514</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>