<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Crossing the Bridge: The Sound of Istanbul</name>
   <company>Strand Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Fatih Akin</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Fatih Akin</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>GermanyTurkey</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Alexer Hacke</actor>
      <actor>Baba Zula</actor>
      <actor>Orient Expressions</actor>
      <actor>Duman</actor>
      <actor>Replikas</actor>
      <actor>Erkin Koray</actor>
      <actor>Ceza</actor>
      <actor>Istanbul Style Breakers</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 9, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>But after surveying pop and rock hybrids, Akin and Hacke go deeper. You will be very happy indeed to make the acquaintance of such Turkish music luminaries as Orhan Gencebay and Sezen Aksu, whose stories and personalities are as fascinating as their music.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2873</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You'll feel lucky for such a comprehensive introduction to Turkish music.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46986&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever you think you know about Turkey, Crossing the Bridge will change your mind. With a dynamite album of music from the film in simultaneous release, I smell a "Buena Vista"-style crossover hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/06/08/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This new film feels like something of a gift, as if the director had decided to burn some of his favorite songs for his newfound friends, the world-cinema audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/06/09/movies/09brid.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This sensational documentary, which follows German avant-garde musician Alexander Hacke around the city with his mobile recording studio, crosses all kinds of bridges.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14245</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Crossing the Bridge does more than offer a wide variety of entertaining and intoxicating Turkish music. It also uses music to paint a portrait of a vibrant, cosmopolitan city and provide a window into a rich and varied national culture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-crossing18aug18,0,256360.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has two main flaws: the emphasis it puts on German bassist Alexander Hacke, the film's ostensible narrator, who shows up in too many scenes, and the fact that it doesn't identify many of the film's performers until the very end. Even so, Crossing the Bridge is satisfying to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/07/14/DDG9KJU2BI1.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Curiel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With adventurous forays into questionable neighborhoods and stimulating tours through street markets, "Crossing the Bridge" is about the city as much as its music.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/279114_limited28.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More than just a musical primer. It's also a valentine to the city on the Bosporus, the strait that separates Istanbul's Asian and European sides.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/69841.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to imagine what Akin left unexplored - but here's hoping he'll share his discoveries if he ever returns.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/424916p-358437c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hacke is in almost every shot, taking in the performances and sometimes singing and dancing along, inviting the audience to share in the joy of discovery.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/49262</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As filmmaking, the docu is only travel-diary so-so. But the chance to experience the machine-gun rhymes of ''the Turkish Eminem'' - a young man called Ceza - is priceless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1201795_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the world's great cities comes vibrantly alive through its music and musical denizens in Crossing the Bridge: The Sound of Istanbul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927084?categoryid=1929&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In briskly edited sequences peppered with fascinating found footage, each genre is tightly linked to a neighborhood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0623,lim,73450,20.html</url>
         <critic>R. Emmet Sweeney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The intimate performance footage ranges from more traditional sounds to Turkish iterations of global styles like rock, hip-hop, and electronica, delivering commentary on the nation's conflicted status as a bridge between Europe and Asia that's even more poignant than the passionate and informative interviews.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29500_CROSSING_THE_BRIDGE.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Margasak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An infectious (in a good way) documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1121557&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This musical documentary likely will find its major audience in Germany, where the immigrant-minority Turk citizenry will take to its array of sounds, smears and social commentary as cultural nourishment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000920117</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie doesn't quite add up beyond its performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A393667</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$70,685</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$9,161</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>