<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>CSA: The Confederate States of America</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Kevin Willmott</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Kevin Willmott</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Charles Frank</actor>
      <actor>Evamarii Johnson</actor>
      <actor>Rupert Pate</actor>
      <actor>Larry Peterson</actor>
      <actor>Ferno Arenas</actor>
      <actor>Sean Blake</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 15, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>89</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brilliant and irresistible counterfactual overview of American history.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/24/DDGSSHD2IJ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fearless and brilliant racial-historical satire, done in a meticulous re-creation of the Ken Burns mode, that chronicles the last 150 years of America as if the South had won the Civil War.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1131178_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the most part, Willmott succeeds thrillingly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45635</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provocative, deeply unsettling mockumentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46741</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>C.S.A. has a love-it-or-hate-it bite that probably will lead to a few passionate post-screening discussions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1146700520168940.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since Spike Lee's "Bamboozled" has such an irreverent carnival of African American stereotypes been so irreverently sent up.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/264117_csa24q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a coherent, well-judged alternative history, the movie's a mess. As a thought-provoking and frequently hilarious jeremiad, it scores again and again.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8870</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>CSA is rough around the edges, especially where the acting and some of the film's invented characters are concerned. But the way CSA works out its ideas is so provoking that its drawbacks are not difficult to ignore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-csa24feb24,0,5805056.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With surprisingly good production values and sly, underhanded wit, Willmott never tips his hand, steadily guiding the satire to a genuinely stunning, back-to-reality conclusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1108519&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>CSA would have benefited from a bigger budget and better actors and it gets weaker as it goes along, but it's still thought-provoking stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/61903.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a clever premise stretched perhaps a little too far.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134433</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>C.S.A. isn't subtle, but its undisguised indignation places it in the same bold polemical tradition as Peter Watkins' incendiary "Punishment Park" (1971), that nightmarish slice of speculative sci-fi about government-sanctioned manhunts for hippies and dissidents.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/now-playing/12754/new-film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Adam Nayman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More intriguing on paper than when it actually unspools onscreen. Kevin Willmott's small-scaled but ambitious picture is well-researched, sometimes amusing and not unintelligent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117923338?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wacky, hodgepodge and decidedly homemade, CSA nevertheless is worth seeing. Sure, it veers off into nonsense, and there are times when the film loses its center. But the premise, the passion and the scathing political commentary ultimately keep CSA afloat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-03-09/film/film4.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yes, there's something terribly familiar about this historical fantasy. As we now know, and Willmott is well aware, the South actually did win the Civil War.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0607,hoberman,72181,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Mr. Lee's hit-and-miss effort  ("Bamboozled"), Mr. Willmott's alternative history takes its inspiration and its rage from an America that has come both a long way and not nearly far enough. But while the filmmaker's anger is palpable it's not very inspired.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/15/movies/15stat.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of course, the very existence of someone like Willmott -- a black university professor who can make an angry, ruthless satire about American racism with impunity -- suggests that we're still a long way from living in the CSA.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/09/btm/index.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a novel twist, the movie's dumbest element--joke commercials for racist consumer products--turns out to be the most provocative when end titles reveal the products were all real.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29302_C_S_A_THE_CONFEDERATE_STATES_OF_AMERICA.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>CSA is a sophomoric film essay that would have barely rated a passing grade from a tougher teacher.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/392186p-332413c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are droll comic flourishes in this very brave film, to be sure, but all you really want to do after watching CSA is hang down your head and cry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A352399</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Less would have been more. Still, CSA has some laughs, most of them bitter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060313&amp;s=kauffmann031306</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$672,156</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$5,706</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>