<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Daddy&amp;#039;s Little Girls</name>
   <company>Lionsgate</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Tyler Perry</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Tyler Perry</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Gabrielle Union</actor>
      <actor>Idris Elba</actor>
      <actor>Louis Gossett Jr.</actor>
      <actor>Tasha Smith</actor>
      <actor>Tracee Ellis Ross</actor>
      <actor>Malinda Williams</actor>
      <actor>Terri J. Vaughn</actor>
      <actor>China Anne McClain</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 14, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This latest market-savvy bit of circuit preaching is less cartoonish than Perry's previous big-tent revival meetings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20012447,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Subtlety is not his strong suit--all the characters here are either adorable or loathsome--yet Perry has toned down the pandering materialism, evangelism, and black empowerment of "Madea's Family Reunion" and "Diary of a Mad Black Woman," letting his heart-tugging story tell itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31083_DADDYS_LITTLE_GIRLS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unflinchingly addressing issues of class and race, Perry juggles multiple plot lines and the result emerges as (dare I say?) a surprising mix of Frank Capra and Douglas Sirk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A443637</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Happily, Perry's strength as a filmmaker is that he genuinely loves his actors, and they love him back. What his movies lack in exposition they make up for in performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=4A16E7043DC5ECF8F8EEC96F8BF1312A.prodapp14_ae_02?id=802401&amp;reviewId=22209&amp;startDate=02%2F16%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chockfull of cathartic moments, Perry's storytelling is best when it defies convention. Like the black man's Frank Capra, Perry tells stories in which every conflict is a test of faith and every victory a testament to the American underdog. Instead of following the proven formulas of screenwriting books, he earnestly shepherds his own messy structure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932820.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More surprising is Perry's inability to write back-and-forth dialogue with any real wit or verve. He is at his best when writing speeches, and some of the film's best moments come when Union is given snappy monologues on the state of contemporary relationships and African American maleness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-daddys16feb16,0,7935882.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry has great casting instincts, and in Elba and Union he's matched two gifted, equally gorgeous actors, both of whom seem ready to make sparks fly. If only their director would let them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-bridge-to-terabithia-daddys-little-girls-and-more/15682/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are fewer laughs and more lectures -- but there's plenty of sass and soul in between.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=285898&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While its look at interclass romance among African-Americans and the struggles of a working-class single father is fresh and vital, the heavy-handed execution isn't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/58635</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Billed as a comedy about a single dad with three girls, the movie is essentially another sudser about the plight of upscale black women in Atlanta.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02152007/entertainment/movies/bland_ambition_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a director, Mr. Perry has his strong points, including a genuine interest in showing the resilience of African-American life and traditions (including church sermons and blues music, which are accorded equal significance here). But those aspects get lost in this turgid and ungainly film.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/02/15/movies/16dadd.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry shelves his crowd-pleasing Madea character and aspires for the impossible mix of 1950s social melodrama, gospel-inflected public service announcement, soap opera, R&amp;B video, girl-centric sitcom on the CW, and any episode of "Good Times," featuring Janet Jackson's oft-affronted Penny. Were Perry a visual director or a logical, patient screenwriter, that hybrid would count as a feat of singular ambition. Instead, it seems like the product of an abbreviated attention span.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9467</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Given his built-in appeal, Perry has the opportunity to broaden the subject matter of so-called black movies. He takes a stab at it in "Girls," but he could do so much better.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/02/15/DDGFLO51HD14.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether because of Madea's on-screen absence or the abilities of the two lead actors, Daddy's Little Girls is still a step up for Perry, boasting moments of charm that transcend the usual mess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070216.DADDY16/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Daddy's Little Girls may be heavy-handed and drearily predictable, but it also should connect with its core audience as solidly as Perry's previous efforts did, even if the drama is frequently just as over the top as its predecessors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=FTBymG6NFPfJx40t25L57R3V11qJzyHJJKTvl57TyWhs1lgjLy23!-1438947543&amp;&amp;rid=8815</url>
         <critic>Luke Sader</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry's indifferent direction flattens everything out: You might fall asleep if his heavy-mitted music cues didn't keep cattle-prodding your ass.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0708,ridley,75871,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Subtlety has never been Perry's strength, but his previous films balanced the sermonizing with good humor and sincerity. Perhaps next time, he'll ease up on the lectures, and bring back the love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/498029p-419667c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$31,366,978</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$16,904,003</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,111</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>