<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dan in Real Life</name>
   <company>Touchstone Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Pierce Gardner</author>
      <author>Peter Hedges</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Peter Hedges</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Steve Carell</actor>
      <actor>Juliette Binoche</actor>
      <actor>Dane Cook</actor>
      <actor>Norbert Leo Butz</actor>
      <actor>John Mahoney</actor>
      <actor>Dianne Wiest</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 26, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan in Real Life fires on so many circuits that at times it's actually shocking how good it is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/10/26/DD4PSVIP2.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A nimble and supple and moving comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20153893,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Carell shows a whole new side to his talents.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/16155430/review/16971691/dan_in_real_life</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a director Hedges is smart enough to allow his actors to share the frame and interact and let the material breathe.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-dan-in/238758/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A smart, sweet, and thoroughly disarming ensemble comedy that isn't afraid to wear its humanism on its sleeve.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4200/dan-in-real-life.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan offers the most pleasing kind of unforced charm as it uses a terrific plot device to examine the conflicts between family and romance as well as the joy and pain of being in love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-dan26oct26,0,1540640.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provides Steve Carell and Juliette Binoche with comic roles that fit them like designer threads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=32Q4Hcxdy8SGJJF1TpkNWs3SlmP4YBnGlw11zFLTG4HybRjTLJjZ!-687471411&amp;&amp;rid=10079</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deftly interlaces heart and humor in a witty, warm and well-observed comedy about the unexpected and inconvenient blooming of romance at the weekend gathering of an extended family.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935150.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Novelist-turned-writer/director Peter Hedges follows up his "Pieces Of April" debut with a comedy that's at once overstuffed and surprisingly subtle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/dan_in_real_life</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the film has a flaw, and I'm afraid it does, it's the Sondre Lerche songs on the soundtrack. They are too foregrounded and literal, either commenting on the action or expounding on associated topics. In such a laid-back movie, they're in our face.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071025/REVIEWS/710250303/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching Binoche dithering about an American comedy takes some getting used to, but she's a believable soul mate for the hangdog Carell. The rest of the family, however, has got to go.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/dan-real-life/review/290055</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The anti-Ben Stiller comedy: There's humiliation aplenty but no mugging, no abuse to the crotch region, no straining to be outrageous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10262007/entertainment/movies/dad_or_alive.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a brief review in Time magazine this week, I gave Dan a gentleman's B-. Let me try to remember why. Because the pressure of keeping his ardor secret turns Dan pleasingly cranky.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1677134,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing groundbreaking about Dan in Real Life -- it's a picture that could have been made 10 or 20 years ago -- and yet its easygoing, affable nature is exactly what makes it pleasurable.</snippet>
         <url>http://salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/10/26/dan/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan in Real Life is neither wildly farcical nor mockingly cruel, but rather, for the most part, winningly gentle and observant.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/10/26/movies/26dan.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, the commercial necessity of wrapping up a family comedy in less than 100 minutes seems to have trumped anything real about Dan's life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071025.wdan26/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan in Real Life is basically a slightly less-sappy version of "TheFamily Stone."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/283640.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sweet it is. Remotely connected to real life, however, it is not.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/10/26/2007-10-26_dan_in_real_life_not_much_like_real_life.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almost reflexively, the filmmakers skirt Dan's messier conflicts. But it is the moments when they don't dance around the awkward issue of a brother falling for his brother's girl that Dan is the most poignant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20071026_Giving_advice_always_beats_taking.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cook has as much depth as a coaster, so it's impossible under any circumstances to imagine Binoche falling in love with him. Her complicated, heartfelt performance is the reason to see the film: When she's around, she pierces the soothing gray nothingness with shafts of sunlight.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=968749&amp;reviewId=null&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan in Real Life steals from that line in "Virgin" about Carell kinda looking like Luke Wilson, since here Carell is, after all, playing the Luke Wilson role from "The Family Stone."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0743,various,78125,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On its own terms, the picture is at least as contrived as it is charming and its characters in many cases bear less resemblance to flesh and blood human beings than those in a Farrelly brothers farce.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10387</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A small but sweetly formed comedy of romantic misfortune that can’t quite keep Hollywood at bay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135159</url>
         <critic>Ian Nathan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cozy, lived-in atmosphere created by the ensemble and the unlikely chemistry of Carell and Binoche are so genuine that you wish the rest of the film was just as effortless and authentic.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/336856_dan26q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beneath its aw-shucks, wants-to-be-liked exterior, this is a bankrupt motion picture. It's cloying, artificial, and not the least bit romantic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/d/dan_real.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dan in Real Life takes a pleasant premise and calls upon the talents of engaging actors and generally squanders both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-10-25-dan-in-real-life_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pleasing moments don't add up to a feature film, even though this one strives desperately for substance and coherence by slathering its slender story with treacly family values.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119335572527972232.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All goes according to course, and that's exactly the problem with Dan in Real Life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A553235</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bad movies invariably stem from bad ideas, and the worst of the several rancid ideas packed inside of Dan in Real Life is that Steve Carell could be the new Alan Alda.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1026/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filmgoers haven't seen a family this neurotically enmeshed since the last Diane Keaton movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1134024&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a great movie to be had in the notion of a busybody whose advice keeps blowing up in his face, but Dan in Real Life merely sets it up and walks away.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10550</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The setup of this comedy by director-cowriter Peter Hedges (Pieces of April) and some subsequent twists may be contrived, and the laughs aren't very plentiful, but much of the behavior seems real, and the able cast makes the most of it.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32286_DAN_IN_REAL_LIFE.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With all its cloying, tone-deaf attempts at genuine emotional warmth, all it really deserves is to be avoided.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.dan26oct26,0,5437542.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I could see people enjoying Dan in Real Life, I guess -- the scenery is nice and the people are pretty and the songs are cute little emotion substitutes. But Dan? Buddy? It's not all about you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1193294055323110.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$47,642,963</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$11,809,445</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,921</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>