<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Darfur Now</name>
   <company>Warner Independent Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Ted Braun</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ted Braun</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Don Cheadle</actor>
      <actor>Hillary Rodham Clinton</actor>
      <actor>John McCain</actor>
      <actor>Adam Sterling</actor>
      <actor>Musa Sharif</actor>
      <actor>Sheikh Ahmed Mohamad Abakar</actor>
      <actor>Jason Miller</actor>
      <actor>Pablo Recalde</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 2, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>99</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the kind of film that doesn’t end after the credits roll, and it’s a gold-star example for what a documentary should do: inspire.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-darfur-now/247655/content</url>
         <critic>Kelley L. Carter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More than any previous film on the subject, Braun's documentary offers an answer to a common question, perfectly phrased and answered by Cheadle himself: "What can I do? More than nothing. A lot more than nothing."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/darfur/review/290835</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the presence of Cheadle and his handsome pal George Clooney can entice otherwise resistant viewers to learn about the ongoing travesty in western Sudan, then Darfur Now has done its job.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1196886307207700.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kind of movie you're glad somebody had the guts to make, but you don't really want to endure.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/338864_darfur09q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instructive as a portrait of activism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/09/DDAFT88O1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the fact that the film is not graphic, you won't want to watch Darfur Now over dinner with your family. But you probably should anyway.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/334072.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slick, impassioned, and guardedly upbeat, Ted Braun's film is a morale booster aimed at US audiences rather than the 2.5 million displaced Sudanese tribespeople whose villages have been destroyed and families slaughtered. That we need a pick-me-up more than they do is pathetic, but there you are.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10321</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is not a compelling documentary (too much exposition, not enough on-the-spot reality), but it is instructive and disturbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071108/REVIEWS/711080301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By showing the struggles and efforts of about half a dozen people, it puts a human face on the tragedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-11-08-also-opening_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Effective advocacy film about the genocide in Darfur.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32395_DARFUR_NOW.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>See Darfur Now, and you won't read the daily news the same way again.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141760&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Darfur Now offers is a collective vision of actions, small and large, taken on many fronts, to end the crisis. The movie is a quiet, methodical call to action.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/02/movies/02darf.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Attempts to both explain the situation to audiences and offer some reason to hope for the future. It's an almost impossible task, and though the film does better than anyone might expect, its success is not complete.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-darfur2nov02,0,3919639.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The depressing subtext is that even with detailed proof of ongoing genocide, it takes movie stars to get to the movers and shakers, and to get worthy movies like this one into theaters.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/40291/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film gets a little ''We can fix this!'' inspirational for a chronicle of such staggering darkness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20155946,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a heartbreaking tale, a sliver of a tragic history still unfolding, but one that Braun largely leaves others to document.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/darfur_now</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A disquieting, and somewhat disjointed, call to arms, Theodore Braun's heartfelt documentary is undeniably important. But it may not be quite focused enough to ignite the passion he so clearly wants his audience to feel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/02/2007-11-02_darfur_now_fuller_picture_needs_focus.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you evaluate Darfur Now against the goals it sets for itself--as a stirring call to action--it must be considered lacking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0744,pinkerton,78184,20.html</url>
         <critic>Nick Pinkerton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary Darfur Now proves that - no matter how im portant the subject matter - following various people around with a camera doesn't necessarily make a film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11022007/entertainment/movies/the_plight_stuff_375732.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the film’s rallying efforts, its meandering structure and absence of a central driving character results in a film about genocide that is, as unbelievable as it sounds, kind of boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A555459</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Theodore Braun's work may well reach and convert one thousand more Adam Sterlings. Here's hoping it does. There is, however, a difference between a worthy cause and a worthy film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071108.darfur09nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$109,107</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$23,217</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>