<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dark Water</name>
   <company>Buena Vista Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Rafael Yglesias</author>
      <author>Hideo Nakata</author>
      <author>Takashige Ichise</author>
      <author>Kôji Suzuki</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Walter Salles</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jennifer Connelly</actor>
      <actor>Ariel Gade</actor>
      <actor>Jennifer Baxter</actor>
      <actor>Pete Postlethwaite</actor>
      <actor>John C. Reilly</actor>
      <actor>Tim Roth</actor>
      <actor>Dougray Scott</actor>
      <actor>Perla Haney-Jardine</actor>
      <actor>Camryn Manheim</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 8, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Salles brings an explorer's eye and breathless curiosity to this fetid milieu, and he gets the most brilliant performances imaginable for this sort of movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2122221/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most important, I cared about the Jennifer Connelly character; she is not a horror heroine, but an actress playing a mother faced with horror. There is a difference, and because of that difference, Dark Water works.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050707/REVIEWS/50607003</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a quieter, more psychologically dense movie, where the payoff is sometimes no payoff at all - for instance, Tim Roth plays a cut-rate divorce lawyer whose own weirdness (he seems to live out of his car) is never explained.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/07-08-2005/entertainment/col/story/326263p-278685c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Salles tends to explain rather than suggest, but he connects with the anguish and abandonment to give this ghost story an emotionally haunting core.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/231668_dark08q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a movie with more subtext than "Rosemary's Baby," nearly everyone, including Tim Roth as Dahlia's lawyer, harbors secrets. Salles unleashes a torrent of suspense for one purpose: to plumb the violence of the mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6132794?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a sheer ghostly thriller, it's mostly a spell-binder, but I was disappointed at the ending.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050707-movies-review-darkwater,0,2088320.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even as Dark Water's horror-movie component flounders, a different, arguably better kind of thriller emerges.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2210</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brazilian Walter Salles, who previously directed the Oscar-nominated films "Central Station" and "The Motorcycle Diaries," guides this stylish remake through treacherous territory to create a distressing, subtly suspenseful film full of emotional resonance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-dark8jul08,0,7949433.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Builds dread masterfully, but don't expect solace or "fun." This is not for those who like mysteries neatly resolved.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/8525948/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A shudder-by-numbers pseudo-J-horror gothic, full of supernatural stunts you feel as if you've seen before the movie even gets to them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1080046_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This picture doesn't have deep enough currents to succeed as a psychological thriller and, as a ghost story, there are times when it has trouble treading water.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/d/dark_water.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dark Water has more substance and a more interesting look than many horror films, but the familiar elements of the story disappoint.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-07-07-dark-water_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While his movie lacks the psychological resonance of "Rosemary's Baby" or "The Sixth Sense," it easily equals their creep-out quotient.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=359359&amp;reviewId=18440</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike "The Ring," Dark Water -- which features one of the mad, whispery ghost children who populate such films -- is never actually frightening.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=359359&amp;reviewId=18448</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>He [Salles] has managed to create a movie that's pretty bleak for a Hollywood -- especially Disney -- thriller. His theme, as a director, is the indignities of poverty and, in his way, he pays more attention to that agenda than he does in generating any real thrills.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050708/DARKFILM08/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The new version is out of scale with the basic premise -- too much rain, too much water, too much doom, gloom and intricate eccentricity.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Favors character development over rude scares, though given the narrow parameters of the genre, it's not really a worthwhile trade.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28242_DARK_WATER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With his stirring visual sense very much intact here, Salles sets the creepy mood eloquently, but the picture -- ultimately fails to reward all the little shivers with any satisfying jolts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000975598</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>True to form, Salles' version is an intelligent, brooding ghost story brimming with atmosphere, emotions and, above all else, water, but it's disappointingly short on scares.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46116</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something that never quite works about the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/07/AR2005070700663.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dark Water devolves into something resembling genre schlock, albeit the kind featuring zesty supporting performances from the classy, Oscar-nominated likes of John C. Reilly, Tim Roth, and Pete Postlethwaite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8674</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well-crafted but thoroughly unsuspenseful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927578?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The end product is so clunky, scattered, and all-around soggy that sometimes you can't help laughing. At least Connelly and Reilly give their all, and Tim Roth is terrific as a weird lawyer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0708/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you can check your brain at the popcorn stand and keep your expectations low, Dark Water is an OK genre exercise that maintains a consistently creepy tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/49422.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This fake-feminist thriller hides its sadism under a show of sympathy for its beleaguered heroine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.dark08jul08,1,5908930.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the movie is in step with Connelly's aching heroine and not trying to scare our socks off, Dark Water is of a piece with Salles's sensitive filmmaking. Obviously, from a genre standpoint, that presents a tremendous problem. Nobody goes to a horror movie for a good cry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7150</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It fails to deliver the narrative thrill twists its origins would promise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0528,halter,65805,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ed Halter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only the explanation and resolution of the action were more compelling, Dark Water might have been a thriller of the first order.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/07/08/DDGQ2DJSHD1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spins toward its glum, dishwater-gray whirlpool of an ending, which doesn't have nearly as much emotional punch as it should. It doesn't leave you feeling spent -- only soaked.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/07/08/dark_water/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is prettily shot by Almodóvar collaborator Affonso Beato, but no amount of tastefully desaturated color or imaginary friends going whoo-whoo in the deserted apartment upstairs can save this lumbering echt-thriller from fatal tedium.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3465&amp;Sumbit.x=52&amp;Sumbit.y=16</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wildly overproduced and filled with fussy flourishes that make even a derelict hallway look like a million bucks, Dark Water fails to rustle up either meaning or meaningful scares.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/08/movies/08dark.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dark, dank, damp, grim, dingy and dour, Dark Water is a tasteful but unremitting bummer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/07/AR2005070702090.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stripped of every major scary moment and restructured in what feels like a deliberate attempt to remove all suspense, this "horror" movie is now a domestic soap opera.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dark Water isn't a bad horror movie, simply because it isn’t horror at all: a full hour passes before anything remotely scary occurs, and all the suspenseful scenes take place in the final ten minutes (and are all fully shown in the trailer). What's left is tedium and a seemingly endless build-up to nothing much at all, making it a bad movie. Period.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7688</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The overall emotion the film generates is one of moist, enervated ennui. Who cares if the apartment is haunted when the best the ghost can do is get things a bit damp and run laps on the floor above?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A278153</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$25,473,093</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$60,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,939,251</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,657</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>