<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Death of Mr. Lazarescu, The</name>
   <company>Tartan USA</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Cristi Puiu</author>
      <author>Razvan Radulescu</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Cristi Puiu</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Romania</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ion Fiscuteanu</actor>
      <actor>Luminita Gheorghiu</actor>
      <actor>Gabriel Spahiu</actor>
      <actor>Doru Ana</actor>
      <actor>Dana Dogaru</actor>
      <actor>Florin Zamfirescu</actor>
      <actor>Clara Voda</actor>
      <actor>Adrian Titieni</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 26, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>154</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Lazarescu is that rich and riveting a film of universal small human moments and big-system failure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1184986_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both sad and darkly funny, the film is so sharply conceived and richly populated that it often registers like a Frederick Wiseman documentary, even though everything is scripted and every part played by a professional... This is only the second feature of Cristi Puiu, who claims to have been inspired by his own hypochondria, but he's already clearly a master.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/28748_DEATH_OF_MISTER_LAZARESCU</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A heartbreakingly powerful masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0421/p16s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never anything less than wholly engrossing. There's a lot of humor to be found here (primarily of the dark comedy variety) and the cumulative impact of Lazarescu's journey through the Bucharest medical system is quite powerful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2772</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's full of humor, pathos and a deep humanism that comes as a warm blast in this age of lifeless, cinematic junk.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46898&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a black comedy, among the blackest. It is also more grueling in some stretches than anything in "United 93."</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060512-movies-review-death,0,1701836.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "United 93" and the work of the Dardenne brothers, it lives entirely in the moment, seeing what happens as it happens, drawing no conclusions, making no speeches, creating no artificial dramatic conflicts, just showing people living one moment after another, as they must.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060511/REVIEWS/60508009/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is a stunner, so hypnotic that the length hardly matters.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/30/DDGIJJM70O1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Death of Mr. Lazarescu runs the same 2 1/2 hours as "Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest," but what a difference a comic-dramatic purpose makes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.death07jul07,0,5398441.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Devastating, uncompromising and riveting.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/279114_limited28.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A watchful, winding-down tragedy of a movie that delivers what it promises. As commentary, it's grim. As filmmaking, it's a powerfully disturbing odyssey through the Bucharest health care system.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8406</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An intoxicating performance piece in which skilled actors pinball off each other with such energy and nuance that the audience almost forgets about the dying man on the edge of the frame. The style alone makes the movie's point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47868</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Puiu's is the art of the seemingly artless: he takes a story that's utterly unglamorous and mundane, and transforms it into something mythic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/12425496/site/newsweek/page/3/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almost as exhilarating as it is depressing. Puiu's filmmaking technique is remarkable, and all the more so because it's almost invisible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/20/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Picture's dour take on the dehumanizing process of medical treatment is leavened by black humor and dialogue that always rings true.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927143?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Jay Weissberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An explicit ode to mortality, not without a certain grim humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0521,hoberman4,64264,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By recording this all too commonplace and dehumanizing process, Puiu's film shows the sick old man and the strangers who deal with him to be all too human - extraordinarily so.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=524997&amp;reviewId=21003</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thorny masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/26/movies/26deat.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Death of Mr. Lazarescu, for all its terrible matter-of-factness, produces tumultuous feelings of amazement and revolt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060501crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Long, but engrossing and frequently enraging drama that not only exposes the flaws in the Romanian health service, but also in modern humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=132310</url>
         <critic>David Parkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's long, but it's also very real and worth every minute.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1114736&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Philip Kennicott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This Romanian movie defies categorization--it's halfway between a black comedy and a Fred Wiseman documentary. And it haunts you like the ghost of any dead person you've ever ignored.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16858/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike the zippy American medical dramas it apes, The Death of Mr. Lazarescu is paid out with the deliberate slowness of a dray horse straining up a mountain path. With every painstaking turn of the screw that seals Lazarescu's sorry fate, Puiu flirts with tedium, but tedium is the point of this hyperrealist tale, paced in what feels like real time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/dantes-inferno/13426/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it is undeniably bleak and pessimistic and marked by a texture of observation worthy of British director Mike Leigh, The Death of Mr. Lazarescu is not as forbidding as it sounds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-death5may05,0,2025920.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Do not, under any circumstance, approach this film lightly. Prepare to be depressed, agitated and shocked. And prepare to see a brilliant work of cinematic art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8003</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this deep probe into modern-day medicine, the old guy is shuttled from hospital to hospital in a surreal, horrifying ordeal of errors, missed diagnoses and institutional malaise. At two hours and 34 minutes, we, seemingly, also endure his agony -- part of this Romanian film's power and, also, its Achilles heel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000922104</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Death of Mr. Lazarescu is hopelessly depressing. Yet as a story of the callous impersonalization we inflict upon one another, the film is timeless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A383382</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Lazarescu's experience is typical in the former Soviet bloc, democracy hasn't done much to humanize the bureaucracy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/412761p-348937c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Needlessly long, visually drab and not just a foreign-language film, with English subtitles, but a film that's ostensibly foreign to our experience. That said, there are compelling reasons to see it.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's supposed to be about a Kafkaesque experience. Instead, it IS a Kafkaesque experience. Why are we here? Is everything absurd? Is anyone in charge?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/65061.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$80,301</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$7,380</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>