<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Defiance</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Ed Zwick</author>
      <author>Clay Frohman</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ed Zwick</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Daniel Craig</actor>
      <actor>Liev Schreiber</actor>
      <actor>Jamie Bell</actor>
      <actor>Alexa Davalos</actor>
      <actor>Allan Corduner</actor>
      <actor>Mark Feuerstein</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 31, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>137</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an exciting action spectacle and a thoughtful, cumulatively moving family drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/396233_defiance16q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The perfect antidote to the post-holiday blues. It's exciting, well-acted, touching, and genuine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/Defiance</url>
         <critic>Gene Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The battle scenes are well choreographed and contain enough uncertainty to make them genuinely exciting, but one would expect no less from a man who has overseen Civil War engagements (Glory) and Japanese strife (The Last Samurai).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1438</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here, Jews are not victims of genocide, but victors in the organized resistance against it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20090116_Dueling_brothers_battle_Nazis.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Remarkable, unheralded story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/01/movie_review_tough_jews_defian.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film isn't much of a character study; too many of its secondary characters are stereotypes, and it never fully engages our emotions the way "Schindler's List" or "The Pianist" did.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/854072.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a heroic story, and Zwick frames it rather too strenuously as an antidote to the generic Holocaust stories of Jewish passivity and martyrdom. And yet, as a piece of historical redress, a great service has been done in bringing this narrative to the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0117/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's impossible to watch Defiance without experiencing a vicarious thrill of resistance and revenge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/defiance,1138071.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defiance says that it took grit, desperation and courage under fire to say, "Not this time," and fire back. Beyond that, it's a pretty good movie -- a bold, uneasy mix of romance, political debate and vigorous action.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1869229,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defiance, as it turns out, makes insistent emotional demands, and those who respond to it at all, as I did, are likely to go all the way and even come out of it feeling slightly stunned.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/01/12/090112crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zwick offers excitingly staged moments, but once you get past the novelty of WWII Jews acting this heroically macho, Defiance bogs down in a not very well-developed script.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20252492,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zwick may be the definition of a modern blockbuster filmmaker, but he's also spent his entire career struggling to find the balance between opposing impulses – the sentimentalist's desire for emotional-historical heft and the artist's fascination with conflicted humanity – a struggle that's all over Defiance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A725177</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best performance, because it's more nuanced, is by Liev Schreiber. His Zus Bielski is more concerned with the big picture, more ideological, more driven by tactics.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090114/REVIEWS/901149982</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the film's flaws, this is a war story told with passion about a band of brothers that still has the power to inspire.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/21376772/review/25329088/defiance</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film should've aimed higher, given all that these people endured to have their story told.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-defiance-review-0116jan16,0,2666542.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This promising premise is turned into basically an overgrown TV movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12312008/entertainment/movies/resists_nazis__not_clich__233_s_146663.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tale of the resistance movement in Belorussia is undeniably inspiring and ideally suited for a cinematic rendering. But Defiance resists bold, passionate storytelling and delivers something rather conventional.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-12-30-defiance_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A Holocaust film that's light on sentimentality but high on human drama, Defiance tells one of those remarkable survival stories that's so incredible it must be true.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/defiance/review/296310</url>
         <critic>Jason Buchanan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are subtitles and vaguely East European accents; there is romance and rebirth, tears and regular pauses for gallows humor (at which we Jews are known to be very good, on account of our long history of persecution).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-12-31/film/from-reverence-to-rape-in-defiance-and-good/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an inspiring story, if one that doesn't need quite as much poetic inspiration as Ed Zwick's movie insists on giving it, with dialogue that's too often ornate and parable-inflected.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=98699832</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That butting of heads, as performed by actors as strong and soulful as Craig and Schreiber, lends Defiance an emotional charge, even as the film itself struggles dramatically to find its way out of those woods.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11947</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Craig, far from James Bond but still swaggering, makes a leathery, craggy commander, and Schreiber - who'll show his full-on action chops this summer in the Hugh Jackman "Wolverine" movie - is tough but sullen. Yet all this old-style moviemaking doesn't always pay off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/12/31/2008-12-31_brothers_in_arms_fight_third_reich_in_de.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An amazing true tale is somewhat diminished by second-hand storytelling: entirely admirable, largely entertaining, and yet curiously hollow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135639</url>
         <critic>Nev Pierce</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defiance comes off as plodding and workmanlike -- and even in the midst of Zwick's too-careful machinations, it's a movie that's unsure of what it wants to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/01/16/defiance/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Depressingly predictable in its dialogue and dramatic beats, Defiance is most interesting as a study of unlikely leaders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12174</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zwick, intent on correcting the perception of Jews as passive victims, lets the action set pieces overwhelm the more intimate scenes, several of which are already diminished by stilted dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34035_DEFIANCE.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a drama - an epic drama, no less, clocking in at 137 minutes - its fascination is diffused, and the movie becomes something of a long slog.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/01/15/DD0615AEKU.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie leaves you in an awful tangle of amazement and disbelief: Amazement that Tuvia Bielski did turn a group of civilians into a nimble fighting force and a commune that could defend itself, but disbelief at his accomplishment's stagey and banal rendering.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.defiance16jan16,0,3706041.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What is puzzling is how Edward Zwick has taken an extraordinary real-life story about a handful of people who defied huge odds, and turned it into an utterly conventional war movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090116.wdefiance16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A little sentimentality can fuel a lot of action, yet Zwick buries his film in cloying guilt, in the end sinking Defiance with the holocaust film's bait.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11477</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are lots of movies about Jews suffering, dying, and surviving in Europe during World War II, but precious few about Jews fighting back. So why does everything in Defiance feel so doggedly familiar?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/defiance</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defiance has some genuine strengths but also some weaker elements, and these opposing traits battle it out kind of the way the contentious Bielskis fought not only the Germans but each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-defiance31-2008dec31,0,6619282.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A potentially exceptional story is told in a flatly unexceptional manner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938977.html?categoryid=3266&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Defiance</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defiance presents itself as an explicit correction of the cultural record, a counterpoint to all those lachrymose World War II tales of helplessness and victimhood. 
This is a perfectly honorable intention, but the problem is that, in setting out to overturn historical stereotypes of Jewish passivity, Mr. Zwick (who co-wrote the screenplay with Clayton Frohman) ends up affirming them.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/12/31/movies/31defi.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$28,644,813</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$50,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$200,614</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>