<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Definitely, Maybe</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Adam Brooks</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Adam Brooks</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ryan Reynolds</actor>
      <actor>Isla Fisher</actor>
      <actor>Derek Luke</actor>
      <actor>Abigail Breslin</actor>
      <actor>Elizabeth Banks</actor>
      <actor>Rachel Weisz</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 14, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sweet, funny, simple, entertaining -- everything a good rom-com should be. Definitely...</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135463</url>
         <critic>Sam Toy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Keeps you interested in its characters and isn’t afraid of complicating your sympathies a little. In these dog-day months for romantic comedy, that means a lot.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-definitely-maybe/305265/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Absolutely, probably more comfortable with human romantic complication than the usual stuff released on Valentine's Day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20177957,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sophisticated story of disappointment and accommodation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/02/13/DD5PV18BU.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brooks' take on the ups and downs of modern romance and the unexpected turns it takes is smart, funny, and (above all) uncommon. It's not hard to recommend this on Valentine's Day or at any other time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/d/definitely_maybe.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lot fresher and bit more sophisticated than the ordinary run of maudlin chick flicks and crude gross-out sex farces that now pass for romantic comedies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/definitely-maybe/review/292344</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All three actresses are appealing, but Fisher, proving her scene-stealing turn in Wedding Crashers was no fluke, shines brightest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-li.definitely14feb14,0,3896924.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Definitely, Maybe gets too coy in spots, and Brooks is a sharper writer at this point in his career than he is a director. But for a film with a half-dozen fully-formed characters that spans 15 years and works in a swell detail about a 1943 edition of "Jane Eyre" - well, it definitely works. No maybes about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080214_Witty__tender__definitely_cute.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Put simply, the film excels most at not being awful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/definitely_maybe</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In serious roles, Weisz can be stiff-backed and righteous, but here, doing comedy, she appears to be a major actress eager to reveal everything she’s been holding inside.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/03/03/080303crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A nimble and winning little romance</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/02/14/movies/14maybe.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprisingly rewarding romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0807,wilonsky,79098,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A pleasingly non-formulaic romantic seriocomedy, Definitely, Maybe has charm and some depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935908.html?categoryid=1019&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The flashback itself is a romantic dramedy that's far smarter than junk like "27 Dresses." Unfortunately, to enjoy that flashback, you have to ignore two gargantuan idiocies: No sane father would twist his daughter into knots by telling this story. It's full of booze, cigarettes, infidelity and sex with women who aren't Mom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1202952306199000.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe it's a measure of the numbing awfulness of romantic comedies in general lately, but Definitely, Maybe isn't nearly so bad as you might fear; it's actually fairly pleasant, a bit too off-color to be a family film but enjoyable just the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/418766.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe writer-director Adam Brooks has made a fluffy Woody Allen pastiche here, but it's arguably more pleasing than anything Allen himself has done lately.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10587</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a decent Valentine's date-night flick, and should earn Reynolds the attention he'll need to snare stronger leading roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/02/14/2008-02-14_ryan_reynolds_is_stuck_in_the_wrong_movi.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the plus side, Definitely, Maybe has an appealing cast, some amusing scenes and at least tries to do something different.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02142008/entertainment/movies/little_miss_matchmaker_97539.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's generally enjoyable, amusing and more sophisticated than most films in this genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-02-13-definitely-maybe_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One thing the movie does well is skewer Bill Clinton. Though Hayes works for him and nominally defends him to detractors, we see old sins rehashed: Gennifer Flowers, Monica Lewinsky, his impeachment.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=1017753&amp;reviewId=null&amp;startDate=02%2F13%2F2008</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a film bound and determined to do whatever it takes to be your Valentine. If it had trusted itself more, it might even have succeeded.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-definitely14feb14,0,3212648.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is far from a complete washout, and this is chiefly a tribute to its immensely attractive and appealing cast. Ryan Reynolds proves to have the stuff of a true leading. man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=J6fpHwZTb81dpnFndmLXZz1JGhxVzJrfDh7PqPwpdnLxTJtJSJF8!900300817&amp;&amp;rid=10614</url>
         <critic>Stephen Farber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reynolds can't help looking rather shifty as he relates his story and Breslin, who was so wonderful in Little Miss Sunshine, is obliged to play a standard-issue wise child.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1713424,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Abigail Breslin, the preteen Oscar nominee for "Little Miss Sunshine" and the most effortless actress of her generation, plays the precocious little girl part without overdoing the precociousness.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/351148_definitely14q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Our mission, should we choose to accept it, is to guess which gal became the wife, which gal should have become the wife and which gal is there just to play with our heads. It's exactly like that old shell game – mildly diverting, pea-sized and otherwise hollow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080214.wdefinitely14/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>May be the first midlife crisis movie for Generation X.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/02/14/definitely/</url>
         <critic>Mary Elizabeth Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There’s a surprising – and truthful – melancholic undercurrent to Definitely, Maybe – the one commonality between the three women is the heartbreak they induce – but Brooks undermines that truthfulness with a dogmatic insistence upon romantic mythologizing. No maybes about it: The reality is far darker, and more interesting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A587896</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a romantic comedy, Definitely, Maybe is an explosion of sweetness and hugs that might cause your stomach to churn if you don't like your sentimentality too strong.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10766</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Isn't terrible exactly, but it's bland, and in some ways that's worse. It's a romance posing as a detective story in which the solution is obvious and not worth the fuss.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0215/p12s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This highly uneven comedy by writer-director Adam Brooks might be easier to take if it were less infatuated with its own cuteness.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32724_DEFINITELY_MAYBE.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To sum up, Definitely, Maybe is crap with compensations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15138032/review/18419632/definitely_maybe</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Definitely an overlong exercise in the concept of kismet, and maybe it's just what you want, in lieu of chocolates.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139579&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no maybe about its standing as romantic comedy -- definitely bad.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120303058668769883.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$32,241,649</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$7,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$12,883,475</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,204</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>