<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Departed, The</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>William Monahan</author>
      <author>Siu Fai Mak and Felix Chong</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Martin Scorsese</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Leonardo DiCaprio</actor>
      <actor>Matt Damon</actor>
      <actor>Jack Nicholson</actor>
      <actor>Mark Wahlberg</actor>
      <actor>Martin Sheen</actor>
      <actor>Ray Winstone</actor>
      <actor>Vera Farmiga</actor>
      <actor>Alec Baldwin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 6, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>149</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A new American crime classic from the legendary Martin Scorsese, whose talent shines here on its highest beams.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/10370647/review/11894453/the_departed</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A ferociously entertaining film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003189319</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Departed is Scorsese's most purely enjoyable movie in years. But it's not for the faint of heart. It's rude, bleak, violent and defiantly un-PC. But if you doubt that it's also OK to laugh throughout this rat's nest of paranoia, deceit and bloodshed, keep your eyes on the final frames. Scorsese's parting shot is an uncharacteristic, but well-earned, wink.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15078349/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The original film was gritty and entertaining ("Infernal Affairs"); the new version is a masterpiece - the best effort Scorsese has brought to the screen since "Goodfellas."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/d/departed.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A triumphant revisiting of territory in which Scorsese is an unchallenged master -- the crime drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3153/the-departed.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>DiCaprio harnesses a terrific, buggy intensity reminiscent of "GoodFellas'" hopped-up Henry Hill (Ray Liotta).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/best-of-la-2006/-cops-and-robbers/14705/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When a director of Scorsese's caliber is working at the top of his game, it's a reminder of why we go to the movies in the first place.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/53743</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The screenplay, by William Monahan, is simply sensational. Scenes play brilliantly. Feelings flow like molten lava. The dialogue overflows with edgy wit and acidulous arias of imprecation.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the most vibrant, exciting and invigorating movie-movie of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=713289&amp;reviewId=21566</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie-movie of the first rank.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/10-06-2006/entertainment/col/story/459043p-386056c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thelma Schoonmaker, a Scorsese collaborator for over a quarter-century, did the bull's-eye editing. The moviemaking throughout is swift, unaffected, masterly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.departed06oct06,0,3624353.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thrilling return to form.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=283573&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is intriguing to wonder what Scorsese saw in the Hong Kong movie that inspired him to make the second remake of his career (after "Cape Fear"). I think he instantly recognized that this story, at a buried level, brought two sides of his art and psyche into equal focus.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070705/REVIEWS/70705002/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It isn't in the same league as the director's best work, chiefly because it lacks the bravura flourishes of cinematic craft that helped make his name. But it's so vital and bloody and funny and wicked and tense and unapologetic that it feels kin to those films, which little of the director's work of the past decade has managed to pull off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1159991705129770.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever it is, the film is the first major release of the fall worth talking about: a fast-paced, visually slick, psychologically fascinating Boston-set cops-and-crooks saga.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/287664_departed06q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The very title The Departed suggests a James Joycean take on Irish-Catholic sentiment when, of course, this story is anything but: It's Scorsesean, and he's in full bloom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1542479_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>DiCaprio's performance is a revelation only for those who have underestimated him. In Scorsese's previous films, "The Gangs of New York" and "The Aviator," he seemed callow and miscast, but here he has the presence of a full-bodied adult. He's grown into his emotions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1006/p11s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This reworking of a popular Hong Kong picture pulses with energy, tangy dialogue and crackling performances from a fine cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931747?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scorsese didn't need to remake "Infernal Affairs," but what he has done with it is a compliment rather than an affront to the original: The Departed reimagines its source material rather than just leeching off it, preserving the bone structure of the first movie while finding new curves in it. The story has been clarified; the ellipses of the original have been filled in with just the right amount of exploratory shading. This is a picture of grand gestures and subtle intricacies, a movie that, even at more than two hours long, feels miraculously lean. It's a smart shot of lucid storytelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/10/06/departed/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a dream cast for both Scorsese and the viewer, and everyone is working at the peak of their craft. Nicholson's flawless performance as the increasingly unhinged crime boss is a marvel of manic, paranoid ruination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A407119</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When The Departed roars to life, as it does in so many of its scenes, you feel like nobody understands movies -- the delirious highs, the unforgiving moral depths -- as well as this man does. Welcome back, Marty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9191</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The profanity-laced but witty and literate dialogue by William Monahan ("Kingdom of Heaven") is delivered by a brilliantly chosen cast, almost all of whom are operating at the very top of their game.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10052006/entertainment/movies/dearly_departed_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's score and editing brilliantly heighten the film's energy, keeping the audience somewhat off-kilter and unsure where things are headed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-10-05-review-the-departed_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a movie with a pulse. Sometimes, it flies off the chart.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=713289&amp;reviewId=21564</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What helps make The Departed at once a success and a relief isn't that the director of "Kundun," Mr. Scorsese's deeply felt film about the Dalai Lama, is back on the mean streets where he belongs; what's at stake here is the film and the filmmaking, not the director's epic importance.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/10/06/movies/06depa.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frequently excessive but never dull, The Departed is a little too much of a lot of the things that define Martin Scorsese films but it's also almost impossible to resist. Too operatic at times, too in love with violence and macho posturing at others, it's a potboiler dressed up in upscale designer clothes, but oh how that pot does boil.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-departed6oct06,0,3866997.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Crackles right along, stopping only long enough for Scorsese's signature bursts of explosive violence. Those brawls feel a bit rote, but what's different here is a newfound playful humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1124068&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie works smashingly, especially if you haven't seen its Hong Kong counterpart and haven't a clue what's coming. But for all its snap, crackle, and pop, it's nowhere near as galvanic emotionally.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/21979/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Back to the streets and with a stellar cast, Martin Scorsese proves once again that he's the master of urban storytelling -- and of thrillingly violent filmmaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=10616</url>
         <critic>Roberto Sadovski</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not one of Scorsese's greatest films; it doesn't use the camera to reveal the psychological and aesthetic dimensions of an entire world, as "Mean Streets," "Taxi Driver," "Raging Bull," and "Goodfellas" did. But it's a viciously merry, violent, high-wattage entertainment, and speech is the most brazenly flamboyant element in it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?061016crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Departed exists in a movie-place about as far from personal statements as a storied director can get. Maybe those days for Scorsese are long gone. But Scorsese's sense of craft remains sure.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061006-movies-review-departed,0,5675501.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no attempt at greatness here, just a fabulously successful attempt at a good crime movie. The Oscar-bait self-consciousness of "Gangs of New York" and "The Aviator" is gone. In its place is a buoyancy, an impish delight in telling a harsh urban story in the most effective terms possible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/10/06/DDGQHLIDDB1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Departed is completely engrossing, a master class in suspense. But in moral terms it may be the least involving story that Scorsese -- an artist much preoccupied with morality -- has ever taken on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/061006/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This isn't to say The Departed is a bad movie, far from it, but knowing who's directing it and the amount of talent he had to work with, it's hard not to be disappointed that Scorsese didn't knock us on our asses. Is it his best movie since "Goodfellas?" Sure, but it falls shy of that film's excellence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9345</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's nice to see Scorsese back in the saddle and a treat to find a cops-and-robbers thriller with some energy and wit. But even so, it's a stylish head rush of a movie that flies by, even at two-and-a-half hours, and keeps turning the knife (and your stomach) up to the final scene.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2151037</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rarely has a star's look-at-me turn so completely torpedoed a project. Whenever the picture threatens to gain some momentum, up pops Jack to stop it dead in its tracks. The loyal few may be laughing with him, but the rest of us are definitely laughing at him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061006.DEPART06/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neither a debacle nor a bore, The Departed works but only up to a point, and never emotionally--even if the director does contrive to supply his version of a happy ending.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0640,hoberman,74637,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scorsese in his prime might've made better use of this hamming, but this picture feels like an exercise by a Scorsese clone who has tackled the master's themes - without his energy and economy of style.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=713289&amp;reviewId=21561&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Is Scorsese desperate? This screenplay has the scent of it, as if he is scraping for material to feed his basic filmic interests. But the risk in this case--not evaded--was that his need led him close to painful strain. I can't remember another Scorsese moment as shockingly banal as the finishing touch here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20061030&amp;s=kauffmann103006</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$133,311,000</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$90,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$26,887,467</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,017</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jack nicholson</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>3</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>alec baldwin</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>matt damon</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>jack nicholson</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>