<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Deuce Bigalow: European Gigolo</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Rob Schneider</author>
      <author>David Garrett</author>
      <author>Jason Ward</author>
      <author>Harris Goldberg</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Mike Bigelow</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Rob Schneider</actor>
      <actor>Eddie Griffin</actor>
      <actor>Jeroen Krabbé</actor>
      <actor>Til Schweiger</actor>
      <actor>Hanna Verboom</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 12, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>77</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Definitely merits its R rating with a fearless approach that will earn genuine laughs as it turns a few stomachs. Yes, a Rob Schneider movie that's funny. Strange but true.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As before, there are moments, when Schneider is turned loose to do his anything-goes, creepy-funny shtick, that are crudely inspired.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3501&amp;Sumbit.x=57&amp;Sumbit.y=5</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Godfather II of manwhore sequels, this improves upon the original in every way. Especially if you're drunk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=10965</url>
         <critic>Chris Hewitt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While sloppier than the sloppiest of seconds, is laudable in one important regard: Its obsession with the male body.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1092065_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Every bit as vulgar, sophomoric and thoroughly tasteless as 1999's Deuce Bigalow: Male Gigolo.  But what is most annoying is the sequel's capability of inducing laughter even as one hates oneself for so easily succumbing to the total silliness of it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001013776</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Mike Bigelow maintains a mercifully swift pace, and while the film's humor is deliberately as crass as humanly possible, it is not truly mean-spirited, even though Amsterdam is depicted as a modern-day Sodom and Gomorrah.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules12aug12,0,2289341.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amazingly, amidst the smutty silliness, there are some laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-08-11-bigalow-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Penis jokes fly fast and furious, and while they're hit-or-miss they're occasionally very funny. Schneider always plays a variation of the same put-upon schlemiel, a formula that worked fine for, well, Buster Keaton and Harold Lloyd.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28345_DEUCE_BIGALOW_EUROPEAN_GIGOLO.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You don't have to rise very high to get above the level of these gags.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/336682p-287362c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the worst scenes in Deuce Bigalow: European Bigalow, it's as if Schneider and Co. are straining to invent new taboos just so they can break them, a strategy that provokes more confused silence than laughter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050812/DEUCE12/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's perhaps most surprising about European Gigolo is its reactionary streak, exemplified by knee-jerk attacks on Europe's equally knee-jerk anti-Americanism. Then again, that seems fitting. The sequel functions as the ultimate Ugly American, good for a few cheap, vulgar laughs and nothing else.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/25622</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is an essential meanness to the entire project, tapping the manipulative power of taunts. Such jokes don't jibe with the times, the culture.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/08/12/movies/12deuc.html</url>
         <critic>Janet Maslin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rude, crude and, uh, cosmopolitan, Deuce Bigalow: European Gigolo waves the flag for R-rated politically incorrect studio comedy but doesn't top the laugh ratio of the first Deuce misadventure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927883?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not Deuce's satisfied clientele, but the audience, that gets the shaft.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081101084.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director is first-timer Mike Bigelow. Nothing's paced or shaped for maximum payoff; the shooting and editing rhythms add only clutter and noise, and the slapstick is strictly of the skull-banging, ear-splitting variety.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050811-movies-review-deuce,0,4716493.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At times, "European Gigolo" feels more like an international incident than a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/08/12/DDG2JE611U1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not to chastise the movie for simply being rude or crude -- since "The Wedding Crashers" proved that hormone-raging '80s throwbacks can still be harmless fun -- but this contemptible sex-com redux should be taken to task for how its infantilized yucks give license to entertaining closed-minded acceptances of very real human ugliness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2234</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This bare-bones plot is merely an excuse to string together a series of gross-out jokes involving bodily fluids, private parts, food and genetic deformities.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46340</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If all the first "Deuce" had going for it was a regular-guy approach to over-the-top humor, that's completely absent in this follow-up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7143</url>
         <critic>Janice Page</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The way I see it, anyone who's made up his mind to see Deuce Bigalow: European Gigolo deserves everything they've got coming to them, and with any luck, they might even enjoy the movie's willfully offensive gutter humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=386094&amp;reviewId=18805</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A vile and laughless follow-up to Schneider's  1999 hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/51719.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Speaking in my official capacity as a Pulitzer Prize winner, Mr. Schneider, your movie sucks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050811/REVIEWS/50725001/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not that there are any actual jokes to be had. The film simply jumps to the punch lines, a non-stop barrage of crude dialogue and vulgar sight gags that passes as humor among adolescent boys. Who exactly is the audience for this R-rated film? The terminally immature?</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/236233_deuce12q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an unimaginative, mean-spirited gross-out that forgot to bring the funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0533,tracking5,66910,20.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not content to merely be lowbrow and stupid – there's room in the world for lowbrow and stupid mass entertainment – the film is pushy and might actually cause chafing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A283686</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$22,400,154</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$22,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,626,287</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,127</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>