<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Disturbia</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures / DreamWorks SKG</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Christopher B. Landon</author>
      <author>Carl Ellsworth</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>D.J. Caruso</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Shia LaBeouf</actor>
      <actor>David Morse</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Roemer</actor>
      <actor>Carrie-Anne Moss</actor>
      <actor>Matt Craven</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 11, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>104</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Breakfast Club meets Rear Window. The result should satisfy dating crowds from high school to night school.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.disturbia13apr13,0,6432083.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's plenty to ensure fresh jolts for viewers who know Hitch's tricks inside out, to say nothing of young moviegoers who don't know Grace Kelly from Thelma Ritter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8900</url>
         <critic>John DeFore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One way you know that D.J. Caruso is a resourceful director is that he scares you silly with a minimum of violence and a few smears of blood. His job was certainly made easier by Morse, whose glassy demeanor and high, soft rasp suggests horrors that not even Quentin Tarantino could imagine.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/30321/index2.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The bloody wrap-up isn't handled especially well, and I must confess that the most shocking thing about the movie was the casting of Carrie-Anne Moss as a suburban mom. I kept expecting her "Matrix" skills to show up in the final reel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0413/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cool stuff. Cool movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/10267145/review/14030346/disturbia</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it's not likely to become a classic like the Hitchcock film, it's a smart and well-acted teen thriller that serves up some lively scares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-04-12-disturbia_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Morse, with his hulking frame, baby face and soft voice, has probably done too many of these villain roles for his own good. But how could you avoid casting him when he manages to present someone who's screamingly insane in the mildest, most pleasant way?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070413.wdisturb13/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Disturbia lacks in complexity, it makes up for in witty jokes, sneaky jolts and a timeless lesson: If you've got windows, someone's always watching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/04/13/2007-04-13_nightmare_in_suburbia.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At a certain point, movies like Disturbia require suspension of belief. To its credit, that moment comes much later in the game than usual. Up until then, like "Rear Window" before it, Disturbia is sly and suspenseful and full of mounting dread.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20070413_Like_Rear_Window_with_ankle_bracelet.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caruso, a very visual director, serves up some surprises and scares, and he's paced his movie briskly. You're out of this disturbing suburbia before you know it, shaken and even stirred.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/04/13/DDGKPP738P1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once the plot finally kicks into gear, director D.J. Caruso (Taking Lives) effectively cranks up the tension.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/disturbia</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The battery of startling shock cuts can get repetitive and the plot has a few potholes, but the palpable atmosphere of vulnerability keeps the drama knotted in tension and the audience rooted to the teens in peril.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/311556_disturbia13q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It did a great job of giving chills and making me jump. It may not be the most original film out there, but which ones out there today are completely original anyways?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9950</url>
         <critic>Zach Haddad</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are no big surprises, but the jumps and jolts are well timed and the overall mood is at once grisly and good-natured -- more diverting than disturbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/movies/13dist.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Squirmingly fun suspenser that brings Alfred Hitchcock's "Rear Window" into the era of vidcams and cell phones, serving up hearty, youth-skewing portions of PG-13 violence and bikini-bait along the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933143.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=%22Disturbia%3A</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If it's possible to be a rip-off with wit, Disturbia qualifies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20034459,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A nice little mystery thriller that takes a wrong turn on the way to its climax and morphs into a slasher movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/d/disturbia.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does so many things right that it's a shame to see it sink into horror-movie cliches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/disturbia/review/286994</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of leaving you lamenting the lack of creativity and originality in the film industry, this modest, playful thriller puts you in a forgiving mood.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=2A58CE98B9EA58848F1B149FF94C9B71.prodapp12_ae_01?id=850933&amp;reviewId=22396&amp;startDate=04%2F13%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's not one single bombshell dropped in Disturbia; everyone is exactly who you think they are and does exactly what you think they'll do precisely when you think they'll do it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0715,wilonsky,76334,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most disturbious part of Disturbia is how engaging this teenage thriller manages to be, even though it's a shameless rip-off of "Rear Window."</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're happy to watch a thriller about a tenth as good as Alfred Hitchcock's, director D.J. Caruso and screenwriters Christopher B. Landon and Carl Ellsworth hold up their end of the deal, at least until the proceedings devolve into standard horror-movie effects and minimal motivations.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31411_DISTURBIA.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are a few decent jolts in Disturbia, but overall this ultra-predictable thriller doesn't live up to the hype.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04132007/entertainment/movies/pain_in_the_rear_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Up-and-comer LaBeouf (Holes) is a young actor to watch, but he's had better opportunities than this teen thriller to show what he's capable of.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A464353</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its glitz and gadgets, is markedly inferior in everything but teen appeal.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070413-movies-review-disturbia,0,3595646.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>LaBeouf is appealing as the frustrated shut-in, and comic-relief cred goes to Aaron Yoo, who plays his neurotic buddy Ronnie. The ending, though, drags, and the film quickly shifts from a clever homage to "Rear Window" to a bad parody of "The Silence of the Lambs."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1133612&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Maynard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Rear Window" never comes up in the Disturbia press notes, which is probably just as well since it steals that movie's premise but none of Alfred Hitchcock's wit, finesse, or seduction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9120</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the new movie lacks in craft, suspense and metaphoric richness it makes up for with, um, gadgets.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-disturbia13apr13,0,4547660.story</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$80,209,692</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$22,224,982</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,925</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>