<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dixie Chicks: Shut Up and Sing</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Barbara Kopple</director>
      <director>Cecilia Peck</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Natalie Maines</actor>
      <actor>Emily Robison</actor>
      <actor>Martie Maguire</actor>
      <actor>Rick Rubin</actor>
      <actor>George W. Bush</actor>
      <actor>Simon Renshaw</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 27, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>99</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Documentary filmmakers pray for something to happen to their subjects when the cameras are rolling, and two-time Academy Award-winning documentarian Kopple struck gold when Maines told a crowd on the opening night of the band's first European tour that she was "ashamed" that President Bush was from Texas.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/11/17/DDGQKMDIME1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Joel Selvin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Dixie Chicks may never regain their prolonged eminence on the country charts. However, the art and entertainment value of this movie (and of their latest album) is off the charts in the best way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.shutup08dec08,0,2242410.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film may be subtitled "Shut Up &amp; Sing," but you can't sing with your mouth closed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1027/p16s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it's unlikely that her film will sway former fans who swore off the band for political reasons, that seems beside the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284106&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Angel Cohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For three years, the camera focuses on the Chicks as wives, mothers, entertainers and political flash points. Their fight to stay uncompromised is inspiring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/11693808/review/12221842/shut_up_and_sing</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A seriously entertaining highlight of the fall season.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061117-movies-review-sing,0,6506642.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary shows what a tight-knit group the Chicks are.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071018/REVIEWS/71019002</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Barbara Kopple and Cecilia Peck's film is a fascinating look at the intersection of commerce, celebrity, and controversy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9558</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Through it all, Natalie Maines' decision to shirk humility, to stick by her guns, to the point that the group returns to that London concert venue in 2006 and she utters the same joke again, becomes a feisty and inspiring act of something there is only one word for: patriotism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1550553_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a mind-bending odyssey ensues--a tale of good old-fashioned American free expression at war with good old-fashioned American capitalism.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/23780/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The filmmakers are clearly in awe of the Chicks' fighting spirit. If you think Maines's original Bush remark was disrespectful, wait till you hear what she calls him here. Maines is not ready to make nice, and neither is this riveting documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15460889/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie endorses the liberal conception of the Chicks as free-speech heroes, which doesn't quite wash: Maines shot her mouth off to a receptive overseas crowd, then issued an apology as soon as the backlash began back home.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#30770</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the advertising plays up the film's Bush-bashing angle, it gives a false impression. This is really more of a backstage drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A420843</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fact that you might emerge from the theater eager to give their albums a listen is a testament to how effective this lively and stirring movie about freedom of speech really is.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=757844&amp;reviewId=21803</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most importantly, Shut Up &amp; Sing is about what happens in the music industry to people who won't.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=757844&amp;reviewId=21883&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both the Chicks and this doc are left to deal with the aftermath as best they can. The film chooses to pad with an occasional over-reliance on cutesy filler -- a pregnant Emily having an ultra-sound, giving birth, recuperating at her beloved ranch away from it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061027.SING27/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maines' big mouth and winning candor got her into trouble, but Shut Up &amp; Sing suffers from filmmakers who are intent on playing it safe.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/54552</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While there is a vague hint of a vanity project in a few extraneous scenes, directors Barbara Kopple and Cecilia Peck have fashioned a compelling and rousing film that will not only appeal to Chicks fans, but make fans of those who weren't before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-10-26-review-shut-up_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As insightful as it is entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/465614p-391687c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sharper and far more entertaining than most political documentaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10272006/entertainment/movies/amid_clucking__dixie_chicks_rise_up_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie offers a revealing case study of the relationship between politics, celebrity and the media in today’s polarized social climate.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/10/27/movies/27chic.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kopple and Peck went on and off the road with the band for the three years of waffling, agonizing and defiance in between Maines’ mouth-offs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14926/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the excellent attributes of Shut Up &amp; Sing is that it lets the cards fall where they may and really doesn't try to spin the Chicks themselves. It's quite possible, then, to watch the film and come to the conclusion that Maines has a big mouth. Spectacularly talented, the young singer is also a spectacular blowhard.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1127847&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the rare thorough documentary on a musical act whose dilemmas are faced in the here and now, one that should win over fans of the Chicks on the fence and of music docus and perhaps create a little cultural stir as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931462.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Phil Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sympathetic, engaging documentary.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joanne Kaufman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An inspiring story of pluck, but its politics fall flat.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/292638_sing17q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's not quite the Bush bashfest its publicity might lead you to believe; it's closer to the Metallica doc "Some Kind of Monster" than to "Fahrenheit 9/11."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0643,thompson,74822,20.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,215,045</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$50,103</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>