<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dominion: Prequel to the Exorcist</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures Inc.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Caleb Carr</author>
      <author>William Wisher Jr.</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paul Schrader</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Stellan Skarsgård</actor>
      <actor>Gabriel Mann</actor>
      <actor>Clara Bellar</actor>
      <actor>Billy Crawford</actor>
      <actor>Ralph Brown</actor>
      <actor>Israel Aduramo</actor>
      <actor>Andrew French</actor>
      <actor>Antonie Kamerling</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 20, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>111</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The material is right up Schrader's alley, and while his vision of the first "Exorcist" chapter isn't a masterpiece, it's far superior to the Renny Harlin prequel to "The Exorcist" released last year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0520/p15s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may not have been what the producers had in mind, but they asked for a Paul Schrader movie, and that's exactly what he delivered.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8521</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of cheap thrills, Schrader gives us a frightening vision of a good priest who fears goodness may not be enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050519/REVIEWS/50412001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a good, thoughtful horror picture--and thiiis close to being a very good one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2119325/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The strengths of Dominion, however, have been little diminished by its long shelf life and, in fact, may have grown stronger with age.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/05/26/film-foundas.php</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not bad. It actually might have been considered pretty good had it been made 30 years ago, when people might have cared about the backstory of Father Merrin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/05-20-2005/entertainment/col/story/311301p-266164c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Result is hardly a diabolical failure, if not quite a heavenly masterpiece. Schrader's intelligent, quietly subversive pic emphasizes spiritual agony over horror ecstasy, while paying occasional lip-service to the need for scares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926588?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Leslie Felperin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film will come to share the video store shelf with Harlin's infinitely stupider rendition soon enough, but it's a shame they couldn't have been released theatrically head-to-head -- a death match-cum-clinical trial that might've supplied some objective stats on how much condescension the American moviegoer actually enjoys.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0520,atkinson1,64010,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instantly forgettable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-dominion20may20,0,3862210.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Schrader, in Auto Focus, displayed a devious sense of sin, but in Dominion the Calvinist schoolboy in him insists on trumping sin with guilt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1062886_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe nothing here is supposed to be as scary as in the 1973 movie because this is merely the opening act. That's the problem with prequels, isn't it? It's like being asked to pay full price just to watch batting practice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/44255.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Awfully dull, with scant evidence of the sort of things that make horror movies attractive -- like mounting suspense and spine-tingling creepiness and, oh yeah, the element of horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000928907</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no escaping that "Dominion" is finally an act of commercial scavenging. You may retrieve the eggshells, coffee grounds and banana peels from your trash and assemble them into a cute, novelty gift basket. But if you bend down and take a whiff, your nose is still met with the scent of garbage.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/05/20/movies/20domi.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The verdict: More thoughtful than Harlin's version, but hardly the invigorating mix of shocks and metaphysical horror needed to revitalize the Exorcist franchise.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46125</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's chatty when it wants to pretend it's deep and spiritual, messy when it's striving for chaotic and thrilling, and boring when it has no other options left.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Devoid of thrills, and with nothing even vaguely frightening to distract moviegoers, it becomes clear that the story wasn't worth telling in the first place.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/05/23/DDG9FCSGD91.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$251,495</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$138,311</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>110</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>