<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Don&amp;#039;t Come Knocking</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sam Shepard</author>
      <author>Wim Wenders</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Wim Wenders</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>GermanyUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sam Shepard</actor>
      <actor>Jessica Lange</actor>
      <actor>Tim Roth</actor>
      <actor>Gabriel Mann</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Polley</actor>
      <actor>Fairuza Balk</actor>
      <actor>Eva Marie Saint</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 17, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>122</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beautifully shot in rich colors by Franz Lustig, it's possibly Wenders' most accessible film to date, and among his most emotionally satisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46794</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its wonderful veteran cast, its heart on its sleeve, and a love for the landscape that suffuses its technique, Don't Come Knocking is a peculiar but rewarding escape.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A356365</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something a little absurd about this story, but for me, it's endearingly goofy.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060407-movies-review-knocking,0,1734154.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shepard's charisma has always reached back to an earlier time, so it's easy to accept him as a kind of pre-counterculture hero - Eastwood without the sneer - who aged into the era of tabloid scandal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1173438_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filled with haunting visual panoramas. One of the most resonant is a nighttime shot of the Elko skyline dominated by a glittering casino. Evoking a once and future gold rush, it says more about the Old West and the New West than all of Mr. Shepard's elliptical, stagy dialogue can muster. Such powerful images make Don't Come Knocking well worth contemplating.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/17/movies/17knoc.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't Come Knocking expresses itself with deadpan humor, striking imagery, Western iconography and outbursts of strong emotions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000928910</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It has long been clear that Shepard is a rare double talent. He has flourished, rightly, as a playwright, and he is also a compelling film actor. His face does more for the reality of this picture than anything he wrote in the script.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060417&amp;s=kauffmann041706</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It rarely strikes the right tone and ultimately falls short of what one would expect from a collaboration between director Wim Wenders and writer Sam Shepard.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.knocking19may19,0,7879612.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Judged on any kind of rational level, this film is a mess, and Fairuza Balk, as a punky friend of Howard's son, gives the single most annoying performance I have ever seen. But Franz Lustig's cinematography has a Walker Evans-like power.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0317/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are scenes that don't even pretend to work. And others that have a sweetness and visual beauty that stops time and simply invites you to share.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060406/REVIEWS/60403004/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The finest scene in Don't Come Knocking is its quietest...The movie could have used a lot more of it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8055</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>T Bone Burnett's soundtrack has the appropriate twang to give Wenders' Hopperesque tableaux a nice, filmic poetry. But as arresting as the images are, Shepard's clunky, soap-opera banter brings most everything, and everyone, crashing down to earth.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=569025&amp;reviewId=20502</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Superb supporting performances from Polley and Baulk go some way to making up for our hero's lesser qualities.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133090</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strikes some resonant chords but also hits notes that simply don't ring true and are borderline risible at times</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927187?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all of its minor pleasures, this encore lacks the depth of its conviction.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/264116_knocking24q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its brilliant cast, its creative pedigree, Don't Come Knocking seemed as close to a sure thing as possible, but it only proves the sad truth that there's no such thing as a sure thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106180&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The narrative that unfolds in the wake of Spence's journey recalls "Paris" but walks too heavy for a character study to gel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8428</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only Lange is a powerful enough presence to raise a flicker of realistic emotion from this kind of stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060421.KNOCKING21/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Kate Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After a funny, highly promising start, Don't Come Knocking starts to fall apart, displaying all of Wenders' weaknesses, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=569025&amp;reviewId=20826</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's "Broken Flowers" with bourbon and ten-gallons and meta-country soundtrack warbles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0611,atkinson,72512,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The theatrical monologues come close to defeating him (Wenders), and only Jessica Lange, as one of Shepard's abandoned girlfriends, manages to avoid cliche.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29494_DONT_COME_KNOCKING.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a beautiful mess, but it's a mess all the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46499</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In what is more a cry of regret than a coherent story, Shepard's character mopes his way through meetings with an old girlfriend (Jessica Lange) and the grown children he sired, the only apparent lesson being that bad behavior has a way of circling back on you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/400538p-339096c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite a fine cast, the film feels as lost as Howard, unsure of its direction or tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-knocking17mar17,0,1633982.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all interspersed with strange attempts at comedy that fail on two levels: They're not funny, and they puncture what little drama there is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/65436.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So radiantly awful that, given the egghead credentials of the director and his screenwriter and star Sam Shepard, I initially took the charitable route and assumed I was in the presence of parody.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/12915/out-to-pasture/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretentious drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/24/DDGBSHSG2L1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$440,793</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$30,630</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jessica lange</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>