<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dot the I</name>
   <company>Summit Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Matthew Parkhill</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Matthew Parkhill</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKSpain</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Gael García Bernal</actor>
      <actor>Natalia Verbeke</actor>
      <actor>James D&amp;#039;Arcy</actor>
      <actor>Tom Hardy</actor>
      <actor>Charlie Cox</actor>
      <actor>Yves Aubert</actor>
      <actor>Myfanwy Waring</actor>
      <actor>Michael Webber</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 11, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The less you know going in, the more you'll enjoy it.  Suffice it to say that it's a hugely entertaining thriller disguised as a chick flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/22959.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>dot the i is like one of those nests of Chinese boxes within boxes. The outer box is a love story.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050414/REVIEWS/50324001/1001/reviews</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fun junk. And it doesn't satisfy. Dot the I is a weird, pretty film with a dumb script, a skilled cast and a good twist, plus one hot sex scene and one brilliant scene-chew by D'Arcy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1116497138305380.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite some moments of genuine tension, Dot the i walks (and occasionally hops right over) a very fine line between thriller/drama and parody.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050414-movies-review-jr-dot.story</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Satisfies and disturbs in just about equal measure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A43663-2005Mar17.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A clever, atmospheric romantic drama that lacks something.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/03/25/DDGQMBTQA71.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You can't have as many twists and turns in a story as dot the i without testing the audience's patience, and losing it before delivering the punch line.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/295522p-252815c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is in love with its own story loops and fancy, pop-dream cinematography from Almodóvar associate Affonso Beato, which is fine; it's also in love with its own indie-culture cleverness, which isn't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1043357_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Dot the i, the directorial debut of Matthew Parkhill, has a crass visual flash, it fails to give its characters any credible substance. Even after it purports to eviscerate their psyches, they remain diagrammatic contrivances.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/04/01/movies/01dot.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its seductive stylishness is undermined by one narrative twist too many; by the time the last revelation has been unveiled with a "But wait!" flourish, the contrivances have entirely overwhelmed the characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=45977</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its trickery might seem cute or clever to viewers who don't take either movies or people very seriously, but to me it recalled cynical "puzzle" films like "Memento" and "Irreversible," with no reason to exist apart from its gimmick.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/27850_DOT_THE_I.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The actors are all good, although not much rapport is conveyed, despite one hot sex scene.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A273814</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Parkhill's heart seems to belong to 1940s film noir, where a lonely man could be driven half-mad by the sight of a mystery woman performing a hot flamenco dance, a scene Parkhill stages here to unintentional titter-inducing effect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3309&amp;Sumbit.x=51&amp;Sumbit.y=18</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But behind its slick veneer and the glibness of its preposterous premise and dark twists, there's a yawning absence of charm or substance in this London-set love triangle, as well as a lack of chemistry between its three leads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117919737?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>First-time writer-director Matthew Parkhill prefers to lean on clever plot devices, amp up the roles of the movie's sideline jesters, crank up the static noise and fail to notice that his engaging little romance has broken with reality and veered into hollow pastiche.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules11mar11,2,6341122.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Along with his tedious array of tricks and twists, Parkhill stuffs the film with enough dizzying flashbacks, camera jitters and rock-and-roll editing techniques to drive a 14-year-old MTV addict nuts.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/issues/2005-04-14/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot's profound implausibility wouldn't matter if the ideas and emotions behind it had any power.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review_pop.php?review_id=8305</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie finally undermines all pretensions of satire with its geeky eagerness to subvert expectations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0513,tracking1,62518,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ben Kenigsberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed it looks as if this otherwise straight-to-video endeavor, which was made in 2003, is being released only to cash in on Bernal's of-the-moment-ness in Hollywood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A45510-2005Mar17.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deplorable piece of cynicism whose only point of interest is Gael Garcia Bernal's accent</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7516</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$306,224</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$9,581</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>