<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Dreamgirls</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures / DreamWorks SKG</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Bill Condon</author>
      <author>Tom Eyen</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Bill Condon</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jamie Foxx</actor>
      <actor>Beyoncé Knowles</actor>
      <actor>Eddie Murphy</actor>
      <actor>Danny Glover</actor>
      <actor>Anika Noni Rose</actor>
      <actor>Keith Robinson</actor>
      <actor>Jennifer Hudson</actor>
      <actor>Sharon Leal</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 15, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>130</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie belongs to Hudson as the proud, self-destructive Effie. When she's center stage, Dreamgirls transports you to movie musical heaven.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15994165/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hudson, taking over the role of Effie played on stage by Jennifer Holliday, is in charge of Dreamgirls from her opening scene, blowing away Grammy-winner Beyoncé Knowles, Oscar-winner Jamie Foxx and anyone else who gets in her way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/story/477633p-401848c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sigh you will hear across the country in the next few weeks is the sound of a gratified audience: a great movie musical has been made at last.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?061225crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is one of the best movie musicals in memory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20061222.wdream22/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ovation that Hudson wins from the movie's audience is one of those miraculous moments when a performer's artistry breaks through the screen and makes you feel part of a live audience. I haven't experienced anything like it since Barbra Streisand sang "My Man" at the end of her astonishing debut in Funny Girl.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.dreamgirls25dec25,0,5386955.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it seems long and its pace occasionally lags, it certainly struck me as a well-mounted, gloriously eye-filling and often exhilarating entertainment that brings back some of the delicious excitement of the great movie musicals.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/296958_dreamgirls25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Elegant, unabashedly theatrical, and packed with lush concert scenes and period-perfect costumes.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#30828</url>
         <critic>Albert Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its flaws, Dreamgirls is what this holiday season needs. It's a big, fat, luscious movie in which no one is tortured, murdered, or mutilated (honestly, how many recent films can you say that about?).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2156022#</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Finally. After "The Phantom of the Opera," "Rent" and "The Producers" botched the transfer from stage to screen, Dreamgirls gets it right. Bill Condon's adaptation of the 1981 show about a Motown trio's climb to crossover stardom pulls off the fundamental double-act those three musical pics all missed: It stays true to the source material while standing on its own as a fully reimagined movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117932225.html</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is the entire musical package, a triumph of old school on-screen glamour, and we wouldn't want it any other way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-dreamgirls15dec15,0,2069940.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even when it feels packaged like a holiday entertainment that aims to please, watching Dreamgirls is like being on cloud nine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.jacquielawson.com/viewcard.asp?code=1092899264460</url>
         <critic>Steve Davis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bill Condon's screen adaptation of the 1981 Broadway sensation is, if possible, as dazzling and energizing as its source.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=1A19278D4A2CB524A61558007B20FE43.prodapp12_ae_01?id=752331&amp;reviewId=22015</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Murphy is a revelation as James, and what American Idol castoff Hudson lacks in technical acting craft she makes up for in raw energy and a voice that could melt the rhinestones off a beauty queen. To complain that Beyonce pales by comparison is to fault her for nailing the essence of the infinitely malleable Deena.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284919&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is good and at times it touches greatness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/d/dreamgirls.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This baby dazzles like nothing else anywhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/9141695/review/12625995/dreamgirls</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The reason to see Dreamgirls is what hasn't been advertised - a film that in spite of its shiny veneer actually hits all the high notes through its underlying rawness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3361/dreamgirls.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Saito</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is the rare movie musical with real rapture in it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1569392_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is like a lot like Effie: It occasionally vexes or disappoints, but -- I am telling you -- it dazzles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/116725110921980.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ardent, accomplished, overwhelmingly emotional, with something to say and a dream cast saying it in song. Bravo.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=11143</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If there is a disappointment, it is this: The anticipation may have exceeded the realization. It's a damn good commercial movie, but it is not the film that will revive the musical or win over the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=FyZJWshNLjppBmwrNZm6vVgnLf0HQDNVW2N2yg16tRvw1gB6bt2l!-720130996&amp;&amp;rid=8464</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Condon grasps what has eluded most of his contemporaries: Anyone can give us the old razzle-dazzle, but what makes a movie musical soar is nothing more or less than the quiet exhilaration of two individuals on the screen, enraptured by song.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0650,foundas,75278,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's great to see a movie musical with a smart sense of the genre. All Dreamgirls lacks is the amazing energy and passion of the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1568455,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss/Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls may be good enough to win the Oscar for Best Picture - great costumes, sets and choreography help - but despite stellar work by erstwhile "American Idol" contestant Hudson and Murphy, it's far from a great picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12152006/entertainment/movies/supreme_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed, without Hudson's magic, without that extra feeling that comes from seeing the launch of something extraordinary, Dreamgirls might have been a break-even affair. The film has strong roles, good actors and a compelling story that takes place over the course of 10 or 15 years. But it has, with only a couple of exceptions, a pedestrian score that sounds like generic show-music schlock and lyrics that are not distinctive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/12/15/DDGR7MV5CG1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This glitzy, infectious and unusually heartfelt musical doesn't always hang together as a satisfying narrative -- too many characters compete for too little screen time -- but its pleasures are numerous enough to override its flaws.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=752331&amp;reviewId=22027&amp;startDate=01%2F29%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jennifer Hudson is the heart and soul of Dreamgirls. When she's on the screen, the movie shines. When she's not, the whole endeavor suffers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-12-14-dreamgirls-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is performed, shot, edited and packaged like a coming-attractions trailer for itself. Ordinarily that would be enough to sink a film straight off, unless you're a fan of "Moulin Rouge." But this one's a good time.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061225-movies-review-dreamgirls,0,672997.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Without Hudson, Dreamgirls would be a whole lot less exciting. Knowles, the ostensible star, is rather bland, and Foxx, surprisingly, seems miscast. Murphy is wonderful, but that should be no surprise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1222/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film soars in the right places, especially when powerful newcomer Jennifer Hudson sings, and the charismatic supporting cast keeps it chugging forward.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=752331&amp;reviewId=22017&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>She's (Jennifer Hudson) the best part of the show by far, but the writer-director Bill Condon, who wrote the screenplay for "Chicago" four years ago, has done the original "Dreamgirls" proud without solving its dramatic problems.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with “Dreamgirls” -- and it is not a small one -- lies in those songs, which are not just musically and lyrically pedestrian, but historically and idiomatically disastrous.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/12/15/movies/15drea.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I know I'm going to bring down the room by saying I think it's just okay. Well, Jennifer Hudson is more than okay.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/25324/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's taken Dreamgirls 25 years and several false starts to get to the screen, so it's a shame to see what a rush job it feels like.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8756</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamgirls is a better musical than "Chicago" or "Rent," but then, that isn't really saying much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9528</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even with Hudson's triumphant arrival and an overall fizzy mood of singing, dancing, pop nostalgia and camp, Dreamgirls is an uneven crowd pleaser.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1123976&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's so little love to be found in Dreamgirls. It's a product that promises magic, and yet gives us nothing to live on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/12/15/dreamgirls/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the ultimate pop-culture sacrilege: a movie about soul music that has no soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/56661</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$103,365,956</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$75,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$378,950</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jamie foxx</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>eddie murphy</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>