<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Duchess, The</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jeffrey Hatcher</author>
      <author>Amanda Foreman</author>
      <author>Saul Dibb</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Saul Dibb</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Keira Knightley</actor>
      <actor>Ralph Fiennes</actor>
      <actor>Charlotte Rampling</actor>
      <actor>Dominic Cooper</actor>
      <actor>Hayley Atwell</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 19, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is not one of those delightful movies based on a Jane Austen novel. It is about hard realists, constrained in a stifling system and using whatever weapons they can command.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080925/REVIEWS/809250303</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thoroughly populist and middlebrow, full of all the high wigs, thick powder, perfect diction, and straightforward dialogue that define bodice-ripping prestige pictures about silently suffering souls.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_duchess</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The players are uniformly good, but a special word must be said for Fiennes, whose portrayal of physical awkwardness and painful taciturnity never begs either for laughs or for sympathy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1842597,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even surrounded by all this quality work, Ralph Fiennes, who plays William Cavendish, the fifth duke of Devonshire, the most powerful man in England next to the king, walks off with the picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-duchess19-2008sep19,0,4471488.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An uncommonly well-crafted historical feminist tearjerker--both anti-patriarchal and a monument to motherhood.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/50259/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is scandal-mongering fun that also lays bare the deforming power of the male aristocracy.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#33595</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It tells the amazing, but mostly true, story of a late-18th century aristocrat who made an indelible mark on English society akin to that of her direct descendant, Lady Diana.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/09/25/DDQG133UHK.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're fond of wigs, you may be in heaven. If you're more interested in Whigs, you may wish the movie had dug deeper under the lovely powdered surface of Lady Georgiana Spencer.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/31862-review-the-duchess</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While I much liked The Duchess, this portrait feels unfinished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080926_A_duchess_adored_by_all_save_her_duke.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>perfectly serviceable costume drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/duchess/review/293232</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Princess Diana's antecedent, both genetically and figuratively, was a beautiful and glamorous duchess named Georgiana Spencer. Like her descendant, her charm and vivacity captivated England.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-09-18-the-duchess_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fiennes speaks with his body what the script cannot formulate about what it's like to be a man apart. The actor creates particulars of time, space, class, and personality with one crook of a finger, one twist of a wrist. I call that nobility of craft; he's the actors' prince.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20226361,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Knightley who makes The Duchess a royal treat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/22790869/review/22790881/the_duchess</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Keira Knightley is a terrific choice to play the 18th century socialite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11573</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>tThere's life at the center of The Duchess, in the form of Keira Knightley. She carries the weight of the movie around her effortlessly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/09/19/duchess/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a number of reasons The Duchess isn't all it could have been. It's fun, but falls short of fabulous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/159446</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provided you don't take it seriously, it makes for an addictively entertaining diversion that's as hard to stop watching as the books are to stop reading.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/380570_duchess26q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, though, it's unfortunate that the movie tries to make so many oblique comparisons to more modern tragedy (paparazzi with sketchbooks; yes, we get it!), since Georgiana's life seems fascinating enough on its own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/09/movie_review_pretty_royal_and.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fans of period drama will find things to like about The Duchess; it's not as ludicrous as "The Other Boleyn Girl," for instance, and it's not overly long or ponderous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/700739.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Taken in isolation from the unsatisfying story, the performances are powerful--Knightley’s vivacious, wounded romantic does a great deal to carry the film on sheer personality, while Fiennes  is a subtle master at projecting banked menace through his seeming detached ennui.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-duchess/631949/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At a certain point, The Duchess stops attending to the topiary and becomes a women's melodrama instead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11625</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As for true-love Charles, he would ascend to the Prime Minister's office, and then rise again to even greater heights: They named the tea after him. Indeed, that may be the smartest way to see this flick, curled up on your sofa with a cup of Earl Grey -- just make sure it's as decaffeinated as what you're watching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080918.wduchess19/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A rousing period drama with all the familiar trimmings: gorgeous costumes, palatial settings and romantic intrigue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/09/18/2008-09-18_the_duchess_is_lovely_to_look_at.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A serviceable picture that offers all the sumptuous visual pleasures of a historical costume drama, yet little in the way of actual history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938114.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=The+duchess</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Saul Dibb, presumably knowing that this is pretty standard stuff for a costume epic, occupies us not just with the usual visuals -- of his star drifting through exquisitely furnished estates, draped in rich silks and brocades -- but also with some intriguingly offbeat sights.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=94662956</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's too bad there's not more substance to The Duchess, because there's lots of acting and, as is required of a Brit-styled period piece, lushness galore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1147441&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem isn't the history that the filmmakers leave in, but how much they leave out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.duchess10oct10,0,898367.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a tale of mature self-sacrifice, the movie would be almost unbearably moving were it not for Knightley's insubstantial performance, which allows her to be fatally upstaged by Ralph Fiennes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-09-17/film/keira-knightley-goes-aristocratic-yet-again-for-the-duchess/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It has impeccable production values but feels like a "Masterpiece Theater" production of a Harlequin romance novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1333</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lumbering number that takes its identity as a costume drama quite literally.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0920/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s a curiously inert, workmanlike production: a whole lot of pomp and incircumstance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A683680</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of scintillation, the movie gives us a succession of discrete set pieces, as if the action takes place in rooms but not in the halls connecting them.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122177747252654291.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An overstuffed, intellectually underbaked portrait of a poor little rich girl.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/09/19/movies/19duch.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everything is predictable three scenes in advance, and it's all stale, stuck, stolid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09192008/entertainment/movies/knightley_snooze_129726.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$13,848,978</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$190,426</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>7</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>