<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Duck Season</name>
   <company>Warner Independent Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Fernando Eimbcke</author>
      <author>Paula Markovitch</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Fernando Eimbcke</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Mexico</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Enrique Arreola</actor>
      <actor>Diego Cataño</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Mira</actor>
      <actor>Danny Perea</actor>
      <actor>Carolina Politi</actor>
      <actor>Antonio Zúñiga</actor>
      <actor>Alfredo Escobar</actor>
      <actor>Sara Castro</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's one of the small, pitch-perfect treasures of the movie year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8508</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A quiet, loopy gem, Duck Season is a goofball celebration of old friends, new beginnings, adolescent freedom, and baked goods laced with a little something extra.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=565109&amp;reviewId=20404</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almost everything that happens - and almost everything happens within Flama's apartment - is food for dry humor and very recognizable humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.duck07apr07,0,5184561.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Duck Season unfolds with a slaphappy logic that only looks casual. In fact, every unfinished conversation and banal picture on the wall (one's of ducks) matters as four little people share one memorable little day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1171076_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inside this small canvas - almost the entire film unfolds in the one apartment - Mr. Eimbcke turns each character into an epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/movies/10duck.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A highly satisfying miniature. Its subject may be adolescence, and some of its pot-smoking, kick-back humor is adolescent too--in a good way. But the film's calm and witty visual rhythm offers a rueful awareness of time passing and of time wasted, in ways that people tend not to appreciate fully until long after they've wasted it.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060317-movies-review-duck,0,5130377.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mexican writer-director Fernando Eimbcke got his start in short films and documentaries, and his first feature reveals a gift for concision: It doesn't overexert itself trying to come to big conclusions about these characters, and even the comedic scenes settle for gentle quirks over broad guffaws.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46304</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Fernando Eimbcke, in an extraordinary debut, never expresses contempt for his characters. By examining their inner lives with compassion and respect, he inspires us to do the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106617&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes a film about nothing can be a film about everything; a film without overwhelmingly dramatic events can delight you more than an outsized epic. The sly and disarming Duck Season is such a film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-duck10mar10,0,4202349.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The lovely, unpredictable comedy Duck Season marks the arrival of a fresh talent in writer-director Fernando Eimbcke. His script is vibrant with unforced humanist observations, the performances are natural and endearing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002155372</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slow but charming film.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46779</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's about the kind of kids who could never sit still enough, unfortunately, for a movie that perfectly captures the frustrations, longings, obsessions and torments of the awkward years before manhood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/398474p-337573c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A hilariously deadpan black-and-white slacker comedy, Duck Season is sort of like "Wayne's World" directed by a Mexican Jim Jarmusch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64968.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not very much really happens in Duck Season, but in its rich details, it remembers how absorbing and endless every single day can seem when you're 14.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060316/REVIEWS/60314008/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The beauty of Duck Season is its insistence that profound human experiences can arrive slowly, in incremental packages, scattered over the course of an average Sunday.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/17/DDGERHOUMO1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some viewers will wonder what exactly it is they are supposed to be laughing at, but those that do find themselves on the movie's wavelength will enjoy its observational approach to comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2650</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Mexican writer-director Fernando Eimbcke attempts to give this story a melancholy overlay, but its main interest is in its confirmation that teenagers are pretty much the same everywhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0310/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Warm, winning and clever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1143665710222400.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The spirits of Jim Jarmusch and Kevin Smith hover over this breezy slacker comedy set on a comatose Sunday afternoon.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/264114_duck24q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Duck Season is something quite different, capable of gratifying film snobs and regular viewers alike.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/03/09/btm/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Duck Season is not (yet) the work of a great filmmaker, but it's the kind of movie in which a fledgling director traps his talent in a bottle and saves it for next time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/12855/child-care/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fullness of Duck Season is in direct proportion to its smallness; its modesty makes it bloom.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16312/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This slight but appealing film's funky eccentricity feels a little contrived at times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2004&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117923852&amp;categoryid=1724&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not in recent memory has a movie so short – 90 minutes on the nose – been so stagnant and stubbornly slow to build. And that's exactly the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A349426</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The characters' behavior isn't always believable, and the jerky rhythm takes some getting used to (there may be more attitude here than observation). But the defiant absence of any conventional plot has a cumulative charm.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29456_DUCK_SEASON.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shot in silvery black-and-white, Duck Season is not charmless, just insubstantial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,atkinson,72436,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes Duck Season is amusing. More often, though, it is boring and icky.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8680</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$147,551</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$24,658</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>