<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Eagle vs. Shark</name>
   <company>Miramax Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Taika Waititi</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Taika Waititi</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>NewZealand</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jemaine Clement</actor>
      <actor>Taika Cohen</actor>
      <actor>David Fane</actor>
      <actor>Craig Hall</actor>
      <actor>Morag Hills</actor>
      <actor>Cohen Holloway</actor>
      <actor>Loren Horsley</actor>
      <actor>Rachel House</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 15, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>88</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>So quirky that it’s almost in danger of collapsing under the weight of its own antic whimsy at times, but a comic delight destined for cult adoration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134932</url>
         <critic>Olly Richards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A Kiwi nerd love story and loopy portrait of Down Under underachievers, Eagle vs. Shark offers a deadpan take on family, friendship, obsession and self-delusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20070622_2_nerdy_clerks_find_costumes_and_true_love.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What rescues Eagle vs. Shark is its focus on Lily. Although Horsley overdoes the winsomeness, she is genuinely appealing. Love erases Lily's geekiness and in its place stands an attractive young woman.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0615/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike so many big-studio films that pass off models in horn-rimmed glasses as nerds, this little New Zealand gem embraces the inner geek and, just as effectively, celebrates misfit love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-06-14-eagle-vs-shark_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Scott Bowles</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With an often very funny story line that eventually touches on parental disappointment and suicide, it's clear that, his debt to Hess and Wes Anderson notwithstanding, Waititi has learned a thing or two from fellow antipodean Jane Campion as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/eagle-vs-shark/review/288325</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is punctuated by a literal knock down, drag out affair that has all the perverse curiosity of watching a "late career" Mike Tyson bout. But by the end, the real knockout is the discovery of this comic gem.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3874/eagle-vs-shark.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Saito</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never before have I been so emotionally involved with an apple core, or seen salvation in a flip-flop. Taika Waititi, you had me at nunchuks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06152007/entertainment/movies/geek_loves_dork___nunchuks_and_all_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn't funny in any big way so much as recognizable in its patterns of dysfunction, delusion and futility. But you believe in it, because you believe in the small but decent lives of its characters, a rare experience for a hot weekend in June.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1133189&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This debut feature, occasionally arch but consistently affecting, shares the deadpan esthetic of "Napoleon Dynamite" and "Ghost World."</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118186395464336075.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film’s resolution is more implied than complete.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A503776</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching Eagle vs Shark is like sitting next to a terminally awkward first date at a restaurant. You cringe and feel protective toward the poor, sweet dweebs at the same time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9881</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eagle vs. Shark feels like a low-budget, foreign cousin to Napolean Dynamite, less polished and sly. But it's definitely in the same family, lulling us into friendly acceptance with its persuasively silly rhythm and deceptively big heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=861707&amp;reviewId=22556</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a perfectly cheerful time at the movies, without any hint of drama or surprise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/06/14/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite Clement's best efforts to make Jarrod a deadpan oddball nerd, it becomes apparent early on that excessive teenage eccentricity and terminal self-delusion isn't quite as cute in the adult male and absent father.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/320764_eagle22q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the kind of movie in which Jarrod's nemesis turns out to be paraplegic, while his dad lives in a wheelchair despite the fact that he can walk just fine. Ha.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/06/15/2007-06-15_geek_with_a_beak_goes_for_cheepcheep_lau.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Might feel like a colorful little train-wreck drama, but given the recent popularity of such films, it comes across more like a nerdcore clip show, a sort of straight-faced "Epic Movie" for fans of discomfort comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/eagle_vs_shark</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, Eagle vs. Shark represents a convincing triumph for Dumb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070621.weagle0622/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are occasional nice moments scattered throughout, but this is mostly a big, uncomfortable cartoon focused on the twisted attraction between two caricatures.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/e/eagle_vs.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Intermittently charming, sometimes tiresome celebration of quirkiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/movies/15eagl.html?em&amp;ex=1181966400&amp;en=b11ceb976636ed29&amp;ei=5087%0A</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As it turns out, spending a couple of hours with emotionally arrested, socially moronic characters is not a whole lot more fun than spending a couple of hours with actual emotionally arrested, socially moronic people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-eagle15jun15,0,3025056.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a tale that reduces angst, not to mention love, to a generational tic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20042384,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's idea of funny is giving the two lovers identical moles bordering their upper lips.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31766_EAGLE_VERSUS_SHARK.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More dumb than funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8755&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>James Greenberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Result is still innocuously mild and inconsequential.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2007&amp;jump=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117932667&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You can't see the forest for the twee in writer-director Taika Waititi's thicket of cutesy conceits, from the stunted supporting characters to the precious animated interludes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0724,various,76922,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$221,846</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$20,361</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>