<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Edmond</name>
   <company>First Independent Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Mamet</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Stuart Gordon</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>William H. Macy</actor>
      <actor>Julia Stiles</actor>
      <actor>Joe Mantegna</actor>
      <actor>Rebecca Pidgeon</actor>
      <actor>Bai Ling</actor>
      <actor>Mena Suvari</actor>
      <actor>Denise Richards</actor>
      <actor>Bokeem Woodbine</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 14, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>82</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mamet is a writer who turns off some audiences, and almost everything that might bother them is in Edmond: foul language, raging machismo, violence and seemingly bigoted tirades. But almost everything audiences like about him is there too: candor, suspense, ideas, crackling slang, vivid characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060728-movies-review-edmond,0,3633474.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Edmond would probably be completely unapproachable were it not spiked with so much dark wit, much of it coming from Macy's painful naïveté and cheapness, which comes through in negotiations with various women of the night.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/50950</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hilarious, and contains some of Mamet's best dialogue. And that somehow, by making a racist, murderous, Everycreep his protagonist, Mamet is able to produce some of his most penetrating psychological and spiritual insights.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/07/13/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the episodic script feels fragmented, Macy’s consistency unifies Edmond’s journey.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9203</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It manages, in the course of a single tersely delineated story, to say more about the dark pathology of American racism than any five character arcs in "Crash." So go, by all means, but be prepared to take a beating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14204/</url>
         <critic>Ron Stringer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Mamet's understanding, straight white maleness is the most powerful weapon such men have. It can also be illusory, which is why the last scenes of Edmond are so touching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8332</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Admirers of the author will find in Edmond all the elements that turned Mamet into a favorite.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=684274&amp;reviewId=21809</url>
         <critic>Marta Barber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Macy, a master at playing sticks of human dynamite in mild-mannered camouflage, gives the nerviest screen performance of his career.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/14/movies/14edmo.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We're in David Mamet World. William H. Macy -- the quintessential player of Mamet men in all their impacted rage -- stars in this claustrophobic adaptation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1219245_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Written in the aftermath of a bitter divorce, Mamet's paranoid rant -- an explosion of middle-aged, white-collar, white-men's rage at losing ground to everyone, from women, hustlers, African Americans and homosexuals to the younger generation nipping at their heels -- is as bilious as ever, but time has overtaken and defanged it.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=281639&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may be too bleak for most.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/never_mamet_a_bad_marriage_he_didnt_like_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Depressing, disgusting, and dated, Edmond is worth braving to experience America’s best-known serious playwright at his most gruesomely undiluted.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/17661/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This, to put it mildly, is new terrain for Macy, and his journey--from Arthur Miller, as it were, to Céline and Dostoyevsky--does not always convince.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060724crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From the beginning, Edmond is too self-absorbed for us to care much about his fate, but like the proverbial train wreck, you can't tear your eyes - or your ears - away from the spectacle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/435053p-366393c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For hard-core David Mamet fans only...Edmond serves to remind you how artificial the dialogue and dramaturgy truly was in early Mamet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002346121</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite agreeably short running time and committed performances, Edmond is rendered inert by its stagy atmosphere and failure to fully mine the depths of its protagonist's complex psyche.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928094?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the full-length sorta-satire it has become, Edmond is all sizzle and little meat, a veritable tangent act dropped from "Glengarry Glen Ross" because it was several marks too silly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0628,atkinson,73806,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An intriguing, disquieting, but ultimately overdrawn nightmare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A405553</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Edmond does, on the surface, seem very much a contemporary tale of urban terror. Yet despite the best efforts of all concerned, what seemed explosive and provocative two decades ago now comes across as schematic and artificial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-edmond11aug11,0,4446184.story</url>
         <critic>Gene Seymour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Disappointing adaptation of Mamet's 1982 drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30067_EDMOND.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the role needs, and what Macy cannot quite provide, is the sense not of a robot but of a potent man who has been imprisoned by rote. Remember Jack Nicholson in "About Schmidt."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060807&amp;s=kauffman080706</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$131,719</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$19,253</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>