<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Edukators, The</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Katharina Held</author>
      <author>Hans Weingartner</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Hans Weingartner</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>GermanyAustria</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Daniel Brühl</actor>
      <actor>Julia Jentsch</actor>
      <actor>Stipe Erceg</actor>
      <actor>Burghart Klaußner</actor>
      <actor>Peer Martiny</actor>
      <actor>Petra Zieser</actor>
      <actor>Laura Schmidt</actor>
      <actor>Sebastian Butz</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 22, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>124</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>That rare beast, a terrific movie that boasts intelligent wit, expert storytelling, delightful characters and grown-up dialogue plus suspense and a wicked surprise ending.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/awards/cannes/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000496939</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film that points out so much wrong with German society and shows such dubious, dangerous behavior, it leaves the audience with high spirits and a sense of crazy exhilaration.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050805-movies-review-edukators,0,2678156.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fluid and gripping drama from Germany (it has the design of a thriller and the mood of a spontaneous, whirling-camera character study).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1087410_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sweet, funny and gripping romantic adventure, it's about the limitations of political activism in this day and age, and what happens when your girlfriend and your best friend fall in love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-edukators29jul29,0,1177575.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Uncommonly smart and interesting.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A slyly effective thriller and of a deft comedy of romantic confusion. Whatever its shortcomings as a consideration of globalization and its discontents, The Edukators succeeds brilliantly in telling the story of a man who falls in love with his best buddy's girlfriend and doesn't know what to do about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/22/movies/22eduk.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unpredictable and hugely entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46286</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An engaging entertainment that packages its thought-provoking ideas in a combination of political thriller, comic adventure and romantic triangle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/07/21/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes the film so affecting, however, is its matter-of-fact evocation of character. Each person in the four-character cast is vivid and specific and believable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/04/AR2005080401978.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deft, entertaining story that mixes menace with charm and satire with seriousness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/04/AR2005080400673.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sticking it to the man, German-style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A285045</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you can look beyond the simple-minded Socratic political discourse, The Edukators reveals itself as warm, humane and sad, a movie that genuinely wants you to think about how idealism eventually collides with human frailty, and about what upstarts and sell-outs might teach one another.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1123754451287770.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an action movie that's also an intellectual-action flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=218321&amp;reviewId=18850</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You can sympathize with both sides in their ideological battle, which ends in a most unexpected way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/50148.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a rare film that gets smarter as it goes along, injecting a satisfying dash of pragmatism every time it seems ready to slip into either unearned idealism or cynical fatalism.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/235270_limited05.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's an evenhanded humanism flowing through The Edukators that may strike doctrinaire viewers on either side of the divide as mushy, but it's tough enough for the rest of us to chew on for a long time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7289</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the story drags for the first hour, this becomes a solid character study once the principals arrive at their hiding place.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/27537_EDUKATORS_DIE_FETTEN_JAHR_SIND_VORBEI</url>
         <critic>Hank Sartin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is certainly a trill of suspense to be had from these ideological heists, but Weingartner’s movie is never quite as keen-edged as it hopes or needs to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050801crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike in, say, "Fight Club," director Hans Weingartner does not hedge his bets on the notion of whether simple-minded anarchy is any better than societal conformity -- his heart is with the Edukators, period.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unless you're the sort who has a Che Guevara T-shirt tucked away somewhere in your closet, the needlessly long The Edukators wears out its welcome.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=218321&amp;reviewId=18995</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps the harshest criticism of the new German film The Edukators is that it doesn't make you feel any better edukated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051007/EDUKATORS07/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dialogue between the captive and the captors gets a little didactic, and the ending is as contrived as it is cynical. Weingartner obviously has more in common with the rich man than the kids.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/07-22-2005/entertainment/movies/story/330355p-282318c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ambling drama shows an exasperating lack of economy and a weakness for diatribe dialogue, but becomes progressively more involving after a laborious start.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2004&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117923875&amp;categoryid=1724&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Edukators smiles indulgently as the kids rage belatedly against the dying of the SDS light.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0529,winter,66014,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Winter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It could have been something substantial.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/08/05/DDGJ8E2JR51.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's daring, honest ending helps redeem the uneven drama, but the road there may occasionally try the patience of even the most sympathetic armchair revolutionaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://redesign.theonion.com/avclub/node/25087</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Put simply, this second feature by the young Austrian director Hans Weingartner is a put-on -- a glib anti-capitalist rant in which the rhetoric rarely rises above the you-too-can-save-a-child-for-less-than-the-price-of-coffee level.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3482&amp;Sumbit.x=71&amp;Sumbit.y=16</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film begs for more action, thrills, and jokes, or more dramatic and painful revelations. What we get is an in-between mash of romantic ideals, a botched kidnapping, and some very good time wasted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7188</url>
         <critic>Heidi Martinuzzi</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$175,493</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,075</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>