<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Eight Below</name>
   <company>Walt Disney Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Di</author>
      <author>Gilio</author>
      <author>Toshirô Ishido, Koreyoshi Kurahara, Tatsuo Nogami and Kan Saji</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Frank Marshall</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Paul Walker</actor>
      <actor>Bruce Greenwood</actor>
      <actor>Jason Biggs</actor>
      <actor>Moon Bloodgood</actor>
      <actor>Panou</actor>
      <actor>Gerard Plunkett</actor>
      <actor>Malcolm Stewart</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 17, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>120</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eight magnificent sled dogs must fend for themselves amid Antarctica's frozen wastes in this top-notch survival adventure that will reduce the coldest heart to a puddle of warm slush.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46650</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something invigorating about this unpretentious dog tale. And if a penguin drops by to promote his own movie product, well, there's room on the frozen continent for all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1159754_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the dogs have surely been Disney-fied to some extent, the sequences of them trying to survive are magnificent and deeply moving. Bring the Kleenex, and hug your pups when you get home.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1088067&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Disney may have written the book on live-action animal adventure stories, but it has been quite a while since there has been a chapter as terrific as Eight Below.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001997238</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With Eight Below,  Marshall has created a family film that doesn't pander, preach, or poop out. That alone is a rare thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A338604</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Remarkable, how in a film where we KNOW with an absolute certainty that all or most of the dogs must survive, Eight Below succeeds as an effective story. It works by focusing on the dogs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060216/REVIEWS/602160301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Walker is adorable, but gives a one-note performance. Greenwood, a charismatic and unsung character actor, has the most noteworthy human performance as a somewhat arrogant academic whose decency keeps him from becoming a stock villain in a formulaic story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-02-16-eight-below_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Americanized remake of the 1983 Japanese movie, "Antarctica," which told the true story of a pack of huskies that somehow managed to survive a brutal winter by themselves at Japan's East Antarctica station in 1957.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/259814_eight17q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dogs are such charismatic performers it's almost a shame that there have to be humans in this story at all. Still, the Antarctica sequences alone make Eight Below one of the better family films out there right now.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2585</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"March of the Penguins" - phooey! Those smelly little birds are built to survive in the frozen tundra, and nobody's asking them to pull a sled.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=302570&amp;reviewId=20160</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The determinedly cynical needn't bother, but just about everyone else should love Eight Below.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.eight17feb17,0,5332888.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the most touching love story about tragically separated sexy beasts since "Cold Mountain."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7979</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film works best among the beasts. Their training is impeccable, their emotions are palpable, and almost all of their behavior is credible. One "Jaws"-like encounter sends a carnivorous leopard seal after a fleeing canine, and it's as tense as anything I hope to see this spring.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=302570&amp;reviewId=20149&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The survival drama is genuinely exciting, and the players, both human and canine, put this across with spirit.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29260_EIGHT_BELOW.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eight Below splits into two movies--the compelling tale of the dogs' struggle to pull together and survive and the much less interesting one about Jerry Shepard's emotional trauma and his search for redemption.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-02-16/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An easy watch, thanks to the splendors of frosty scenery and furry canines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929531?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Longtime Steven Spielberg collaborator Frank Marshall is smart enough to know his core audience of kiddies came to see the dogs, who take center stage in many of the film's best sequences, especially a jolting leopard-seal attack that's as terrifying as anything in "Jurassic Park."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45430</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An actress named Moon Bloodgood, who started out as a hip-hop dancer and Laker Girl before getting into movie and TV work, plays a bush pilot and sometime girlfriend of Jerry's. The role is bland but that name is great.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0217/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dogs are fantastic. The humans need more work with their trainers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/392116p-332423c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's formulaic and frequently over the top, 30 minutes too long and altogether too slow, but oh when those gorgeous, graceful pups tilt their heads just so … love.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060217-movies-review-below,0,5896161.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Solid family entertainment, with thrilling action sequences and gorgeous scenery.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=302570&amp;reviewId=20163</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dogs learn to fight for themselves and eventually tangle with a (computer-generated) leopard seal in the movie's most thrilling encounter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2136883/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>Emily Yoffe</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dogs, whose individual personalities shine through without recourse to crass anthropomorphism, are superstars.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=132289</url>
         <critic>Simon Braund</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Marshall isn't exactly a cinematic poet, but he does a fine job delineating each individual dog's personality, as well as the shifting hierarchy of power within the pack, which is why it's so exasperating that he and first-time screenwriter Dave Digillo are forever cutting away to dull Jerry and his stateside quest for rescue-mission funds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12687&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eight Below is Grade A pooch porn, an orgy of canine cuteness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/17/movies/17eigh.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This family adventure about a team of sled dogs abandoned in Antarctica naturally invokes the traditional shout of "Mush!" urging the canines to go faster, but it's also an apt descriptor of both its shameless sentimentality and ineptly structured story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-eight17feb17,0,7350423.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eight Below doesn't always quite put across the idea of extreme weather, either; the way the actors keep appearing outside with bare heads and jackets unzipped suggests November in Burbank, not 31 degrees below zero. The scenes in which Biggs appears in shorts kind of clinch the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/63681.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gorgeous art film full of snowy silences and spare, gestural performances threatens to break loose (the most inspired acting comes courtesy of the canines), though the plot's slavish schmaltz proves as oppressive as the harsh winter that descends upon the dogs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0608,lofficial,72266,20.html</url>
         <critic>Peter L&amp;#039;Official</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is one of those lazy, lukewarm pictures that's even more disappointing than a purely bad one, and for one glaring reason: How could Marshall, his writers, and even his actors have let these dogs down so badly?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/17/eight_below/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At two hours, Eight Below becomes rather repetitive and arduous in its final stretch, the rescue mission. But the canine cuteness, breathtaking action and acts of bravery are worth braving the Disney elements -- overpowering, poignant music, an unnecessary romantic subplot -- if you like your movies doggy-style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060217.EIGHT17/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is overly long and much too intense for small children, yet it's filled with dialogue and plot turns that are too juvenile to thrill adult audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/17/DDGT9H9ALL1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$81,612,565</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$40,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$20,188,176</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,066</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>