<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Encounters at the End of the World</name>
   <company>THINKFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Werner Herzog</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Werner Herzog</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 11, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>G</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A supremely cranky and lyrical feat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0614/p25s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The stunning images aren't enough for Herzog, though. He wants us to see how these quirky researchers, in their lust to explore, are acting out a drive as primitive as nature: the need to break away from the world in order to find it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20206283,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a poem of oddness and beauty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080710/REVIEWS/807100305/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Werner Herzog is a stranger in a strange land as soon as he gets out of bed in the morning: in this travelogue of Antarctica, his perverse curiosity and zest for the harshest extremes of nature transform what might have been a standard TV special into an idiosyncratic expression of wonder.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#33340</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like many of Mr. Herzog's movies, fiction and nonfiction, Encounters at the End of the World itself has the quality of a dream: it's at once vivid and vague, easy to grasp and somehow beyond reach.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/11/movies/11enco.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deranged penguin is seen racing toward his certain doom amid the crags of a mountain range. It may not be "Happy Feet," but Herzog has made a penguin movie after all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/encounters-end-world/review/293752</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does Antarctica attract dreamers or create them? It's a thread that runs throughout the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11682</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Takes you places an ordinary documentary filmmaker might’ve gone to yet missed completely.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-encounters-at/491536/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Through Herzog's eyes it is a desolate, strangely beautiful frozen Edenish hell where the planet, having shaken out its pockets, lets the loners, fanatics and cosmologist-crackpots fall to bottom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080711_It_s__End_of_the_World___as_Herzog_knows_it.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All this is as fascinating as it is humbling, even when Herzog ventures a little too far down eccentricity's back alley.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080627.wworld27/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An engaging and generous profile of the fascinating folks who have chosen to live at the end of the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/370297_limited11.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The images captured by Herzog and cinematographer Peter Zeitlinger are dazzling all on their own, finding the disorienting psychedelia that is nature at its weirdest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-encounters27-2008jun27,0,366967.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I also think Herzog is making a case for those crazy enough to follow their dreams, even when they take you to the end of the earth. Literally.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11103</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's as much fun to anticipate what he's (Herzog) going to say as it is to appreciate the snowy landscapes, belching volcanoes and mustachioed seals before his lens. And what could have been a conventional travelogue becomes a sort of ruminative odyssey of the mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1143835&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enjoyable example of this extraordinary director's documentary work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/26/DD9D11DRKQ.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sort of distracted, freewheeling form of inquiry and observation drives Encounters At The End Of The World, a loosely constructed documentary that seems to have been made on a whim.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/encounters_at_the_end_of_the</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Encounters may lack the power of, say, the Herzog doc "Grizzly Man," because it has no bigger-than-life character at its nexus, but it does confirm the filmmaker as an iconoclastic master.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06132008/entertainment/movies/encounters_in_antarctica_with_a_cinemati_115247.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a loosely bound collection of miscellany filmed at the McMurdo Station, a 1,000-person settlement of researchers in Antarctica, during the five-month "austral summer" of round-the-clock sunlight. Herzog was sent to Antarctica by the National Science Foundation with carte blanche to make whatever movie he wanted--all he could tell them for sure was that it wouldn't involve penguins.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2193357/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Midway through, an eerier theme creeps in, all the more powerful for Herzog's lack of insistence. By the "end of the world" he means the end of the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47552/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Retains considerable entertainment value on the strength of Herzog's never-dull, very personal narrating style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9831</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Resultant picture -- one of Herzog's best and most purely enjoyable -- may lack the built-in curio factor of "Grizzly Man."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934764.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps because Herzog is approaching old-master status, Encounters at the End of the World skews toward the observational. As in "Grizzly Man," his 2005 portrait of a deranged bear lover, Herzog seems at least as fascinated with other people's obsessions as his own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0824,deep-freeze,464873,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Herzog-light, in a way -- more travelogue than dissection. But it's filled with small riches, not least of which is the director's amazing narration. Can't you just imagine him reading "Green Eggs and Ham"?</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/08/movie_review_werner_herzogs_fr.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You get the impression that Herzog believes wholeheartedly the planet will be better off without us. Nosferatu that we have proven ourselves to be, he may be right.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A645425</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Creating a hypnotically digressive travelogue, Herzog wanders from soul to soul, asking deceptively mild questions to potent effect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/13/2008-06-13_short_takes_encounters_at_the_end_of_the.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$944,933</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$25,913</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>