<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Everything&amp;#039;s Gone Green</name>
   <company>First Independent Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Douglas Coupland</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paul Fox</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Canada</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Paulo Costanzo</actor>
      <actor>Steph Song</actor>
      <actor>JR Bourne</actor>
      <actor>Aidan Devine</actor>
      <actor>Susan Hogan</actor>
      <actor>Tom Butler</actor>
      <actor>Peter Kelamis</actor>
      <actor>Gordon Michael Woolvett</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 13, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story -- is slight, but an appealing cast and lots of scenic leafery make Green feel fresh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20034466,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everything's Gone Green is the second feature directed by Paul Fox (The Dark Hours), who maintains an energetic, lighthearted tone throughout the film, even when the story loses focus at its not-quite-satisfying ending.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070427.wgreen27/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's more clever than smart, but Paul Fox directs with the same easygoing attitude of its slacker hero and finds some modest truths (also lower case) behind the props.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/314241_limited04.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A romantic comedy/social satire that, on a modest budget, manages to be hip, charming, funny and dressed to kill.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070518-movies-review-green,0,7202277.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Novelist Douglas Coupland (Generation X) brings his millennial irony and middle-class angst to the big screen with this offbeat Canadian comedy about the lure of easy money.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#31613</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Starring an excellent Paulo Costanzo (late of "Joey") as a twentysomething uberslacker who is nonetheless willing to fall into accidental success, pic is seasoned with fine perfs by JR Bourne as a charismatic, creepy hustler and Steph Song as Constanzo's sexy potential love interest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931815.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Ken Eisner</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Green, the first feature Coupland's written, doesn't really make any innovations to the Almost 30-Underachievers genre, but it's an endearing, solidly-crafted example.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3720/everythings-gone-green.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Letkemann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's tone is on the sitcom side, but its likable cast and zany subplots make it palatable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-green20apr20,0,2954920.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not the big picture that charms here, it's the details. More than anything, though, it's Costanzo--a spindly Everydork who grows up not because he has to, but because he just kinda wants to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0715,various,76339,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fundamentally, it's a well-executed formula movie, perfect for first-date couples or miscellaneous group outings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/04/12/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Coupland's first screenplay, and it shows -- in a cheerfully discursive quality, but also in a reliance on gestures, contrivance and dialectic speeches rather than dramatic development and conflict.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the plus side, Costanzo is an appealing and likable young actor who carries the film easily; he gives the impression that he is thinking deeply and mildly amused.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A466607</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a charming disappointment that retains the elements that make the writer's novels so good without ever bending them into cinematic shape.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=2084</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a bit of a shaky first screenwriting effort for Coupland, but not without its charms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9821</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dialogue does have Coupland's characteristic snap, but like its mellow hero, the movie takes the easy route just a little too often.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/04/13/2007-04-13_short_takes.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bloodless film that aims for wry but leaves you merely asking "why?"</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/117753090461370.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some ideas are auto-stolen (from Coupland's last novel, "JPod"), but those quirky atmospherics aren't enough to sustain a largely plotless film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04132007/entertainment/movies/everythings_gone_green_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$19,373</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$3,426</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>