<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Failure to Launch</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Tom J. Astle</author>
      <author>Matt Ember</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Tom Dey</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Matthew McConaughey</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Jessica Parker</actor>
      <actor>Zooey Deschanel</actor>
      <actor>Justin Bartha</actor>
      <actor>Bradley Cooper</actor>
      <actor>Terry Bradshaw</actor>
      <actor>Kathy Bates</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>97</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a guy comedy being mismarketed as a chick flick, complete with a poster that looks like a page from Lucky magazine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64975.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is one of the best American films in months and months and the best comedy since I don't know when. It even makes you sorta kinda like Matthew McConaughey.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1115177&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"The Family Stone" did nothing for Parker, but Failure to Launch makes a strong case for life after "Sex and the City."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/10/DDGTAHKMOI8.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's comfort in seeing actors we know doing what we've come to expect them to do. But more important, the film surrounds them with supporting characters who are less familiar to us, who act in ways we don't expect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.launch10mar10,0,5799718.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie brings to mind the more polite parts of "Wedding Crashers."  Failure to Launch, while totally exuberant and appealingly made, is not nearly as randy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8454</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bradshaw, who is funnier than you might suspect, also turns out to be the most fearless of performers.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=534413&amp;reviewId=20295</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That there's precious little chemistry between buffed-and-tanned stars Parker and McConaughey is only the first of this slight, overly busy film's problems.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46648</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An especially slight romantic comedy whose modest charms are derived largely from its supporting players.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929831?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has only the most tenuous connection with reality. But the same could be said of classic 30's screwball comedies in which the treacherous feints and ploys of the mating game are transmuted into witty, romantically charged repartee.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/movies/10fail.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Failure to Launch fails at more than just launching. It fails at romance and comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/f/failure_launch.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deschanel, as the token oddball of the gang, runs off with the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A345387</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Failure to Launch has all the gravitas of a midseason-replacement sitcom.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,wilonsky,72453,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you like Kathy Bates movies, you'll probably be frustrated with this one, since as Tripp's mother, the invaluable character actress is made to whipsaw between playing sappy domestic slave to her son's laundry and salty, overly sexual wife.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1171061_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Failure to Launch sounds like really bad Oscar Wilde, but it's not that good. You are not supposed to dislike anybody here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-10-2006/front/story/398544p-337572c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Matthew McConaughey and Sarah Jessica Parker look and act, quite attractively, like grown-ups, and their easy rapport makes them convincing and appealing as an on-screen couple. So all throughout Failure to Launch, I found myself wishing they were in a different movie, maybe one as sophisticated as "The Philadelphia Story," which the movie references, but doesn't remotely live up to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-failure10mar10,0,4814152.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thanks largely to Ms. Parker and to the delectable Zooey Deschanel as her anhedonic house-mate, the filmmakers still manage to squeeze some juice out.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>McConaughey and Parker get stranded with thanklessly predictable scenes, while Zooey Deschanel, Kathy Bates and Terry Bradshaw garner the film's few laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002115865</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Suffers from the problem that plagues too many romantic comedies: The supporting characters are roughly 1,000 percent more interesting than the main characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1141858523148590.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deschanel may not be as brilliant as the great comedian Gracie Allen (and, at any rate, it's too soon to tell). But her Rube Goldberg timing (which only seems indirect) and blissfully zonked demeanor suggest the spirit of Allen. She's the only actor in Failure to Launch who isn't earthbound; she leaves everyone else in the dust simply by hanging back.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/03/10/failure/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though McConaughey has proven himself game for romantic comedy contrivance in the past, his charisma is all wrong for the immature Tripp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2658</url>
         <critic>Allison Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somehow the screwball concoction does not jell. The stars are pleasant but unexciting, the goofy ensemble has a few moments of hilarity but never catches fire, the laughs are very scattered and the film's title is a self-fulfilling prophecy.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/262402_launch10q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only bright spot--beyond McConaughey's boyish Southern charm and a pleasant soundtrack--is Zooey Deschanel as Parker's acid-tongued roommate, whose quirks include alcoholism and nihilism. Someone really should tell Deschanel that she's already too big and too good for thankless Eve Arden roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46104</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even by the low standards of high-concept Hollywood rom-coms, this charmless, prophetically titled stinker stands apart, suggesting that the recent mass firings at studio Paramount may not have been such a bad idea after all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film-reviews/12859/film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's amazing is how far McConaughey carries this nonsense despite his total lack of chemistry with Parker and almost Zen-like indifference to his circumstances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060310.FAILURE10/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Apocalyptically awful romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=534413&amp;reviewId=20310</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cursed with an honest title, Failure to Launch waves a white flag in scene after scene, declaring surrender. We give up! We do not know how to make a decent mainstream romantic comedy!</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060310-movies-review-failure,0,1515661.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Parker is bland throughout. Maybe all those episodes of "Sex and the City" have soured her on this sort of thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0310/p11s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's notion of humor is exemplified by Bradshaw's extended nude scene, which might be termed "roughing the viewer."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29399_FAILURE_TO_LAUNCH.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that normally someone like Adam Sandler would star in, but for some reason Matthew McConaughey decided to star and show that he's still not funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8829</url>
         <critic>Felix Vasques Jr.</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The premise is misbegotten, the chemistry non-existent and the dialogue leaden. Did we mention how tediously the plot unfolds?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-03-09-failure-to-launch_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>During the course of Failure to Launch, characters are bitten by a chipmunk, a dolphin, a lizard and a mockingbird. I am thinking my hardest why this is considered funny, and I confess defeat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060309/REVIEWS/60308002/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$88,715,192</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$50,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$24,411,322</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,057</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>kathy bates</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>kathy bates</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>