<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Fierce People</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dirk Wittenborn</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Griffin Dunne</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USACanada</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Diane Lane</actor>
      <actor>Anton Yelchin</actor>
      <actor>Donald Sutherl</actor>
      <actor>Chris Evans</actor>
      <actor>Kristen Stewart</actor>
      <actor>Paz de la Huerta</actor>
      <actor>Blu Mankuma</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 7, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>135</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is worthwhile primarily for the fun, breezy first hour. After that, it's a case of watching to find out how things turn out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/f/fierce_people.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Griffin Dunne's adaptation of Dirk Wittenborn's fiercely personal novel ambles pleasantly through coming-of-age movie territory, then takes a jarring Agatha Christie detour.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09072007/entertainment/movies/boy_meets_world__its_odd.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whenever Sutherland comes on scene, any inadequacies in the film's depiction of the well-to-do become irrelevant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926923.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=lions+gate%2C+%22Fierce+people%22</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whereas most of the injustices suffered by "Nanny's" nanny are of the skin-deep variety, the hopelessly reductive Fierce People ups the ante.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0736,foundas_ts,77687,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fierce People's first hour is dominated by brittle social satire, but in its third act, the film takes a jarring turn toward tremblingly sincere melodrama it can't pull off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/fierce_people</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When F. Scott Fitzgerald remarked that the rich “are different from you and me,” he might have been thinking of someone like the moody billionaire from Fierce People.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/09/07/movies/07fier.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not even the always reliable Diane Lane can save this one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/fierce-people/review/290263</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What might have read as a dense allegory comparing the rituals of the super-rich with the tribal customs of the violent Ishkanani tribe in the Amazon becomes a tedious, over-ripe soap opera on screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/09/07/2007-09-07_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dunne and Wittenborn, who adapted his book, work too hard at stressing just how ruthless the unspoken standards of the stinking rich can be, leading to a story-pivoting act of brutality toward Finn that careens the movie into a tonal wilderness that it never recovers from.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules14sep14,0,6680268.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Robert Abele</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The idea that rich people are an alien tribe is just one of many that get lost in Wittenborn’s distracted script. Instead of exploring the concept, he throws out random incidents until he hits one that sends the film into a dark, grotesque spiral.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-fierce-people/193798/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fierce People is no ordinary dud. This seedy soap opera is the most outlandish, campy romp through the mud since "Showgirls."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/332479_fierce21q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When the tone goes from daffy to dour in the course of a harrowing plot point, the story becomes more forced than fierce.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1094210&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The platitudes in this gratuitously sentimental movie are taken a lot more seriously than the people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=6975</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never recovers from a jarring and improbable act of ritualized violence that occurs halfway through the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32110_FIERCE_PEOPLE.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plays like a movie that some teenage boy cooked up in his chemistry lab. There are lots of potent things floating around in it - sexual initiation, drugs, fantasy-land wealth, brute violence, primitive rituals, Diane Lane and Donald Sutherland - but the mix just sits there without producing any notable reactions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/09/21/DD6TS9EBL.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Steve Winn</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$85,410</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$19,968</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>