<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Final Season, The</name>
   <company>Yari Film Group</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>James Grayford</author>
      <author>Art D&amp;#039;Alessandro</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>David M. Evans</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sean Astin</actor>
      <actor>Powers Boothe</actor>
      <actor>Rachael Leigh Cook</actor>
      <actor>Michael Angarano</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 12, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>114</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yes it's as corny as Kansas in August, but this admittedly formulaic sports drama is base on a true story and has something important to say about the fate of many small Midwestern American towns whose popular sports teams fall victim to school consolidation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/final-season/review/290394</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a sign on the way into Norway, or at least a sign that somebody from the film crew put up: "On the eighth day, God created baseball." If amen is your answer to that, then The Final Season is the movie for you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20071012_The_Final_Season___1_2.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Formulaic but not cynical, The Final Season has some sweet, thoughtful passages in what is otherwise just one more well-meaning inspirational sports movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/movie-reviews-berkeley-the-heartbreak-kid-lust-caution/17457/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are too many unearned runs to fully embrace this underdog triumph.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/335129_final12q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nathan Wang's score borrows blatantly from "The Natural" and is slathered on thick in all the big emotional scenes. They establish the right nostalgic mood, but it's broken with that loud "ping" of a metal bat every time a kid gets a hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1140021&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Mike Mayo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's not quite as much corn in The Final Season as there is in the Iowa farm fields that run through it, but it's close.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934998.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Evans' goal is to do for high school baseball what "Hoosiers" did for high school basketball, but to mention both titles in one sentence is almost an insult to a picture that many rank as the first or second all-time sports film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/f/final_season.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Follows a predictable format.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/10/12/DDJVSOEGF.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This takes place in the same sort of pathologically sports-obsessed hamlet as "Friday Night Lights," though in contrast to that movie's grim honesty there's enough heartland schmaltz here to embarrass John Mellencamp. Remarkably, the movie rights itself once the actual season begins, focusing on game strategy more than the usual heart-stopping pep talks.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32238_FINAL_SEASON.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is decent and heartfelt, and it eventually settles into some sharp diamond action, but the small-town homilies are dropped like an anvil. If you thought 1993's "Rudy" was too spare and unsentimental, Final Season is for you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10618</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a movie where the timing of a squeeze bunt is presented as the thing of beauty that it is, and the eradication of small-town culture in a changing world is a genuine concern, the simplifying countrified morality of The Final Season is the real crying shame.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules12oct12,0,4714182.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Exactly the formulaic, by-the-numbers movie it appears to be. These Tigers deserved better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/267449.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All these stereotypes are meant to exalt small-town values, but The Final Season is proof that it's hard to paint masterpiece in broad strokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_final_season</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Poor writing, an indifferent production and sincere but often wooden acting make "Season" one big strikeout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=1Z2WHK2hn6QGyTg8wygQgLLnRyN2FC4mdbNz4CXpfNHk5vTzn8sj!-1002209892&amp;&amp;rid=10008</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Viewers who don’t flee the intrusively uplifting soundtrack and choking sentiment get just what that opening promised: a by-the-numbers, based-in-reality inspirational sports movie, thick with overwhelming pride and nostalgia for small-town farmland America.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-final/220106/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kind of "Hoosiers": Part 2. But the storytelling is so backassward that it’s impossible to care about any of the characters or really engage in the movie whatsoever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A548589</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,159,691</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$664,351</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,011</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>