<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Firewall</name>
   <company>Warner Bros.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Joe Forte</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Richard Loncraine</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Harrison Ford</actor>
      <actor>Paul Bettany</actor>
      <actor>Virginia Madsen</actor>
      <actor>Mary Lynn Rajskub</actor>
      <actor>Robert Patrick</actor>
      <actor>Robert Forster</actor>
      <actor>Alan Arkin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thriller with enough of the right ingredients to provide a couple hours of escapism.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/f/firewall.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An ingenious attempt to update an old plot with new technology, and it is made with competence, skillful acting, and the ability to make us feel cleverer about digital stuff than we really are.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060209/REVIEWS/60131009/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, it's a satisfying example of the classic thriller, with a nifty digital update for these times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060210.FIREWALL10/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Kate Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's almost nothing you haven't seen before in this slick, preposterous, but occasionally exciting thriller. An angry Ford absorbs, and dishes out, massive punishment for a fellow his age, while Virginia Madsen is sadly wasted as his wife.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/11178535/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the wrestling match between the banker and the bad guy that fuels the audience's adrenaline.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.firewall10feb10,0,5459339.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie, an efficient time-passer at least until the plot starts obsessing over the fate of the family dog, is more into gadgets than people.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060210-movies-review-firewall,0,3512822.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's just not enough of Forster, who has a small role as Ford's work colleague and confidant. ..Sometimes star quality shines out from the corners of a movie, and not from the center.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/10/firewall/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The amount of enjoyment one gets out of the Harrison Ford crime-action thriller Firewall depends on one's tolerance for watching thugs terrify an innocent family for most of the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001957329</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Firewall begins slowly, exhibits hints of promise in the middle and then descends into silliness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929465?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director, Richard Loncraine, doesn't generate much tension in Firewall's first half...The standard-issue climax is pretty exciting, though.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/15702/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To make something like Firewall good, you have to make it at least a little bit new--or add more than an unending patter of rain and techno-talk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1156608,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a thriller, Firewall is flabby and familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/8088653/rid/9249502/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ford, soon to be eligible for Medicare, gives his entire performance without
losing his breath or changing his expression, and Bettany, a British actor
whose pasty complexion won him the role of Silas the Albino in the coming
"The Da Vinci Code," is an apt tormentor cum foil of his prey.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-10-2006/entertainment/col/story/390199p-330830c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everything here is a known quantity except one question that could have been inspired by a Tootsie Roll Pop commercial: How many twists does it take to finally, at long last, get to the predictable ending?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45222</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Firewall might be worth renting on an inclement weekend when the pickings are slim. It does have some tense moments - even if some of the technical plot points don't quite scan. But, overall, it just feels like a rehash.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-02-09-firewall-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It disrespects Seattle. Not only is this yet another filmed-in-Vancouver movie that's supposed to be set here, it takes place in a blinding rainstorm of the kind only a Hollywood rain machine can make. As we all know, it never rains like that in Seattle.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/258968_firewall10q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For though it is a reasonable facsimile of a successful thriller, this film (named after a barrier that protects computers from hackers) never manages to be more than mildly effective.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-firewall10feb10,0,3079116.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Manages to entertain mildly only because it traffics in all the familiar action-movie clichés, giving moviegoers ample opportunity to test their action-movie I.Q.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/10/movies/10fire.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I like it for the thing it is, a reasonably solid B movie, and I like it as one in the continuum of bizarre Ford vehicles that combine high-stakes action with household horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/10/DDGK8H57F31.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We spend too much time with the kidnappers - a veritable Geek Squad of undifferentiated techies - as each successive escape attempt is foiled and our eyes are warped by abundant shots of computer screens and grainy surveillance-camera footage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12621&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>John Patterson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Firewall’s predictable second half betrays the film's early promise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8636</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It starts off with a slick split-screen bang, but this high tech heist thriller is like a For Dummies guide to the genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A336278</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the many disappointments of Firewall is how it squanders its own cast. Good character actors, including Robert Forster and Alan Arkin, are wasted--literally, in some cases, as the body count piles up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2135825/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Harrison Ford carries this talky, formulaic thriller by virtue of his authority, culled from years in front of the camera, but his performance can't obscure the obvious plot machinations.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29282_FIREWALL.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie like this needs a suave, amoral villain, so here's Paul Bettany.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8586</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although a happy ending is preordained, at least Joe Forte's script takes the less-obvious route there.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=534420&amp;reviewId=20104</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a while, Firewall whips up the accordant dollops of suspense and dread, but it's not long before the timely issue of identity theft takes a backseat to old-fashioned Hollywood villainy, unnecessary (and nonsensical) red herrings, and STUFF THAT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=534420&amp;reviewId=20097&amp;startDate=02%2F10%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Firewall does more to destroy my desire to see a new Indiana Jones movie than anything the aging process could conjure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1139444711110160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's disconcerting to see Virginia Madsen, who was so marvelous in her 2004 comeback role in "Sideways" reduced to playing the terrified wife here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0210/p11s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As used cars go, the latest and possibly last Harrison Ford thriller, Firewall, is no deal: It runs rough, stalls frequently, smells like the stale sweat of four dozen older movies, and handles like a blind mule.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0606,atkinson,72087,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flagging energy isn't the only issue here; Ford has become enslaved in his own cliches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1116970&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Covers disappointingly predictable territory for an actor of Ford's skills and reputation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=11144</url>
         <critic>Tony Horkins</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Clichés are often a big part of what makes suspense films enjoyable. But Firewall goes out of its way to promise something more than business as usual, and then makes no attempt whatsoever to deliver.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2478</url>
         <critic>John Migliore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kind of thriller whose ridiculous climax hinges on a hitherto undisclosed GPS tracking device in a dog's collar - an appropriate touch in a movie that's more than a little flea-ridden itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/63260.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The charismatic Rajskub, who played a prickly computer geek on TV's "24," has nothing to do as Jack's loyal secretary.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46647</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its execution is stultifying, laughable and ultimately a little offensive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-02-09/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Before Firewall crumbles into foolishness, Harrison Ford and Paul Bettany make an oft-recycled plot look like a stylish model that just rolled out of a showroom.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Firewall is a witless entertainment, and a derivative one, too; it's everything listless about Hollywood in February, everything discardable about the genre in general.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1157675_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$48,751,189</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,635,463</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,840</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>harrison ford</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>