<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Flawless</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Edward Anderson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Radford</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael Caine</actor>
      <actor>Demi Moore</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 28, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>100</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>As heist films go, Radford has crafted an engaging, if not especially memorable one, with Flawless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/f/flawless2008.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pleasure of watching such well-crafted entertainment offsets the small disappointments.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/356709_flawless28q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the diamond-heist thriller Flawless, there aren't a lot of diamonds, heists or thrills. But there is a nice sense of style, and appreciation for tense face-to-face confrontations among characters trying to ignore the temptations around them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/03/28/2008-03-28_michael_caine_and_demi_moore_shine_in_fl.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flawless is a fictional tale, but something in director Michael Radford's conscientious, methodical presentation gives it the feeling of true history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/03/27/DDVIVQB19.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's assured and neatly crafted - the time zips by while you're watching it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10775</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caine is reason enough to see any movie. He gives this clever, somewhat lumbering caper movie a deep-seated soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0328/p15s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A modest little caper film that satisfies chiefly because of its relative familiarity and lack of ambition.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/04/review_flawless_not_exactly.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The joy of this movie, which features Joss Ackland as a memorably intimidating, Afrikaner-accented boss, is in the gradual revelation of intrigue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1060683&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Over all though, this is a first rate caper piece elevated by Caine’s effortlessly elegant portrayal. The movie is wall to wall with pompous, sexist, greedy backstabbers and it’s a hoot to watch Hobbs mop the floor with the lot of them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10917</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Polished but oddly lifeless heist thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/flawless/review/291341</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The filmmakers' narrative device of framing Quinn's tale as a feature-length flashback doesn't pay off - we get a goody-two-shoes moral lesson at the end, and a look at movie studio aging makeup gone wild.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080328__Flawless__loses_a_few_points_on_clarity.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I enjoyed seeing Joss Ackland as well. The veteran character actor with the world’s lowest voice plays the diamond company chairman, and when he rumbles out orders, it’s like Sensurround never left us.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-flawless/355462/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The heist in Flawless comes at the film's midpoint, but although Radford wrings some nice suspense from the sequence, the theft isn't his primary focus here. It's what happens next.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/490124.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mildly diverting period heist movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/03/28/movies/28flaw.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not the freshest heist movie ever made, Flawless still has a few pleasures to offer, thanks to a well-studied social and political background and to Michael Caine's lovely creation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9978&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Gregory Valens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As neatly tailored, clean-cut, and visually appealing as a Savile Row suit. But audiences accustomed to more knowing fare are likely to find its twists and turns outdated while yearning for a little of the rebellious fun that made the genre gleam in the first place.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934943.html?categoryid=2850&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Holland</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Moore hasn't tackled a lead role since the turn of the century, and judging by her eminently forgettable work here, she hasn't spent that time painstakingly honing her chops.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/flawless</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's left to Caine to wink and nod at his own contribution to real caper classics of the 1960s and '70s, produced with more emphasis on fun and less on instructive fact-finding.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20186510,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flawless never begins to live up to its title.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/151/story/585022.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot contortions that very slowly unfold under Michael Radford's arthritic direction in Flawless are not much more entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03282008/entertainment/movies/latest_demi_chore__blame_it_on_botox_103816.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flawless is the sort of movie that tends to get called "enjoyably old-fashioned," except that there's nothing enjoyable about it. The pacing is torpid, the plotting slack, and the performances utterly joyless--chiefly Moore, who walks through every scene with her face stretched into an expressionless mask, her lips pressed into a permanent pout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0813,flawless,389148,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,200,234</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$181,910</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>35</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>michael caine</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>