<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Flicka</name>
   <company>Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Rosenthal</author>
      <author>Lawrence Konner</author>
      <author>Mary O&amp;#039;Hara</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Mayer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Alison Lohman</actor>
      <actor>Tim McGraw</actor>
      <actor>Maria Bello</actor>
      <actor>Ryan Kwanten</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Pino</actor>
      <actor>Dallas Roberts</actor>
      <actor>Kaylee DeFer</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Nordling</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 20, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>94</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not really either an animal or a kids' film but rather a young adult drama that rings emotionally true.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931913.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is purely and fearlessly a girl-and-her-horse movie that isn't trying to be all things for all audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/289300_flicka20q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So those seeking a softer approach to the realities of both child- and animal-rearing should search elsewhere. The rest of us, meanwhile, are free to enjoy a well-made family drama pitched to young adults that's honest, tough and surprisingly engaging.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118092&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best parts of Flicka are its pinch-me optimism and its old-fashioned-movie flourishes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7898</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film paints a fairly realistic portrait of four people bound by blood but -- like all of us -- all too capable of underestimating each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=726455&amp;reviewId=21645</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to argue with the movie's big heart, solid craftsmanship, likable characters, decent acting, gorgeous scenery or the fact that it's going to leave its audience blubbering and smiling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1161212111133160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Give Flicka credit for one thing: It stays on message. Set against the gorgeous backdrop of a Wyoming mountain range--a view this time unobstructed by the gay cowboys who so alarm family audiences--the film offers up fantasy footage for every strong-willed girl who ever straddled a saddle, and little more.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/54281</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As for our heroine (Lohman), her archetypal struggle with crusty Pa (uncrusty Tim McGraw) feels attitude-heavy and life-lesson-light.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1547551_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One casting wild card is the country singer Tim McGraw, and he's very solid in the role of Katie's horse-rancher dad, the kind of guy whose hard-headedness can't mask the size of his heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3196/flicka.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With some movies, you know exactly what you're going to see before you even enter the theater, and Michael Mayer's Flicka is one of them: You've got your girl, you've got your horse, and you've got your strict father trying to keep them apart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/10-20-2006/entertainment/col/story/463502p-389824c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mayer knows how to tug at the heartstrings, and his admirably restrained cast keeps the family drama from becoming too sugary.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=283877&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Angel Cohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yet -- and this must be said in all fairness -- as things progress, the magic of the story asserts itself over the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061020.FLICKA20/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>David Gilmour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An entertainingly ridiculous update of Mary O’Hara’s 1941 children’s novel, “My Friend Flicka.”</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/10/20/movies/20flic.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A modernized version of that great sentimental horse movie, 1943's "My Friend Flicka," and it comes with the shiny trappings, high professionalism and glamorous accessories you might expect...Something is missing though.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061020-movies-review-flicka,0,5744402.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoroughly uninspiring drama that ultimately buckles under Michael Mayer's weighty direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003285041</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are some nice moments and beautiful scenery, but the film is often slow and the dialogue is overwrought.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/20/DDGFFLRSLP1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Another miscalculation by sophomore director Michael Mayer.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30474_FLICKA.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It takes a pristine gift for mediocrity to ruin Mary O'Hara’s muscular children's novel about a wild boy and his wild horse, but director Michael Mayer has brought off the massacre with aplomb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14820/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As misconceived as it is corny and predictable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10202006/entertainment/movies/just_vote_neigh_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If all you ask of a movie is that it have scenic stars and some scenery (here the Sierras of California substitute for the Rockies of Wyoming), then Flicka is adequate. Me, I expected some conflict, some resolution, and a horse that took me on a wild ride. This one really never gets out of the gate.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/movies/15801019.htm</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No doubt the most devoted horse lovers in the tween set will get their fill, but parents should sneak out for a very long popcorn break.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A411588</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$21,000,147</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$7,703,551</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,877</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>