<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Flight of the Red Balloon, The</name>
   <company>IFC First Take</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Hsiao-hsien Hou</author>
      <author>François Margolin</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Hsiao-hsien Hou</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>France</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Juliette Binoche</actor>
      <actor>Hippolyte Girardot</actor>
      <actor>Simon Iteanu</actor>
      <actor>Fang Song</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 4, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>113</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flight of the Red Balloon is in a class by itself. In its unexpected rhythms and visual surprises, its structural innovations and experimental perfs, its creative misunderstandings and its outré syntheses, this is a movie of genius.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0814,floating-life,396126,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is not a children's picture, although it touches on the imaginative powers and emotional resilience of children. It's another slice of Hou's distinctly poetic realism, and as such, also a kind of tribute to Paris -- the Paris of both today and of the older film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4491/flight-of-the-red-balloon.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gem made by a filmmaker who loves life, and knows how to capture its ebb and flow and sweet complication.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-flight-of/380516/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because it's one of the most beautiful films ever. Because it's a work of art on the order of a poem by Yeats or a painting by Rothko.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/04/17/AR2008041703662.html</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hou's first film made outside of Asia is his most emotionally turbulent, yet he remains, like the balloon, outside looking in, a compassionate but distant observer capturing it all with a graceful restraint and floating beauty that ultimately carried me away with it.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/361412_limited02.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Juliette Binoche is outstanding as a wildly untogether single mother who parks her son with a French-speaking Chinese nanny while she whirls and worries.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20187733,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's both happy and sad. That's exactly the way to describe Hou's marvelous film as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/05/18/cannes_3/index.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end what elevates Mr. Hou’s films to the sublime -- and this one comes close at times -- are not the stories but their telling.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/04/04/movies/04ball.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Mr. Hou has done is borrow power and some gentle intimations of a state of grace from one of the most enchanting images in movie history.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120847468724024687.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The camera is so unobtrusive and the acting so naturalistic that it takes a while for a narrative to emerge. When it finally does, you're surprised to find you're deeply invested in the characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-balloon18apr18,0,6190426.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In The Flight of the Red Balloon, the great Taiwanese filmmaker Hou Hsiao Hsien uses Albert Lamorisse’s 1956 masterpiece "The Red Balloon" as a springboard for his own masterpiece--a distinctively modern and allusive one, yet so tender and plaintive that you understand what Hou is up to on a preconscious level.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/45605/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hou intends to celebrate the classic 1956 children's film "The Red Balloon," and he has done a beautiful job. In fact, he may well have created a future classic of his own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/04/04/2008-04-04_short_takes_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The subject is the privileged state of childhood itself - how we're all lucky to have had it and how it so easily floats away from our grasp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2008/04/18/childhood_floats_away_in_red_balloon/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A meditation on art, life, loneliness and the links between friends and strangers, the movie has a grace and humor that's wonderfully inviting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080509_Flight_of_the_Red_Balloon____1_2.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its fuss and fury, Flight of the Red Balloon succeeds magnificently.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080516.wballoon16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too much of this film is attenuated and vague, but it has moments of deep melancholy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0404/p15s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This eloquent study of loneliness and postmodern drift likely will be received with more admiration than rapture by the helmer's followers. But Juliette Binoche's turn as a harried single mom and pic's enlivening portrait of domestic rupture make this a highly accessible Hou.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117933651&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flight was commissioned by producers overseas, and it feels similarly, impeccably slight.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_flight_of_the_red_balloon</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fans of Hou know just what to expect from his slow, contemplative films - and they won't be disappointed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04042008/entertainment/movies/flight_of_fancy_goes_the_distance_104878.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's not much story here, but the characters are substantial: a single mother (nicely played by Juliette Binoche) who runs a local avant-garde puppet theater and is preoccupied with such matters as a downstairs tenant who refuses to pay rent or leave, her neglected but mainly cheerful son, and his Taiwanese nanny, a filmmaker in her spare time.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/32380_FLIGHT_OF_THE_RED_BALLOON</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, though, it's hard not to feel like Hou is saying more explicitly and expansively in nearly two hours what Lamorisse managed to convey in only one-fourth as much film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/05/review_a_limpid_journey_in_the.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The balloon will resurface throughout, but far more interesting, and substantial, is the slow reveal of Simon's domestic situation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A639287</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not surprisingly, we're left with characters that feel only half sketched and fail to resonate on their own -- but onto which much can be read by Hou's most ardent fans -- in a poetic looking film that's ultimately as inflated and empty as the balloon itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/flight-red-balloon/review/293186</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$459,364</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$35,222</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>