<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Food, Inc.</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert Kenner</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael Pollan</actor>
      <actor>Eric Schlosserhberg</actor>
      <actor>Gary Hirschberg</actor>
      <actor>Joe Salatin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 12, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>94</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Food, Inc. is hard to shake, because days after you've seen it, you may find yourself eating something -- a cookie, a piece of poultry, cereal out of the box, a perfectly round waxen tomato -- and you'll realize that you have virtually no idea what it actually is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20284274,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Essential viewing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-food12-2009jun12,0,1904112.story</url>
         <critic>Gary Goldstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mind-boggling, heart-rending, stomach-churning expose on the food industry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/06/11/MVE1184DN6.DTL</url>
         <critic>Amy Binacolli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not a pretty picture. But Food, Inc. is an essential one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090619__Food__Inc___can_throw_a_scare_into_any_eater.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A scary movie that's also funny, touching and good for you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/bal-ae.mo.food03jul03,0,4736004.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smart, gripping, and untainted by the influence of Michael Moore, this muckraking 2008 documentary transcends anticorporate demonology to build a visceral but reasoned case against modern agribusiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#34491</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An engaging and often wrenching film, Food, Inc. covers a wide range of material, including the horrific, the humorous and the exemplary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/06/12/food_inc/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Expertly crafted documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-06-10/film/dying-to-eat-in-food-inc/</url>
         <critic>Robert Sietsema</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eating can be one dangerous business. Don't take another bite till you see Robert Kenner's Food, Inc., an essential, indelible documentary that is scarier than anything in the last five Saw horror shows.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/24044311/review/28631104/food_inc</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I figured it wasn't important for me to go into detail about the photography and the editing. I just wanted to scare the bejesus out of you, which is what Food, Inc. did to me.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090617/REVIEWS/906179985</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like many social issue documentaries, Food, Inc. is better at addressing problems than offering solutions: its endorsement of organic food in particular feels a little flimsy. Nevertheless, it’s entertaining and fast-moving enough to make audiences intermittently forget they’re consuming cinematic health food.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/food-inc,29094/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though slickly packaged, Robert Kenner's unsparing exposé is harder to watch than any horror film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/06/11/2009-06-11_short_film_reviews_moon_.html?page=1</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For many of this movie's likely viewers, the sting built into Food, Inc. is the realization that, without unending effort, they are not all that much freer in their choices than that hard-pressed family.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/06/29/090629crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>See Food, Inc. after dinner, but see it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/food-inc.,1156494.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Compelling, entertaining and illuminating documentary which makes you think twice, and then a few more times, about eating anything at all in U.S.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136687</url>
         <critic>Phil Wilding</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why wait for 2012? If you're hankering for a taste of the apocalypse, the opening sequence of this eye-opening, stomach-queasing doc has plenty to go on – witness menacing superimpositions on a bleak, blighted landscape – and the hits just keep on coming.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A785271</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a result, the slickly produced Food, Inc. is more deeply unsettling than it is out-and-out stomach-turning.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/07/food_inc_serves_up_troubling_t.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In many areas, Food Inc. could be accused of being a fast-food version of a documentary – it's everywhere at once, skipping across the surface of a vast subject, and adding nuggets of sweetness to the scary filler.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/food-inc/article1187449/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kenner mounts it all with a pleasingly fluent and varied style, which makes it more or less easy to absorb his arguments, even if they're familiar from other books and movies and are presented with unopposed certainty.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/06/you_are_what_you_eat_food_inc.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Food, Inc. argues that part of the reason why the food industry is so difficult to regulate is that many of the government officials currently assigned to watchdog roles were once employed by the companies they now keep tabs on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1102703.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The whole thing is as subtle as a watermelon in a bowl of Cheerios but necessary, nonetheless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/06/19/food_inc_serves_up_righteous_indignation/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Wal-Mart, the Lucifer of multinational corporations in many liberal eyes, sees the fiscal sense in stocking an increasingly wide array of organic foodstuffs, consumer habits truly are changing. Not fast enough, though, for documentary filmmaker Robert Kenner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-tc-mov-food-inc-0617-0619jun19,0,7275683.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Time and again the movie stops short before it really gets started, as with the debates over the big business of organic food.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/12/movies/12food.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No question, watching this film is a tough go. Horror films cause less seat-squirming.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-food-inc-1003984159.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sheer scale of the movie is mind-blowing--it touches on every aspect of modern life. It's the documentary equivalent of "The Matrix": It shows us how we're living in a simulacrum, fed by machines run by larger machines with names like Monsanto, Perdue, Tyson, and the handful of other corporations that make everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/57178/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A civilized horror movie for the socially conscious, the nutritionally curious and the hungry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938322.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Food%2C+Inc%2E</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>And to all you sane folk out there, be prepared when seeing this film: you'll ponder the old adage about being what you eat. For those new to the truth about food, this is a great starting point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11785</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie offers very little that food radicals don't already know.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06122009/entertainment/movies/bean_there__bun_that_173780.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$4,417,124</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$60,513</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>