<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Frozen River</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Courtney Hunt</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Courtney Hunt</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Melissa Leo</actor>
      <actor>Misty Upham</actor>
      <actor>Michael O&amp;#039;Keefe</actor>
      <actor>Charlie McDermott</actor>
      <actor>Mark Boone Jr.</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 1, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>97</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's tough and cold and gives an inside look at poverty in America. Yet the film is also incredibly compelling and intense and I can't think of another film that's this small and powerful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10558</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the summer heats up, let Frozen River wash over you; let its bracing drama and the intensity of its acting restore your spirits as well as your faith in American independent film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/la-et-river1-2008aug01,0,628939.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, you feel that Frozen River gives about as truthful a picture of American bleakness as it's possible for a movie to present. It is a movie that asks something of an audience, but it richly rewards our curiously rapt attention.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1828471,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes two performances come along that are so perfectly matched that no overt signals are needed to show how the characters feel about each other. That's what happens between Melissa Leo and Misty Upham in Frozen River.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080814/REVIEWS/808140302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is nothing sentimental or picturesque about the performances or imagery. The word that best describes both is elemental.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080822__Frozen_River___A_survival_story.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A tale of ordinary Americans scraping bottom, yet there's a redemption in that. The film asks: If you were this desperate, wouldn't you do the same?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20215916,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a debut feature, though you'd never know it from the filmmaker's commandingly confident style, or from the heartbreaking beauty -- heartbreaking, then heartmending -- of Melissa Leo's performance as a poor single mother who's living her whole life on thin ice.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121754141052502239.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ms. Hunt's eye for detail has the precision of a short story writer's. She misses nothing.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/08/01/movies/01froz.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Made with uncommon skill and assurance, the film never succumbs to rank sentimentality, but it manages to get at the nuances of human relationships.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1148148&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does what too many independent American movies only pretend to do: Takes you to an unnoticed corner of our country and shows what it's like to actually live there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11705</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A Sundance hit that is both absorbing and bleak, Frozen River is anchored by powerful performances, believable scenarios and excellent writing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-07-31-frozen-river_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Possibly one of the biggest reasons Frozen River stands out among bad-decision movies is that Ray never really tries to justify her actions.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-frozen-river/553259/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strikingly authentic, socially conscious crime drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/frozen-river/review/294758</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is no shortage of indie movies about economically challenged women. This one is different, in that the women actually do something besides just talk about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08012008/entertainment/movies/ice_road_suckers_122461.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Melissa Leo is startlingly good...You feel like you're watching a life, not a performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0802/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If there's one thing this movie gets dead right, it's the desperation of impoverished single mothers trying to fend for their children.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-07-29/film/frozen-river-lays-it-on-thick/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frozen River isn't cinematically ambitious or formally adventurous, but it's built around powerful and nuanced performances by Leo, Upham and Charlie McDermott.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2008/07/30/frozen_river/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Original, sad, suspenseful and involving: the kind of work that helps independent American cinema retain its good name.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=136482</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A first-rate thriller, maintaining a high level of suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33435_FROZEN_RIVER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frozen River skates matter-of-factly on thin ice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A668288</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A solid, satisfying movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.river05sep05,0,2772464.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's greatest achievement is that it allows us to know Ray.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080825.wfrozen25/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Melissa Leo is one of America's most underrated character actresses, and Frozen River confirms that opinion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotteobserver.com/312/story/169510.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not a happy film, but it feels true.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/08/movie_review_the_thaw_of_the_h.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the role brings her more recognition and work, all the better, but Leo certainly isn't lobbying for it. She doesn't show off. She just does what she's always done: Reveals a character for who she is, nothing more, nothing less.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/frozen_river</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most films about illegal immigration are set on the Mexican border, and Frozen River is free of the stereotypical characters and situations of that familiar setting. It also offers a rare look at modern Native American life, exploring the ambiguity of what it means to say that the laws of the white man cannot be enforced on Indian territory.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/375018_frozenriver15q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No trendsetter or breakthrough, this is more than anything else a welcome chance for the fine actor Melissa Leo to finally dominate a film in a terrific and affecting lead role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117935841&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All in all, Frozen River is gripping stuff. Except it's also rigged and cheaply manipulative.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/48934/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If we're going to be honest, we need to look inside and ask ourselves: Do we really want to see a listless movie about a woman whose dream is to move into a double-wide trailer?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/08/14/DDH2125GS1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has moments of honesty, but more often the barren landscape - both outside and inside - drains the emotions out of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/08/01/2008-08-01_short_takes_films_for_the_week_of_august.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,503,902</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$70,234</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>7</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>