<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Georgia Rule</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Andrus</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Garry Marshall</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jane Fonda</actor>
      <actor>Lindsay Lohan</actor>
      <actor>Felicity Huffman</actor>
      <actor>Dermot Mulroney</actor>
      <actor>Cary Elwes</actor>
      <actor>Garrett Hedlund</actor>
      <actor>Hector Elizondo</actor>
      <actor>Laurie Metcalf</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 11, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>113</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hector Elizondo, who has appeared in all 15 of Marshall's features, turns up as a Basque rancher and adds a bit of sparkle. I just wish Marshall's good luck charm was not a 70-year-old actor but a fresh, honest screenplay.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=868345&amp;reviewId=22439&amp;startDate=05%2F11%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The American public likes nothing better than a tragedy with a happy ending, William Dean Howells observed. But Marshall so cautiously downplays the tragic elements of his plot that the sweetness and light left a sour taste in my mouth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20070511_The_actresses_rule_in_this_soapy_story_of_3_generations.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A clunky family-therapy soaper.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20038337,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the acting contest that ensues, each star comes off reasonably well, though, surprisingly, Lohan (who had well-publicized emotional problems on the set) wins out over Huffman's comic drunk and Fonda's leathery evocation of her father, Henry, in "On Golden Pond."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/315195_georgia11q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe Georgia Rule should be required viewing for Paris Hilton during her term in the slammer. But not for us.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070511-movies-review-georgia,0,1445518.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an interesting, maddening mess -- not a terrible movie, and by no means a dull one.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/05/11/movies/11geor.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's enough family dysfunction here to fill out a dozen soppy soap operas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0511/p11s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>[Georgia Rule] is clearly intended to be an uplifting multigenerational drama about abuse, healing and forgiveness. Yet there's something unsavory about the way it uses a character's emotional and psychological scars as a gimmick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/05/11/georgia_rule/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Georgia Rule isn’t serious enough for a drama and not funny enough for a comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9995</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's almost no rescuing this wobbly movie from its showdowns and insights. Except, that is, when Lohan's around.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0719,taylor,76596,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never rings true. It's a dramedy whose blend of melodrama and humor is awkward and incongruous, leaping between the two modes like a fat frog jumping lilypads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A472763</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spin it however they like, the troubled but talented Lohan isn't what's wrong with this misbegotten mess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/georgia-rule/review/287652</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Another flabby big-screen sitcom from "Happy Days" creator Garry Marshall.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31602_GEORGIA_RULE.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Georgia Rule oscillates clumsily from shock to slapstick to schmaltz. The result of these big tonal swings is a cinematic strikeout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-georgia11may11,0,538398.story</url>
         <critic>Lael Loewenstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proves to be more prone to malfunction than dysfunction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9156</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No offense to either of them, but Georgia Rule suggests an Ingmar Bergman script as directed by Jerry Lewis. The subject matter is grim, the relationships are gnarled, the worldview is bleak, and, at any given moment, you suspect someone's going to be hit with a pie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933575.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>And so it goes, leaving an awful taste and the inevitable question: Jane Fonda made a comeback to do dreck like this and "Monster-in-Law?"</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3788/georgia-rule.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It tries to pass itself off as a film about feistiness, forgiveness and the bonds of motherhood. Instead, it deals lightly and inappropriately with promiscuity, alcoholism, drug abuse, grief and child molestation. Georgia Rule doesn't make you feel good; it makes you queasy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-05-10-georgia-rule_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Garry Marshall has too much confidence that he can match the weighty issues here with the light comedy. He can't. Or at least he can't with this cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/georgia_rule</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fonda, playing grandmother to this clan of narcissists, is the only one who keeps her dignity. She's funny and low-key and deserves better comeback material than this and "Monster-in-Law." The other two actresses are humiliated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1178749546236540.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Georgia Rule is so artificial, it feels like more of a flow chart than a slice of life.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=868345&amp;reviewId=22442</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is intended to be light and whimsical, but with a core of sincere emotion. But it's as if the thing were made by Martian anthropologists who assume that human audiences are as twisted as the people onscreen.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/05/11/DDGF5POF0P1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Misguided at best and repellent at worst, the movie has, ironically enough, a single asset: Lohan's performance as a rebellious, uncontrollable teen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/05/11/2007-05-11_georgia_goes_south.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jane Fonda does an about-face on her persona and her talent, playing a teetotaler and, what's worse, a pious bore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.georgia11may11,0,6725297.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For proof that some actresses can take on a misconceived role and get out alive, there's Huffman as Lilly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9999</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>WARNING: Do not take your mom to Georgia Rule unless she's Roseanne Barr. You may expect a three-generational chick flick, but what you get is a child-rape comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05112007/entertainment/movies/it_blohans_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just what we need least: a warm family comedy about child molestation.That's Georgia Rule, which combines battleship actresses of the "Steel Magnolias" variety, fall-down-go-boom comedy that was obsolete in the '30s, Lindsay Lohan's cleavage and intergenerational fondling just for kicks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1133688&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Marshall ( Pretty Woman) has created a comic drama so confused in tone, the actors often seem to be acting in different movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070511.wgeorgia11/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Certain words should be reserved for special occasions. "Abysmal" is one of them, and Georgia Rule is as special as such occasions get.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB117883611736999139.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$18,882,880</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$6,773,870</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,523</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jane fonda</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>