<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Get Smart</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Buck Henry</author>
      <author>Mel Brooks</author>
      <author>Matt Ember</author>
      <author>Tom J. Astle</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Peter Segal</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Steve Carell</actor>
      <actor>Anne Hathaway</actor>
      <actor>Dwayne &amp;#034;The Rock&amp;#034; Johnson</actor>
      <actor>Alan Arkin</actor>
      <actor>Terrence Stamp</actor>
      <actor>Terry Crews</actor>
      <actor>David Koechner</actor>
      <actor>James Caan</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 20, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s funny, exciting, preposterous, great to look at, and made with the same level of technical expertise we’d expect from a new Bond movie itself. And all of that is very nice, but nicer still is the perfect pitch of the casting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080619/REVIEWS/867249699/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Get Smart is action movie and spoof and, though it's often a little unbalanced, the ultimate result is a harmlessly entertaining picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/367668_get20q.html</url>
         <critic>Andy Spletzer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The unexpected star is Hathaway, looking cool as a runway model in the role originated by Barbara Feldon, lithe as a (pink) panther, and displaying great comic timing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20208092,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is fun, and hilarious, because of its child-like whimsy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11030</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Get Smart turns out to be a much more entertaining movie than its tedious trailers suggest. It's not going to redefine comedy as we know it, but it's amusing and briskly paced, busy with an engaging mix of supporting actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/575613.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Steve Carell's portrayal of Max is just about perfect for the material.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1077</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This redux is a rare device: a TV remake for the big screen that works on its own terms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0825,get-smart-a-pleasant-surprise,471367,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As for Hathaway, she's a revelation. Those eyes are still as big as Beamer hubcaps, but she's able to show more edge than her previous goody-goody roles have allowed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145215&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Get Smart could have been smarter. But like the show that inspired it, it's still smarter than it looks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/06/20/get_smart/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Get Smart the sitcom was a one-joke affair and got tedious fast, whereas Carell’s starry-eyed dweeb has room for nuance, for growth, for inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47982/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie errs by turning Max into a figure of hangdog sympathy: "The 40 Year Old Virgin" with a shoe phone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10151</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mixes broad slapstick and off-hand one-liners in a sometimes surprisingly funny mixture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20080620.SMART20/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a light, silly instantly forgettable comedy peppered with action set-pieces and affectionate nods to its fondly remembered predecessor, including a gracious end-credits dedication to the late Don Adams and Edward Platt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/smart/review/292490</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Max's even more fabled shoe phone also makes an appearance - and, fortunately for Get Smart, the self-deprecating Carell isn't shoe-phoning in his inspired performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06202008/entertainment/movies/smarts_in_the_right_place_116287.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Peter Segal ups the ante on the action, aiming for Bourne more than Bond, but the stunts grow frenzied and increasingly flat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15528090/review/21382946/get_smart</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bright enough, but stops short of being clever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-18-get-smart_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite a plot that should be simpler, Get Smart is as big on action as it is on laughs and works because it?s less a tired spoof and more a quality comedic adventure movie in its own right.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134837</url>
         <critic>Tony Horkins</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the most part it's dull, bland and unsatisfying: a food-court version of home cooking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/06/review_get_smart_misses_by_tha.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You never get the sense that the director, Peter Segal, knows where the funny is, whether in his star or in the story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-smart0620,0,4455705.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Get Smart neglects the laughs and amps up the action, resulting in a not very funny comedy joined at the hip to a not very exciting spy movie. Talk about killing two birds with one stone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-et-smart20-2008jun20,0,6046730.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Remaking Get Smart without Don Adams and Barbara Feldon is like remaking "My Little Chickadee" without Mae West and W.C. Fields--the best possible outcome is disappointment.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33262_GET_SMART.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It flounders whenever it tries to weave the real world into its fantasia, partly because it isn't really about anything other than making money, partly because the spy-versus-spy battle doesn't entertain the way it once did.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/20/movies/20smar.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All that's missing is the spirit and the anarchic humor of the sitcom created by Mel Brooks and Buck Henry. The result is an overdressed, carefully stitched scarecrow of a comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080620_Sorry_about_that__classic__Get_Smart__fans.html</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film reunites Carell with his "Little Miss Sunshine" co-star Arkin, who, as always, delivers the goods, as do most of the other supporting players. Too long by at least 15-20 minutes, Get Smart is nevertheless a giggly summer movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A637110</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Missed it by that much. Actually, the new version of Get Smart misses by a fair-size  margin.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-get-smart/463153/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a slap-dash effort whose producers threw money and stunts onscreen instead of the satirical gags and one-liners that made the old spy spoof so memorable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=HtWTLW1Fbk6jRyvTgGT6PNGRnT1N2ZNbj125GdBrFJfLPKv2f6hS!-228458968&amp;&amp;rid=11252</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Helmer Peter Segal's formulaic takeoff is neither fish nor fowl, not quite faithful to the show, but not quite bringing it into the 21st century either.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937374.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are many stretches when it's easy to forget that Get Smart is a spoof; it's more like a third-rate James Bond with pratfalls.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/get_smart</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At least we have Alan Arkin playing the head of CONTROL. His drone and deadpan are a perfect complement to Carell's. But please, pretty please, let's not go for a sequel on this one, OK?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0621/p25s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the whole cast -- including Dwayne (The Rock) Johnson -- is game, too much time was spent coordinating chase scenes and explosions, and too little fixing a slack script that relies on bathroom humor and snickering sex jokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/20/2008-06-20_tv_update_get_smart_needs_to_get_smarter.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That Max Smart is played by the admirable Steve Carell, who is desperately looking for deadpan jokes in all the wrong places, is beside the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1816518,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this distressingly generic spy spoof, it's not Maxwell who's clueless, but the filmmakers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/141503</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rather than the laugh a minute promised by old comedies, Get Smart generates approximately one laugh per hour, and I can't remember either one.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121391259991589875.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Remaking Get Smart for the big screen might have sounded like a bad idea, but the movie shows it to have been something else: a REALLY bad idea.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/19/DDAS11AKT1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$130,319,208</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$38,683,480</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,911</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>