<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Gonzo: The Life and Work of Dr. Hunter S. Thompson</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Alex Gibney</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Johnny Depp</actor>
      <actor>Jimmy Carter</actor>
      <actor>George McGovern</actor>
      <actor>Pat Buchanan</actor>
      <actor>Jann Wenner</actor>
      <actor>Tom Wolfe</actor>
      <actor>Jimmy Buffett</actor>
      <actor>Ralph Steadman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 4, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>118</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie also captures Thompson's tragedy: the haze of drugs and bad writing that consumed him for no less than his last 30 years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20210201,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A biographical documentary doesn't get any better than this.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=10538</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is to Mr. Gibney’s great credit that while he pays due attention to the outsize, cartoonish celebrity persona Thompson fell back on when his literary powers began to wane, this film concentrates on the bold, innovative journalism that secured Thompson’s reputation and assures his immortality.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/07/04/movies/04gonz.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gibney's immensely funny and sad new motion picture Gonzo: The Life and Work of Dr. Hunter S. Thompson -- the "Dr." was a mail-order divinity degree -- is principally intended to rehabilitate Thompson and introduce his work to a new audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2008/07/04/gibney_gonzo/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The July 4th release is fitting, for Thompson was a true patriot. His longstanding association with the counterculture notwithstanding, Thompson loved this country and the things it once stood for, and his voice is sorely missed today, and whether you were a fan of his work or not, you'll find Gonzo well worth your time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11069</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It leaves you wondering, how was it that so many people liked this man who does not seem to have liked himself?</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080703/REVIEWS/305058413</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Johnny Depp, who paid for the 2005 funeral in which Thompson's ashes were fired out of a cannon, narrates with just the right mix of awe and impertinence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18139826/review/21477306/gonzo_the_life_and_work_of_dr_hunter_s_thompson</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mesmerizing look at the mythic quality and anarchic spirit of the irreverent and rabble-rousing journalist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-07-02-gonzo_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A tender, even-tempered elegy to a writer who at his peak could ingest staggering (literally) amounts of drugs and alcohol and transform, like Popeye after a can of spinach, into a superhuman version of himself--more trenchant, more cutting, more hilarious than any political journalist before or since.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47982/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Subject's career being inextricably tied to two extremely entertaining U.S. decades, Gonzo has a wealth of delightful archival footage to draw on, both directly involving Thompson and evoking the cultural landscape around him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117935993&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Thompson's work itself, it sometimes feels like a smoke screen, a colorful but distracting, distracted set of pretenses hiding as much as they reveal.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-gonzo-the/484471/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's more Thompson-for-beginners than an exhaustive inquiry, but as introductions go, it's thorough and thoughtful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/gonzo_the_life_and_work_of_dr</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This handsomely mounted documentary takes the same, indulgent tone that at lot of Thompson's friends and associates seem to have had.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/gonzo-life-work/review/294439</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is thorough and entertaining. It's enthusiastic about his contributions, but it's no hagiography, and it serves as both a celebration and a cautionary tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/07/03/DD4811IPIL.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Johnny Depp, who portrayed Thompson's alter-ego in Gilliam's film, provides the narration. If there's hagiography here, it's counterbalanced by biographical truth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080704_Journalism_s_wild_one__loved_and_loathed.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is annoyingly sketchy on Thompson's early years and education, and it spends so much time on his coverage of the 1972 presidential election and his own race for sheriff of Aspen, Colo., that major aspects of his career get short shrift or go unmentioned.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/369376_gonzo04q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An amused and affectionate look at the writer who formed a crucial link between the New Journalism of the 1960s and today's blogosphere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080718.wgonzo18/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Feels a little soft and boomer-indulgent with its 10,000th rehash of the Nixon years and its soundtrack of trite 60s anthems.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/080703/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the evidence of his spotty post-1970s work is hard to refute, Gonzo proves what a vapid, overvalued commodity edginess is, championing Thompson's best work for brass-tacks insight more than brass-balled outrage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0827,gonzo-salutes-hunter-s-thompson-s-substance,499177,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because there was anarchy and randomness in Thompson's life and work, you find it in Gonzo.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/07/movie_review_gonzo_the_life_an.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We are treated to all manner of worshipy recollections from a stable of Thompson's admirers, including, believe it or not, Patrick Buchanan and James Baker. Who said gonzo politics doesn't make for strange bedfellows?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0704/p25s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a nagging sense throughout Gonzo that, despite his late-life decline into caricature, Thompson was too complex, too self-mythologized, too big, too American to ever fit onscreen – especially in a movie aiming for "objectivity," which was, for Thompson, the worst of all possible words.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A641263</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So I was curious to see why we needed a two-hour documentary about the three-hit wonder who cast away his career halfway through life and coasted on celebrity status for 30 years. After seeing Gonzo: The Life and Work of Dr. Hunter S. Thompson, I'm still not convinced we do.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/entertainment/columnists/lawrence_toppman/story/716697.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may be impossible to make an uninteresting documentary about Hunter S. Thompson, but is it unfair to ask Gonzo for more Hunter and less Jimmy Carter?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/07042008/entertainment/movies/hes_gonzo_but_not_forgotten_118390.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thompson - his brilliance, his self-destruction, and the ground he broke - is always at the center, but the film occasionally loses its focus.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12013</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I think Gonzo, which is wonderfully rich in historical footage, needs some skeptics, some voices suggesting that maybe, just maybe, Thompson was part of the problem, not the solution, when America flirted briefly with revolution (or was it merely anarchy?), leaving consequences that continue to resonate today -- and not always to our advantage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1820266,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of pushing for tough answers to difficult questions, this film is content to mythologize Thompson's bad-boy behavior, celebrating things like his willingness to drink a bottle of bourbon a day and go hunting with a submachine gun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-gonzo4-2008jul04,0,3639021.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It seems to celebrate him more for his attitude, his fashionably leftist politics, his fame and his friendships than for any meaningful accomplishment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1149983&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,252,100</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$191,942</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>25</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>johnny depp</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>true</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>