<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Good Shepherd, The</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Eric Roth</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert De Niro</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Matt Damon</actor>
      <actor>Robert De Niro</actor>
      <actor>Angelina Jolie</actor>
      <actor>Joe Pesci</actor>
      <actor>John Turturro</actor>
      <actor>Alec Baldwin</actor>
      <actor>William Hurt</actor>
      <actor>Billy Crudup</actor>
      <actor>Timothy Hutton</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 22, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>160</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most impressive movies ever made about espionage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?061225crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A remarkable study of the corrosive effects of fear and power on an establishment insider who puts duty above all else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/12/22/DDGNRN3GFS1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the type of film that may be forgiven its imperfections when they are compared with the vastness of its accomplishments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1166664338238670.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Niro pulls the viewer into the world he has created and holds him there, sometimes spellbound, until the story is over and the end credits roll.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/g/good_shepherd.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While a bit unwieldy at nearly three hours and at times slow going, the film is absolutely fascinating for anyone who shares De Niro's passions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=F7xTQn2JFCYTSbqck171tn2Y4y0jDR536nlbpNCyMWNVpQcnsp3F!-512341271&amp;&amp;rid=8516</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Damon is terrific in the role--all-knowing, never overtly expressing a feeling. Indeed, so is everyone else in this intricate, understated but ultimately devastating account of how secrets, when they are left to fester, can become an illness, dangerous to those who keep them, more so to nations that base their policies on them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1568455-2,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss/Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's taken a dozen years for Eric Roth's smart, thoughtful, psychologically complicated script to reach the screen under Robert De Niro's careful and methodical direction, and it is easy to see why.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-good22dec22,0,5200550.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Good Shepherd is serious adult moviemaking, a truly surprising effort from De Niro, a man deeply interested in the art, craft and psychology of espionage. He seems to believe that we'd better be interested in it, because it's interested in us.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106129&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Roth's screenplay, steeped in the peculiar rituals, lock-jawed repression and smug sense of superiority of the WASP ruling class that both shaped America's intelligence community and made it vulnerable, is less interested in derring-do than back-room deals and the day-to-day drudgery of spying, driven by the notion that espionage is a cynical high-stakes game played with people's lives and the ante is human decency and connectedness.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=285025&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deliberately paced, epic and ambitious, The Good Shepherd feels related in tone, mood and style to "The Godfather."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-12-21-good-shepherd_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with The Good Shepherd is that it's a closed-off movie about a closed-off individual. Wilson is inscrutable from the get-go, and remains so. Damon does subtle work within the narrowest of confines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1222/p14s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here, he's (Damon) the ultimate enigma machine, a man willing to erase himself for his country. Does that make him a hero? The Good Shepherd is too closemouthed to let on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1569416_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A cool-headed thriller, and a richly detailed character study that traces the birth and evolution of America's foreign espionage bureaucracy, The Good Shepherd also marks a significantly more mature, assured directing turn from Robert De Niro.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=777101&amp;reviewId=21992</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Still, even if the movie's vast reach exceeds its grasp, it's a spellbinding history lesson. The Good Shepherd demands you watch it like a spy: alert, paranoid, never knowing whom you can trust, or who will stab you in the back.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/16115744/site/newsweek/page/6/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fitting that a drama trading in classified information would turn out to be such a cryptic bugger.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061222-movies-review-shepherd,0,4032510.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shepherd wants to say something profound about the effect of a deceitful government on human values. But it's tough to slog through a movie that has no pulse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/7405477/review/12812399/the_good_shepherd</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Leaves you longing for the other, better political thrillers it evokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8199</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even with its first-rate cast, current political relevance and tangled mysteries, The Good Shepherd remains as remote as Wilson himself. But frankly, if the lives of CIA spies are really this dreary, they may as well keep their secrets to themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/482173p-405799c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well-crafted and well-acted, but ever-so-slightly worthy and strangely unaffecting. Given the track record of the CIA, it probably ought to be angrier.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=10599</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most interesting thing about The Good Shepherd is how hard the filmmakers work not only to demystify the agency, but also to strip it of its allure, its heat.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/12/22/movies/22shep.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In some ways, De Niro does a competent job in his second directorial effort but his characterizations are clumsy, and his members of the Power Elite always seem less real people than stick figures in a propaganda movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/296775_shepherd22q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only De Niro or screenwriter Eric Roth had the instinct to play some of this for laughs or even outrageous burlesque. Despite their conviction and intelligence and their game, amazing cast, all they do is eke out a series of straight-faced dramatic reversals and personal betrayals that leave the dramatis personae, and the audience, numb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.good22dec22,0,859158.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A glacially paced, emotionally frosty epic (with a top-drawer cast).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12222006/entertainment/movies/the_spy_who_bored_me_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Good Shepherd, soft when it needs to be sharp, is all cloak with very little dagger.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/12/22/good_shepherd/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If serious intent led inevitably to greatness, The Good Shepherd would be a masterpiece. It turtles forward for 160 minutes with unrelenting, humorless solemnity, as if everyone involved were unaware that it has arrived three decades too late to matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=EB1DF5B5F26B5B022CB56203F77917D2.prodapp12_ae_01?id=777101&amp;reviewId=21986</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Good Shepherd, for all its noble intentions, manages to make even espionage boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=777101&amp;reviewId=22010</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Niro made the right choice in making this a film of cold, gray Leiters rather than dynamic Bonds. But he never makes us feel the chill.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/56895</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where's 007 when you need him? Neither shaken nor stirred, The Good Shepherd is a flat draft of history that looks at the Central Intelligence Agency's early years through the horn-rimmed gaze of a fictional spook.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20061222.wshepherd22/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps it's fitting that a movie about the early CIA be tangled and opaque, but this drama loosely based on the life of uberspook James Angleton verges on incoherence.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30874_GOOD_SHEPHERD.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite successfully creating the illusion of forbidden glimpses, The Good Shepherd slogs through most of its lengthy running time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A430249</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Good Shepherd needed to be either considerably longer -- more like 1979's "Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy" miniseries -- or considerably shorter (word has it De Niro cut 30 minutes). Right now, it's stuck in the deadly dull middle in which everything happens but nothing matters since the filmmakers can't stick with one event or idea long enough for it to, well, stick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0651,wilonsky,75346,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Robert De Niro's second film as a director adopts a methodical approach and deliberate pace in attempting to grasp an almost forbiddingly intricate subject, with a result that is not boring, exactly, but undeniably tedious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932275.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Niro is damned if he's going to make a standard thriller out of this view from within the CIA, which might be refreshing if his solemn moral parable weren't so lacking in any other kind of juice, and if its hero were less of a round-shouldered, whey-faced organization man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/the-good-shepherd-trust-no-one/15240/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$59,908,565</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,033,960</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,215</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>william hurt</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>2</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>alec baldwin</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>matt damon</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>