<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Grace Is Gone</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>James C. Strouse</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>James C. Strouse</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>John Cusack</actor>
      <actor>Alessro Nivola</actor>
      <actor>Shelan O&amp;#039;Keefe</actor>
      <actor>Gracie Bednarczyk</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 7, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>85</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Attempts to address grief frankly, gently, and without didacticism, and it largely succeeds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/grace_is_gone</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Cusack demonstrates once again that he is Hollywood’s second-most-reliable nice guy, after Tom Hanks. Devoid of vanity, with no hidden agendas, he never strains to be likable. Good will, integrity and a native common sense ooze out of him.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/07/movies/07grac.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A picture about tragedy in one American family's life, and it's a convincing and humane one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4295/grace-is-gone.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As subtle and shattering as its title.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-06-grace-is-gone_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simplicity -- four-square, not sappy -- is rare in film. James C. Strouse had it in his script for Lonesome Jim. As writer and first-time director, he gives Grace Is Gonethe quiet power to sneak up and floor you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/12729848/review/16681945/grace_is_gone</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a minimalist plot, Grace Is Gone turns its primary focus on John Cusack, giving the actor an opportunity to display both his talent and his range.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/g/grace_gone.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s a close call, but Grace is Gone is worth seeing for the way John Cusack works with Shelan O’Keefe and Gracie Bednarczyk, two of the least affected and most affecting young actors to hit the screen this year.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-grace-is/268153/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not a great movie, simply functional, but Cusack gives a great performance. The film somehow doesn't live up to his work.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071213/REVIEWS/712130302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An emotionally rich and satisfying drama featuring a terrifically understated performance from John Cusack.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-grace7dec07,0,4141450.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that depends entirely on whether you feel empathy for its characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9561</url>
         <critic>Jeremy Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although clearly coming from an antiwar perspective, the story's emotional effectiveness and family grounding give the film a real shot at connecting with general audiences across the political spectrum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2007&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=berlin&amp;nav=RBerlin&amp;articleid=VE1117932523&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most noteworthy thing about the Iraq war home-front drama, Grace Is Gone, is that Clint Eastwood composed its musical score and title song, which have both been garnering all sorts of accolades, including dual Golden Globe nominations.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/348649_grace25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bednarczyk's natural instincts put most programmed Hollywood moppets to shame, and the quietly affecting O'Keefe shows genuine talent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/07/2007-12-07_john_cusacks_grief_encounter_in_grace_is.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A disappointing and manipulative look at one family's loss in the Iraq war.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=H3P3HgqcySs19546Gyxh2FZbT1c7rXJBV6y6kyPgptywFHGSh8v5!-1411234053&amp;&amp;rid=10312</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>His (John Cusack) quickness and intelligence make him a poor choice to play the flat-footed main character, a rigidly conservative family man who can't work up the nerve to tell his two daughters their soldier mother has been killed in action.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32530_GRACE_IS_GONE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The music--a gently jazzy piano-and-strings theme--is just fine, and a good deal less cloying than what was there before. One can only regret that Eastwood didn't offer to reshoot the whole movie while he was at it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0749,foundas,78512,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Grace Is Gone grabs on to a name, a war, and the metaphor-come-to-life of a theme park with rides going nowhere. And we, the people, are spun around and shaken for tears.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20164469,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A barbell of a movie that carries some weight at either end. What's in between is purely utilitarian, though.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12072007/entertainment/movies/cant_say_anything_372653.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$50,080</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,880</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>