<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Great Debaters, The</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robert Eisele</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Denzel Washington</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Denzel Washington</actor>
      <actor>Forest Whitaker</actor>
      <actor>Jurnee Smollett</actor>
      <actor>Denzel Whitaker</actor>
      <actor>Kimberly Elise</actor>
      <actor>Nate Parker</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 25, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>123</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a film that is affirming and inspiring and re-creates the stories of a remarkable team and its coach.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071224/REVIEWS/712240301</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A triumph. Unapologetically old-school, in both the literal and metaphorical meanings of the term, Debaters overlays the story of social underdogs onto the familiar template of the stand-and-deliver saga, the staple of sports inspirationals like "Rocky," "Invincible" and "The Karate Kid."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071224_In_the_annals_of_David_and_Goliath_contests__collegiate_NO_HEAD_SPECIFIED.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately an uplifting movie because it is about triumph.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/g/great_debaters.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The three young actors are good, but the movie is held together from beginning to end by another riveting performance from Washington. Few actors can dominate a film with their diction as well as Washington, and the role of the erudite, passionate Mel Tolson gives him plenty of opportunity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/25/2007-12-25_denzel_washingtons_great_debaters_is_a_b.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Great Debaters is like one of those sentimentally revved youth-sports-team crowd-pleasers. This time, though, the sport is debating, and the setting is an elite black college in Marshall, Tex., in 1935</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20168262,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Good story, well told. Interesting concept. I wonder if people will go for it.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-great/271207/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An edifying and forthright drama that aims to create a lump in the throat, and succeeds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/12/25/DDR2U2TST.DTL</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Succeeds in bringing a lump to the throat without, as is de rigueur these days, insulting our intelligence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1228/p16s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eisele and Washington lacked faith in their material. So they've made the big debate opponent not USC but Harvard, a more clear-cut epitome of the white world of privilege that has to face the hard truths of racial equality.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=995100&amp;reviewId=22816&amp;startDate=12%2F27%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film about the power of speech, it's the quiet moments of rapture that say everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10970</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If I had to pick one word to describe The Great Debaters, it would be "nutritious."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1198290304278080.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film may be manipulative in its construction, and cliché-ridden in some of the incidents it recounts, but it has a good, large heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1698252,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Washington is splendid, as always. So is Forest Whitaker as James Farmer, Sr.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119880937547154683.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a great family movie, if not historically perfect, and something that a lot of people are going to like.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141237&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Conceived like a sports movie, this delivers passion, nuance, and historical insight along with unnecessary hokum.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32605_GREAT_DEBATERS.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because it is so old-school Hollywood, with a weakness for standard moments and pat situations, The Great Debaters initially comes off as easily dismissible. Largely saving it from that fate is the presence and ability of Denzel Washington, who costars with Forest Whitaker and directs from Robert Eisele's script.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-debaters25dec25,0,5186697.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wouldn't it have been more fascinating if, just once, they had to argue, as all debate teams must, against their own beliefs? That would have really tested these amazing kids' mettle--and the movie's too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/74409</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tailor-made for maximum inspirational, historical and educational impact, The Great Debaters shines a bright spotlight on a remarkable example of black achievement long forgotten in the sorry history of the Jim Crow South.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935673.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An earnest drama about the search for self-esteem and sense of responsibility among young black people that successfully relies on its fine actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=10372</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not the most thrilling of competition films. There are only two short debate scenes, and each time the team gets to argue (in sound bites of rhetoric) the politically correct side of the issue.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/344502_great25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even when you're disappointed with the film's predictability, there's something invigorating about the way it embraces literacy and argument.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.debater25dec25,0,2943748.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enjoyable, rousing film, despite its formulaic quality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-23-great-debaters_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While The Great Debaters' intentions don't lead it to movie hell, this picture is far more diffuse, commonplace, and predictable than the surprisingly convincing "Fisher."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4339/the-great-debaters.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's an air of extreme predictability and inevitability in the script - which takes liberties like moving the climactic debate from the University of Southern California to the grander precincts of Harvard.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12252007/entertainment/movies/great__its_debatable_204012.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The wonder is that The Great Debaters transcends its own simplifying and manipulative ploys; it radiates nobility of spirit.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/25/movies/25deba.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About midway through Denzel Washington's new film The Great Debaters comes a raw and terrifying scene that exemplifies why the movie's worth seeing, despite its hackneyed and awkward story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/12/25/great_debaters/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too bad the story is all over the place. One second, it focuses on a love triangle between students; the next, it's about Washington's efforts to unionize the local farmers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_great_debaters</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Polished, pokey and cloyingly formulaic, Denzel Washington's directing follow-up to "Antwone Fisher" is a Harpo -- as in Oprah spelled backwards -- Production all the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/great-debaters/review/291270</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is hobbled by the narrative predictability that inevitably governs this type of drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A573330</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film avoids potentially interesting frictions by always letting the team debate (and win) on the "correct" side of every issue--that which aligns with generally accepted modern liberal sympathies. The kids follow their party line all the way to the big game, a ridiculous, fallacy-riddled face-off against Harvard.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0751,pinkerton,78652,20.html</url>
         <critic>Nick Pinkerton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of this unfolds with such predictability, the title might as well be The Great Foregone Conclusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071223.debaters24/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Great Debaters keeps things on the surface and pushes the obvious buttons, hoping you won't notice its distinct lack of depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/355692.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$30,226,144</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$13,256,188</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,171</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>2</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>forest whitaker</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_actor>denzel washington</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>denzel washington</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>true</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>