<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Greatest Game Ever Played, The</name>
   <company>Buena Vista Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Frost</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Bill Paxton</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Shia LaBeouf</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Dillane</actor>
      <actor>Justin Ashforth</actor>
      <actor>Peter Firth</actor>
      <actor>George Asprey</actor>
      <actor>Elias Koteas</actor>
      <actor>Josh Flitter</actor>
      <actor>Peyton List</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 30, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>115</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's by far the most inspirational sports movie to come along in many a month.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/242763_greatestgame30q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a society where athletic competitions are too often likened to war, the recognition that everyone's equal once they're off the playing field is a welcome reminder of that little thing called perspective, not to mention sportsmanship.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.game30sep30,1,7617446.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers an inspiring story, lush visuals and accessible characters to give a black-hat-white-hat view of class struggle in America and England.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928246?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As feel-good as any sports movie you're likely to find. It's a solid choice for family viewing, but is equally worthy of viewing by solo adults.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/g/greatest_game.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I am not a golf fan but found The Greatest Game Ever Played absorbing all the same, partly because of the human element, partly because Paxton and his technicians have used every trick in the book to dramatize the flight and destination of the golf balls.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050929/REVIEWS/509290302/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>LaBeouf ("Holes") has a scrubbed, ego-free innocence that is perfect for his working-class hero.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/351086p-299353c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The mixture of old-fashioned themes with newfangled techniques makes The Greatest Game Ever Played a canny piece of feel-good entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/30/movies/30game.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Actor-turned-helmer Bill Paxton has fashioned solid family entertainment in this well-cast feature.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001138674</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is sugary, simplistic and riddled with cliches -- yet it still manages to absorb you in its story and even carry you with some of its emotions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1127991967181420.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Greatest Game Ever Played is far too inconsistent to be great, but at least Paxton has made an honourable attempt to treat this piece of sports history with the gravity it deserves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050930/GAME30/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To be fair, Ouimet's story is pretty magical, one of the great sports underdog tales.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2311</url>
         <critic>Matt Cheplic</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's missing here is the one thing any duffer knows you need: Focus. The Greatest Game Ever Played works so hard to convince you of the truth of its title that it never settles down to address the ball.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7795</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An inconsistent and endearing sports inspirational that aims to be "Chariots of Fire" for golf.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=420226&amp;reviewId=19162</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To help break the monotony, Frost relies on relentless digital effects; there are so many shots of giant golf balls whizzing toward the screen it looks like the film was meant to be projected in 3-D.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46491</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As Ouimet, the always-terrific Shia LeBeouf is an oasis of depth in a film that otherwise can't pass up a sports-film cliché.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41057</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It can be seen for what it is: a well-crafted entertainment that boasts excellent performances (particularly from Dillane) and fully engages the mythology of sport, reminding us that in its transcendent moments, even a tossy one like golf has the power to capture the collective imagination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=133043</url>
         <critic>Simon Braund</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ouimet versus Vardon probably was the greatest golf game ever played, and Paxton and Frost do it justice, but I wouldn't sit through another simulated hole of it for Tiger Woods's salary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0540,tracking1,68564,20.html</url>
         <critic>Mark Holcomb</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film will have to settle for a bogey rather than a par. Still, some hyperbole is warranted, like "Safest Movie to Take the Entire Family To."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/30/DDGHOEVF061.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Greatest Game mostly sits there limply -- it lacks the charming swagger Paxton dependably brings to his own acting roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3578&amp;Sumbit.x=50&amp;Sumbit.y=13</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About overcoming adversity and one's innermost fears. On this count, Paxton hits the ball squarely in capturing the psychology of his characters, but hooks it into the sand trap of effects and thematic overselling.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050930-movies-review-greatest,0,554517.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Robert K. Elder</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never thrills on an emotional level the way the best of sports films – a "Hoosiers," say – can, but it's a satisfying entertainment nonetheless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A293538</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sports films about underdogs overcoming long odds run the gamut from flinty intelligence (Million Dollar Baby) to mushy sentimentality (Seabiscuit). This Disney drama...falls somewhere in the middle.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28555_GREATEST_GAME_EVER_PLAYED.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>And how good should we feel about this match anyway? Absolutely anyone, we learn, can win the 1913 U.S. Open. Except blacks, Jews or women.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/53190.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paxton and Frost lay the schmaltz on thickly, but the deal-breaker is the overuse of special effects, which make the game in question look more like pinball than golf.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-greatestgame30sep30,0,5877855.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Considering its superlative title (second only to George Stevens's New Testament epic, "The Greatest Story Ever Told"), I'm sorry to report that The Greatest Game Ever Played ranks somewhere in the murky middleground of sports movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=420226&amp;reviewId=19160</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An inert family golf movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1110755_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's such a great story, you have to ask two questions: Why didn't they make this movie before? And why did they make it this way?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/29/AR2005092902420.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This highly sanitized, heavily costumed, dramatically inert nonsense makes last year's dreadful golf biopic "Bobby Jones: Stroke of Genius" look like a masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-09-29/film/film6.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$15,331,289</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$25,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,657,322</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,014</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>