<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Grizzly Man</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films Inc.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Werner Herzog</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Werner Herzog</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Franc G. Fallico</actor>
      <actor>Amie Huguenard</actor>
      <actor>Timothy Treadwell</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 12, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>103</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brilliant, poetic, and utterly unique.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0805/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog not only tells an incredible story but implies a dark metaphysic of the natural world that makes this film unsettlingly larger than its human subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2231</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brilliant documentary about an American saint and fool--a man who understands everything about nature except death.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050808crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brilliant portrait of adventure, activism, obsession and potential madness that ranks among helmer Werner Herzog's strongest work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117925988&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A small masterpiece of a documentary that takes us into the heart of a complex darkness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/11/AR2005081100568.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Herzog is also no ordinary filmmaker. It is the rare documentary like Grizzly Man, which has beauty and passion often lacking in any type of film, that makes you want to grab its maker and head off to the nearest bar to discuss man's domination of nature and how Disney's cute critters reflect our profound alienation from the natural order.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/08/12/movies/12griz.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary is an uncommon meeting between Treadwell's loony idealism, and Herzog's bleak worldview.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050811/REVIEWS/50726001/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Treadwell's contradictions and controversies that fascinate Herzog the filmmaker, inspiring him to create this enthralling documentary portrait, his best film in years.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/236234_grizzly12q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Werner Herzog's magnificent tragedy, Grizzly Man, a Shakespearean character study that packs the sheer terror of "The Blair Witch Project."</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=334596&amp;reviewId=18794&amp;startDate=08%2F12%2F2005</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A complex, unique and engrossing journey into the murky recesses of an unhinged mind. It really needs to be seen to be believed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=133206</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mesmerizing work of disturbing power and unease.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1092064_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shows and tells an astonishing story, a disturbing and provocative tale of obsession, bravado and self-invention that leaves you open-mouthed for all kinds of reasons.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-grizzly12aug12,0,520929.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For many the question remains about how Treadwell's eventual death should be regarded--as a tragedy, as a fool's fate, or as comeuppance for daring to humanize wild predators and habituating them to human presence. Herzog's perspective is, of course, scrupulously nonjudgmental.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0532,atkinson1,66670,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Herzog's perspective is an invaluable balance to Mr. Treadwell's as the animal advocate approaches what seems like madness.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Jim Fusilli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A truly provocative essay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A284898</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's an element of the nature film to Grizzly Man, and those passages are truly stunning, offering an up-close look at these magnificent animals.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.grizzly19aug19,1,4823582.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog himself is one of the great lunatic directors of our century, a mad genius who repeatedly attempts to challenge nature and the gods in his own films.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=334596&amp;reviewId=19095</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A haunting and fascinating portrait of so much that is worth exploring: the implacability of nature, the hubris of human endeavor and the line between supreme dedication and madness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-08-18-grizzly-man_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Compelling, disturbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050930/GRIZZLY30/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Timothy Treadwell was killed, along with his girlfriend, by a rogue bear in October 2003.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7575</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog tries to make sense out of the blond-haired young man, who looked an awful lot like Kinski.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/51722.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Actually three movies in one: a wildlife film about how grizzly bears behave in their natural habitat, a character study of an eccentric environmentalist, and a chilling, voyeuristic narrative of how death stalks that man.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/g/grizzly_man.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog conducts his own expedition into knowing the unknowable -- the true task of any filmmaker. Herzog makes it an art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6824050?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog is still the only person who could have made Grizzly Man. His admiration for Treadwell has its limits, but he understands, better than most directors, what it means to follow dreams into the belly of the beast.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/25459</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog is primarily interested in Treadwell the filmmaker, but you'll likely be fascinated with him as a human being.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is an engrossing look at obsessive behavior gone terribly awry.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28372_GRIZZLY_MAN.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Makes for quite an emotional roller-coaster ride. You don't know whether to celebrate or mock, to laugh or weep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2124360/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog wants us to see a deluded nobility in this quest. Treadwell's flawed dreams were, in the end, all too human.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/08/11/btm/index.html?sid=1375902</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie here is Treadwell's footage--some of it beautiful, much of it difficult to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050811-movies-review-grizzly,0,5766355.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the heart-rending true story of a man with a seemingly benign preoccupation that turned into something close to madness and brought him to a terrible end.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/08/12/DDGQAE5UJF1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though some see Treadwell as an idealistic martyr who made the ultimate sacrifice for his passion, others vilify him as an arrogant fool who courted his own end.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/336678p-287360c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A rapt fascination with transcendent lunacy runs through Herzog's work, both fiction and documentary; while disdaining Treadwell's rhapsodically anthropomorphized vision of nature.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46068</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Grizzly Man is never less than a fascinating portrait of a troubled Peter Pan who couldn't function in human society and tried to remake the animal kingdom into his own private Hanna-Barbera cartoon, it fails to establish Treadwell as much more than a serious headcase, let alone a titanic figure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/05/38/film-taylor.php</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The results are by turns fascinating, horrifying, and maddening.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=6956</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is repetitious. Herzog has varied the original footage with some interviews that he conducted with a former Treadwell girlfriend and some other friends and observers. Still, an hour of it would have been more effective than the present feature length.</snippet>
         <url>http://tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20051003&amp;s=kauffmann100305</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,178,403</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$269,131</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>29</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>