<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Guide to Recognizing Your Saints, A</name>
   <company>First Look Pictures Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dito Montiel</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Dito Montiel</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Robert Downey Jr.</actor>
      <actor>Rosario Dawson</actor>
      <actor>Shia LaBeouf</actor>
      <actor>Chazz Palminteri</actor>
      <actor>Dianne Wiest</actor>
      <actor>Channing Tatum</actor>
      <actor>Eric Roberts</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 29, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Downey Jr. and LaBeouf as Dito as well as Chazz Palminteri as Monty are outstanding. Channing Tatum (who I've never heard of) is also amazing as the tortured soul Antonio.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8353</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is awash in great performances by actors known and otherwise.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061020-movies-review-saints,0,3773761.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This gallantly imperfect indie pops with attitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1539970_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's forceful and alive and spilling over with crazy poetry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/rescue-me/14577/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In "A Guide," passion and imagination go a long way in transforming seemingly conventional material and characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-guide29sep29,0,2661958.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>hough the picture is wrenching, at times devastating, it leaves you with that buoyant feeling of having encountered a raw, authentic work of art.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/09/29/movies/29sain.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is an exceptionally assured debut, and Montiel exhibits rare care with editing and sound design. His real forte, though, is casting, to which a brief scene featuring Downey and the incandescent Rosario Dawson powerfully attests.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1126972&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Compelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/13/DDGV9LNKB61.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most viewers will discover this picture - and it is worth discovering - when it is released on DVD.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/g/guide_recognizing.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a gifted director who actually has something to say and knows how to say it. We'll be hearing from him again.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09292006/entertainment/movies/memories_of_mean_queens_create_vivid_tale_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scenemaker Dito Montiel's rough, grating memoir of growing up in a poor, violent section of Astoria, Queens, in the mid-1980s features a few too many arty flourishes, but also packs a raw power that's hard to shake.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=282557&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the boys, Montiel's first film is rough and uneven, with more energy than it knows what to do with. But it still manages to feel fresh and authentic, perhaps because it's so deeply autobiographical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2150312</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film feels like an earnest retread over old territory, albeit one that intermittently comes to life thanks to an amazing cast, expressive cinematography by French master Eric Gautier (Irma Vep), and Montiel's obviously heartfelt sentiments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/53495</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the American cinema's rare excursions into pure autobiography: the movie is Montiel's own coming-of-age story, with little or nothing disguised as fiction.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/288500_saints13q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints is inchoate, but it demonstrates that instincts and brio can compensate for a lot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A413665</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As it dips in and out of the boys' lives, and occasionally wanders back to the contemporary Dito surveying the old neighbourhood, Saints never really integrates its two time periods.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061117.GUIDE17/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first-time filmmaker aspires to show us what caused him to leave his neighborhood and stay gone for 20 years. All I can really glean is that the place was too loud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9456</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The framing sequences with Downey and the climactic scenes between father and son are a mess. Downey, at 41, is too old to be playing a character who can be no more than 31 or 32, and 50-year-old Eric Roberts is an even greater distraction as Montiel's imprisoned friend Antonio.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/456727p-384255c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For my money, if I'm in the mood for the kind of aesthetic and emotional experience Saints is selling, I'll just blast Jim Carroll's more concise (and rocking!) "People Who Died" out of my iPod.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=3136</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Montiel creates a movie of many parts that don't always congeal. Mix this with the many meaty scenes and a roster of often exceptional actors and the effect is one of a fabulous acting showcase more than a wholly finished work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929307?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever the first-time filmmaker lacks in subtlety and finesse--not even the snow-white Sundance Screenwriters Lab could bleach Montiel's script of its corner-deli grit--he recoups by other, more playfully attitudinal means.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0639,nelson,74559,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Given all the filmed memory pieces about screaming, violent Italian-American families in New York boroughs, I'm not especially thrilled by even a well-made example.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30460_GUIDE_TO_RECOGNIZING_YOUR_SAINTS.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story of Dito escaping and then facing his demons is meaningful. But that story is so buried in actorly noise that it feels false.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1161212116133160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After a while, the crudeness and venality of the central characters proves as stifling as the incessant Queens summer heat does to our dubious protagonists.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001882945</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I suspect this guy can make a good movie if he learns the right lessons; he's made about half of one here. But the praise heaped upon A Guide to Recognizing Your Saints is way too much, way too soon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/09/28/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$516,139</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$94,784</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>