<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Gunner Palace</name>
   <company>Palm Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Petra Epperlein</director>
      <director>Michael Tucker</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors/>
   <release_date>March 4, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>85</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Illuminating, disturbing, evenhanded.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0304/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At the very least, it's more honest and involved in its portraiture of American soldiers in Iraq than anything TV news of any political persuasion has given us.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chireader.com/movies/archives/2005/0305/050311.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rousing, provocative film.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A nerve-jangling work of visual poetry and ironic juxtaposition, and a powerful human story of a group of brave young Americans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/03/04/gunner/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A riveting and indispensable record of the war in Iraq because it comes from the men who lived it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6824107</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A ground-level documentary, messy and immediate, about the daily life of a combat soldier in Iraq. It is not pro-war or anti-war.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050310/REVIEWS/50301002/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ironies and contradictions that give the first half a dark humor give way to gravity and respect as soldiers are killed (off camera).</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/215384_gunner11q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is more of an anthropological essay on the way young Americans relate while they make war, not love, and try to survive in the meantime.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A5733-2005Mar3.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sensational viewing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/05/15/film-taylor.php</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The resulting film is an unruly, riveting assemblage of anecdotes and impressions. The larger political and military questions about the war in Iraq are kept deliberately in the background, which some viewers may find frustrating.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/03/04/movies/04GUNN.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A striking new documentary that shows the war in a way it's not been seen before: from the ground up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-palace4mar04,2,3405631.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best glimpse yet of what it's like to be in Iraq.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/03/04/DDGE0BJGHO1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a simple, direct manner, Gunner Palace reminds you that the thousands of faceless, nameless troops in Iraq are still there after you switch off CNN.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=262713&amp;reviewId=17545</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gets behind the armor and the camouflage to give viewers a clear if brief view of the men and women who fight and die under the American flag every day in Iraq.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1111057302153320.xml</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the jumpy, ride-along camera work and the ever-present threat of engagement, a certain tedium sets in during the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=262713&amp;reviewId=17630</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lack of artful filmmaking doesn't detract from the dramatic impact of this fly-on-the-wall, cinema verite documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000834809</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why don't we see this kind of thing on the news every night? Undoubtedly military censorship comes into play, but probably more so it's the prevailing notion that talking-head shoutfests stacked with pundits bring in the ratings, while actual field reporting costs more money.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/issues/2005-03-10/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Do these soldiers make it? We keep watching and waiting. There's not much more to Gunner Palace than that, but it's no different than the soldiers' lot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A4058-2005Mar3.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the soldiers, it's about living to see the next day and living with the things they see, and Gunner Palace honors their perspective like no other Iraq documentary has to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review_pop.php?review_id=8263</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Put together by Tucker and his co-director/editor wife Petra Epperlein without a hint of artifice, docu offers up its sounds and images bluntly, and they are very much sounds and images worth having as part of the record.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117924910?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Floating on the surface of confusion, Gunner Palace has a raw home video quality that's often quite beautiful. Much of the movie is hardly more than an immersion in sights and sounds. Vivid as it is, Gunner Palace is dominated by what isn't shown. It's the human face of Abu Ghraib.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0509,hoberman1,61522,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defies any expectations you bring to it. There are sights in Michael Tucker and Petra Epperlein's eye-opening documentary that will confirm and confound both right and left.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/6998826/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's fragmentary structure, though, is suspect. It says that the soldiers find no real meaning in their combat actions, yet Gunner Palace presents the operations we're seeing in so little context, reducing them to a random hash of ''sensational'' moments, that Tucker at times appears to be exploiting the war to create a didactic canvas of manic military unease.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1033447_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With so many soldiers interviewed, some only fleetingly, it's impossible to keep track of them all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A262798</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Works purely as a series of complex snapshots of the conflict in Iraq.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7518</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provides an intimate, nonpoliticized, uncensored and totally unappealing look at the lives of U.S. soldiers serving during a grim and uncertain period of insurgency.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-04-2005/entertainment/movies/story/286411p-245230c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The picture is too long. It repeats and repeats. Thirty minutes, instead of its eighty-six, could have told us all we need to know about the danger and tedium of these lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml%3Fi%3D20050328%26s%3Dkauffmann032805</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the acclaimed documentary Gunner Palace contains some electrifying vignettes of the Iraq war, its jaggedly elliptical and hopped-up style lands it in a limbo between ragged and slick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.palace18mar18,1,3934739.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sorry, but this level of insight is readily available from daily news reports.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050415/GUNNER15/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tucker has done a bang-up job, distancing and hypnotizing us with his frenzied, fragmented, sexy images. But war isn't a video game.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050310-movies-review-ab-gunner.story</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But good intentions aside, Tucker and codirector Petra Epperlein only further confuse the issue: Their rap-video stylings and use of non-source music create the impression that you're watching characters trapped in a Tom Clancy Xbox game.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=45972</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best, the film just sits back and lets the weird times roll.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/41716.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gunner Palace too often makes the grunts look like mean slackers -- precisely the opposite, one presumes, of what was intended.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/nymetro/movies/reviews/11216/</url>
         <critic>Ken Tucker</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$607,502</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$63,520</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>