<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Halloween II</name>
   <company/>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Rob Zombie</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rob Zombie</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Scout Taylor-Compton</actor>
      <actor>Tyler Mane</actor>
      <actor>Danielle Harris</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Roebuck</actor>
      <actor>Ezra Buzzington</actor>
      <actor>Mark Christopher Lawrence</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Daniel Phillips</actor>
      <actor>Dayton Callie</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 28, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>101</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Halloween II, writer-director Rob Zombie's completely unsettling but incompletely satisfying continuation of his 2007 reboot, offers up a rush of fiercely imagined nightmare images. Be warned: It's one of the most gruesome films of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08292009/entertainment/movies/horror_show_shtick_or_treat_186964.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only he (Zombie) had more on his mind than his love of 1970s Italian horror films, his meticulous color schemes and his body count. Halloween II is full of in jokes and references but nearly devoid of wit.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/08/29/movies/29hallow.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Mike Hale</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zombie walks the walk, you can't deny it. And he's found the medium where he can let his freak flag fly highest. Now, he can proudly put that battered old William Shatner Halloween mask on a stick, too, and let it rip.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/08/28/2009-08-28_halloween_ii_.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Laurie’s story holds interest thanks to Taylor-Compton’s intense, nontrivializing dedication to the role, especially when the character’s feral brother comes calling.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/77981/halloween-ii-film-review</url>
         <critic>Keith Uhlich</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Halloween II does have, though, is Zombie's claustrophobic visual style; he half-drowns his actors in shadow, then tracks them through windows and around corners like a focused predator. If only we cared about the prey.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20301199,00.html</url>
         <critic>Adam Markovitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zombie does a lot extremely well. Maybe someday he’ll find a movie into which it all fits.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/halloween-ii,32305/</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This time, Zombie doesn’t appear to have many deep thoughts, so Michael doesn’t just stab his victims, he slices and chomps them into gooey pulp -- an overkill motif that actually feels false to the character and quickly becomes a depressing bore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/2009-08-27/film-tv/movie-reviews-the-final-destination-halloween-ii-world-39-s-greatest-dad/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie lacks the strong vision and memorable carnage of Zombie's masterpiece, "The Devil's Rejects."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/08/28/DD6019ET5A.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What you won't feel is genuine horror, because unlike John Carpenter -- whose original 1978 film is a sly game of nerve-racking peekaboo -- Zombie isn't out to engage fans of the genre with a slaughterhouse bonbon like "Halloween II."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-halloween31-2009aug31,0,1958166.story</url>
         <critic>Robert Abele</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps reflecting the filmmaker's other career as a recording artist, many of the film's scares come as much from the ultra-vivid horrifying sound effects as the gore itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/halloween-ii-film-review-1004007654.story</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With his new sequel, Zombie spends less time paying tribute and more time getting inventive, with mixed results.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/08/29/halloween_sequel_has_few_treats/</url>
         <critic>Tom Russo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Could be the work of any journeyman, give or take a few hundred gratuitous pop-culture references. Let no one accuse Zombie of stinting on the gore, however.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?oid=977769</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's visceral bloodbathery at its most repellent, but worse than that, it's horrific like the aftermath of a suicide bombing instead of terrifying like the bomb beneath the table or the knife behind the back.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A825038</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Repellent not only in content but in visual style, writer-director Rob Zombie's hatchet job on the series he revived so artfully two years ago plays like a violent act of euthanasia upon the huge, brain-dead body of work inspired by the 30-year-old "Halloween."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940908.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A complete and utter abomination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1780</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$33,386,128</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$16,349,565</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,025</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>