<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things, The</name>
   <company>Palm Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Asia Argento</author>
      <author>Alessandro Magania</author>
      <author>J.T. Le</author>
      <author>Roy</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Asia Argento</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUKFranceJapan</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Asia Argento</actor>
      <actor>Jimmy Bennett</actor>
      <actor>Peter Fonda</actor>
      <actor>Ben Foster</actor>
      <actor>Marilyn Manson</actor>
      <actor>Ornella Muti</actor>
      <actor>Kip Pardue</actor>
      <actor>Michael Pitt</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not a film for everyone. If you are squeamish about children being placed in danger then do not see this film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=6646</url>
         <critic>Greg Bellavia</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Heart Is Deceitful has a daring that's hard to dismiss, even when it only amounts to Argento shamelessly getting off on human rot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46112</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is an unpleasant film, but Argento, whose bloodline positively seethes with unpleasantness, is, in her own right, a master cinematic stylist of the first order.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A355946</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The results are shapeless, excessively lurid and often unpleasant, with Argento shamelessly vamping the white-trash junkie mother and truck-stop hooker. She apparently forgot whose story she was telling.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/265782_limited07.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Given Argento's willingness to attempt the controversial book at all, she pulls a surprising number of punches. What at first appears to go too far in reality doesn't go far enough: Argento doesn't even broach the subject of child prostitution.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46781</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>My two-star rating represents a compromise between admiration and horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060316/REVIEWS/60314004/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is some directorial skill here--Argento should be congratulated for a few interesting storytelling choices--but the end result feels grimy and strangely pathetic.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060317-movies-review-heart,0,7403485.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Asia Argento is not what I would call a good actress, but she's a prime specimen of train-wreck sexuality: a debauched Eurotrash starlet who oozes punk cred more than she does talent. It's not too hard to see why she wanted to write, direct, and star in The Heart Is Deceitful Above All Things.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1171066_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it's decidedly for perverse palates, some kind of cult audience seems assured for this one-note onslaught, which exercises a bizarre fascination despite its excesses.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2004&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117923863&amp;categoryid=1724&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever her limitations, Argento the actor makes certain that Argento the director doesn't lack for "action"--and that the audience doesn't lack for pain.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,nelson,72440,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An almost comically lurid tale of a little boy abused by his malignant hooker mother, malignant fundamentalist grandfather, and malignant surrogate dads.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29463_HEART_IS_DECEITFUL_ABOVE_ALL_THINGS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performances by all three children are scarily convincing. Still, it's a taxing bit of exploitation, which, although you're glad to know it's a work of fiction, doesn't exactly make a case for itself as art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-heart10mar10,0,4630084.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is an execrable movie depicting the improbable events in the life of a young boy being intermittently raised by his crackhead, highway-hookin' mom (actress-director Asia Argento, with a face that makes Courtney Love's mug shot look glamorous), her plumb-nuts evangelical parents and a cartoonishly incompetent West Virginia social system.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/398474p-337573c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watchable in a train-wreck kind of way, but you'll probably want to take a shower afterwards.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64963.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unwatchable.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/24/DDGORHSGGR1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Tamara Straus</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The whole enterprise heaves and strains with a sadistic overkill that even Dario might find too rich.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060313crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tale grows only more toxic with time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1113299&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A degraded and degrading film, of interest only because it's symptomatic of so much that's wrong with the drearily repetitive tabloid mentality that has infected not just the news media, but the whole culture industry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/12855/child-care/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Heart Is Deceitful wants to cauterize us into feeling something -- anything -- but it's far too heartless to know what.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8348</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is terrible, but made with verve and sincerity, all of it pointed in the wrong direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/03/09/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Viewer discretion is advised, if only because it's well-nigh unwatchable.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/movies/10hear.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inspirationally impaired and dramatically retarded.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000512842</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$26,092</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,000</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>