<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hellboy II: The Golden Army</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mike Mignola</author>
      <author>Guillermo del Toro</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Guillermo del Toro</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ron Perlman</actor>
      <actor>Selma Blair</actor>
      <actor>Doug Jones</actor>
      <actor>Luke Goss</actor>
      <actor>Seth MacFarlane</actor>
      <actor>Anna Walton</actor>
      <actor>Brian Steele</actor>
      <actor>John Hurt</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 11, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>With writer-director del Toro given free license to go where his singular vision takes him, Hellboy II plays like Guillermo's Greatest Hits with even hotter visual effects.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=dGDXLqtVcD202vHmhDlsYw1c57n1lq9xV5nCWq9JLffP71sTpZhp!1675083006&amp;&amp;rid=11343</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Poetic, funny, darkly romantic and beautifully structured -- is a very different picture from "Pan's Labyrinth." But there's no doubt that it springs from the same cathedral.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/07/11/hellboy_ii/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Del Toro is almost alone in his ability to re-create on screen the wide-eyed exhilaration and disturbing grotesqueness that is the legacy of reading comics on the page.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-hellboy11-2008jul11,0,5459116.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perlman's Red is hilarious, combining the gritty delivery of a film noir cop with the physiognomy of a horned behemoth. And the script, by del Toro and Mignola, alternates action smackdowns with sweet, goofy moments, like a scene in which Red and the lovelorn Abe drink beer and croon along with a Barry Manilow record.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2195136/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the film is just as strange and endearing as its glowing protagonist -- and it is -- that's because the director and co-writer (with Mignola) is Guillermo del Toro, 43, who has the wildest imagination and grandest ambitions of anybody in modern movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1821613,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not to disparage the f/x guys, but what's onscreen in Hellboy II is all about the seismic eruptions in del Toro's head. Comparing his work to most fantasy cinema is like comparing cave drawings to the Cathedral of Cologne.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937571.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As he has done in all his movies, from creature features such as "Mimic" to serious dramas such as "Pan's Labyrinth," del Toro creates unforgettable images, filled with color, texture, lyricism and horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145192&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hugely inventive -- and smashingly beautiful.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121571484050243281.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Imagine the forges of hell crossed with the extraterrestrial saloon on Tatooine, and you have a notion of Guillermo del Toro's Hellboy II: The Golden Army.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080710/REVIEWS/522191483</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a dry, mundane title. It's also the only thing about the film that doesn't blow your mind right out of its comfortable, I've-seen-all-this-before rut.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/599566.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ron Perlman returns as the film's loveable title character, a demon gone good who's tough on the outside but tender underneath, with a soft spot for kittens, candy, and babies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/hellboy_ii_the_golden_army</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Golden Army dazzles like something out of "Jason and the Argonauts." To make a comic-book fantasy this derivative yet this dazzling requires more than technique. It takes a director in touch with his inner hellboy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20211446,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the rosary beads Red wraps around his wrist, Hellboy II doesn't have much on its mind, but few will care since del Toro and his stellar "Pan's Labyrinth" team, including Oscar-winning cinematographer Guillermo Navarro, stage one virtuoso set-piece after another.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-07-09/film/devil-may-care-about-hellboy-ii/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The endlessly inventive del Toro creates visual fantasies unlike any other, and the creatures on display here are truly extraordinary. But amid all the costumes, all the action, and all the special effects, it's the humanity that makes his work so memorable. Yes, the monsters are amazing. But the moment when a heartsick Hellboy discovers Barry Manilow? Priceless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/07/11/2008-07-11_hellboy_ii_tugs_at_the_heart_strings.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Better than the first in some ways: the superfluous Agent Meyers is gone, Doug Jones is great as Abe, and Strauss is an amusing addition (if almost structurally identical to Kroenen).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11083</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As much Tolkien's baby as Mignola's, this has more heart and humour than most fantasy films can dream of. Hellaciously good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=10321</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not perfect -- thank Satan! -- but Hellboy II: The Golden Army is by far the most splendidly imaginative and creatively uncorked piece of fantastic cinema since the director's "Pan's Labyrinth" netted an Oscar trifecta in 2007.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A642730</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie overall is engaging, though it's more cavalier regarding story and relentless in its action than its predecessor.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-hellboy-ii/491574/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hellboy II is solid entertainment, but it's a shame such blemishes prevent it from achieving a higher level.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1196</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It definitely gives us our money's worth in the sheer volume of its imaginative fantasy creatures and it's that rare superhero-movie sequel that's better than the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/370294_hellboy11q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Highly imaginative and consistently amusing without pretensions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-07-09-hellboy_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The talented fantasy filmmaker and heir to the "Lord of the Rings" throne gets the tone right throughout Hellboy 2, and the hip retro charm alone is enough to merit recommendation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/07/10/DDJ611M96Q.DTL</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprise package of fun, fright and untamed imagination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18263923/review/21772402/hellboy_ii_the_golden_army</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sheer volume of amazing things that del Toro is able to mine from his unconscious and render plausibly on the screen is remarkable. Hellboy II feels pretty sequel-y, as these things go, but there's a lot in it that has no precedent of any kind, anywhere, ever. That stuff makes it worthwhile.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/07/hellboy_101_original_comics_vs.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hellboy II comes across as an original. But being original is not always the same thing as being wonderful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0712/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Del Toro stuffs the film with wit and wonderments. Yet, coming out this superhero summer, it plays like a lovingly crafted synthesis of every fantasy saga we've seen in the past decade.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.hellboy11jul11,0,1684806.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of all the comic book movies that have spun out of theaters this long and pulpy summer, Guillermo del Toro's Hellboy II: The Golden Army is the most unapologetically comic book-y.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11119</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The same super-heated visual imagination that made Guillermo del Toro's "Pan's Labyrinth" such a darkly thrilling delight is very much in evidence in his sequel to "Hellboy." It's a shame that it's at the service of such a blandly conventional story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/hellboy-2-golden/review/292003</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A funny, offbeat superhero flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33317_HELLBOY_TWO_THE_GOLDEN_ARMY.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The whole affair is pulpy, jokey, sometimes touching and frequently nonsensical: a big mess and, mostly, a lot of fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/07/11/movies/11hell.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Goes somewhere the first "Hellboy" never ventured: into the Realms of Tedium.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080711_Hellboy_fights_for_good__and_screen_time.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fanboys won't mind the absence of depth or emotion; they may even welcome it for making the film more representative of its comic-book origins. The rest of us, however, cannot rejoice at the overspending and overkill likely to come in Hellboy III.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/707424.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's in the script, however, that del Toro the writer falls a wee bit short of del Toro the visionary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4644/hellboy-ii-the-golden-army.html</url>
         <critic>Stuart Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like a lot of well-staged parties, though, the affair peaks shortly after the introductions, and then devolves into intrigues, fights and mayhem.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080711.whell11rvt/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite all of the hideous critters Hellboy encounters, there is a hint that things are considerably weirder elsewhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/07112008/entertainment/movies/go_to_hell__boy_ii__119336.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best scene is when Hellboy and Abe get drunk and sing out raucously, which after "Hancock" suggests a trend toward superhero alcoholism.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/48323/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$75,986,503</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$82,500,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$34,539,115</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,204</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>