<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>He&amp;#039;s Just Not That Into You</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema (Warner Bros. Pictures)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Abby Kohn</author>
      <author>Marc Silverstein</author>
      <author>Greg Behrendt</author>
      <author>Liz Tuccillo</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ken Kwapis</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ben Affleck</actor>
      <actor>Jennifer Aniston</actor>
      <actor>Drew Barrymore</actor>
      <actor>Jennifer Connelly</actor>
      <actor>Kevin Connolly</actor>
      <actor>Bradley Cooper</actor>
      <actor>Ginnifer Goodwin</actor>
      <actor>Scarlett Johansson</actor>
      <actor>Kris Kristofferson</actor>
      <actor>Justin Long</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 6, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>129</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ginnifer Goodwin gives a standout performance--and that’s saying a lot considering the large cast--as the insecure, neurotic female looking for love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/He-s-Just-Not-that-Into-You</url>
         <critic>Olivia Putnal and Krista Soriano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never soars, but it never flags. It remains brisk, engaging and pleasant throughout, and face it: If a movie this well made had Spanish or French subtitles, we'd all be talking about it as a searing examination of sexual politics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/02/05/DDHM15N9QF.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This amiable romantic comedy benefits from its stellar ensemble.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34076_HES_JUST_NOT_THAT_INTO_YOU.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has a few too many story threads, but it also has some very funny lines and offers sharp-eyed commentary on the state of relationships in the era of instant messages and MySpace.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-02-05-not-that-into-you_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With an all-star cast maintaining an amiable tone throughout, the result is a movie in which everyone should see themselves for at least a few minutes (and wish they were that young, that beautiful and that well-off).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.notjust06feb06,0,2981741.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While "Love, Actually" succeeded in providing well-developed characters in (mostly) interesting situations, He's Just Not That Into You is often flat with subplots that feel rushed and/or contrived.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1468</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Good comfort food for most of its running time, thanks to a cast of attractive, unchallenging pros and Ken Kwapis's smooth direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10981</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is Woody Allen lite, with some deft observations about how the social media designed to bring singles together are actually coming between them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20090206_A_diverting_rom-com_with_nine_characters.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a bit like a weightless swirl of cotton candy with a mere second of sweetness before it dissolves on your tongue. But then there's nothing wrong with cotton candy, and besides, the filmmakers never promised more. I guess they're just not into that.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-intoyou6-2009feb06,0,7656459.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Easily the least passionate romantic comedy I've seen in years.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/398944_justnot06q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>He's Just Not That Into You turns romantic sanity into something so sanitized that it starts to make delusion look good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20256768,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I suppose it's a good thing that this movie has so many crisscrossing subplots. If one gaggle of whiners gets on your nerves, rest assured the scenery will soon change and another will take center stage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0207/p25s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I think the movie intends to empower all of its female characters, but it ends up chaining them to stale, timeworn ideas.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/39716-review-hes-just-not-that-into-you</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretty routine, pretty forgettable. Don't know how else to say this, so best to be frank: I'm just not that into He's Just Not That Into You.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090205.winto0206/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the recent "Sex and the City" movie, this spinoff not so subtly tries to have its cake and eat it by ALSO suggesting that a woman is nothing without a man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02062009/entertainment/movies/neediest_cases_153745.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The "star-studded" cast seems to have been cast according to their Premiere power ranking and/or desperation for exposure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11554</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a very far from perfect movie, and it ends on an unsatisfactory note.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090204/REVIEWS/902049993</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If all you ask for is a few gay jokes, a perky score, pretty shots of Baltimore, and some clever but callow observations of sexual mores in the city, He's Just Not That Into You is an amiable enough night out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-02-04/film/he-s-just-not-that-into-you-sets-bar-low-for-women/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of this results in way too much relationship chatter and not nearly enough comedy, romance or even dysfunctional relationships. We want to laugh -- but at what?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-he-s-just-not-that-into-you-1003936800.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No one has anything to distract them from the minutiae of their love lives, which they proceed to incinerate through overanalysis. It's a moral fable, maybe, if you make half a million a year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939538.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The big names don't do needy as well as "Big Love's" Ginnifer Goodwin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/hesjust-not-that-into-you,23465/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fact that you won't remember any of these names for more than a minute should indicate exactly how much depth each character displays.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/888833.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After more than two hours, what we're left with feels like a Robert Altman movie on Botox. It has some real substance and heft, but it also might be a bit too glossy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/hes-just-not-that-into-you,1142965.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's tons of professionalism in He's Just Not That Into You, but it lacks passion -- they should have called it "Like, Actually."</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/hes-just/review/293502</url>
         <critic>Perry Seibert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The possibilities of the dating game are endless and the potential for pain is great, yet the permutations of the movie's plot are predictable and repetitive.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123387493001354305.html?mod=article-outset-box</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yes, that's an impressive collection of actors. And yes, it's deflating to watch them wandering in and out of half-written scenes with no discernable direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/02/05/2009-02-05_sorry__but_you_likely_wont_be_into_hes_j.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whenever faced with another puerile movie ostensibly about women, I play a little game called What Would Thelma and Louise Do?</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/02/06/movies/06into.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's some funny stuff here that doesn't involve degrading its female protagonists, and the cast, by and large, is appealing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A735084</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here's a true S&amp;M date movie. Only sadistic men and masochistic women could love it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18271266/review/25900810/hes_just_not_that_into_you</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some of the players comport themselves better than others--Barrymore is sweetly wistful in her minor role, while Johansson, as a confident go-getter who sets out to steal her crush object rather than moon over him, is sexier than the whole cast put together.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-0206-not-that-into-you-revie.ar0feb06,0,5871902.story</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boring at best and insidious at worst.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/02/06/just_not_into_you/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scratch the surface, and the movie's underpinnings are an insult to women everywhere -- the film is slick stupid propaganda for the myth of The One True Love that wastes the talents of fine actresses.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/02/review_allstar_romcom_hes_just.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$93,953,653</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$27,785,487</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,175</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>