<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hills Have Eyes II, The</name>
   <company>Fox Atomic / 20th Century Fox</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jonathan Craven</author>
      <author>Wes Craven</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Martin Weisz</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael McMillian</actor>
      <actor>Jessica Stroup</actor>
      <actor>Daniella Alonso</actor>
      <actor>Jacob Vargas</actor>
      <actor>Lee Thompson Young</actor>
      <actor>Ben Crowley</actor>
      <actor>Eric Edelstein</actor>
      <actor>Flex Alexer</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 23, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>89</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director, Martin Weisz , doesn't lean on a lot of noise and editing tricks. He can relax, since all the scares are built into the Cravens' script, which invokes both "Goonies" and last year's instant-classic, chicks-versus-cave-dwelling-vampires flick "The Descent."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9379</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretty solid gory horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134677</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A retro horror-comedy featuring quick deaths and cheapo-looking gore, with a few dorky laughs and gross-outs but not so many scares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20016266,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For anyone other than hardcore gore-hounds, this flipbook of deliberately invoked global-unrest horrors, from friendly-fire killings to rape as a breeding weapon, is effectively mean and unrelenting--and pretty far from fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0713,ridley,76213,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though written by Wes Craven and his son, Jonathan Craven, this is pretty standard stuff: A lot of creeping through dark tunnels with just enough characterization to help you keep track of who's still alive, but not enough gore to really satisfy fans of Aja's bloodbath.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286670&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The politics of "Hills 2" won't enlist any new converts to the horror ranks, but existing fans will be drawn to the combination of visceral tension, violent payoff and the patented Craven gift for innovative gore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933180.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not fun to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/03/26/DDGFHOQO361.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is brazenly indebted to old cowboys-and-Indians movies and to James Cameron’s "Aliens." Gleefully sensationalistic and paced like an adults-only shoot-'em-up video game, it's ultimately less interested in subversion and subtext than in making viewers squirm, shriek and throw up into their popcorn bags.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/24/movies/24eyes.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hills Have Eyes 2 proves that even grisly, gory violence can be awfully boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=DJ6BGLDTpr75PGvbSd45Vp0ybpLlGPmhjvMtR38mp2C2nrlthh7c!-1287570033&amp;&amp;rid=8964</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The mutants are brain-damaged; the filmmakers don't have that excuse to justify this movie, which is the kind of thing the sergeant would call "a stunning display of individual and group stupidity."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03242007/entertainment/movies/potty_time_for_mutants_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A perfunctory gore fest and quite possibly the year's worst date movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070326.HILLS26/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a fan of the genre, and someone who genuinely loves such recent horror efforts as "The Descent" and "The Host," I respectfully suggest that the atmosphere for horror movies might be better if moviemakers stopped making ones like this.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3647/the-hills-have-eyes-ii.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You'd like to think such bankruptcy of imagination means we've seen the last of these subterranean creeps. But you know they'll be back soon to collect their royalties from the gore hounds who apparently don't care how dull or warmed over the accompanying package.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/la-et-hills26mar26,0,1705153.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Gene Seymour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After this disgrace, it's time to shut the hills' eyes for good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/h/hills_have2.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the whole, this is an awfully long slog through very arid terrain, in which generic soldiers track, fight and try to escape from generic villains (you'd be surprised at how uninteresting mutant flesh-eaters can be). I can't speak for the hills, but I spent most of the movie just trying to keep my eyes open.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/03/24/2007-03-24_dont_head_for_the_hills.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Assembles the most motley group of incompetents this side of a "Police Academy" movie, yet somehow misses the laughs. But humorlessness is probably the least of the film's problems, lagging behind amateur-night performances from the no-name cast, a homogenous visual palette (and from a music-video director, no less!), and lots of pointless sadism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_hills_have_eyes_2</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As witless and simpleminded as the irradiated humanoids that serve as the franchise’s bad guys.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A457620</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This horror fanatic doesn't have room for Craven in his genre anymore. Collect your cash and call it a day already, Wes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9921</url>
         <critic>Felix Vasquez, Jr.</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$20,804,166</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,686,362</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,447</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>