<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>History of Violence, A</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Josh Olson</author>
      <author>John Wagner</author>
      <author>Vince Locke</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>David Cronenberg</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Viggo Mortensen</actor>
      <actor>Maria Bello</actor>
      <actor>William Hurt</actor>
      <actor>Ed Harris</actor>
      <actor>Ashton Holmes</actor>
      <actor>Heidi Hayes</actor>
      <actor>Stephen McHattie</actor>
      <actor>Greg Bryk</actor>
      <actor>Peter MacNeill</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 23, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Other films this year will have to sweat bullets to match the explosive power and subversive wit of David Cronenberg's A History of Violence. It slams you like a body punch and then starts messing with your head.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6824681?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A masterpiece of indirection and pure visceral thrills, David Cronenberg's latest mindblower, A History of Violence, is the feel-good, feel-bad movie of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/09/23/movies/23viol.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Violence is in the spirit of the hardest-hitting film noir offerings from the '50s, but far more explicit. It's also in the spirit of the Western.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-09-22-history-violence-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This masterpiece, an art film deftly masquerading as a thriller, seems to celebrate small-town pastoralism and critique big-city violence, but this position turns out to be double-edged.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#28587</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>David Cronenberg's brilliant movie -- without a doubt one of the very best of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1110769_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is definitely not your typical Cronenberg. No matter if you either love his cinematic oddities, or if you’re put off by them, watching A History of Violence would prove beneficial. It’s no doubt one of the best films of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=8024</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Cronenberg's most mainstream work, and yet it has all the power of his creepiest nightmares.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1127991994181420.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although Josh Olson's script was originally based on a graphic novel by John Wagner and Vince Locke, it has now unmistakably become a Cronenberg movie, and one of his finest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/09/22/btm/index.html?sid=1392209</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A ticking time bomb of a movie, a gripping, incendiary, casually subversive piece of work that marries pulp watchability with larger concerns without skipping a beat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-violence23sep23,0,1300476.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cronenberg holds up a mirror, but he leaves it up to us to recoil at what we see.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/05/43/film-foundas.php</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cronenberg's movie manages to have its cake and eat it--impersonating an action flick in its staccato mayhem while questioning these violent attractions every step of the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0521,hoberman1,64285,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A History of Violence poses the right question: Are those who don't study history doomed to repeat it?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A293441</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a punchy, straight-up genre picture, a crime drama that might have once starred Charles Bronson or Steven Seagal.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=425572&amp;reviewId=19149</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film has the perverse intelligence of Cronenberg's other movies. It's not his best, but it is certainly his most accessible, least stagy work, obeying the laws of chronology and serving up characters whom we recognize as people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7815</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From its quiet opening sequence to its silent final shot, everything about A History of Violence is deceptive, and deceptively simple.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050923/VIOLENCE23/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cronenberg's movie is eerily compelling and darkly humorous. And chilling - to the bone.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=425572&amp;reviewId=19077</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seems deceptively straightforward, coming from a director with Cronenberg's quirky complexity. But think again. This is not a movie about plot, but about character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050922/REVIEWS/50919002/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the bloodshed, it's fundamentally a cold, cold fable, the icy whisper that turns every happy thing to ash.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46427</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It ranks high on the Cronenberg scale as one of his more disturbing forays into depravity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0923/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It turns a hot topic into a pretty cool entertainment--one that satisfies the viewers' need for righteous revenge while leaving them a queasy little question on the way out: Does gun diplomacy make sense only in movies? Or do Americans want it to play out in real life?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1106325-2,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ed Harris and William Hurt deliver inspired turns as the villains.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/40897</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Clever and fast-paced thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000922022</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sobering reflection on our culture's attitude toward violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/22/AR2005092202179.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cronenberg's best for a long time -- broad and entertaining enough for those unacquainted with the director's work, but layered with the themes of infection and mutation that have defined it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=10138</url>
         <critic>Adam Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'd like to hear from some women about the sole scene I didn't buy--Bello getting angry, then super-turned-on when she learns about her calm Tom's tough-guy origins--but otherwise, A History of Violence is a remarkably convincing examination of heroism, hero worship, and the seductive allure of villainy.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/nymetro/movies/reviews/14698/</url>
         <critic>Ken Tucker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But for director David Cronenberg and the commitment of his actors, A History of Violence might have been a cartoony action film. Its origins are in a cartoon, of sorts -- specifically, in a graphic novel, by John Wagner and Vince Locke.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/23/DDGMQERNLI1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Solid entertainment value for the money, but those who think it's saying anything new or profound are kidding themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/53041.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although there's little wrong with the first two-thirds, A History of Violence slides onto a tangential path during its final act, and this misstep reduces the production's overall effectiveness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/h/history_violence.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If this all sounds very heavy, well, it is, but it's also very, very funny. Cronenberg may want to say something important about violence, but he's also head over heels for it, ending each gunfight and neck-breaking with a close-up on the victim, blood either pooling behind his head or brains spilling from his face. Big laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050923-movies-review-history,0,1239765.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's absorbing and often excruciatingly suspenseful, and it gives Viggo Mortensen a strong, change-of-pace vehicle to follow up his "Lord of the Rings" triumph.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/241838_violence23q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't let the slow, deliberate pace fool you. A lot is going on in David Cronenberg's masterful A History of Violence, and you'll miss it if you blink.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/09-23-2005/entertainment/col/story/349076p-297645c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lack of depth, complexity or strangeness make this a relatively routine entry for the director.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927127?categoryid=1929&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Over-the-top and shockingly vicious. But what strikes some critics as complexity feels to me like shame--the shame of Cronenberg, an uncompromising director whose bloodshed has always been genuinely horrifying.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2126742/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A History of Violence is a hollow story from an empty graphic novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.violence30sep30,1,4700532.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This sort of investigation has been done so masterfully by Sam Peckinpah in "The Wild Bunch" and Oliver Stone in "Natural Born Killers" that, in a sternly utilitarian sense, we don't need Cronenberg. He is not, as far as I have seen, in their class. He proves it again in A History of Violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20051017&amp;s=kauffmann101705</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes junk is junk, no matter how fancy the platter upon which it's served. Which isn't to say A History of Violence is useless junk. It provides a few pleasures and a few giggles; it's a comedy, after all, an action movie in which things unfold at a deadpan pace.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-09-22/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This peculiarly predictable picture has been calculated, or miscalculated, to set up certain expectations, fulfill them, and then do the same thing again, thereby giving us a chance to see what's coming and, at least in theory, be shocked when it actually comes.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$31,493,782</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$32,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$515,992</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>14</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>william hurt</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>