<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hitcher, The</name>
   <company>Rogue Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jake Wade Wall</author>
      <author>Eric Red</author>
      <author>Eric Bernt</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Dave Meyers</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sean Bean</actor>
      <actor>Sophia Bush</actor>
      <actor>Zachary Knighton</actor>
      <actor>Neal McDonough</actor>
      <actor>Kyle Davis</actor>
      <actor>Skip O&amp;#039;Brien</actor>
      <actor>Travis Schuldt</actor>
      <actor>Danny Bolero</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 19, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>83</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hitcher's main problem is that many of the title character's dirty deeds are done off-camera. Instead of seeing Ryder trap his victims before he kills them, the audience is treated to plenty of butchered corpses that seem to magically appear after Ryder leaves a room.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3438/the-hitcher.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Saito</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hitcher is the Jessica Simpson of psycho killer flicks - cheerfully in touch with its own brainlessness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01202007/entertainment/movies/hitchhike_horror_thumb__thumber_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The young couple is far less compelling, which is one reason why the remake is only intermittently effective. Bland and dim-witted, it's hard to see why they'd attract Ryder's wrath.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070120.HITCHER20/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A remake of the 1986 suspense ''classic,'' is as processed and hoot-worthy as the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20009591,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somehow, music-video veteran David Meyers fails to hurtle this project into the pantheon of great horror movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/57679</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bean carves out his own modest variations on the theme of John Ryder-on-the-storm, but Bush and Knighton are so blandly forgettable that it's hard to believe that they're the protagonists and not Victims 1 and 2.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284341&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a mechanical gore-fest that offers preposterous stunts in place of escalating tension and waxwork mannequins in place of marginally interesting characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/h/hitcher.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The original film was intellectually engaging as well as tangibly creepy, while the new remake is just plain bad, and boring to boot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-hitcher20jan20,0,2176793.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reviewing it is a wholly meaningless exercise, but I do it against my better judgment that anyone even seeks a second opinion before plopping down their hard-earned money for garbage like this.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9639</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That leaves little to fill 83 expendable minutes, which barely register as a movie even with snazzy KNB gore effects, critic-baiting clips from "The Birds," a splattery variation on the '86 "Hitcher's" most notorious scene, and some out-of-place Bruckheimerisms on loan from producer Michael Bay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/15435/</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie genuflects toward pop depth in a scene where Grace sprawls on a motel bed watching Alfred Hitchcock’s "Birds," another thriller about implacable, undefined evil, but there’s a difference between refusing to give viewers the answers and having nothing to say. For all its death-metal vigor, The Hitcher falls into the latter camp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/20/movies/20hitc.html?_r=1&amp;ref=movies&amp;oref=slogin</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you boil off dialogue, performance, narrative logic and grind a movie down to the nub of genre, will there be any suspense left? The answer is yes, but only in a Pavlovian sense. You react to this dull shockathon like a wired lab rat who's seen it all before. And guess what? You have.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/blog/2007/01/the_hitcher_mov.html</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any good will built up during the decent first half hour is quickly vaporized.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/01/20/DDGRNNL9C41.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the 1986 edition was no classic, it's light years better than this update, which naturally opened without being screened for those ultimate villains, the critics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8641</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the absence of actors with the tremendous presence of Rutger Hauer and Jennifer Jason Leigh, picture loses its raison d'etre. Yet, directed by video helmer Dave Meyers with a certain fastidious distance from its plentiful gore, picture is also insufficiently over-the-top or corny to incite gleeful audience feedback.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932493.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first film was near-mythic in its tone and treatment of its characters, while this remake barely serves as a primer in how not to generate suspense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A436690</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$16,379,582</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$7,818,239</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,835</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>