<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hottest State, The</name>
   <company>THINKFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Ethan Hawke</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ethan Hawke</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Mark Webber</actor>
      <actor>Jesse Harris</actor>
      <actor>Laura Linney</actor>
      <actor>Frank Whaley</actor>
      <actor>Lynn Cohen</actor>
      <actor>Greta Gaines</actor>
      <actor>Nick McDonnel</actor>
      <actor>Alexra Daddario</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 24, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hawke has made this movie his way and the result is a story that is by turns romantic and disquieting. It's well worth the price of admission.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/h/hottest_state.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Could be an overwrought mess if it were in less capable hands. But Webber and Moreno are so good, it's hard to believe they're not really deeply and meaningfully in lust.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08242007/entertainment/movies/the_hot_thickens.htm</url>
         <critic>Linda Stasi</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hawke’s script is admirably light-handed in showing how the hero’s unreasoning passion is fueled by his parents’ painful divorce, and despite the story’s date-movie aspects, its most penetrating observations come not from the kids but from the young man’s estranged father and mother (Hawke and Laura Linney, both superb).</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#32035</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's nothing new, but Hawke captures some evocative textures and honest moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/331551_hot14q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At times this indie is as repetitive and self-indulgent as its protagonist, but it captures a bit of the madness of being unrequitedly in love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0824/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hawke quite capably taps into the bittersweet complexities of young, love-struck idiocy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0734,hillis,77569,20.html</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Patchy lead perfs and mannered helming subtract value from pic's tangible plus points (solid supporting turns, pleasant score).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931449.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Leslie Felperin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At around the halfway point, its characters’ haranguing voices begin to grate on you. People in their early 20s, even pretty people, lose their appeal when they dwell this obsessively on their own inchoate turmoil.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/08/24/movies/24hott.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Actor-turned-filmmaker Ethan Hawke's second feature, an adaptation of his own novel about youthful heartbreak, is hobbled by its singularly unappealing lead characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/hottest-state/review/287559</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hawke, who is very good as the young man's estranged father, had best stick to what he does best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/08/24/2007-08-24_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In The Hottest State, Hawke uses fairly standard childhood motivations for his unhappiness and reveals too little real interest in the Sara character.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070906/REVIEWS/709060302/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Personal and heartfelt, it's nevertheless bogged down by a lack of perspective on the material and a pointlessly frilly visual style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-hottest24aug24,0,5689125.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A viewing of The Hottest State is likely to conclude with a crosstown sprint of a different kind: As soon as the credits start rolling, you can't wait to get out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2172699/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hawke has created a standard-issue, Sundance-friendly indie film that's full of the predictable angst suffered by Manhattan artistic types, but unfortunately the lead characters are both so callow that you finally don't care much about them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/09/07/DDMHS0DPF.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Judging by the far more interesting adults in the film--Braga, a terrific Laura Linney as Webber's mother, and Hawke as his father--the solution for Webber and Moreno is to grow up and not be so full of themselves. In their current state, they make for unpleasant company, and so does the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_hottest_state</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To quote Dennis Hopper from the film "Search and Destroy": "Just because it happened to you doesn't make it interesting."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/118963437138580.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When Laura Linney turns up about an hour into The Hottest State, you can see the movie that might have been.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10168</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This self-important movie can't save itself from being disheartening.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070907-movies-review-state,0,7459838.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Scott Schueller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem is the material itself, with its trite observations and shockingly flat writing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4027/the-hottest-state.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever you're imagining -- self-serving self-awareness; unedited hipster mopes; yammering dear-diary script -- The Hottest State, Ethan Hawke's bathetic tale of a good-looking young actor's first heartbreak, is far worse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20053793,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$31,216</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$8,545</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>