<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hounddog</name>
   <company>Empire Film Group</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Deborah Kampmeier</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Deborah Kampmeier</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Dakota Fanning</actor>
      <actor>Robin Wright-Penn</actor>
      <actor>Piper Laurie</actor>
      <actor>David Morse</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 19, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>93</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fanning is a child actor with a grown-up soul, and every move, every breath, seems mysteriously right.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/50259/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In spite of a few missteps, the cumulative impact of the film is undeniable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8693&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>James Greenberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the wake of the inadvertent betrayal that leads to her now-notorious rape (a sequence that, ironically, seems to have lost the horrific impact it needs), the film turns listless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-09-17/film/hounddog/</url>
         <critic>Michelle Orange</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is responsible, earnest, well-intentioned and, as it was in Sundance, maddeningly inconsistent.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-hounddog/617367/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretty but overwrought, Hounddog doesn't deserve its infamy, nor does it merit being seen or remembered.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/hounddog</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Assembled from the debris of countless worn-out images of the Deep South and is indeed beautifully photographed. But the writer-director, Deborah Kampmeier, has become inflamed by the imagery and trusts it as the material for a story, which seems grotesque and lurid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080918/REVIEWS/809180302/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A handsomely produced but unintentionally risible film that mistakes high grotesquerie for high gothic.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/hounddog/review/294735</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hounddog is never more than a sluggish dawdle from shack to swimmin' hole and back again.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/09/19/movies/19houn.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A failure on pretty much every level, Hounddog would never have been known beyond Park City had it not been for the notoriety surrounding the rape scene.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1337</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It was received at Sundance 2007 with a resounding thud. Not because of this controversial rape scene, but because, well, it just wasn't good. Unfortunately, even with over a year of rejiggering, it's still not good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4736/hounddog.html</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An indigestible gumbo of Southern Gothic ingredients seasoned with snake oil, biblical hash and thoroughly unpalatable spice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117932535&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, director Deborah Kempmeir mistakes ominous and depressing for deep and meaningful, a misfire that undermines the effect it tries to achieve.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9705</url>
         <critic>Jamie Tipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bewildering slice of southern gothic hokum, it suffers from a weak script.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33554_HOUNDDOG.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fanning gives a sensitive and fairly impressive performance. But like her over-the-top movie family, Hounddog is still trailer trash of the worst kind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/09192008/entertainment/movies/fanning__but_no_flames_129732.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rarely has there been a movie as misguided as Hounddog, which self-righteously indulges in exploitation while loudly decrying it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/09/19/2008-09-19_short_takes_for_the_weekend_of_september.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What I can't figure is why anyone would want to release this tripe in theaters just when Fanning has nearly lived it down. They ain't no friends of mine, or any other moviegoer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/14705177/review/23178147/hounddog</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problems that plague the movie land squarely with the writer, director and producer, Deborah Kampmeier, who has crafted a howler of a bad script, shows little affinity for working with actors and displays no visual sense behind the camera.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-hounddog19-2008sep19,0,7437882.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fanning is remarkably collected and even dignified. As for the rest of the gang, they ought to be returned to sender.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20226432,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$132,016</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,744</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>11</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>