<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>How She Move</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Annmarie Morais</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ian Iqbal Rashid</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Canada</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tracey Armstrong</actor>
      <actor>Clé Bennett</actor>
      <actor>Nina Dobrey</actor>
      <actor>Romina D&amp;#039;Ugo</actor>
      <actor>Kevin Duhaney</actor>
      <actor>Shawn Fernez</actor>
      <actor>Brennan Gademans</actor>
      <actor>Jason Harrow</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 25, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mainly it’s a very solid dance picture, which is the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-how-she/289903/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rutina Wesley glowers with just the right touch of sweetness as a brainy student (and stellar after-school stepper).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20173411,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Choreographer Hi Hat and director Ian Iqbal Rashid kick the film into high gear every so often with dance sequences, climaxing with a dance-off in Detroit that seems too short.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=1012865&amp;reviewId=22856&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie, which is burdened by a rather mediocre script by Annmarie Morais but boasts some terrific performances -- is not just a sports movie. It's a girls-can't-do-it/girls-can-do-it/girls-do-it/girls-beat-the-boys-at-it movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1140260&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Title refers not only to its heroine's physical gyrations but also her moral maneuverings as she strives to break out of her lower-class surroundings in this moody, intelligent take on conventional material.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117932560&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Especially good are Wesley, whose expressions are a study in shifting thought, and Tre Armstrong as her street-hardened but good-hearted rival, a stock role that Armstrong fills with unmediated feeling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0804,ridley,78930,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There’s nary a twist you don’t see coming. But the film’s strong acting, spectacular dance routines and culturally specific details turn clichés into catharsis. It’s the sort of film that sends you home with a spring in your step.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/01/25/movies/25move.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A rudimentary but thoroughly enjoyable step musical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/02/04/080204crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's tremendous energy in How She Move, so much that the audience can't help but be swept up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.howshe25jan25,0,1048980.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How She Move is the latest urban music drama from MTV Films, and it manages to give a familiar story a vivid jolt of character.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/348647_howshe25q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This kind of a dance film lives and dies by the routines, and this one wins: Mixing elements of gymnastics, karate, and break with the almighty step – an exceedingly polite term for what is really an awesome stomp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A583303</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How She Move has two key assets: powerful dance sequences and an emphasis on education.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-01-24-how-she-move_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Formulaic but well-acted variation on the theme of pursuing your dreams through dance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/she/review/292198</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dialogue isn't Morais's strength, and it's only when the actors stop trading “Just give me a chance” chestnuts that the film really takes off. The deftly shot dance sequences are entirely satisfying, thrillingly choreographed by Hihat (most famous for her work with Missy Elliott) to music by the likes of Lil Mama and Toronto's Tha Smugglaz.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080124.wmove25/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason McBride</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The atmosphere is convincing - there is an "Eight Mile" desperation to Raya's plight - but nothing makes sense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01252008/entertainment/movies/step_dancing_tales_plot_flunks_the_logic_134641.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When the cast starts clomping atop a car, their synchronized bodies joining with the booming cross-rhythms, we're sold.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9914</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How She Move doesn't exactly break any new ground. But the terrific dance numbers on display should please its teenage target audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=yBYRHZdGGZCThXCFGLhw4KcRvp3Pnl3XKv6XP4XbNH2fDJGpzf8F!3588094&amp;&amp;rid=10523</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's good intentions gradually get lost in a sea of overwrought contrivances, stock characters, awkward cameos from B- and C-listers (R&amp;B singer Keyshia Cole and not-so-funnyman DeRay Davis) and warmed-over family issues.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/how_she_move</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gets it right in every dance sequence, but stumbles badly whenever the characters step offstage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/01/25/2008-01-25_only_the_dance_steps_are_moving.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Produced by MTV Films, this step-dancing drama is mired in cliche, but with its dingy ghetto settings and hardened, despondent young characters, it's marginally more interesting than "Stomp the Yard," the 2007 movie that inaugurated the subgenre.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32684_HOW_SHE_MOVE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Movie cliches are supposed to be bad things because they make the movie too predictable. But you know, there are times when they actually work in a film's favor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/25/DDQDUDPR5.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>David Wiegand</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,070,641</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$3,957,471</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,531</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>