<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Hurt Locker, The</name>
   <company/>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Boal</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Kathryn Bigelow</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jeremy Renner</actor>
      <actor>Anthony Mackie</actor>
      <actor>Brian Geraghty</actor>
      <actor>Ralph Fiennes</actor>
      <actor>Guy Pearce</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 26, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>131</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is an intense, action-driven war pic, a muscular, efficient standout that  simultaneously conveys the feeling of combat from within as well as what it looks like on the ground.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20285519,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A near-perfect movie about men in war, men at work. Through sturdy imagery and violent action, it says that even Hell needs heroes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1838615,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A small classic of tension, bravery, and fear, which will be studied twenty years from now when people want to understand something of what happened to American soldiers in Iraq. If there are moviegoers who are exhausted by the current fashion for relentless fantasy violence, this is the convincingly blunt and forceful movie for them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/06/29/090629crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something about this story, and this war, that brings out the stripped-down conceptual artist in her (Bigelow): Against blank canvases of desert sand and rubble, explosive wires are linked to nerve ends, and everything that matters depends on the twitch of a muscle or a finger on a button.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/the-hurt-locker/article1212781/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A full-throttle body shock of a movie. It gets inside you like a virus, puts your nerves in a blender, and twists your guts into a Gordian knot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-06-24/film/the-hurt-locker-ticking-time-bomb-of-a-movie/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best nondocumentary American feature made yet about the war in Iraq.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/26/movies/26hurt.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After The Hurt Locker (which is without question the most exciting and least ideological movie yet made about the war in Iraq), everyone will remember Renner's name.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2221398/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A first-rate action thriller, a vivid evocation of urban warfare in Iraq, a penetrating study of heroism and a showcase for austere technique, terse writing and a trio of brilliant performances. Most of all, though, it’s an instant classic that demonstrates, in a brutally hot and dusty laboratory setting, how the drug of war hooks its victims and why they can’t kick the habit.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overwhelmingly tense, overflowing with crackling verisimilitude, it's both the film about the war in Iraq that we've been waiting for and the kind of unqualified triumph that's been long expected from director Kathryn Bigelow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-hurtlocker26-2009jun26,0,4546320.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What you'll remember most will be Renner's remarkably complex commander. By the time we finally figure him out, it's become clear we've witnessed a star-making performance, in a movie that deserves to stand as one of the defining films of the decade.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/06/26/2009-06-26_the_hurt_locker.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A great film, an intelligent film, a film shot clearly so that we know exactly who everybody is and where they are and what they’re doing and why.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090708/REVIEWS/907089997</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This one enters the pantheon of great American war films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/07/09/MV6N18L4N4.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When viewers are ultimately released from The Hurt Locker's exhilarating vice grip, they'll find themselves shaken, energized and, more than likely, eager to see it again.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/the-hurt-locker,1156511.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Such is the extraordinary achievement of The Hurt Locker: it has the perspective of years when those years have yet to pass.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/090709/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like every war before it, the U.S. invasion of Iraq has generated its share of movies. But The Hurt Locker is the first of them that can properly be called a masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1153684.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hurt Locker redefines war-film electricity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-ae.mo.hurtlocker24jul24,0,6104437.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At once an unforgettable war film and a brilliant character study.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/0825924E2D1C644D862575FB006B8A9B?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Calvin Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most literally exciting film you will see this year. Forget the off-putting banner of another Iraq movie -- go, watch, marvel, endure and book in the palliative of a stiff drink afterwards.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136506</url>
         <critic>Ian Nathan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Renner gives a full-bore performance of great individuality and industriousness, but essentially his character is as glamorized as any classic Westerner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0626/p17s07-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the first hour or more, The Hurt Locker boldly forsakes any conventional narrative hook beyond the ongoing tensions between these men and the terrifying grind of defusing bombs day after day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/the-hurt-locker,29677/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The adrenaline rush of war has been largely missing from Hollywood's Iraq, but it's certainly front and center in The Hurt Locker, the first war movie in a while that feels as if it could have starred John Wayne.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105755842</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hurt Locker might be the first Iraq-set film to break through to a mass audience because it doesn't lead with the paralysis of the guilt-ridden Yank. The horror is there, but under the rush.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/57462/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tensely action-packed and muscularly directed by Kathryn Bigelow, this tale of an elite U.S. army bomb disposal unit in Baghdad is a familiar story in new clothes, targeted at the young male demographic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/awards_festivals/fest_reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=11592</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kathryn Bigelow's The Hurt Locker is a grinding, nightmarish machine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11733</url>
         <critic>Nick Antosca</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tension is enough to make you slightly sick, and the overall mood of the thing is deeply dispiriting, but then, nobody ever said that war isn't hell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A806610</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In The Hurt Locker, the thrill is unexpectedly contagious. You don't realize how riveted you are until you're back on American soil observing James in civilian life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/07/10/explosively_high_stakes_in_the_hurt_locker/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fused with paranoia and almost unbearable suspense, The Hurt Locker is powerful stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090710_Brave__reckless__bloody_and_just_like_war_itself.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Vivid, assured and extremely suspenseful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/reviews/critics/chi-0710_hurt_lockerjul10,0,457931.column</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a tense, well-crafted motion picture that keeps viewers on edge. It's an exhausting 130 minutes; many viewers will leave the theater feeling drained.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1697</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here's the Iraq War movie for those who don't like Iraq War movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/21799075/review/28818800/the_hurt_locker</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both a psychological portrait and an exciting action film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-06-25-hurt-locker_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Episodic and, at times, overwrought. And occasionally its deliberate opacity becomes too cloudy. But the things that shine through are remarkable. War is indeed Hell, it tells us, but that isn't necessarily a bad thing if you're filled with demons.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/07/the_hurt_locker_digs_into_a_fe.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The drawback is that even though The Hurt Locker is extremely effective in places, it ultimately feels unformed and somewhat unfinished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/06/26/hurt_locker/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stretched both timewise and for plausibility.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06262009/entertainment/movies/defuse_or_lose_176112.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boal's script stirs a little of everything into the pot, which boils down into seven setpieces divided by brief intervals of camaraderie/conflict among the three protags.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938188.html?categoryid=3212&amp;cs=1&amp;query=the+hurt+locker</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$14,700,000</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$145,352</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>