<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>I Am a Sex Addict</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Caveh Zahedi</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Caveh Zahedi</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Rebecca Lord</actor>
      <actor>Emily Morse</actor>
      <actor>Ama Henderson</actor>
      <actor>Alexra Guerineaud</actor>
      <actor>Katarina Fabic</actor>
      <actor>Corinna Chan</actor>
      <actor>Greg Watkins</actor>
      <actor>Caveh Zahedi</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 5, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no other film like it. It's embarrassingly frank and self-revealing, sometimes funny, sometimes creepy, sometimes both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/04/05/DDGBPI2RF01.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zahedi isn't afraid to put himself out there, even when his thoughts and actions are profoundly unflattering; his self-effacement makes the film a reflection on narcissism and misogyny rather than an exercise in both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47540</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caveh Zahedi's one-of-a-kind movie--a funny, inventive, ground-shifting hybrid of essay film, mea culpa, and pathological real-life romantic farce--aims for truth by wrecking its own verisimilitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0615,ridley,72831,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zahedi is ruefully funny and savage in his self-exposure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1184977_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although there's nothing funny about addiction, Zahedi - a thin, bug-eyed fellow with the air of an R. Crumb sad sack - brings wit and self-deprecation to his tale of obsession and woe.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=580558&amp;reviewId=20601</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zahedi's search for fulfillment is depleting, like throwing good sex after bad. The more we learn about the hole in his soul, the more vivid his misogamy becomes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9006</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This deconstructive, minimalist comedy, like his 1990 "A Little Stiff" and 1994 "I Don't Hate Las Vegas Anymore," re-creates events with the vain self-deprecation of one of his role models, Woody Allen.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/28763_I_AM_A_SEX_ADDICT</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hits its stride from the opening scenes and continues hilariously for a while, before declining into more of same. Its undeniable appeal lies in shocking frankness shackled to irony, a combo that should attract indie lovers with psychoanalytic leanings and droll senses of humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926265?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Technically, I Am a Sex Addict is a stellar achievement, as it coaxes viewers to accompany Zahedi down avenues of sexual desire that have had little frank exposure on film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A377899</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A confessional film that's almost too confessional--is like getting buttonholed by a casual acquaintance at a party and then subjected to a flood of highly intimate revelations that just don't stop.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060616-movies-review-sex,0,5211988.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zahedi has been compared to Woody Allen, and he shares Allen's neurotic sense of entitlement and navel-gazing fascination with his own sexual peccadilloes. Whether you find either man funny or infuriating depends in large part on whether you identify more with their narcissistic quests for self-knowledge or the collateral damage left in their wakes.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46864</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The way he presents his romantic history is both clever and entertaining, but after a while the story becomes tediously familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/408852p-345871c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film is an inevitable product of our age, and enjoyable, right up to whatever your ickiness threshold is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/13/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is a minor triumph of sincerity, neatly skirting the pitfalls of narcissism and unexamined misogyny. It never mugs for our good will, only our witness, which it rewards with honesty and wit.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/12/movies/12addi.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While some may bail early, those who stay to the end are likely to dwell on Zahedi's unwavering (some would say unrelenting) belief in his own artistry, as well as the film's many funny, quotable lines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13307/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What this is remains mysterious after a single viewing, but not so mysterious as to inspire a second.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-sex28apr28,0,2481137.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As for the overriding reason to see the film, that's easy. Lighten Zahedi's complexion, stuff him in a fright wig, and this fellow would be a ringer for Harpo Marx.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060424crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Now that even Woody Allen has stopped making "Woody Allen movies," you would think that wannabes would move on, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64331.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$115,694</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$14,987</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>