<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Idlewild</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures / HBO Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Bryan Barber</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Bryan Barber</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>André Benjamin</actor>
      <actor>Antwan A. Patton</actor>
      <actor>Terrence Howard</actor>
      <actor>Faizon Love</actor>
      <actor>Ben Vereen</actor>
      <actor>Ving Rhames</actor>
      <actor>Jackie Long</actor>
      <actor>Oscar Dillon</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 25, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild is a romp, a ticket to rowdy good times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1328500_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild has just about everything a popular entertainment can offer. It also has a soul, and that comes free with the price of a ticket.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/08/25/idlewild/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a passionate, enthralling film that isn't afraid to take chances - even if it sometimes should be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.idlewild25aug25,0,6180255.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aiding Barber is the terrific work of choreographer Hinton Battle, delivering a ferocious, contemporary update of swing and bridging the gap between quick-take MTV flash and the longer needs of cinematic dancing--a hybrid that works better here than in the frenetic, overrated "Chicago."</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060825-movies-review-idlewild,0,5207560.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Sid Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its shortcomings, Idlewild also has something that few films can pull off: Moments of such pure cinematic fabulousness, breathtaking dance sequences and idiosyncratic 3-D animation flourishes that we are more than willing to forgive it for all its sins.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1115911&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Teresa Wiltz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Bryan Barber (known for his music videos) and his cast display so much gusto that it's hard to keep up your resistance--I wound up finding this more enjoyable than the Oscar-bestrewn "Chicago."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30176_IDLEWILD.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Achieves magic--something sorely missing from so many movies these days--and does so via a philosophy of respect, but not reverence, for what's come before it; it never recycles, it just reimagines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931341?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild has a sober, loving respect for history and the old South, and thereby grants itself a measure of distinction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0634,atkinson,74251,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the best efforts of Barber the director, he never quite overcomes the shortcomings of Barber the writer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/i/idlewild.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The music by Outkast is great, and the rowdy, randy en masse dance sequences are riveting. The story, however, is rather thin and lacks focus.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-08-24-idlewild-movie-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A mess, but an energetic, convivial mess.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=684591&amp;reviewId=21346</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idle it is not. Wild it is most assuredly. Set in Prohibition-era Georgia, Idlewild boasts yesterday's style, today's music, and the Harlem Renaissance's romanticism.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=684591&amp;reviewId=21355</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Artistic originality is not so common a commodity that you can afford to get too fussy about the details.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060825.IDLE25/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Barber's screenplay is mired in cliches that got old in 1935.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=282028&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild is diverting enough to suggest all the unexplored avenues in movie musicals.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/19739/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone unfamiliar with or underwhelmed by the music of OutKast will find little in this thin piece of cinematic storytelling. Fans happy to luxuriate in its artistic indulgence, however, will be swept up in the weird, random, fantastic OutKastness of it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134410</url>
         <critic>Olly Richards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The camerawork is steady, the editing patient, the choreography playful. It's a zippy and inspired piece of moviemaking. But there's one problem. It's playing under the closing credits.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8575</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild has moments of sticky sentimentality and stretches of dull exposition, but you've got to give it this: It's unpredictable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2148337</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The soundtrack is a genre-hopping joy, and each musical number is cleverly staged and creatively choreographed. The problem is the noble mess of a movie that takes up so much space in between.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/08-25-2006/entertainment/col/story/446558p-375830c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's basically a series of music videos - a few quite good - strung together over two long hours and loosely connected by a weak story line loaded with anachronisms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/kastaway_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Idlewild had something beyond OutKast's songwriting, it would make a swell musical.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/08/25/DDGBAKO4DQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Idlewild boasts too much personality around the edges--especially in Terrence Howard and Macy Gray's scene-stealing turns--and not enough at its center. It's a vehicle for OutKast's music and personality in which the music and lead roles feel like afterthoughts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/52050</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film only rarely harnesses the power of the anachronistic, funk-driven, beat-heavy rap music that swells its soundtrack. Even the intricately choreographed crowd dance scenes, filled with frenzied movement, are more often stillborn than stimulating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/southern-comfort/14324/</url>
         <critic>Ernest Hardy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Patton and Benjamin can both hold the screen and are great in their musical sequences, but sorry, they aren't actors -- Terrence Howard, as the villain Trumpy, blows them into dust when he's on camera -- and their limited expressiveness detracts from the film's hallucinatory edge. The plot fails them too, as it takes turns we've seen in a dozen melodramas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/nightlife/reviews/cl-et-idlewild23aug23,0,889013.story</url>
         <critic>Ann Powers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This oddball mix of "The Cotton Club" and "Six Feet Under" is a big, beautiful mess. But it offers the not-uninstructive spectacle of talented people stumbling over large and unwieldy ambitions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6166937/rid/11077742/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An entertaining mess. It blends together musical styles and dances, historical periods with howling anachronisms, coy, almost childish gimmicks with R-rated sex and violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003019867</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The joint doesn't jump in the musical Idlewild; it just twitches and stumbles. As much a missed opportunity as a terrible tease.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/08/25/movies/25idle.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thin sprinkling of exuberance and a couple of choice cameos, that's about all this underwritten and overly choreographed spectacle has to tease us with.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=3047</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shakespeare has been quoted many, many times over the past 400 or so years, but never to such empty purpose as in the inchoate, self-indulgent musical drama Idlewild, a star vehicle for the wildly popular hip-hop duo OutKast.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joanne Kaufman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are moments in Idlewild that resonate with the painful "if only" of missed opportunity, and more than a few that just make you scratch your head. It's like some wildly overlong music video, minus the sexy thump 'n' grind. It's all blow, no pop.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A396886</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most ridiculous period film since rappers took on the Old West in "Posse."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/282465_idlewild25q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$12,669,914</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$5,745,780</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>973</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>