<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>I&amp;#039;m Not There</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Oren Moverman</author>
      <author>Todd Haynes</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Todd Haynes</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAGermany</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Cate Blanchett</actor>
      <actor>Richard Gere</actor>
      <actor>Heath Ledger</actor>
      <actor>Christian Bale</actor>
      <actor>Michelle Williams</actor>
      <actor>Julianne Moore</actor>
      <actor>Ben Whishaw</actor>
      <actor>Marcus Carl Franklin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 21, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>135</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'm Not There lets you hear it again, more majestically than ever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20161964,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'm Not There is the movie of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0747,hoberman,78422,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The strangest thing about Todd Haynes's new movie isn't that he cast six actors to play the various faces and phases of Bob Dylan. It's that he needed only six.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8495</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Haynes has essentially done is create a film that is a Bob Dylan song, one of his best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10424</url>
         <critic>Jeff Beresford-Howe</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film insists on being taken on its own terms -- the sort of demand, in other words, that defines the best art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/reviews/</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Faced with an artist defined more by his lyrics than his life story, Haynes delivers a song-cycle of a movie: vivid, exaggerated, contradictory impressions of a man who confounds a culture still looking to define him.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/340443_notthere21q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most inventive and joyous movies of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/09/12/toronto5/index.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brilliantly strange, often funny and ultimately heartbreaking film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/70994</url>
         <critic>David Gates</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Among its many achievements, Todd Haynes’s I’m Not There hurls a Molotov cocktail through the facade of the Hollywood biopic factory.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/21/movies/21ther.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A loopy, surreal, beguiling collage of a film, the writer-director's meta-biopic embraces its subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071120_To_paraphrase_a_line_from__quot_Idiot_Wind__quot__one_of_a_bunch_of_Bob_Dylan_songs_that_show_up_in_I_m_Not_There__the_mind_of_Todd_Haynes_is_filled_with_big_ideas__images_and_distorted_facts_.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Haynes's picture may not be perfect -- hell, I'm not even sure that perfection is a state it even aspires to -- but it's bold and individualistic and accomplished. A reason to take heart for the state of current American moviemaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4263/im-not-there.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So what if nothing is revealed. Todd Haynes is a mischievous visionary who puts the music and the myth of Bob Dylan before us in I'm Not There and dares us not to revel in the troubadour's poetic, contentious, ever-changing essence. It's a feast for the eyes, the ears and the Dylanologist scratching around our minds and hearts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/16155328/review/17335194/im_not_there</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Haynes does is take away the reassuring segues that argue everything flows and makes sense, and to show what's really chaos under the skin of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071120/REVIEWS/711200304</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lot of chaotic fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=987014&amp;reviewId=22778&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An ingenious, maddening film inspired by the "many lives of Bob Dylan."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/im_not_there</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A challenging film, one that I suspect can only benefit from multiple viewings. The success of its approaches varies, but its intent is unfailingly interesting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-there21nov21,0,6161608.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fascinating experiment that, if the viewer is willing to surrender to Haynes's sometimes hermetic meditations on Dylan's life, heartily rewards the investment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1140654&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extraordinary attempt to encapsulate the many faces of Bob Dylan that plays better to the convert than the sceptic. Like the nasal twang of the man in question, the film finally beguiles more than it irritates.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133122</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There’s an undeniable thrill to watching something so experimental and yet totally accessible to those of us who speak only layman’s Dylanese, and it’s Haynes’ warmest film yet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A562476</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I appreciate Haynes’ craft and ambition. I love the Ledger/Gainsbourg scenes, which are sweet and sad and delicately shaded. And Blanchett’s inspired not-quite-impersonation of Dylan is reason enough to tussle with the rest of it.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-im-not/254946/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bob Dylan would probably love I'm Not There, which may be all a Dylanist needs to know before seeing it. Non-devotees are in for puzzlement, if not exasperation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11212007/entertainment/movies/im_not_there_708158.htm</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end it remains an academic exercise, though a dazzlingly ambitious one that’s well worth seeing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/im/review/291159</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even with new information provided in the film, however, his personality remains not so much elusive as cantankerous, particularly in contrast with the expansiveness of his songs. That gap gives I'm Not There something of a hollow centre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071129.wthere29/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What emerges is a speculative, critical essay about the 60s, weighted down in spots by political correctness and a conflicted desire to mock Dylan's denseness while catering to his hardcore fans, but otherwise lively, fluid, and watchable.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32514_IM_NOT_THERE.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the singer's gnomic comments to the press, the movie can be maddeningly slippery; like his music, it's fierce, thrilling, and unapologetically itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2178384/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The star of the show is undoubtedly Blanchett, who has great fun playing Dylan as a showboat who quite knowingly goes about creating his reputation for rebellious independence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9720</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only devout Dylan fans will be able to derive much sense out of it. Dylan novices can only sit back and surrender to the ride Haynes offers: It's a strange, surreal trip.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/316704.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some of it is brilliant, some is tedious and some is just plain incoherent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/21/2007-11-21_needed_shelter_from_the_storm_of_six_bob.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If any man should be more than the sum of his parts, it's an artist. But Todd Haynes' I'm Not There makes Bob Dylan less than the sum of his parts. It's like a tony art-school parlor game.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.there21nov21,0,2842592.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stylistically audacious in the way it employs six different actors and assorted visual styles to depict various aspects of the troubadour's life and career, the film nevertheless lacks a narrative and a center, much like the "ghost" at its core.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934602.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not nearly as enjoyable as one of his rambling, meditative songs, though perhaps it is aspiring to be the cinematic equivalent. Give me "Tangled Up in Blue" any day over this incoherent, tangled trip.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-11-20-not-there_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too often, it’s the MOVIE that isn’t there. What’s meant to be archetypal comes across as superficial.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/40974/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It makes “Yellow Submarine” look like a miracle of sober narrative.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/11/26/071126crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It doesn't work. It is just a mess -- though the sound track, full of Dylan songs is, of course, good to hear. But it is not better than the track on Martin Scorsese's "No Direction Home" documentary of two years ago.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1686684,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone can make a bad movie, but it takes a good filmmaker to make one as bad as I'm Not There.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/21/DDODTF2KN.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$4,017,609</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$974,601</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>130</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>cate blanchett</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>