<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Inconvenient Truth, An</name>
   <company>Paramount Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Davis Guggenheim</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Al Gore</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 24, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>100</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most realistic documentaries I've ever seen--and, dry as it is, one of the most devastating in its implications.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/listings/rv_52847.htm</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Absolutely riveting.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/272438_inconvenient02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Am I acting as an advocate in this review? Yes, I am. I believe that to be "impartial" and "balanced" on global warming means one must take a position like Gore's. There is no other view that can be defended.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060601/REVIEWS/60517002/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Virtually everyone who sees this movie will be galvanized to do something about global warming -- and everyone should see this movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/02/DDGJVJ5COA1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its knockout success is a testament to Gore's eloquence and humanity and to the dexterity of his director, Davis Guggenheim.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.truth09jun09,0,1771011.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie, like the man, seems more interested in spreading the gospel of environmental responsibility, and in doing so it's probably the most important film of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1149728130185170.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Powerful, intelligent and surprisingly entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134187</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It seems to me that too often in this country, and especially now, science has become politicized to the detriment of those who could be helped by it. Just because truths are inconvenient is no reason to suppose they are not real.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0526/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Inconvenient Truth can't, of course, reveal a future that is still up to us, but by the time you're done watching, the real question is, Which way on God's green earth would you want to err?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1197646_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Haunting and inspiring film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-05-23-inconvenient-truth_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its scary warnings, the film ends on an upbeat note, unless of course you happen to be Hillary Clinton's campaign manager.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=616935&amp;reviewId=20952</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A disarming, funny and animated Al Gore, once a robot among presidential candidates, proves himself a rock star among environmental activists.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=616935&amp;reviewId=20907</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The faults of the movie, semi-excusable as self-vindicating ploys, are nothing compared with its strengths.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060612crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with An Inconvenient Truth isn't the message; it's the messenger.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/i/inconvenient_truth.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even a politically naive film critic can see that An Inconvenient Truth isn't only about science or economics; it's also about ideology.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060602.TRUTH02/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In an eco-horror show that politely masquerades as a documentary, the former vice president effectively warns of man-made cataclysm.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8874</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gore looks as energized and purposeful as Mother Earth looks sickly and mad as hell, which is no doubt why many commentators suggested it was less an environmental action statement than a test balloon for future political ambitions.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46954&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Quite apart from its environmental agenda, the film is a reminder that there's no space for substance in political discourse: A 30-second soundbite on global warming could easily be brushed off as tree-hugging rhetoric, but after 100 minutes of level-headed elaboration, it's chillingly undeniable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/48825</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As long as Guggenheim keeps his cameras trained on Gore's presentation, An Inconvenient Truth is an engaging film. Less successful are the scenes where Gore is seen off-stage, traveling around the world and visiting his childhood home.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2841</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gore keeps us riveted by being charming, literate and profoundly persuasive on a topic that's scarier than anything in a dozen Japanese horror flicks. Vote Gore on this one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/9144850/rid/10383624/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film succeeds powerfully, even though it's short on practical solutions, makes some questionable statements of fact and, given Gore's current ambiguous position in public life, requires a tighter focus on the message than on the messenger.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the message of the film sounds bleak, it is actually quite rousing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-truth24may24,0,2655755.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As unsettling as it can be, it is also intellectually exhilarating, and, like any good piece of pedagogy, whets the appetite for further study.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/24/movies/24trut.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly absorbing film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1120675&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Inconvenient Truth may not save the planet, but it's already gone a long way toward rescuing Gore's public profile.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/060602/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a film An Inconvenient Truth is a treasury of information. Attention may occasionally drift, but the film’s message of urgency is abundantly clear.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A369889</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's context and talking points are more interesting than the film itself, which settles for an earnest (though rarely dull) nudge in its chosen direction: PowerPoint cinema.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060602-movies-review-truth,0,6350340.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A straightforward record of the lecture Gore has toured for years, juiced by elaborate graphics. An excellent educational tool, picture may prove an awkward fit for theatrical distribution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=cannes&amp;nav=RCannes&amp;articleid=VE1117929428&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Inconvenient Truth does restore one's faith in the value of documentary-as-lecture, not least by extolling the virtues (rare as clean water these days) of politician-as-teacher.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0621,nelson,73313,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary is an act of political activism. Guggenheim and his politically conscious producers, Laurie David, Lawrence Bender and Scott Z. Burns, have no interest in either challenging Gore's viewpoint or giving opposing opinions equal time. The film is simply a conduit for Gore's message.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001918442</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Avoiding the usual vein-popping diatribes, he comes across as learned, calm and folksy. But much of what Gore says in this slide show he gives to people whose minds are not yet fully formed (undergraduates, actors) is absurd, and his assertions often contradict each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/66485.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Inconvenient Truth is something you rarely see in movies today: a blatant intellectual fraud. Shame on all of the people involved in this travesty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8451</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$24,146,161</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$404,879</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>true</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>