<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Incredible Hulk, The</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures, Marvel Studios</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Stan Lee</author>
      <author>Jack Kirby</author>
      <author>Zak Penn</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Louis Leterrier</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Edward Norton</actor>
      <actor>Liv Tyler</actor>
      <actor>Tim Roth</actor>
      <actor>Tim Blake Nelson</actor>
      <actor>Ty Burrell</actor>
      <actor>William Hurt</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 13, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>114</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Iron Man" has more wit and style, but Hulk is a neat thrill ride with an intelligent script by Zak Penn and smart, well-paced direction by the French director of "The Transporter" series, Louis Leterrier.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=Ytf0LQhCVK5Z0JqMbHPl421NvLrQ3GX8ghBrVgbGG3BH2JTJZwJL!-1498964393&amp;&amp;rid=11242</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Five years after Ang Lee attempted a stylistically and narratively daring reimagining of what a comic-book movie could be (an example that tanked disastrously at the box office), the big green gamma-guy returns to the screen in a purer, more unadulterated, vastly more entertaining form.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A633427</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Embraces its identity as a sci-fi-summer-action-blockbuster extravaganza. Along the way, it actually comes close to finding the balance that Lee was looking for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/12/DDSK116SV9.DTL</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Incredible Hulk is a more traditional superhero movie than its predecessor and should please those who want their not-so-jolly green giant served with helpings of action. This film provides less talk and more smashing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1039</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By handing the directorial reigns to Louis Leterrier, the Parisian filmmaker responsible for the breathless "Transporter" films, Universal reveals its desire to emphasize spectacle over story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4612/the-incredible-hulk.html</url>
         <critic>Eric Kohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Edward Norton's a more evocative actor than Eric Bana, and he supplies all the emotions required by Leterrier and writer Zak Penn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/666397.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Until the last 20 minutes, which stumble around in an attempt to set up a sequel, The Incredible Hulk keeps slamming everything forward, satisfyingly.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-incredible/454265/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dialogue is minimal but sharp, the pace swift and the action sequences suitably loud and brutal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/incredible-hulk/review/292486</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Luckily, the new The Incredible Hulk is more like those 80-page special issues that comic-book publishers sold in the early 1960s for a quarter, packed with old, favorite story lines.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.hulk13jun13,0,563766.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Loses something when it depends on its computer-generated creatures to carry the story. The effects are a mile above the previous Hulk film, but there's still a certain awkwardness to some movements, and an odd lack of definition to the massive muscles that makes them seem like gelatinous sacks of meat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/06/review_the_incredible_hulk_sma.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Incredible Hulk is weightless--as disposable as an Xbox game. It's also fairly entertaining: swift, playful without pitching into camp, and acted with high spirits.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47836/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's enough adrenaline pulsating throughout this bang-up Marvel Comics adaptation to erase 2003's Hulk from memory (Ang who?).</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33237_INCREDIBLE_HULK.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a classic comic-book hero quest that, while not entirely novel, hews to its own rules and conventions with dignity and artfulness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145213&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A straightforward actioner that delivers the goods with no unnecessary frills or digressions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937386.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Incredible Hulk is just a luridly reductive and violent B movie -- one that clears a bar that hadn't been set very high.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20205934,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may be that the Hulk role was not made for sensitive method actors like Norton or Bana. When '70s TV-"Hulk" Lou Ferrigno made his obligatory cameo, a palpable wave of affection swept through the Seattle preview audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/366821_hulk13q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Hulk himself looks more steroidal than superheroic, as if the expressive beast from the first film had been replaced by a WWE star.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_incredible_hulk</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a certain pleasure to be had in some of the physical blowouts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9815</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time the Incredible Hulk had completed his hulk-on-hulk showdown with the Incredible Blonsky, I had been using my Timex with the illuminated dial way too often.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080612/REVIEWS/848151866</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Closer in spirit and tone to the comic books that spawned it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/567293.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like its monstrous hero, The Incredible Hulk gets the job done with minimal artistry and a lot of noise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06122008/entertainment/movies/green_day_115208.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The final confrontation between the Hulk and Blonsky, now the roaring Abomination, is like the clash of Downey and Bridges in "Iron Man," only not as exciting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/17191966/review/21254065/the_incredible_hulk</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't run off before the credits start to roll, though: The Incredible Hulk ends with a jokey cameo by a certain movie star with his own newfound superhero franchise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080613_Grumpy__green_Hulk_a_gamer__but_he_s_not_incredible_enough.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This Hulk is more viscerally angry and packs a bigger wallop than Ang Lee's talkier, more introspective version. But it's hardly the best superhero movie around. "Iron Man" was wittier and more fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-11-incredible-hulk_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A franchise rebooted with efficiency, energy and sporadic invention, although Hulk 2.0 hardly smashes it out of the park.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134654</url>
         <critic>Simon Crook</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cheers to lower expectations, then, because The Incredible Hulk is The Pretty Good Hulk. All things considered, of course.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0824,the-not-terrible-hulk,464982,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is solid and efficient, if unadventurous, illustrating both the lure and the limitations of comic book extravaganzas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-hulk13-2008jun13,0,2950261.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's nothing we haven't seen done better before (by Paul Greengrass in the recent "Bourne Ultimatum," for instance), but it's good enough as kinetic entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/06/23/080623crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, don't go see this if you are looking for an intellectual film. If you're into seeing some fun, mindless action in a faithful Marvel comic adaptation for a couple hours, then go see the Hulk smash some stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11000</url>
         <critic>Zack Haddad</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Do we really need another Hulk movie? I was one of the few critics who actually liked Ang Lee's 2003 "Hulk," but it didn't exactly ring the cash registers or clamor for a continuation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0614/p25s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Playing characters familiar to the fans, we have William Hurt as a blustering general, Tim Blake Nelson as a kooky scientist and Tim Roth as an evil soldier who morphs into a monster. All of them seem to be directing themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080613.whulk13/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why remake a crappy movie five years later if it's only going to be marginally less crappy?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2193479/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A middling superhero movie! I wish I could say that was incredible.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/13/movies/13hulk.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once again, though, the film is defined by the strengths and weaknesses of the source material. While Bruce is working on anger management, you may find yourself working on boredom management, and matching his rate of success.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121331008196869571.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Incredible Hulk suggests only that we've bottomed out on special effects: They're not necessarily getting better -- they're just getting bigger. Technically, Leterrier's Hulk is as realistic-looking as a rampaging green giant could be. But that doesn't make him credible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/06/13/hulk/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One has to admit that enormous moviemaking skill goes into the creation of pictures like The Incredible Hulk. The sheer craft directors such as Leterrier lavish on them is awesome to me. I can't imagine how they orchestrate -- or even remember -- all the little pieces of film they require to build their big set pieces. That thought, however, is nearly always followed by this question: Why do they bother?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1813937,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For me, there's a problem with The Hulk, always has been, though it hasn't seemed to bother the tale's legions of fans. When the sensitive, physically unprepossessing Banner/Norton turns into the gargantuan, muscle-bound, growling Hulk, there's a total disconnect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/141172</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Roth and Hurt glower semi-engagingly, and while Norton's scrawniness works, he seems intellectually disengaged, despite his helping to craft Zak Penn's script.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/13/2008-06-13_incredible_hulk_is_not_so_smashing.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$134,806,913</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$137,500,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$55,414,050</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,505</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>william hurt</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>