<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Inkheart</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema (Warner Bros. Pictures)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Lindsay-Abaire</author>
      <author>Cornelia Funke</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Iain Softley</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Germany</origin>
      <origin>UK</origin>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Brendan Fraser</actor>
      <actor>Paul Bettany</actor>
      <actor>Helen Mirren</actor>
      <actor>Jim Broadbent</actor>
      <actor>Andy Serkis</actor>
      <actor>Sienna Guillory</actor>
      <actor>Eliza Hope Bennett</actor>
      <actor>Rafi Gavron</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 23, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>106</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inkheart was shot in and around Liguria on the Italian Riviera, and it looks absolutely ravishing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A727802</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story itself is so charmingly dense, fractious, and complicated that it frequently leaves the obvious good-guy-fights-bad-guy groove, and noses toward Terry Gilliam-esque randomness and ebullience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/inkheart,22967/</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inkheart feels a little confused in its tone and direction, but only a little, and I appreciate the way it both celebrates the power of literature and reminds us that stories have a life beyond the page, even if they are only in our hearts and minds.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/397096_inkheart23q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mirren's all-out display in this distinctly British absurdo-literary extravaganza had me wishing Elinor were my own fabulous auntie and that she'd lend me some magic items from her closet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20254186,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the young people in its demographic wheelhouse, Inkheart packs a welcome amount of entertainment value, creating a genuinely original world of enchantment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/inkheart,1141776.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a shame that by its conclusion the movie feels like just another special-effects-driven story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-01-22-inkheart_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that's brimming with fascinating ideas and elevated by some memorable performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/inkheart/review/295381</url>
         <critic>Jason Buchanan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fine ensemble, some gorgeous Italian Riviera locales, intermittent flashes of magic amid a more manufactured air of whimsy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-0123-inkheart-reviewjan23,0,1021332.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inkheart looks good and is well acted but, in the end, it left me indifferent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1450</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This children's fantasy flirts with the dark side, though family values win out. Thus, the movie remains devoted to heroism and is as opposed to the bad guys as it would be to killing off Brendan Fraser.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11527</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cold, bland and gimmicky - that's how the movie has turned out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.inkheart23jan23,0,6641393.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie begins to seem a little overloaded and gimmicky once characters from children's classics begin turning up (including Toto from The Wizard of Oz), but it's handsomely mounted.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34051_INKHEART.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You know a movie's not working when you see minotaurs, flying monkeys, "The Wizard of Oz's" Toto and Helen Mirren riding a unicorn -- all on the screen at the same time -- and you're still waiting for the thing to be over so you can go home and get on with your life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/866146.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a stunning-looking film with a dark romantic cloud (quite literally) hanging over its every shot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090123.winkheart23/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Kamal AL-Solaylee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite abundant talent on both sides of the camera and a bevy of eye-catching supernatural beasties, this f/x-heavy story of a literature-loving father and daughter battling dark forces unleashed from the pages of a rare tome doesn't conjure much in the way of bigscreen magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939193.html?categoryid=3479&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Inkheart</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most of the time it looks like we're on the back lot for a Romanian production of "Lord of the Rings IV."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10233</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not realizing that Inkheart is based on a famous fantasy novel, I had the foolish hope the movie might be about books. No luck. Wait till you hear what it's about.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090121/REVIEWS/901219989</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The actors are mostly charming; Bettany in particular is broody and cool.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/01/movie_review_inkheart_doesnt_m.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Graced with so many fanciful touches and features such a marvelous assortment of U.K. and American actors that it seems almost unjust that the final product is so curiously lacking in magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/01/23/inkheart/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With no unifying sensibility, the magic thuds more often than it soars.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-inkheart23-2009jan23,0,3249395.story</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inkheart goes crazy with fairy tale characters popping in and out, all sorts of fantastical creatures materializing and so many rescues one loses count. Yet the movie fails to involve the key constituent: the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-inkheart-1003922899.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It all smacks of that overdone "passion for literature" common in English teachers who send any healthy-minded kid running from books.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-01-21/film/brendan-fraser-s-inkheart-intones-literary-fluff/</url>
         <critic>Nick Pinkerton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aims for a blend of whimsy and tingly suspense but botches nearly every spell it tries to cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/01/23/movies/23inkh.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all handsomely produced, but none of the characters (save perhaps Bettany's fire-juggler) has a distinctive enough personality to make much of an impression.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=99648270</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A flea market of fairy tales and hocus-pocus, Inkheart makes as much sense as an inkblot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01232009/entertainment/movies/stinkheart_151409.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since the thunderous digital onslaughts of "Jumanji" has the big screen seen such too-muchness.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seemingly intended as a celebration of the power of books, it's an occasionally incoherent, sleep-inducing picture that reduces narrative to mere mechanics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/01/22/DDML15EJKE.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A kids' adventure movie can be a lot of things -- wild and woolly, loosey-goosey, full of foolishness -- but they should never be shabby. And that's the best word for Inkheart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/01/22/2009-01-22_inkheart_is_a_wrong_turn_for_the_write_s.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$17,303,424</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$60,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$7,601,379</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,655</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>helen mirren</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>