<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Inside Deep Throat</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Fenton Bailey</director>
      <director>Randy Barbato</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Dennis Hopper (narrator)</actor>
      <actor>Linda Lovelace</actor>
      <actor>David Winters</actor>
      <actor>Gerard Damiano</actor>
      <actor>Erica Jong</actor>
      <actor>Norman Mailer</actor>
      <actor>Harry Reems</actor>
      <actor>Gore Vidal</actor>
      <actor>John Waters</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 11, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>NC-17</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nimble, engrossing, and journalistically eye-opening, a movie that pulls into focus 30 years of porn in America. It also pulls no punches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1026160_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inside Deep Throat, an NC-17 documentary that deftly chronicles the fallout -- with about 15 seconds of hard-core footage -- has some surprise credits.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-02-10-inside-deep-throat_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Isn't as campy or as unhinged as the delightful Bailey and Barbato Tammy Faye Baker documentary, "The Eyes of Tammy Faye"; it's more like your standard HBO documentary (and HBO co-produced). But it's extremely entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2113361/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film falls short only in its refusal to take a stand on whether star Linda Lovelace was a victim, as she claimed.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Michael Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Delightful, insightful documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/nymetro/movies/reviews/10987/</url>
         <critic>Ken Tucker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offbeat documentary filmmakers Fenton Bailey and Randy Barbato dissect the history and legend of perhaps the best known and most profitable pornographic movies ever made.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=45912</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing preachy about this slick and funny doc (narrated by Dennis Hopper), which as a brief history of how porn spurted into the mainstream has all the money shots you could ask for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=11185</url>
         <critic>Nick De Semlyen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The doc is longer on historical interest than original insights or analysis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0211/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film goes beyond historical anecdotes. Besides fresh and funny insights from the likes of Norman Mailer and John Waters, it shows how little censorship politics have changed from Nixon to Bush.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6806983?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Considering the seedy nature of the adult film industry and the sad fates of many of its stars, Inside Deep Throat is surprisingly light on tragedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=247473&amp;reviewId=17474</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When Inside Deep Throat is over, it's tough to say which tragic moment lingers longer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.deep18mar18,1,993717.story?coll=bal-movies-storyutil</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deliriously entertaining field report from a historical moment when porn darned near became mainstream.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1108645244151200.xml</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does a fine job.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/02/11/DDG8QB8GSD1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers a diverting tale of erstwhile indie filmmaking and the power of porn to generate change - both at the box office and in the bedroom.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=247473&amp;reviewId=17342</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thorough but highly entertaining documentary details the making of the notorious 1972 film, the series of legal battles that helped make it immensely popular and the flick's considerable cultural legacy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/39650.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inside Deep Throat, a documentary that premiered at Sundance and is now going into national release, was made not on the fringes but by the very establishment itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050210/REVIEWS/50128001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An often lively investigation of the social forces that produced the original movie and made it an unlikely political shibboleth in the ongoing culture wars.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A15665-2005Feb10.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inside Deep Throat starts small and keeps expanding outward until there's seemingly no facet of American life the phenomenon hasn't touched.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review_pop.php?review_id=8235</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provocative and perceptive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000770587</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a gaudy pop-culture personality that perfectly suits its subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117925949&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a Kafkaesque turn of events, Reems was the fall guy--facing prison, he became a Hollywood cause célèbre. Inside Deep Throat includes footage of him partying with Jack and Warren and debating Roy Cohn on TV.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0506,hoberman,60833,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By turns funny and sobering, sweeping and intimate, the consistently entertaining Inside Deep Throat plays like a giddy prance through the minefield of the last three decades of American sex and politics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-deep11feb11,2,2603083.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a reductive moral to a story full of fascinating contradictions, but Bailey and Barbato draw a convincing line between the social and political atmosphere of the film and the culture wars of today. The issues are still very much alive.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/211527_deep11q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not even the film's director Gerard Damiano will argue for Deep Throat being a great movie. But, hey, at least there's no gag order anymore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A258973</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Passably interesting, occasionally compelling, sporadically amusing, and badly lacking in focus.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/i/inside_deep.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While brisk, informative, and entertaining, feels frustratingly sketchy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=1970</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beautifully assembled and edited by Fenton Bailey and Randy Barbato ("The Eyes of Tammy Faye") and is often very funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-11-2005/news/gossip/story/279882p-239598c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Full of groovy music and comic characters--many with a priceless reaction to Lovelace's oral party trick--but it hardly manages to say anything new or thoughtful.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050209-movies-review-ab-deepthroat.story</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inside Deep Throat is more scattershot than deep, but it vividly evokes the days when the "sexual revolution" was supposed to liberate the American libido.</snippet>
         <url>http://msnbc.msn.com/id/6919470/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>William Underhill</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seeks to establish a pioneering role for the movie in liberating America’s sex life. To me it’s far from clear that that cheerfully cheesy slice of hardcore, made for $25,000 by a middle-aged hairdresser named Gerard Damiano, has spawned much in the way of a cultural legacy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/05/12/film-taylor.php</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well-crafted and, in places, highly informative, but with the exception of some of the original film's hardcore sex scenes and the aforementioned Mob angle, there's little we haven't been exposed to before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=6865</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fascinating story but not so fascinatingly told.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A14409-2005Feb10.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the smirking title might suggest, the movie is least prepared to process the feminist backlash against porn movies that followed their early-70s crossover -- in a way the most interesting part of the story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chireader.com/movies/archives/2005/0205/050211.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This feeble documentary ends up perpetuating the very hypocrisy it means to probe.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050211/DEEP11/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an unfocused overview that intersperses choppy interviews and observations with clips from "Deep Throat," including some of its most notorious and explicit scenes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7580</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If a movie can be fascinating and tedious at the same time, Inside Deep Throat -- which more or less depicts the America I have just described -- is that movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/02/11/deep_throat/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Deep Throat" bore an X certificate. Inside Deep Throat is an NC-17. Neither is suitable for grownups.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050228crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A "slam, bam, thank you, ma'am" trifle of an entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/02/11/movies/11deep.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$691,880</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$2,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$88,709</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>12</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>