<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Into the Blue</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Studios</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Matt Johnson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>John Stockwell</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Paul Walker</actor>
      <actor>Jessica Alba</actor>
      <actor>Scott Caan</actor>
      <actor>Ashley Scott</actor>
      <actor>Josh Brolin</actor>
      <actor>James Frain</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 30, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers modest pleasures. It is not an essential film, but if you go to see it, it will not insult your intelligence, and there's genuine suspense toward the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050929/REVIEWS/50926005/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Into the Blue is as much a mesmerizing aquatic expedition as it is a reasonably suspenseful action adventure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7108</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enjoyable, gorgeously photographed aquatic adventure whose stars are blissfully bodacious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/351126p-299357c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stockwell takes an especially leaden screenplay, floats the dull thing up from the depths of mediocrity, and makes it cinematically buoyant. Within limits, that is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050930/BLUE30/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mad props to Peter Zuccarini, who headed the team of ocean-bound photographers and captured some remarkably vivid footage, and also to the actors, who spend plenty of time looking cool, calm and collected swimming with the predatory fishes.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050930-movies-review-blue,0,5458058.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's "The Deep" reimagined as an Abercrombie catalog.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=426438&amp;reviewId=19156</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cast is little more than the sum total of golden skin, firm flesh and blindingly white teeth, but in a film that demands them to be half-naked and soaking wet most of the time, looks trump technical acting skill every time.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46309</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Let's be honest: Whether it's Jessica Alba or Paul Walker you're dying to see stripped down to her/his sexiest swimwear, there's only one reason anyone is interested in diving Into the Blue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2307</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Academy might not be troubled, but at times Into The Blue's wet Hollywood bodies really hit the spot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=11359</url>
         <critic>Ian Nathan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Granted, the cast has a certain rumpy charm, and setting four-fifths of the movie underwater keeps the pesky surfer-speak to a minimum, but the film is less about thrills than punishing the wicked.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0540,tracking7,68595,20.html</url>
         <critic>Matt Singer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The makers of Into the Blue know what the audience wants. And they deliver a little bit more.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/30/DDGHOEVF021.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Accommodates some great water photography.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28602_INTO_THE_BLUE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are far, far worse ways to spend two hours than watching Jessica Alba in a skimpy bikini - as well as other natural wonders photographed in the Bahamas - in the airheaded underwater adventure Into the Blue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/53187.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its characterizations are as bland as sand.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A293430</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There will always be an audience for the escapist rewards this type of movie always dangles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-09-29-into-the-deep_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the thriller Into the Blue, the Bahamian waters dazzle the eye. They are breathtaking and welcoming, possessing mysterious depths.
The same cannot be said for the film's stars, Paul Walker and Jessica Alba, who are every bit as gorgeous as the scenery but not quite so profound.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=426438&amp;reviewId=19157</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Walker is supposed to be lured by the buried treasure, but the actor, wearing Brad Pitt's bristle cut, is like Pitt with his sexy appetite sucked out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1110750_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Into the Blue is a likable bimbo of a movie, all surface and -- despite breathtaking underwater photography and a marked resemblance to Peter Yates' "The Deep" -- zero depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3579&amp;Sumbit.x=42&amp;Sumbit.y=12</url>
         <critic>John Patterson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An undistinguished treasure-hunting epic that rips off the 1977 movie, "The Deep," in virtually every frame. It's pretty to look at, but so low-voltage and instantly forgettable that it's hardly worth anyone's time.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/242766_intotheblue30q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not a thriller so much as an extremely violent swimsuit calendar, the lushly lensed but dramatically waterlogged Into the Blue is too infatuated with its scantily clad stars to make sense of all the drug dealers, boat looters and bloodthirsty sharks trying to hunt them down.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928373?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This logic-challenged dive-bum thriller directed by John Stockwell, who did the equally silly surf movie "Blue Crush."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-intotheblue30sep30,0,7540438.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When under water, the action-adventure Into the Blue has genuine thrills. Above water or on dry land, this is one dead fish.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001219173</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This undiluted nonsense is best suited to DVD-rental desperation. Still, aficionados of cheap cinematic thrills involving beautiful and stupid young people will be happy to learn that while the film fizzles far more than it sizzles, its director, John Stockwell, is a connoisseur of the female backside, which he displays to great and frequent advantage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/30/movies/30into.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Into the Blue drowns before it even surfaces.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-09-29/film/film3.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>May look good cavorting prettily on deck, but ultimately it deserves to walk the plank.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/29/AR2005092900665.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It has all the elements one would expect from a "so bad it's good" feature: cheesy dialogue, a script that could have been written by two chimpanzees, acting that would make a high school drama teacher cringe, and lots of tight female bodies poured into tiny bikinis. Despite all of that, however, I found Into the Blue to be a real trial.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/i/into_blue.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not even the repeated sight of Jessica Alba in a bikini, the camera caressing her like the eyes of a strip-club patron, can lift this leaden refuse off the ocean floor.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=426438&amp;reviewId=19129&amp;startDate=09%2F30%2F2005</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Laughably awful.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41060</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$18,782,227</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$50,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$7,057,854</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,789</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>