<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Is Anybody There?</name>
   <company>Big Beach Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Peter Harness</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>John Crowley</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael Caine</actor>
      <actor>Bill Milner</actor>
      <actor>Anne-Marie Duff</actor>
      <actor>David Morrissey</actor>
      <actor>Leslie Phillips</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 17, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is also hard not to see remnants of a younger Michael Caine -- beautifully seductive and enigmatic all those years ago in "Alfie." He has said his wife cried when she saw the performance; you understand why.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/la-et-anybody17-2009apr17,0,5324620.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caine leads an impeccable cast in a story that is as touching as it is funny, turning the mundane minutiae of fading lives into a vibrant display.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136310</url>
         <critic>Philip Wilding</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sentimentality is held in check by Caine, who rises to the occasion with a bleak, angry performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#34338</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A kid-meets-curmudgeon comedy that transcends its formulaic skeleton thanks both to the veteran actor's charm and a smarter-than-average screenplay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/04/review_a_magicians_adieu_is_an.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Blending humor and heartbreak in a performance that makes a small movie a richly satisfying one, Caine truly is magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18308311/review/27538177/is_anybody_there</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Caine and young Milner make for amusing adversaries, it's nice to see Crowley paying respect to his elders by populating the retirement home with a number of familiar faces, including those belonging to Rosemary Harris, Sylvia Syms and longtime "Coronation Street" resident Thelma Barlow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11675</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All-too-familiar and schmaltzy territory for both coming-of-age films and movies with elderly actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04172009/entertainment/movies/only_caine_able_to_muster_movie_magic_164754.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I can't really recommend the film, unless you admire Caine as much as I do, which is certainly possible.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090429/REVIEWS/904299972</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You don't need a Ouija board to suss out where all this is heading, but Is Anybody There? counteracts its deficiencies -- predictability, sentimentality -- with a healthy dose of dark humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1024871.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More deft than it first appears, director John Crowley's gentle-but-not-sappy drama features another late-day masterpiece-in-miniature from Michael Caine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/04/17/2009-04-17_short_takes_.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Caine is magnificent, and the film is worth a look for his contribution alone. But Milner is a promising actor, too, and the pairing of young and old is believable and occasionally very moving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/is-anybody-there,1156476.html</url>
         <critic>Philip Kennicott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Requires us to repress any thoughts about stale material and keep Caine's heartfelt performance front and center.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/04/23/MV8F176HOR.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer Peter Harness has based his screenplay on his own childhood experiences, but personal doesn't necessarily translate to fresh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/05/01/a_little_magic_and_maturity_from_caine/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script is always shakier than the performers trying to bring it across, and by the third act, it lets them down completely.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/is-anybody-there,26754/</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What balances the movie is Mr. Caine's exceptional portrayal of old age as the accumulation of a lifetime's experience. In his performance the child, the youthful rogue and the forgetful codger all live at once.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/04/17/movies/17ther.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of this is at once predictable and implausible -- a two-hander of a story so overplotted and overpopulated that by the time it's winding up, the question isn't so much Is Anybody There? as it is, "Why on earth are so many bodies here?"</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103075565</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No one could save Is Anybody There? from its treacly self and Michael Caine doesn't, but he gives it a grand try.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123992063794426951.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the whole, there are precious few life lessons in Is Anybody There? that haven't been noted before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A772412</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even Crowley, who seems to have a knack with overloaded material, can't quite bring the thing in for a safe landing in all the slush.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-04-15/film/is-anybody-there-is-crowley-s-lighter-follow-up-to-boy-a/</url>
         <critic>Nicolas Rapold</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,026,756</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$46,209</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>michael caine</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>