<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Jackass: Number Two</name>
   <company>Paramount Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sean Cliver</author>
      <author>Preston Lacy</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jeff Tremaine</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Johnny Knoxville</actor>
      <actor>Bam Margera</actor>
      <actor>Steve-O</actor>
      <actor>Chris Pontius</actor>
      <actor>Preston Lacy</actor>
      <actor>Ryan Dunn</actor>
      <actor>Ehren McGhehey</actor>
      <actor>Jason Acuña</actor>
      <actor>Dave Engl</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 22, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Comedy, like most everything else, is subjective, and this may be the greatest example out there of "getting it" or not. If you thought the first movie, the original TV show, the Three Stooges, or "Football in the Groin," was funny, chances are “ackass: Number Two is right up your alley.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9315</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It didn't seem possible, but Johnny Knoxville, Bam Margera, Steve-O, Chris Pontius, Wee Man and company might just have cooked up a sequel that's even wilder, funnier, extra-depraved and more gag-inducing than the seemingly incomparable "Jackass the Movie."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003155337</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Debased, infantile and reckless in the extreme, this compendium of body bravado and malfunction makes for some of the most fearless, liberated and cathartic comedy in modern movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/09/22/movies/22jack.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As merry pranksters they have no match, and as they age (Knoxville is 35 now), they only grow in appeal. As they proudly hurl their tattooed (by ink and battle scars) bodies into harm's way, a devilish glint in their eyes, it's as if they've discovered the fountain of youth, and its name is Jackass.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14533/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jackass: Number Two aims low and hits lower, but is as hilarious and uncomfortable an encounter as possible</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133112</url>
         <critic>Tony Horkins</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just the kind of vicarious excitement for which the movies were invented.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A403427</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is extreme comedy, and it's amazing how director Jeff Tremaine, who along with Spike Jonze has been affiliated with this troupe from its outset, creates an environment where self-inflicted torture is uncontrollably funny without being morally offensive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8698</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some movies simply shouldn't be seen sober or alone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/53164</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jackass Number Two is not as original, aberrantly beautiful, unrepetitious, or good as Jackass Number One, yet it will still double a lot of people over with big laughs and grossed-out disbelief.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1537079_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirshling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the "Godfather II" of tasteless prank films.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/09/22/DDGUAL9CIA1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The heart of Jackass - the adolescent drive to bash body and soul into the symbolic brick wall of maturity - remains pure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/8871059/review/11756641/jackass_number_two</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Part of what makes "ackass Number Two so frighteningly watchable -- even against your better judgment -- is the way the guys delight in one another's bumps, bangs and bruisings: First, they feel one another's pain; then they laugh like hell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/09/22/jackass_two/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performers understand the simple integrity of a slapstick gag, and they're prepared to suffer for its entertainment value. This is what the Jackassers do for fun -- and their fans, already well versed in such previous shows as the original MTV series and the 2002 "Jackass: The Movie," understand that perfectly. And is there any significant moral difference between these performers and dedicated ballerinas who damage their feet in the highfalutin interests of art, or Daytona drivers risking their lives on the track?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118094&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Parts of this are screamingly funny, other parts downright stomach turning, but you have to admire the fact that, for these guys, "anything for a laugh" really means anything. And for all the moronic behavior, there are also some inspired dadaist moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30320_JACKASS_NUMBER_TWO.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unapologetically appalling, more disgusting than anything you've ever seen and moronic enough to make you wonder about that theory on the depletion of the gene pool. It is also so funny it will make you choke.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=A4766B9541DA2CE158B2855FC03271A5.prodapp14_ae_01?id=694085&amp;reviewId=21515&amp;startDate=09%2F22%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sequel is a dizzying succession of pranks, Candid Camera-like sketches, and, that old crowd-pleaser, the boys actively courting their own grievous harm. This is what you get when a generation grows up watching far too many "Roadrunner" cartoons while sitting on the couch eating bowl after bowl of Lucky Charms.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=991C04486818599B7D4670FBAD892327.prodapp14_ae_02?id=694085&amp;reviewId=21492&amp;startDate=09%2F22%2F2006</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ask yourself this: Did the title make you laugh? If so, you're probably the target audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=282921&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A buffet of dumb and degrading stunts halfway between Looney Tunes and Abu Ghraib?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/poop_dreck_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are moments, heaven forgive me, that left me chuckling. Not to mention eternally grateful that it's these guys doing this stuff, and not me.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.jackass22sep22,0,5283512.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a certain morbid fascination, and perverse humor, in watching grown men enthusiastically turn themselves into human cartoons. (For better or worse, these guys are their generation's Stooges.)</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/454795p-382572c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This stunningly shameless follow-up to the 2002 theatrical sleeper (and homdevid mega-seller) offers more of the same -- a lot more -- while repeatedly upping the ante in terms of offensiveness. Which, of course, should greatly -- and profitably -- please is target aud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931664?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a point, however, at which the movie becomes simply sickening. Between the electric shocks and hot-iron branding, feats of grossness are accomplished that are so vile even the hardiest among the cast cannot suppress the upchuck.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/285989_jackass22q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no plot here; like the MTV show that spawned it, this movie is just a progression of increasingly disgusting and/or dangerous stunts.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060922-movies-review-jackass,0,4656789.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$72,778,712</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$11,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$29,002,002</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,059</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>