<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Jesus Camp</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Heidi Ewing</director>
      <director>Rachel Grady</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Becky Fischer</actor>
      <actor>Mike Papantonio</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 22, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>84</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fact that Pastor Fischer would probably consider the film an accurate portrayal of her mission may be the most terrifying thing of all.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=282748&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a documentary, Jesus Camp could lose its haunted-house score and contrapuntal Air America refrains and still deliver its message: that, here and elsewhere, fundamentalism is no longer content with a separate peace. It wants the meat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1542503_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It makes an unsettling case that America is fast becoming the thing it professes to hate.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/287692_camp06q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This team has succeeded at making a film that opens a subculture without programming our responses to it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.jesus06oct06,0,2304475.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funny, sad and horrifying. Anti-fundamentalist rather than anti-Christian, this deserves to preach to more than just the converted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135284</url>
         <critic>Owen Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a call to arms, a call to pick sides in the deepening cultural, political, and spiritual schism between the two Americas of the 21st century.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A407837</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At heart, all documentaries aim to be important films. Few actually pull it off. Minor flaws and all, Jesus Camp is among the year's most important films, if only because it forces us to learn about an America we seldom see and seldom want to see.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/09/29/DDGH8LDU6M1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Ewing and Grady have accomplished here is remarkable--capturing the visceral humanity, desire and unflagging political will of a religious movement.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060929-movies-review-camp,0,7222931.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Doesn't function particularly well as a documentary; it lacks a strong editorial point of view and doesn't really comment on the evangelical movement so much as it just portrays a selection of people and their views.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=3106</url>
         <critic>Sara Brady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What most interests the directors is the way young minds are shaped by adults with clear moral and political agendas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/454817p-382579c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jesus Camp is not a "hatchet job." The filmmakers did not go in with an anti-Christian agenda and use selective editing to prove their point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/j/jesus_camp.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I felt depressed when I realized all 87 minutes had passed without one word about forgiving sin or reaching out to the image of God in neighbors who don't think as you do.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=701293&amp;reviewId=21560&amp;startDate=10%2F13%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's almost impossible not to respond emotionally to this fascinating, sobering and all-too-brief exploration of the politicized religious right and its hopes, dreams and power.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=701293&amp;reviewId=21607</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cinematic dynamite.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=701293&amp;reviewId=21620</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jesus Camp doesn't pretend to be a comprehensive survey of the charismatic-evangelical phenomenon. It offers no history or sociology and only scattered statistics about its growth. It analyzes the political agenda only glancingly, centering on abortion but not on homosexuality or other items.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/09/22/movies/22camp.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fascinating glimpse of kids' role in the evangelical movement's political agenda.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003122670</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether you are a religious, churchgoing person or not, if you are the least bit liberal or tolerant in your world view, this has got to be one of the most unnerving films of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-jesus29sep29,0,1407600.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If we are in the midst of a culture war, as many people proclaim in Jesus Camp, then the left should be concerned. The right's Christian soldiers appear to be extremely well trained.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9474</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jesus Camp works nicely as a time-capsule document confirming the impact -- and popularity -- of American evangelism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9414</url>
         <critic>KJ Doughton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Often funny (just listen to Becky fulminate against Harry Potter), but it's also a scary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1127027&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A frightening, infuriating, yet profoundly compassionate documentary about the indoctrination of children by the Evangelical right.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/21366/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why do Ewing and Grady feel the need to tip their hand by underscoring it all with creepy ambient music or by using Air America host Mike Papantonio as a Greek Chorus expressing the voice of reason?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/53166</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By gilding the lily so shamelessly, Ewing and Grady guarantee they'll preach only to the converted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1160013345299160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a glimpse into a world most secular, metropolitan liberals never see, and it's likely to induce howls of both terror and hilarity from big-city audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/09/21/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>May shock many viewers, especially political liberals.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930515?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hamstrung by its polemics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/060929/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A snapshot, to be sure, but scattershot as well.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The doc these kids would make with flea market camcorders couldn't possibly be as ugly as this absurdly hypocritical critique of the far right's role in escalating the culture war. The classier indoctrination to which Gap-shopping urban Democrats subject their kids might look damn spooky, too, but it probably wouldn't sell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0638,nelson,74510,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$902,544</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$17,659</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>13</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>