<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Jindabyne</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Beatrix Christian</author>
      <author>Raymond Carver</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ray Lawrence</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Australia</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Laura Linney</actor>
      <actor>Gabriel Byrne</actor>
      <actor>Chris Haywood</actor>
      <actor>Deborra-Lee Furness</actor>
      <actor>John Howard</actor>
      <actor>Leah Purcell</actor>
      <actor>Eva Lazzaro</actor>
      <actor>Sean Rees-Wemyss</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 27, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>123</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lawrence delves deep into the moral dilemma at the heart of Carver's deceptively simple tale. By deliberately making the young woman in the river aboriginal, the film also opens up yet another dimension in the reaction to the men's inaction: Would they have acted any differently had the murder victim been white?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=287598&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne's strength and power come from a number of factors: its origin, its current landscape and the unusual way its writer-director, Ray Lawrence, has chosen to work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-jindabyne27apr27,0,3901493.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The same organic characterizations that marked Lawrence's acclaimed 2001 film "Lantana" will attract fans of strong adult drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=353</url>
         <critic>Megan Lehmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne wears its class politics lightly, weaving them into a ghost story about the intimate connection between how we treat our living and our dead that will hover around your shoulders long after you leave the theater.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/jindabyne-so-much-carver-so-far-from-home/16225/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Ray Lawrence, well regarded for his two previous films, "Bliss" and "Lantana," expands Carver's work into an indictment of colonialism and an examination of the chasm that supposedly exists between men and women over matters of the heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0427/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne -- named for the lakeside town in which the troubles spill -- can't contain all that the filmmakers want to throw in. Best to keep glued to the taut performance by Laura Linney.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20035190,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, it's all a bit too self-consciously mysterious and Lawrence leans a bit too much on the atmosphere to do the work for him as he builds to a frustrating ending. But his vision of a place haunted by a restlessness it can't define proves unsettlingly infectious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/jindabyne</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While not everything in Jindabyne works, especially in its final, redemptive third, the film and its faces stay with you.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070504-movies-review-jindabyne,0,2944869.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dublin-born Byrne and native New Yorker Linney...are both exceptional at depicting characters about to burst from inner turmoil, and Linney, in particular, is heartbreaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/04/27/2007-04-27_a_down_under_drama_with_emotional_depth.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne is uniquely Australian, dealing with Australian issues, and it boasts a wickedly wry conclusion that -- for everything that has come before -- is karmically just.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/316146_jindabyne18q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deliberately paced, with an eerie, country-ish score from the Australian singer/songwriter Paul Kelly, Jindabyne is definitely a mystery. But it's not about who killed the woman - audiences know that practically from the outset.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20070518_Aussies_spin_a_mystery__although_its_not_a_whodunit.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its core, the story is a Mars vs. Venus case study.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/117995730454270.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Above all, this story is about the peril that lurks under life's surfaces.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=876889&amp;reviewId=22458</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a mature and challenging motion picture, and something that will stick with viewers after the screen has gone dark.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/j/jindabyne.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too many extraneous elements have been added--the victim here is an aborigine, which prompts a racial backlash against the men and their families--but at the movie's center lies the knotty story of a marriage poisoned by amorality.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31577_JINDABYNE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The real flaw is that the movie's best features -- the aching clarity of its central performances -- threaten to be lost in a wilderness of metaphor and mystification.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/movies/27jind.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hand it to Lawrence and Christian. Jindabyne is a soberly, if sluggishly, crafted movie in which the bitterness never stops.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0717,hoberman,76450,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never obtains the full impact of its potentially powerful inner core.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=cannes&amp;nav=RCannes&amp;articleid=VE1117930632&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wish one-tenth of the films I saw were made with this much craft and integrity, this much intuitive understanding of where to put the camera, how much of the story to explain in words (not much) and how much to trust his outstanding cast to carry the film with their voices, faces and bodies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/04/26/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never manages to get its relationships framed in as sharp focus as "Lantana" and goes down some unproductive side roads in its attempt to get to the point.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A479295</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where it works best is in the domestic dance of death between a husband and a wife. Linney flutters with increasingly panicky intelligence throughout the film, while Byrne sinks further into his own bulk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9650</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lawrence too often errs on the side of embellishing details that didn't need to be expanded upon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3763/jindabyne.html</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adapting a great short story, like Carver's "So Much Water So Close to Home," into a movie poses a dilemma: How to flesh it out to feature length without destroying what made it great in the first place?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070511.wjinda11/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scene by scene, Jindabyne has dramatic force, but it's an awfully long slog. Carver's smartest tactic was never outstaying his welcome.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/30922/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A great idea is weighed down by an over-egged screenplay, but the setting and cast bring out its best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134833</url>
         <critic>Sam Toy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes, the sincerest form of tribute is inferiority. Watching the Australian film Jindabyne, one soon embraces the conclusion: Robert Altman did this work better. And with fewer brush strokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1105447&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne started with a bad idea and the finished film doesn't do well by it.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB117762850119984028.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has some strong acting. But largely because of its glacial pacing, the story ends up feeling too detached to move us as it should.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-04-26-indie-reviews_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jindabyne suffers from too many extraneous elements and from a story that doesn't land with enough force or purpose.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/05/11/DDGF5POCSE1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A depressing and tedious movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04272007/entertainment/movies/tedious_fish_tale_baited_with_misery_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$399,879</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$10,800,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$28,298</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>