<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Just Friends</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Adam &amp;#039;Tex&amp;#039; Davis</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Roger Kumble</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USACanada</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ryan Reynolds</actor>
      <actor>Anna Faris</actor>
      <actor>Chris Klein</actor>
      <actor>Amy Smart</actor>
      <actor>Christopher Marquette</actor>
      <actor>Julie Haggarty</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Root</actor>
      <actor>Fred Ewanuick</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 23, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>94</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Argues on behalf of the Darwinian theory that all of life imitates high school...But the argument is only halfhearted. Just Friends is much more interested in - and hilarious about - the small nostalgias of suburbia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1133622_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoroughly enjoyable three-or four-gimmick comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/11/23/DDGSKFS4EH1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The infectious high spirits of the performers help to carry the day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3665&amp;Sumbit.x=47&amp;Sumbit.y=7</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprisingly shrewd and energetic romantic comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928889?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A refreshingly mean-spirited breeze through both the holiday movie and romantic-comedy checklists.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0547,wood,70234,20.html</url>
         <critic>Mikael Wood</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Still, there are some funny surprises, from skewering overdone Christmas decorations to casting Chris Klein as a creep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-11-22-just-friends_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funnier than any low-rent rip-off of "There's Something About Mary" has a right to be. It's crass, it's unsophisticated, it aims right for the slapsticky pleasure center of the under-30 moviegoer's brain. So sue me, I laughed. A lot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7935</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A welcome antidote to the usual seasonal sweetness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051125/FRIENDS25/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thanks to director Roger Kumble's breathless pacing, Just Friends manages to outrun most of its flaws. And its likable leads - the coolly clownish Reynolds and the feline-faced Smart - fill this empty Christmas stocking with glee.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=479448&amp;reviewId=19608&amp;startDate=11%2F23%2F2005</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funnier than it has any right to be, thanks to Reynolds’ charisma and Faris’ bubbleheaded blonde.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=133148</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the fact that we are watching Reynolds do the same schtick yet again, director Roger Kumble never lets him outlast a joke or take a gimmick too far. The plot is nothing short of formulaic but what comedy of this nature isn’t these days?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8194</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whenever Just Friends threatens to become a total drag, Faris bops onscreen for some serious comic business - either saving the film, or making things worse by pointing out what could have been.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.friends23nov23,1,511973.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is superficial entertainment to say the least. But if you're looking for laughs, then Just Friends is just fine.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=479448&amp;reviewId=19592</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But alas, even with young talent, director Roger Kumble and writer Adam Davis rely way too heavily (no pun intended) on the fat-suit joke and titular impasse.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501122-movies-review-friends,0,7032183.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chris Klein steals the film as a rival ex-nerd, now the most gorgeous guy in town, while director Roger Kumble (Cruel Intentions) cribs from the Farrelly brothers and the Three Stooges.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29021_JUST_FRIENDS.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where are our Tracy/Hepburn screwball combos? Part of the appeal of "Wedding Crashers" was that Isla Fisher truly did have the comedic chops to match Vince Vaughn, and Just Friends suggests that Reynolds and Faris have potential greatness together too. Just not so much in this film.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-11-24/film/film3.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In all, it's not too bad and it's not too long.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1097598&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although set 10 years after high school graduation, Just Friends is a dumb teen comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/249316_friends23q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tantalizing promise of 90 heavenly minutes of Ryan Reynolds in a roly-poly fatsuit and unconvincing tubby make-up (which make him look like a younger version of Martin Short's Jiminy Glick) proves a case of the old bait-and-switch.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/42859</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a standard-issue gross Hollywood knockabout comedy in which slapstick antics have been piled up with a steam shovel and driven home with a sledgehammer. Reynolds and Smart are game and even dimensional, but all others are stuck playing tiresome, obnoxious characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-justfriends23nov23,0,590143.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>And though Samantha is written as a sly spoof of Ashlee Simpson, Faris frantically overplays her. She might have taken a tip from Smart, a lovely, understated actress who wastes too much time in lousy films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/11-23-2005/entertainment/movies/story/368325p-313378c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a line between rogue and jerk, and Reynolds lives on the wrong side of it. As Dusty, Klein is such a smooth operator that he could have been - should have been - the lead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/31710.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ironically, Faris' Samantha is the most convincing personality in the mix: She's a grotesque caricature of Courtney Love by way of Nancy Spungen, a vulgar, selfish monster of unbridled id, but you always know where she's coming from.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46513</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overcompensates for its sloppiness with loud, knockabout farce.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/11/23/movies/23frie.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just lousy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001524259</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script, by Adam "Tex" Vegas, ricochets between over-earnest romantic comedy staples and a noticeable lack of any consistent tone for Reynolds’ character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A312727</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are bad movies and annoying movies, and this one contains elements of both.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/j/just_friends.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is not a spark of chemistry between Chris and Jamie, although the plot clearly requires them to fall in love. There is so much chemistry involved with the Anna Faris character, however, that she can set off multiple chain reactions with herself, if you see what I mean.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20051122/REVIEWS/51120001/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$32,596,916</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$13,243,107</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,505</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>