<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Kinky Boots</name>
   <company>Buena Vista Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Geoff Deane</author>
      <author>Tim Firth</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Julian Jarrold</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Joel Edgerton</actor>
      <actor>Chiwetel Ejiofor</actor>
      <actor>Sarah-Jane Potts</actor>
      <actor>Jemima Rooper</actor>
      <actor>Ewan Hooper</actor>
      <actor>Linda Bassett</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 14, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>107</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This pleasant but predictable affair does one thing very well: showcasing the versatility of Chiwetel Ejiofor. The London actor can be seen as Denzel Washington's detective sidekick in "Inside Man." Watch him chomp down on a New York accent with Washington, and then watch him as Lola (a.k.a. Simon), a cabaret performer in makeup, wig and wild gowns. That's acting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/movies/14280661.htm</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ejiofor's polished, energetic performance -- including several song-and-dance numbers -- enlivens what's basically comfort food in movie form, but sometimes comfort food is exactly what the doctor ordered.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46838</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directed by Julian Jarrold and co-written by Tim Firth ("Calendar Girls"), the movie is quite enjoyable, effortlessly well-done on every level, even moving at times, but relatively light weight.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060421-movies-review-boots,0,5699564.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is in the naughty-but-nice British tradition in which characters walk on the wild side but never seem to do anything else there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060420/REVIEWS/60419003/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't let the title trick you. The British comedy Kinky Boots is probably the most kinkless film featuring fetish wear ever to strut its stilettoed heels across the silver screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/267463_kinky21q.html</url>
         <critic>Winda Benedetti</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A humanist parable about how to be a good person, live a good life and make gallons of lemonade when life suddenly hands you lemons, it's predictably delightful and delightfully predictable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-kinky14apr14,0,2720367.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neatly scripted by Tim Firth and Geoff Deane, this sticks to the "Full Monty" formula of starchy working-class types learning to loosen up about sex, but Julian Jarrold's sincere, low-key direction erases any sense of artifice.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/29423_Kinky_Boots</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kinky Boots is diverting, but it's only worth shouting about thanks to Ejiofor' quietly subversive take on what has become a stock movie character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13131/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best reason to check the film out is Ejiofor's performance, which is packed with grace and wit and pathos.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0414/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chiwetel Ejiofor's performance alone makes it worth giving your "Full Monty" DVD a rest and heading out to Kinky Boots.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1146698715135300.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Trite? Sure. Obvious? And then some. But a lesson to be taken to heart nonetheless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A365983</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since ''Mannequin on the Move" has a flamboyant black man brought so much fabulousness to stiff white heterosexuals.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8152</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't think for a second that Hollywood has cornered the market on formula flicks. Ever since the prototypical success of "The Full Monty," those crafty Brits have been running their own mimeograph machine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060421.KINKY21/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An above-average entry in this niche genre, wherein groups of working-class people band together against adversity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/66990.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't worry. It just sounds like another bad Sharon Stone movie. Kinky Boots trips on its contrived plot, but this blend of trash and sass is a comfy fit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/7373736/rid/9579217/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A London drag queen and a bunch of Midlands working stiffs find common ground and, uh, mutual respect in Kinky Boots, a slick, cross-tracks Britcom whose stride is hampered by its desire not to offend.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;head=sundance&amp;nav=RSundance&amp;articleid=VE1117927975&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All it wants is to divert you for about 100 minutes and leave you with the glow of vicarious comradeship, as blue-collar blokes and drag queens pull together to save the day. Foot fetishists will drool.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/14/movies/14kink.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This English heart-warmer isn't all that kinky. It's actually quite sweet-spirited, as well as unswervingly formulaic.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sweet-tempered, mildly entertaining picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/14/kinky/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fact that this formulaically winsome movie, directed by British TV helmer Julian Jarrold, is based on product-line changes at a real Northamptonshire factory does little to freshen its approach.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1182917_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boots is unforgivably tame; only foot fetishists (or possibly Imelda Marcos) could get off on such desexualized, PG-13-rated fare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0615,singer,72853,20.html</url>
         <critic>Matt Singer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even if its premise weren't so achingly familiar, the film's bland humor and oddly conservative depiction of its central character, a flamboyant drag queen named Lola, would still make it seem like a museum piece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2740</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Really, the only thing kinky about this movie is its title.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/04/14/DDGA2I88EQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Julian Jarrold's cheerful, utterly predictable crowd-pleaser affirms that, according to many recent films out of Britain, there's a quirky interest to cure whatever ails you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/408852p-345871c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is so determinedly lightweight that it floats above the fray, stopping only for the occasional mild chuckle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.boots05may05,0,7355344.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The trouble with Kinky Boots is that director Julian Jarrold doesn't seem to know whether his movie would play better to young hipsters or the blue-haired old lady crowd.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=577911&amp;reviewId=20611</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ejiofor was a revelation in "Dirty Pretty Things" as a Nigerian doctor forced to live illegally in London. Though he's charismatic as the husky-voiced Simon, he never transcends the movie's pandering agenda.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1115742&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It would be nice to be able to report that Kinky Boots is a kick in the pants. But this conventional, manipulative British import feels like a re-soled pair of shoes that unquestionably have seen their day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-04-20-kinky-boots_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once you notice Ejiofor, you won't stop noticing--and Kinky Boots ensures that you will notice, thanks not only to the nature of his role, but also because there isn't much else here to get excited about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-05-18/film/film4.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kinky Boots doesn't seem to realize that its time came and went long, long ago.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47306</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I once said I'd watch Chiwetel Ejiofor act in any piece of disposable fluff, and now I have.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=577911&amp;reviewId=20884&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,822,428</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$77,529</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>9</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>