<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Kit Kittredge: An American Girl</name>
   <company>Picturehouse</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Valerie Tripp</author>
      <author>Ann Peacock</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Patricia Rozema</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Abigail Breslin</actor>
      <actor>Joan Cusack</actor>
      <actor>Glenne Headly</actor>
      <actor>Jane Krakowski</actor>
      <actor>Chris O&amp;#039;Donnell</actor>
      <actor>Julia Ormond</actor>
      <actor>Wallace Shawn</actor>
      <actor>Stanley Tucci</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 20, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>G</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Preteen girls – and not just those who are already American Girl fanatics – should be entranced. And why not? Not many movies for that audience are as respectful as is this one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0621/p25s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the 10 best American movies released so far this year, Kit Kittredge: An American Girl is the surprisingly satisfying first theatrical film inspired by a long-running series of historically themed dolls.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06202008/entertainment/movies/legend_of_the_doll_116288.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just about perfect for its target audience, and more than that. It has a great look, engaging performances, real substance and even a few whispers of political ideas, all surrounding the freshness and charm of Abigail Breslin, who was 11 when it was filmed.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/section?category=RT</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A smart, playful, informative pleasure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20210198,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anchored by a fine performance from Abigail Breslin, this wholesome, engaging entertainment offers something for viewers ages 7 to 107.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937460.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Lael Loewenstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Offers solid, kid-friendly storytelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=lGMhLd8J9yN72vT3khNh3ChxL1xQZgyhlTFXgjynY2h3s9ZHpTrd!1587555933&amp;&amp;rid=11282</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fun, fast-paced, educational entertainment that's fit for the whole family -- American boys included.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/kit-kittredge-american/review/293492</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Much as she did in "Little Miss Sunshine," Breslin imbues Kit with joy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/07/01/DDBQ11HL6S.DTL</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The period ambience, comforting yet urgent, is the best part of Kit Kittredge - that and Breslin, who never once gets actressy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10401</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoroughly satisfying and engaging children's picture that never forgets those kids probably didn't get to the theater by themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/589324.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A crime wave gives the heroine a mystery to solve and provides most of the comedy, but the film is stronger in its dramatic stretches.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33274_KIT_KITTREDGE_AN_AMERICAN_GIRL.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Kit’s world the absent father (a familiar theme from girls' novels including "Little Women" and "A Little Princess") is an epidemic, and the picture makes this the impetus for children's resourcefulness and emotional development.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/20/movies/20kitt.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not only fresh and unassuming, but a film that serves, very nicely, the severely underserved audience of young girls.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121391259991589875.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This can be strong stuff for kids, but the film's humanistic approach preaches tolerance and hope.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-kittredge20-2008jun20,0,3977138.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Ordona</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an unashamedly old-fashioned and richly visualized evocation of a time when values were key, trust in your neighbor complete, and a way of life that should be simple is made unfathomably complex because of economic hardship.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/369136_kit02q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the film starring Abigail Breslin as a resourceful 10-year-old is faithful to the Kit books, it's pokey where it should be perky.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080701_Review__Kit_Kittredge__An_American_Girl.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sure, this is marginal, but it's precisely in the margins that the movie excels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080703.wkit04rvt/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has its heart in the right place and its head shoved well down into a box of clichés.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/entertainment/story/694389.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This sweetly enjoyable family film stars the endearing Abigail Breslin as Kit. And, refreshingly, it's actually about something -- the Great Depression -- and tackles such serious issues as prejudice, poverty and homelessness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-19-kit-kittredge-american-girl_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strictly a kids' movie--brimming with easy-to-swallow life lessons.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-kit-kittredge/463272/content</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Based on several American Girl stories about a 1930s cub reporter in Cincinnati, this dull theatrical debut especially disappoints because I'm usually fond of square, sepia-toned, period-costumed kids' movies (like Fly Away Home) that go nowhere at the box office.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0825,kit-kittredge-as-american-as-overpriced-dolls,471277,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Roughly speaking, the characters in Kit Kittredge may be stereotypes, but they're stereotypes with soul. And they live in a very real place.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/06/20/kit_kittredge/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's certainly been a while since we've seen a movie this resolutely old-fashioned. But while the script feels a little stiff and moralistic at times, it's hard to fault a film with such an intelligent, good-hearted heroine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/20/2008-06-20_abigail_breslin_gives_relief_for_our_dep.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With all the good will in the world, I couldn't warm up to Kit Kittredge. The movie is like a 1930s or 1940s short about Americans pulling together, stretched out to feature length.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.kit02jul02,0,382082.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time it reaches an action-packed finale that's choreographed like an ancient Keystone Kops short, Kit Kittredge has cornered the market on bland.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/kit_kittredge_an_american_girl</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kit Kittredge is a dutiful bore. Still, I couldn't help but wonder if, in the face of all-out market collapse, it might serve a dual purpose as primer for kiddies on economic depression – because food stamps always taste better with a side order of spunk. Or is it pluck?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A639862</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director, Patricia Rozema, has a rare talent: She gets third-rate performances out of first-rate performers with almost startling efficiency. All are bland, some hardly exist at all, and as performance, the whole thing seems a waste.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145217&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$17,657,973</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$220,297</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>