<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Kurt Cobain About a Son</name>
   <company>Balcony Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>AJ Schnack</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Kurt Cobain</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 3, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating/>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everyone involved with the film brings their top talents to the fore, and the result is a touching, heartbreaking and an ultimately honest personal experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9403</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filmmaker AJ Schnack's hauntingly beautiful film is a bold and successful attempt to recover the human being who disappeared under the heavy mantle of "face and voice of a lost generation," and whose life has been increasingly overshadowed by his sensational early death in 1994.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/kurt-cobain-son/review/290692</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even without the oral history, this trippy exploration of Cobain's earthy habitations would be worth seeing as a "Koyaanisqatsi" for the Puget Sound area.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/335135_limited12.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No single film or book can dispel the cloud of enigma surrounding Kurt Cobain, but simply sitting in the dark and hearing him talk to you for 90 minutes, while the dreary gray-green beauty of his home state moves through your eyeballs and into your brain, goes a pretty long way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/03/15/btm_sxsw/index1.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a film exponentially more vivid and absorbing than the garden-variety rock-doc or biopic. "About a Son" is a must for anyone who still loves Cobain, or still has hope for cinematic portraiture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1135842&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About a Son is essentially a dead rock star talking about his life for an hour and a half, and—here, jacket-blurbers!—it's deeply moving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0740,dodero,77938,20.html</url>
         <critic>Camille Dodero</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About A Son may not let in anybody who doesn't already have one foot in Nirvana's doorway, but those people are invited in fully, to experience the contradictions and preoccupations of a man whose music defined his era.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/kurt_cobain_about_a_son</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Be advised that this is no ordinary music doc. There are no talking heads and no performance footage of Nirvana. In fact, there's no Nirvana music at all. Instead, Schnack gives us other artists' music that had an effect on the troubled rocker.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10052007/entertainment/movies/still_waters_grunge_deep.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lovely piece of filmmaking, a gripping, minimalist marriage of sound and image.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10734</url>
         <critic>Joan Anderman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a study in human behavior, describing how a self-confessed "emotional wreck," through accident and ambition, talent and temperament, became a star.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20071019_Kurt_Cobain__About_a_Son____.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing particularly revelatory about the interviews recorded over a two-month span, but there's an intimate quality that gives the impression you're listening to a private conversation, which, in a sense, you are.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-kurt5oct05,0,1578663.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some fans will find the approach (which avoids Nirvana music and perf footage) too arty and indirect; but others will welcome the specialized theatrical release and the subsequent DVD.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931629.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A true gift to fans of this important musician.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=6765</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Near the end, we hear Cobain reveal his disdain for adults who “can’t even pretend, or at least have enough courtesy for their children, to talk to one another civilly.” A painful and unexpected moment.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-kurt-cobain/281678/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only loosely connected to the story, the visuals quickly grow monotonous, and as the chronicle arrives at Cobain's late years of curdled fame and fortune, his bitterness and cynicism make even the narration hard to take.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32632_KURT_COBAIN_ABOUT_A_SON.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s hard to know who the audience might be for the documentary oddity Kurt Cobain About a Son, but I bet its subject, the guy who’s still being called on to entertain us even after his death, would have hated it.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/10/03/movies/03coba.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never penetrates Cobain's circumstances or character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/30/DD3ITKHLE.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Joel Selvin</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$82,718</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$15,700</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>