<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Lady Vengeance</name>
   <company>Tartan USA</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Seo-Gyeong Jeong</author>
      <author>Chan-wook Park</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Chan-wook Park</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>SouthKorea</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Yeong-ae Lee</actor>
      <actor>Min-sik Choi</actor>
      <actor>Su-hee Go</actor>
      <actor>Dal-su Oh</actor>
      <actor>Shi-hoo Kim</actor>
      <actor>Seung-Shin Lee</actor>
      <actor>Bu-seon Kim</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>112</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It concludes Park's trilogy on a dual note of circular tragedy and fragile hope, while working equally well as an introduction to his universe of retribution and repentance or as a stand-alone thriller with a darkly feminist twist.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46903&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike the previous two installments, Lady Vengeance generates on odd feeling: hope.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/23/DDGP9JI4OG1.DTL#flick2</url>
         <critic>G. Allen Johnson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Old Boy's" vivid star Choi Min-sik plays a terrible schoolteacher -- yet another damned soul in Park's inflammatory, inimitable movie inventory of hell on earth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1192908_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Park is one sick puppy, and I mean that in the very best sense of the phrase.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A380274</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady Vengeance is not for everyone. The violence, while less over-the-top and orgiastic than Park's two previous installments, is still hard and crackling. The sex is grim and graphic. And deadpan nihilism permeates the air.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=624472&amp;reviewId=20909</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Less bloody than its predecessors, Lady Vengeance wraps up with a killer (literally) finale that calls into question the killer instinct. It's one of the reasons Park's brutal films are so emotionally rewarding.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/412761p-348937c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Park is a visual virtuoso, with imaginative transitions and clever use of special effects wrapped around a sly, effective performance from Lee at the center of it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1150928716279780.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dense with pathos, poetry and humor, this is Park's finest work to date. His stomach-churning climax -- which depicts gruesome bloodshed without directly showing it -- simultaneously gratifies and indicts our most primitive instincts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/27/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What you get for your entertainment dollar in Lady Vengeance is Korean director Chan-wook Park's brilliantly orchestrated story of how Lee Geum-ja (Lee Young-ae ) got her groove back.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1111914&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chan-wook Park completes his "revenge trilogy" with this ravishing black comedy about a notorious child killer.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29375_LADY_VENGEANCE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brutal mystery that's more beautifully poetic than the previous entries but still just as captivating. From opening to closing credits, every image is photographed as if it were a painting; even those involving ferocious violence are wonderful to look at.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8838</url>
         <critic>Michael Ferraro</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady Vengeance contains violence (some extreme), but it is not an action film. It is deliberately paced, allowing the audience to have time to reflect upon what's happening. And the comedy is of the gallows variety.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/l/lady_vengeance.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It takes patience and industry to make sense of the first half, intestinal fortitude to deal with the second, and a little flexibility to make the transition from one to the other. But the whole process adds up to a fairly impressive two-stage thrill ride, like rafting through choppy waters, then plummeting over a waterfall into a dark and deadly pit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47877</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady Vengeance is more than half over before we discover the object of Geum-Ja's hatred: a kindergarten teacher named Mr. Baek. He's played by Choi Min-sik, the prisoner in "Old Boy," and here he's as tepid as he was heated in that film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060519.LADY19/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A comedy of evil and strange redemption, Lady Vengeance makes sure that we feel the pain, that we know what it's like to unreasonably suffer, because those are the rules of its mad, wounding, vengeful world.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060526-movies-review-lady,0,7293070.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Those last thirty minutes are worth the price of admission.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2782</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For most of Lady Vengeance, Park is playing with us. But the jokey atmosphere dissipates and the fun turns inside out in the movie's last act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8415</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As much as Lady Vengeance spins around its implacable protagonist like a rabid dog on a rope, the film becomes in its last, galling act an unlikely but stunning ensemble piece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0617,atkinson,72986,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mixes comedy and melodrama to a typically baroque degree. Like his "Oldboy" and "Sympathy for Mr. Vengeance," the film displays an audacious visual and narrative style, often sacrificing credibility and coherence along the way. But there is no denying its originality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001221700</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A wildly inventive, highly cinematic director's showcase that looks likely, at least in the West, to enthuse fans of Asian -- especially Korean -- genre movies more than general auds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927794?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you've seen either of the first two flicks in this outrageous series - "Oldboy" and "Sympathy for Mister Vengeance" - you know what's coming. Novices should prepare for mind-bending bloodshed and violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/67703.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If this is what qualifies, as some critics have suggested, as an artistic advance for Mr. Park, let us pray for a hasty retreat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13496/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A convoluted hodge-podge of time frames, subplots and bit player back stories.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/28/movies/28lady.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$211,667</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$4,500,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,850</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>