<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Lady in the Water</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>M. Night Shyamalan</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>M. Night Shyamalan</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Paul Giamatti</actor>
      <actor>Bryce Dallas Howard</actor>
      <actor>Bob Balaban</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Wright</actor>
      <actor>Sarita Choudhury</actor>
      <actor>Freddy Rodríguez</actor>
      <actor>Bill Irwin</actor>
      <actor>Jared Harris</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 21, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the ultimate goal is entertainment, then Lady in the Water enthusiastically rises to the task. In a movie laden with enough symbolism, shamanism and mythic lore to make Joseph Campbell dance a tribal jig, Shyamalan never forgets to have fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1110388&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a good chunk of Lady in the Water that is simply too well made and affectingly acted to dismiss as a mere exercise in arrogance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8693</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is much pleasure to be had watching a born storyteller juggle more balls than even he can carry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=11023</url>
         <critic>Ian Freer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shyamalan does project genuine menace and suspense into this mundane location, especially in nighttime scenes. But the magic that would transport you from reality into fantasy is missing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002839930</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The man has gifts -- but acting and, it's increasingly clear, storytelling aren't among them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1153346139321870.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You leave Lady thinking there are still voices in Shyamalan's head well worth a listen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/7514147/rid/10905053/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, this narf's a drag: she talks like a fortune cookie and doesn't really do anything. Still, the multicultural cast is fun, the images have a painterly beauty and there are some beguiling comic touches before the story sinks into a swamp of solemn metaphysical glop.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/13989047/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The character played by lead Paul Giamatti is a dead-on Shyamalan protagonist: emotionally distanced and something of a train wreck.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-07-20-lady-water-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to think of a deadlier shotgun marriage than Jacques Tourneur's poetry of absence and Spielbergian uplift, but Shyamalan has patented the combo, adding pretentious camera movements that are peculiarly his own--even the jokes are pretty solemn.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30033_LADY_IN_THE_WATER.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It lacks the simplicity and resonance of classic fairy tales: It's so muddled and belabored, it's hard to imagine the tykes ever staying awake long enough to hear how it all turned out.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=392443C99B4C9BA51EEB8D026D4ED6FB.prodapp12_ae_01?id=656398&amp;reviewId=21158</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady, like all of Shyamalan's movies, is a slick production with consistently interesting visuals... But the story is so convoluted and ultimately preposterous that you're almost embarrassed by the earnestness of the actors trying to carry it off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/436911p-367961c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has the strengths and weaknesses of a one-man show.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/07/21/DDGA8K223L1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's odd about Lady in the Water is that for all Shyamalan's histrionics, he's overcontrolled.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/17661/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shyamalan's most alienating and self-absorbed project to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1216516_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady in the Water boasts an eclectic cast - almost entirely squandered.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/special_packages/summer_movies/15082230.htm</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the more watchable films of the summer. A folly, true, but watchable.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/07/21/movies/21wate.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shockingly misconceived, poorly executed effort.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/50658</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I will hold against him (Shyamalan) that Lady in the Water isn't scary, that its own inner logic breaks down at countless points along the way, and that its ending is disappointingly literal and just plain stupid. Lady in the Water is, however, funny at times, even intentionally so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2146227#</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are moments of great beauty throughout (the film was lensed by Wong Kar-Wai cinematographer Christopher Doyle), and Shyamalan's heart is nowhere if not on his sleeve, but even these moments cannot steer Lady in the Water clear of its director's zealously over-earnest pretensions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A387873</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady in the Water feels very much like something its author made up as he went along; and, if it weren't so damn weird, it would most certainly put you right to sleep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/aquawoman/14063/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady doesn't work. Although he detonates a few terrific frissons involving the scrunt, the stabs at comedy are lurching and arrant. The spreading of tension from one character to many dilutes the mood. The would-be rapturous Spielbergian ending is on the wussy side.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1214952,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A ponderous, self-indulgent bedtime tale.  Awkwardly positioned, this gloomy gothic fantasy falls well short of horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931086?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is a rogue hunk of hooey.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060721-movies-review-water,0,4384242.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is sloppy filmmaking, and it's likely to wipe away whatever luster still remains to Shyamalan's reputation.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/l/lady_water.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a soggy swamp of nyah-nyah-nyah-nyah-nyahing, its only grace notes are Giamatti's fine, nuanced performance as Heep and Christopher Doyle's handsome cinematography.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=280130&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This isn't nitpicking. Every bit of the tale is as full of holes as a wool sweater at a moth convention, and Shyamalan telegraphs each potential surprise.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=656398&amp;reviewId=21141&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're not a fan of M. Night Shyamalan's convoluted, teasing thrillers, you'll find that getting into this movie is like cracking a puzzle in which the constructor keeps breaking his own rules or grabbing new ones from ultra-thin air.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.lady21jul21,0,7281716.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Challenges us to believe in the power of myth. But the big challenge here is surviving the tedium of Shyamalan's meandering inventiveness. What's supposed to be fanciful storytelling is really just audience punishment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/07/21/lady/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lady is more of an ensemble picture, and truly the Cove is the most ethnically diverse and community-minded apartment complex in the continental United States.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9183</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is something bizarrely compelling about the movie. It's slower than watching a train wreck but invokes that same level of disbelief.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-lady21jul21,0,7951723.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It comes off as tedious, pretentious, self-indulgent, talky and so garbled it might have been improvised by the actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/278291_lady21q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I suspect audiences will see Shyamalan's portentous doodle for what it is - the height of arrogance and a bad night out at the movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0721/p11s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Crazy as this might sound, it turns out that self-indulgent ramblings designed to put your children to sleep are pretty much the opposite of art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060721.LADY21/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A charmless, unscary, fatuous and largely incoherent fairy tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/lady_is_a_tramp_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This cloying piece of claptrap sets a high-water mark for pomposity, condescension, false profundity and true turgidity -- no small accomplishment for the man whose last two features were the deadly duo "Signs" and "The Village."</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's as if on some semiconscious level, Shyamalan, who I do not doubt is a serious and self-serious pop-creative original, is calling his own success into question and daring his audience to gulp down larger and spikier clusters of manure, just to see if they will. Or he's lost his mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0629,atkinson,73889,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$42,285,169</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$75,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$18,044,396</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,235</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>