<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>La Mujer de Mi Hermano</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jaime Bayly</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ricardo de Montreuil</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>ArgentinaMexicoPeruUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Bárbara Mori</actor>
      <actor>Christian Meier</actor>
      <actor>Manolo Cardona</actor>
      <actor>Gaby Espino</actor>
      <actor>Beto Cuevas</actor>
      <actor>Bruno Bichir</actor>
      <actor>Angélica Aragón</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 14, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>89</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>As pared down, stylish and deceptively simple as the stark glass and concrete block inhabited by two of its main characters, La Mujer de Mi Hermano (My Brother's Wife) is an adultery drama that skips the big life lessons in favor of observing the mysteries of human interdependency and social behavior.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-mujer14apr14,0,3113580.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie feels more like a thriller than a drama; it's paced like a thriller, building to a murder that never happens, exciting passions that are never unleashed, waiting for a crime to occur. The only crimes, however, are of the heart. Meanwhile, the movie knows exactly what it's doing, and does exactly what it intends, without making one false move.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118778&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some movies sell and you don't know why. With La Mujer de mi Hermano, a big-screen romantic drama with the aura of a nicely steamed telenovela, you know why: because the three stars look good in plush white bathrobes, that's why.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060414-movies-review-mujer,0,2549233.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story's no great shakes here. However, the power of this film lies in the sexual tension boiling between the characters and that makes for a great date movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8882</url>
         <critic>Eric Campos</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its gender-bending, La Mujer De Mi Hermano's primary appeal is Mori's stunning beauty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47308</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mexican soap opera star Bárbara Mori may be the most beautiful woman to grace an American screen this year, and female viewers may feel similarly about her male co-stars Christian Meier and Manolo Cardona. But a telenovela with three gorgeous actors is still a telenovela.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/408852p-345871c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the lowbrow story, this is supposed to be tasteful; expect modest nudity, swelling strings, and plenty of water imagery.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29613_MUJER_DE_MI_HERMANO.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You could dismiss this swankily shot Latin American trifle as an upscale soap opera, but that would be an insult to soap operas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1184974_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the great things about international cinema is the way it can remind us of our common humanity. For instance, it's good to know that beautiful, rich people are selfish and miserable the world over. That's one of the few positives a viewer can take away from a film such as La Mujer de Mi Hermano.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1146700531168940.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only La Mujer de mi Hermano had a dollop of humor and at least one character worth rooting for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.mujer05may05,0,7683020.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The characters never come across as anything more than self-interested parties. It’s hard to have a rooting interest in any of their fates, and even less in the outcome of this movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A355942</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>La Mujer lumbers along, trapped in a long-faced score that appears to have been borrowed from a thriller, and without a smidgen of the saving irony that might have made of it a decent screwball comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13131/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie bubbles with incest, adultery, religion and homosexuality -- steamy themes that incite the cast to fits of enthusiastic overemoting.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/14/movies/14muje.html</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Soapy melodrama and a small-screen cast undermine the first-time director's efforts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930010?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Part of La Mujer's problem is its pace: Everything happens so slowly, and so meaningfully, that we see it coming for miles. Also, none of the three principals is remotely likable until the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0615,levine,72798,20.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It never comes close to touching the audience's heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=586373&amp;reviewId=20528</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Essentially a telenovela with cinematic pretensions, La Mujer de Mi Hermano (My Brother's Wife) is a vapid slab of soap depicting a love triangle among three remarkably uninteresting characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002237728</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An oddly unsexy melodrama in which every supposedly shocking revelation (rape, incest, homosexuality, pedophilia) is treated with the same blithe shrug of recognition. It's numbing, especially with the film's deadly serious mood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8699</url>
         <critic>Justine Elias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is astonishingly simple-minded, depicting characters who obediently perform their assigned roles as adulterers, cuckolds, etc.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060413/REVIEWS/60403009/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Repressed desire! A sultry soap-opera star! Incest! Gay politics! "La Mujer de Mi Hermano" has it all. Now if it only had a decent plot.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/04/14/DDGA2I88EO1.DTL#flick4</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most of the movie's plot becomes obvious before you even meet the brother, 10 minutes into it. Even the sex scenes turn out to be tasteful and tame. You've seen hotter stuff on Oxygen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/66996.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,808,241</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$1,018,750</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>206</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>