<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Land of the Dead</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>George A. Romero</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>George A. Romero</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>CanadaFranceUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Simon Baker</actor>
      <actor>John Leguizamo</actor>
      <actor>Asia Argento</actor>
      <actor>Robert Joy</actor>
      <actor>Dennis Hopper</actor>
      <actor>Eugene Clark</actor>
      <actor>Jennifer Baxter</actor>
      <actor>Boyd Banks</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 24, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>93</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The latest installment could well be Romero's masterpiece. Taking full advantage of state-of-the-art makeup and visual effects, he has a more vivid canvas at his disposal, not to mention two decades worth of pent-up observations about American society.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000964865</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero's newest is a horror movie for hard-core fans of the gory and the gruesome and a classic genre film for genre aficionados.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050623-movies-review-dead,0,149615.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the enormous pleasures of genre filmmaking is watching great directors push against form and predictability, as Mr. Romero does brilliantly in Land of the Dead. One thing is for sure: You won't go home hungry.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/06/24/movies/24rome.html?</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land of the Dead is Romero's long-awaited masterpiece, a slyly suspenseful and droll thrill-ride that expounds on both the highbrow and the chewed-off-brow concepts of his previous trilogy, then flippantly dismisses the cheap scare tactics of the control-pad generation's gimmicky genre knockoffs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2184</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>George A. Romero shows 'em how it's done in Land of the Dead, resurrecting his legendary franchise with top-flight visuals, terrific genre smarts and tantalizing layers of implication.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927425?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero easily commands an enormous cast, a plethora of action sequences and a cornucopia of special effects -- some of them very gory -- and creates one darkly dazzling image after another that allows Land of the Dead to emerge without any nudging whatsoever as a bleakly humorous, hard-charging allegory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-dead24jun24,0,1795920.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the ghouls evolve toward humanity and the humans toward ghouldom, we can appreciate Romero for using horror to show us How We Live Now, and How We're Living Dead now, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2121383/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The social commentary isn't subtle, but Romero delivers the goods so effectively that many won't even notice.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/229750_dead24q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land of the Dead is huge. It's Romero doing what he does best: using zombies to create a lowbrow social parable. It shows up junk like "Resident Evil: Apocalypse" for the brainless pap it is. And it's got something that even the best previous "Dead" films have lacked: good acting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/111952100819160.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The satire is headline-fresh, the action scenes keep pace with summer blockbusters, and no one shoots an evisceration with as much skill.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8652</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inventive suspense, spiky characters, outrageous horror and wicked satire. Welcome back, George - you've been away too long.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=11097</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hopper, unsurprisingly, devours scenery like he's already dead and loving it, but for once his penchant for overacting is overshadowed by the real stars of Romero's world: They're dead, they're all messed up, but it's great to finally have them back in town.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A275699</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land is pure entertainment and superbly well done. It is not as scary as it is gross, and its grossness is so outrageously graphic (hint: don't seat yourself next to a zombie at your next barbecue) that it is laugh-out-loud funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/06-24-2005/entertainment/col/story/322022p-275208c.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not Credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brains! Brains! Why can't they make a zombie movie with brains? This is one. Romero has given us, as well as the zombies, a lot to chew on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/48733.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fairly solid fun, though, without breaking any new ground, just as January's remake of "Assault on Precinct 13" was.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-06-23-land-of-the-dead_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oddly enough, though Land of the Dead is more clever and grand than Romero's early classics, it is not as haunting.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=350193&amp;reviewId=18359</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero finds still new and entertaining ways for unspeakably disgusting things to happen to the zombies and their victims.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050623/REVIEWS/50614001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The master is back, and there's no shortage of exploding brain matter -- or fun -- to be had in the theaters this weekend.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/06/24/DDG7TDD9AN1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land of the Dead is a horror flick, but not a screamy one -- the booming soundtrack pumps up the drama, and the gore induces squirms, but zombies more titillate than anything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050624/DEAD24/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Brad Wheeler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero isn't a subtle filmmaker -- the sociopolitical underpinnings of his DEAD films have always been brutally clear -- but LAND is alive with subtle touches.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46053</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero's fourth entry, turns out to be his most conventional as an action thriller--though it's every bit as gory as the others and more clearly class-conscious.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28162_LAND_OF_THE_DEAD.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not startling or frightening enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/l/land_dead.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A perfectly adequate horror romp, but it's hard to imagine anyone remembering it five years from now.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miami.com/mld/miamiherald/entertainment/movies/11963264.htm</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Romero's fourth-grade dialogue doesn't help matters, but anyone seeking out the latest achievements in cranial ruptures, spewing-blood gouts, and ground-beef spillage need look no further.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0526,atkindead,65379,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the Star Wars movies have taught us anything, it's that waiting 20 years for a new sequel by a guy named George can lead to disappointment.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land of the Dead is fairly intense. Intensely gory and violent, that is, as has come to be expected from the genre. It's just not very frightening. Not half as frightening as, say, last year's "Dawn of the Dead."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/23/AR2005062300657.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Land falls well short of the greatness of Romero’s previous zombie efforts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7647</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Looks and feels like someone else's better-made schlock.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7266</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Land of the Dead there are virtually no good parts. The movie is listless and uninspired.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1078199_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too bad the plot held no surprises and the acting no revelations. No actor could be said to stand out and the movie never acquires much tension or momentum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/23/AR2005062302082.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$20,700,082</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$10,221,705</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,249</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>