<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Little Ashes</name>
   <company>Regent Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Philippa Goslett</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paul Morrison</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Javier Beltrán</actor>
      <actor>Robert Pattinson</actor>
      <actor>Matthew McNulty</actor>
      <actor>Marina Gatell</actor>
      <actor>Arly Jover</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 8, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>112</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Little Ashes is absorbing but not compelling. Most of its action is inward.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090506/REVIEWS/905069989</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ashes makes no claims to be an entirely accurate biopic; it's a speculative, impressionistic portrait without a lot of dramatic force or psychological depth. But it's an elegantly designed film that fascinates as often as it frustrates.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-little-ashes-1003969163.story</url>
         <critic>Stephen Farber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Spanish actress Marina Gatell is exotic and engaging as a young writer drawn to Lorca and puzzled why he is not drawn to her in return.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090626__Little_Ashes___Dal_and_Lorca_in_love.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone interested in hearing the artist's heart-to-hearts properly translated is encouraged to seek out Leonard Cohen's flamenco serenade, "Take This Waltz."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/little-ashes/article1146814/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beltrn, for his part, makes a solidly believable Garca Lorca. The problem is with the man with whom he's obsessed. In Pattinson's performance, we never see what Garca Lorca sees in Dal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/little-ashes,1151404.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Little Ashes succumbs to the dreaded Masterpiece Theater syndrome as a talky historical drama weighed down by self-importance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1080268.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A painfully sincere study in creative passion, sexual ardor and political zeal that embalms a mad and exuberant historical moment within the talky, balky conventions of period-costumed highbrow soap opera.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/05/08/movies/08ashe.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A typically bombastic lives-of-the-artists production made even more stilted by having all the actors (including the Spanish ones) speak accented English.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-05-06/film/little-ashes-is-pattinson-s-attempt-to-expand-past-twilight-fan-base/</url>
         <critic>Melissa Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you'd like to know about the famously eccentric psyche of surrealist artist Salvador Dali, whom Pattinson plays, you're better off consulting written biographies. Little Ashes does nothing to illuminate the iconic Spanish artist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-05-07-little-ashes_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A trifling historical fantasy, gossip wrapped in gossamer, beautiful to watch but it takes only a light wind to leave the story in tatters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-ashes8-2009may08,0,1417818.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Paul Morrison ("Wondrous Oblivion") nicely re-creates the period, but puts too much weight on the sexual relationship as determining the men's artistic courses.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/05/07/MV3817ER6Q.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie could use less romantic boo-hoo-hoo and more Bunuel: It's engaging whenever Bunuel acts as ringleader or troublemaker, even when he's blustery and piggish.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-ae.mo.ashes07aug07,0,2617107.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I can't imagine what Dali or Buñuel would have made of such bourgeois sentimentality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20276710,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film’s biggest problem, beyond the overheated melodrama and paper-thin period trappings, is that the trio's fictionalized dalliances diminish their real art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/little-ashes,27708/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story and performances (save for Matthew McNulty’s angry Luis Buñuel) are paint-by-numbers, with social upheaval and sexual adventurism as dramatic as an after-dinner mint.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/05/08/2009-05-08_short_takes_rudo_y_cursi_little_ashes_julia_outrage_brothers_at_war.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For much of its running time, Little Ashes wavers between the polite, stuffy style of a "Masterpiece Theater" production and the more pointed agenda of gay indie cinema, with real Spanish locations classing up the otherwise low-budget affair. Acting is stagy and hindered by thick Spanish accents.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940203.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem is that both Philippa Goslett's script and Paul Morrison's direction lack the stylistic craziness - the sense of real, lunatic danger - a project like this desperately needs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/05/22/dali_lorca_buuel___for_teens/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Paul Morrison forfeits any meaningful statement about art for a pedestrian coming-out story, based in part on Dali's unreliable, self-aggrandizing memoirs.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34361_LITTLE_ASHES.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The revelation of Little Ashes turns out to be none of the leading men but rather Gatell, a riveting actress cast as the girlfriend who is mystified by Lorca’s lack of sexual interest in her.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A818416</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exceedingly silly historical fantasy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05082009/entertainment/movies/gay_romp_is_dali_folly_168177.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$480,912</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$73,394</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>12</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>