<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Lost City, The</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>G. Cabrera Infante</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Andy Garcia</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Andy Garcia</actor>
      <actor>Dustin Hoffman</actor>
      <actor>Tomas Milian</actor>
      <actor>Bill Murray</actor>
      <actor>Jsu Garcia</actor>
      <actor>Inés Sastre</actor>
      <actor>Enrique Murciano</actor>
      <actor>Nestor Carbonell</actor>
      <actor>Victor Rivers</actor>
      <actor>Steven Bauer</actor>
      <actor>Dominik García-Lorido</actor>
      <actor>Juan Fernández</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>143</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Throbbing with music, seething with anger and romance, The Lost City is a film that breaks your heart, bewilders, alienates and ravishes you by turns.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060512-movies-review-city,0,1984664.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie evokes that long-ago world carefully and with a certain poetry; it was shot in the Dominican Republic. There is a lot of music, much of it from the period and performed by the same musicians or their successors.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060511/REVIEWS/60508007/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some of the tropes of The Lost City are ineffective. What does work is the sense of loss. The late Cuban novelist and screenwriter G. Cabrera Infante finds a brilliant device in the love affair between Fico and Aurora (Ines Sastre), his sister-in-law, in that Aurora in some way becomes Cuba.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106232&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What keeps the film watchable, aside from the vibrant musical numbers in the nightclub, is Garcia's obvious love for the Cuba of his ancestors, of his dreams. A lot goes wrong in this overlong movie, but it has a human touch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0428/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching The Lost City is like falling into a delirious dream on a marathon train ride only to be roused every 15 minutes by a conductor punching your ticket or barking out the next stop.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.lost23jun23,0,7993440.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A handsome production but one that struggles to integrate its various elements -- cabaret-society glamour, intellectual fervor, family drama, impossible romance and droll humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001436151</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A handsomely produced, deeply passionate, but seriously flawed historical epic whose reach far exceeds its grasp. Somewhere inside this overlong, sometimes engaging, often tedious affair, there may be a solid, 100-minute movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928086?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When an intensely emotional scene calls for the voice to break, call in Andy Garcia. He does the best voice-breaking, half-choked sob of anguish in the business, and he does it a lot in Lost City, his well-meaning directorial debut.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/412761p-348937c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Falls far short of the sweep, complexity and passion it seeks.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=596190&amp;reviewId=20662</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In its groggy way The Lost City holds your attention. Incoherent, but splendidly panoramic and drenched in wonderful Cuban music, it has the texture of a vivid, intoxicating dream that seems to mean something until you wake up and feel it slipping away. All that remains are feelings and impressions connected by a mood.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/28/movies/28lost.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In an era when so many films are cynical, cash-grabbing mechanisms of global corporate culture, no more and no less, it is frustrating to come across a work such as this, in which the grasp-exceeding reach and reckless vision of its creators become the biggest drawbacks rather than the film's greatest assets.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-lostcity28apr28,0,4569345.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bill Murray plays the secondary role of a nameless American gag writer brimming with one-liners about the absurdity of Cuban life, Dustin Hoffman has a cameo as kvetching gangster Meyer Lansky.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46902&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the color and lively music, it's an overlong, messy labor of love built on a sense of personal betrayal that rings hollow.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/270756_lostcity19q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even though the movie is made with an abundance of heart, it's sad to report that the final result has only a weak pulse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A375507</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story may be scattered and sagging and the picture may have little emotional impact -- certainly nothing to justify the epic running time -- but Garcia at least succeeds in making Havana in the 1950s seem like a vibrant, special place. He doesn't exactly make the audience care, but he does make the audience understand why he cares, and that's something.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/05/12/DDG8PIPC391.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Garcia seems to be aping the "Godfather" movies and Warren Beatty's "Reds," but the movie's gracefulness is limited to its handling of the music (some of which Garcia wrote).</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29804_LOST_CITY.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Compelling in fits and starts, actor-director Andy Garcia's The Lost City possesses grand aspirations but troublesome execution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13307/</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the filmmaker's feel for his Cuban heritage is bone-deep, it's a glazed and dolorous movie - a depressed epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1195051_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Garcia might have thought he was making a Cuban "Casablanca," but his big, empty spectacle amounts to less than a hill of beans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/48049</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The lower orders seem to have been left out of The Lost City -- there just aren't any poor characters -- which for a movie about a workers' revolution seems downright slipshod.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060616.LOST16/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Garcia's tale bemoans the loss of easy wealth for a precious few. Poor people are absolutely absent; Garcia and Infante seem to have thought that peasant revolutions happen for no particular reason--or at least no reason the moneyed 1 percent should have to worry about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0617,atkinson,73003,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes there's a fine line between a labor of love and a vanity project, and The Lost City, Andy Garcia's heartfelt - but hackneyed and interminable - love letter to his native Cuba, repeatedly crosses it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/67689.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Lost City is Andy Garcia's ballad to Havana during the Cuban revolution. You'll have to forgive the penthouse view, though -- it's the only one Garcia can seem to find.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8354</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,484,186</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$9,600,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$191,560</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>18</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>dustin hoffman</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>dustin hoffman</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>