<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Made of Honor</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures (Sony)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Adam Sztykiel</author>
      <author>Harry Elfont</author>
      <author>Deborah Kaplan</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paul Weiland</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Patrick Dempsey</actor>
      <actor>Michelle Monaghan</actor>
      <actor>Kevin McKidd</actor>
      <actor>Kathleen Quinlan</actor>
      <actor>Sydney Pollack</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 2, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>101</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A nice cookie-cutter comedy, no more and no less, but Dempsey, with his relaxed charm, and Monaghan, with her soft and peachy sensual spark, rise to the challenge of making friendship look like the wellspring of true love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20196645,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has something a bit edgier in mind than the usual, soft-focused wedding bell high jinks. 
For the most part, that's exactly what it delivers -- an amusing, smartly cast romantic comedy told from a guy's perspective.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=dPVFLYCKdBwH0ThGW2hVWy2R2b1RLhnpG3T73LjjhH20jnf35PFS!569075428&amp;&amp;rid=11028</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As unpalatable as stale wedding cake.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/honor/review/293102</url>
         <critic>Erin Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is just middling. A clever line here and there, a debonair Dempsey wink, a cute Monaghan nod, and another Bill and Monica reference to tie things all together.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080502_McDreamy_s_go-to_guy_for_this_rom-com.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Patrick Dempsey and Michelle Monaghan make an agreeable pair in this above-average comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33085_MADE_OF_HONOR.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Made of Honor has some funny moments, and it keeps your attention, but it's certainly not worth rushing out to the multiplex and paying top dollar for. Catch it on TV on a lazy afternoon with little else to do.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-05-01-made-of-honor_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Made of Honor retains enough sweetness to satisfy the cotton-candy addicts. For true believers in fairy tales, no romantic fantasy is too extravagant if the heroine is a sweetheart. The rest of us can sit there and roll our eyes.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/05/02/movies/02hono.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What do you call it when someone pulls a gender reversal on someone else's movie? If that movie is "My Best Friend's Wedding," you call it Made Of Honor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/made_of_honor</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're in the mood for seeing a Lothario humbled by true love, you're in luck. You may wish, however, that Made of Honor had given its stars something more of interest to occupy their time. And ours.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-made2-2008may02,0,87351.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A prefabricated example of shoddy workmanship.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/m/made_honor.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only surprise to me about this movie is that there no jokes about kilts – a serious omission in an otherwise entirely predictable farce.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0502/p25s11-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dempsey also needs some fashion advice. As always, he sports his trademark five o'clock shadow in every scene (which in itself is excessive). But with Dempsey at age 42, it's beginning to make his face look more sinister than sexy, less Dr. McDreamy, more Richard Nixon.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/361414_made02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like a shopworn wedding gown disguised with a new sash, Made of Honor feels recycled from top to bottom. That's because it's essentially a gender-swapped version of "My Best Friend's Wedding."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936989.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Lael Loewenstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A strong opening, bursting with wit and vigour, gives way to a predictable, patronising and immensely lazy second half. Could have been so much more.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135232</url>
         <critic>Anna Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no energy, no spark, in Made of Honor. Even its clichés -- including a dashing rescue on horseback -- are trotted out with bland indifference.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/05/02/made_of_honor/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cinematic equivalent of a cookie-cutter wedding, Made of Honor ultimately feels a little depressing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/05/02/2008-05-02_made_of_honor_is_wedding_tale_with_a_fam.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Made of Honor should come with a bar code and a Wal-Mart display - this isn't a movie, it's a commodity. The generic brand is the romantic comedy, and the manufacturer's material of choice is recycled plastic, smoothly glued together to assure the consumer that the purchase is risk-free and thoroughly predictable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080502.wmade02/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Made of Honor, the leads are beautiful and everyone else is a freak. So where does that leave us?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9984</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dempsey's pleasant enough, but he hasn't yet learned how to play against a mediocre script's obviousness. Monaghan has, which is gratifying.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-made-of/397011/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its worst (and this is where Made of Honor comes in), it can leave you with a bad taste, not just in your mouth but in your soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1143191&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Paul Weiland and the three (!) screenwriters it took to boil down thousands of bad movies into 101 minutes haven't provided this one with a single original thought; it should only entertain those still getting adjusted to the idea of talkies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0818,made-of-honor,427349,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What this really comes down to is the film's central lie. Made of Honor pins its hopes on a character who acts utterly without honor, and on an actor who has only two settings – sensitive or smarmy. The smarm wins.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid:617505</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a story that should have been, at the absolute most, 20 minutes long.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/05/01/DD3M10E22F.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't waste your money.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/516641.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's something old, it's something new, it's something borrowed and it's something that blows.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05022008/entertainment/movies/maid_man_109014.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$46,012,734</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$40,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$14,756,850</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,729</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>