<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Madea&amp;#039;s Family Reunion</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Tyler Perry</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Tyler Perry</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Lynn Whitfield</actor>
      <actor>Tyler Perry</actor>
      <actor>Blair Underwood</actor>
      <actor>Boris Kodjoe</actor>
      <actor>Maya Angelou</actor>
      <actor>Jenifer Lewis</actor>
      <actor>Keke Palmer</actor>
      <actor>Rochelle Aytes</actor>
      <actor>Cicely Tyson</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 24, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>107</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Let's not sell Tyler Perry short. As the vinegar-witted Madea, he's a drag performer of testy charm, but in his overlit patchwork way he's also making the most primal women's pictures since Joan Crawford flexed her shoulder pads.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1168926_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Madea's a riot, but what makes this richer, more textured follow-up to "Diary of a Mad Black Woman" so fascinating is the way Perry - a first-time director adapting his own hit play - shifts on a dime from a silly fart joke scene to one of intense, Sirkian melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film-reviews/12754/new-film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too long and its tone is disconcertingly uneven, but Perry never betrays or condescends to his characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46737</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gussied up for the big time, Perry now is aiming himself squarely at a mainstream, middle-class female audience -- with some sops for their dates.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060224-movies-review-madea,0,1439678.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Chris Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry's soap opera story lines are awful, with their nobly suffering sistas, gorgeous do-right men, and shamelessly materialistic dream endings. But the movie's message of gospel joy and racial pride couldn't be more sincere, and Perry gives an impeccable comic performance as the title character.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29340_MADEAS_FAMILY_REUNION.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry's vaudevillian shamelessness and indifference to committee-approved taste are energizing and frequently jaw-dropping.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,ridley,72451,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Madea's Family Reunion represents an advance on Diary, if only because it dials down Madea's shtick (she no longer waves a gun around) and irons out some of those awkward tonal transitions. The chance that Perry's followers will leave disappointed is approximately 0 percent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45843</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tyler Perry offers another blithely unbalanced mix of low comedy, sudsy sentiment and spiritual uplift in Madea's Family Reunion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929775?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry makes sure villains get their comeuppance, while heroines get big, frilly weddings - with God, and an imperious Maya Angelou - presiding over it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-25-2006/entertainment/movies/story/394413p-334409c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both Ms. Angelou and Ms. Tyson deliver powerful, touching messages. Just as they're sinking in, the film turns into an unabashed chick flick with a painfully gaudy wedding that includes live angels hanging on wires from the ceiling.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/25/movies/25made.html</url>
         <critic>Anita Gates</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perry is a playwright, and his dialogue here is usually entertaining.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2006/02/25/reunion_brings_together_melodrama_bawdy_comedy/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neither good nor so-bad-it's-good, Perry's odd oeuvre has an allure all its own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002075057</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reunion is an awkward compound of paradoxical tones and ideas... But one shouldn't underestimate Perry's ability to make such contradictions work and get away with the most wretched excess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-madea27feb27,0,4845966.story</url>
         <critic>Gene Seymour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When you've got Maya Angelou and Cicely Tyson in the kitchen, laying on the sophomoric laughs is just plain stupid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A341195</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too bad the story is so predictable and the big wedding scene, in which women dressed as angels dangle from the church ceiling strumming harps, is cornier than an Orville Redenbacher factory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/60342.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A disappointing sequel to the far funnier "Diary of a Mad Black Woman."</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/27/DDG56HDTEQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All the while Madea's wit, which is refreshing on the stage, feels spurious and often misfires.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8747</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ends up on screen is confused storytelling that tries to solve too many social and family problems, sends mixed messages and, even worse, makes you laugh during parts when it's trying to be dead serious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060224.MADEA24/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$63,257,940</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$10,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$30,030,661</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,194</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>