<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Melinda and Melinda</name>
   <company>Fox Searchlight Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Woody Allen</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Woody Allen</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Chiwetel Ejiofor</actor>
      <actor>Will Ferrell</actor>
      <actor>Jonny Lee Miller</actor>
      <actor>Radha Mitchell</actor>
      <actor>Ama Peet</actor>
      <actor>Chloë Sevigny</actor>
      <actor>Wallace Shawn</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 18, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>100</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smart, satisfying and compact but so modest in scale that only true-blue fans will sense - immediately - that it's Woody Allen's best outing in many years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-03-17-melinda-and-melinda_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In its complexity and wit, this is one of his (Allen's) best recent films.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050322/REVIEWS/50309007</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen gives us at least half a classic comedy - more than we usually get at the movies these days - while having some elegant fun with an idea that has intrigued poets and smart alecks through the ages: the interchangeability of comedy and tragedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050322-movies-review-mw-melinda.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It has great performances, snappy one-liners and a likeably tricksy structure, all wrapped up in an affirmative antidote to life’s daunting complexities. Welcome back, Woody.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=10272</url>
         <critic>Emma Cochrane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Full of entertaining vignettes that eventually make a happy mockery, as they're meant to do, of the tragedy vs. comedy dialectic.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Woody's back on solid ground with his first memorable pic of the new millennium.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000810033</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Radha Mitchell stirs memories of complex Allen heroines from Annie Hall on down, even if the action is dispersed via a larger ensemble cast which he currently favors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117924939?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Deborah Young</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With Melinda and Melinda he's (Allen) not just going through the motions. He's saying the game isn't over before you laugh till it hurts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6169786?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is closer to an Allen comeback than anything else he's made recently. Maybe he'll achieve it with his next movie, "Match Point," due this year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0318/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Melinda is no masterpiece, it’s also an Allen film that requires almost zero special pleading.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2051</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More accomplished, adventurous and original. Instead of Allen's usual investigation into the nature of existence, this new film looks at the way stories are created, particularly comedies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/03/23/DDGHTBSLLD1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As he (Allen) interweaves two versions of the Melinda story, one meant to be bathed in pathos, the other sprinkled with whimsy, it becomes apparent that his notions of comedy and tragedy do not quite correspond either to scholarly dogma or to everyday usage.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/03/18/movies/18meli.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's emotionally more alive than anything Allen has done since "Sweet and Lowdown," in 1999. I was absorbed in it, and I liked parts of it. And I wish to God it were better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050321crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best reason to see Melinda and Melinda is Radha Mitchell, who has her grabbiest role (or two of them) since she broke through with "High Art."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1038437_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>tTere are two things going for Melinda and Melinda: Woody's not in it and Radha Mitchell is.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/217078_melinda23q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's breezy enough, though, as a romantic comedy. And the stakes at risk in it are more grown-up and weighty than those in most Hollywood fare. Like Allen himself, you could do worse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1111489428296680.xml</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever you think of Melinda and Melinda, you have to admire Woody Allen for this: After years of criticism that he didn't use people of color in films, he's written two interracial romances.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=273531&amp;reviewId=17733&amp;startDate=04%2F15%2F2005</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dialogue rings tinny in the ear, as if enunciated in the phony arc of a stage light.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=273531&amp;reviewId=17614</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a fascinating premise; it's the execution that's sloppy.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/m/melinda.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen's best effort since 1999's "Sweet and Lowdown," but that's not saying a lot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050323/MELINDA23/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But Allen can still write a good joke and there are some here. Not enough to say he has returned to form, but enough to remind you of what that form was.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-18-2005/entertainment/col/story/291117p-248982c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen has assembled an attractive cast and given most of them clichés to inhabit. He has also stinted on inventiveness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1037658,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Neither comedy nor tragedy, the movie is closest to genteel soap opera.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0511,hoberman2,62099,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A medium-boil good time, mostly for its humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A62989-2005Mar24.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's merely all right--very high-concept and on its way to interesting, but never there.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/issues/2005-03-31/film/film2.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beautifully shot by the great Vilmos Zsigmond, the movie is watchable, sporadically amusing and ultimately frustrating, because Allen is capable of so much more, but doesn't appear interested -- or willing -- to push himself any longer.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=273531&amp;reviewId=17608</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From its austere opening credits to its screechy women, this 35th film by Woody Allen looks and sounds like a dozen other Allen movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3333&amp;Sumbit.x=48&amp;Sumbit.y=9</url>
         <critic>Brendan Bernhard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When are we going to get a generation of actors who will finally decline to succumb to The Woody Mystique, and refuse to accept a proffered role without first deciding whether the entire damn project is worthwhile?</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/nymetro/movies/reviews/11525/</url>
         <critic>Ken Tucker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Doesn't entirely work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7154</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since Edward Norton kicked his own butt in Fight Club has the screen witnessed such a brutal self-drubbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/41183.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all very well to say that laughter and tears are just a heartbeat apart, but both variations on Melinda's story bear the unmistakable mark of Allen's morose sensibilities.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=45995</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Australian actress Radha Mitchell is the only reason to see the movie: She has an extraordinary open face and a way of mixing dreaminess with sudden bursts of lacerating emotion that recalls Jessica Lange.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2115011/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even these actors -- who, in other pictures, are often wonderful in distinctive ways -- don't seem like themselves: It's as if they've been pulverized and pressed into convenient actor shapes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/03/18/melinda/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Allen's view of what's "deeply real" feels ever more deeply bogus as the movie progresses, his trademark wit having calcified into pastiche and unintended self-parody.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-melinda23mar23,2,7105656.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The grave story is leaden, the comic story isn't funny, and the comparison--the rivalry--between the two modes is never crystallized.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20050418&amp;s=kauffmann041805</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's disconcerting to see Ferrell, a master of macho psychosis, adopt the stop-and-go dithering of Woody Allen-style neurosis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.melinda08apr08,1,3994556.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is mainly a narrative brain-teaser like "Memento" or "The Jacket"; merely keeping up with the game requires so much energy that the thinness of the material becomes fully apparent only toward the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chireader.com/movies/archives/2005/0305/050325.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Give Woody Allen credit for ambition. Failing at one movie wasn't enough. Nearly anyone can do that; it happens all the time. He's chosen to fail at two simultaneously.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A58609-2005Mar22.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A second-rate comedy and a third-rate drama, Melinda And Melinda gives viewers two unsatisfying movies in one. The only genuine tragedy here involves a once-brilliant comedy writer plunging further into a seemingly permanent artistic freefall.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review_pop.php?review_id=8307</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>These days, Allen's pictures are more like snuff films, in which the viewer must suffer both gifted actors committing screen hara-kiri and a once-brilliant filmmaker soldiering on with his long, bullheaded decline.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A264379</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,826,280</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$74,238</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>woody allen</oscar_winning_director>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>