<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Memoirs of a Geisha</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robin Swicord</author>
      <author>Doug Wright</author>
      <author>Arthur Golden</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rob Marshall</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ziyi Zhang</actor>
      <actor>Ken Watanabe</actor>
      <actor>Michelle Yeoh</actor>
      <actor>Kôji Yakusho</actor>
      <actor>Kaori Momoi</actor>
      <actor>Youki Kudoh</actor>
      <actor>Li Gong</actor>
      <actor>Kenneth Tsang</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 9, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>144</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story is so compelling and the movie is such a pleasure to the eyes and ears.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/252235_geisha16q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here is a film about Japan made by Americans, shot mostly in the U.S. and, of course, in English. Once you accept these compromises in the name of international filmmaking, none is a real deterrent to enjoying this lush period film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001525055</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From a filmmaking point of view, this is a work that the old Hollywood moguls themselves would have been proud to present.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117928913?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no doubting that Memoirs of a Geisha is a lush motion picture, and it has much to recommend it, but this will not go down as one of the great screen romances of the 2000s.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/m/memoirs_geisha.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie may be set in prewar Japan, but it's pure 1940s Hollywood. There's costume, pageantry, melodrama, the feeling of a sweeping epic without the bother of too much accuracy, equal doses of heartbreak and uplift.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/12-09-2005/front/story/373295p-317187c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any doubts about three Chinese actresses speaking English with Japanese accents vanish in the face of their deeply felt performances and the world Marshall conjures with magical finesse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6169909?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't be misled by the chopsticks and cherry blossoms: Memoirs of a Geisha, for all its exotic casting and locale, is our friend "Cinderella" in a kimono.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=491985&amp;reviewId=19751&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Marshall's Memoirs achieves something few other high-profile literary adaptations do: Rather than simply inspiring us to hunt down the source material, it actually stands alone as a film, rich in drama and star-crossed romance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2426</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spanning two decades and a momentous war, Memoirs of a Geisha displays all the pomp and grandeur of an epic, but you wouldn't call it sweeping.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-geisha9dec09,0,553090.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not a great movie, or even a particularly good one, but it's spectacular. No expense has been spared. The technical crew reads like a roll call of Oscar-night regulars.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/06/03/film-foundas.php</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed, the film is altogether too much like Sayuri: trying to overwhelm with surface beauty and unspoken emotion, it never hits deeper than the skin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1135214715197100.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film version of Memoirs of a Geisha is very like a geisha itself: a thing of exquisitely refined surfaces beneath which beats an ordinary heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7803</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I object to the movie not on sociological grounds but because I suspect a real geisha house floated on currents deeper and more subtle than the broad melodrama on display here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20051215/REVIEWS/51213001/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Memoirs of a Geisha is like a sumptuous piece of silk: stunning yet ultimately flimsy. You wish it were more like a kimono, richly woven, multilayered and more substantial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-12-08-memoirs-geisha_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simultaneously gorgeous and forgettable, sentimental and prurient.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46523</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Full of falling rain, fluttering silk, John Williams's music and whispery voiceover, Memoirs of a Geisha is one long oxymoronic exercise in attempting to show delicacy through overkill.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051209/GEISHA09/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film comes to life whenever the cartoonishly vindictive Gong throws a tantrum, but she played virtually the same role in Zhang Yimou's "Shanghai Triad," which presented a far more compelling rationale for her star fits. Without her, this expensive piece of backlot pageantry turns vivid history into an ossified tchotchke.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/43278</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Memoirs of a Geisha is everything you'd expect it to be: beautiful, mesmerizing, tasteful, Japanese. It's just not very hot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1105435&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The international Asian stars gamely tackle their English-language roles, aided by superior costumes, makeup, and set design. But despite all the hothouse intrigue, the film lacks passion.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29058_MEMOIRS_OF_A_GEISHA.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A beautiful, exotic and well-acted cultural hybrid, but it’s never as moving as it ought to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=10276</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Memoirs of a Geisha was never primed to be a film that burns down the house.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.geisha23dec23,1,3344898.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since "Snow Falling on Cedars" have I seen so pedigreed a lit-pic sit there like such an inert teapot, available only to be admired for its mysterious, ineffable Asian teapotness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1138534_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beautiful geishas flit and whoosh through the equally beautiful scenery. Their kimonos are artworks-in-motion. So why is the film so boring? It could be because director Rob Marshall is so transfixed by all the ritualistic hoo-ha that he never brings the story down to earth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/1209/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Marshall can't rescue the film from its embarrassing screenplay or its awkward Chinese-Japanese-Hollywood culture klatch, but Memoirs of a Geisha is one of those bad Hollywood films that by virtue of their production values nonetheless afford a few dividends, in this case, fabulous clothes and three eminently watchable female leads.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/12/09/movies/09geis.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no life, no juice, in the picture. Instead of tempting you into submission, it merely drugs you. It's surprising that a filmmaker who gave us such a lively debut, "Chicago," could slap us with a picture as dull and worthy as this one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/12/09/geisha/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's based on a novel, but you'd guess it came from a coffee-table book. Marvelous design, photography and costuming mark this period piece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/59223.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Too labored and cliched to incite passion in an audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/12/09/DDGEFG4LO31.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oh, what awful voices -- clumsy words as well as cheesy accents -- come out of the actors' mouths! Though I wanted to appreciate the human story, and the lavish spectacle, I couldn't get past the clangorous echoes of Charlie Chan.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lush, lovely snooze-fest.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=491985&amp;reviewId=19719</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well, we're not in "Chicago" anymore, or even its soundstage approximation, but that hasn't stopped Oscar-nominated director Rob Marshall from fashioning another epic spectacle out of two squabbling women in (a sort-of) show business.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A320903</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Rob Marshall, as he did in "Chicago," plays the movie as though it's all an embellished memory inside the head of geisha Sayuri (Ziyi Zhang), but why would she remember everyone speaking in choppy English?</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Colleen Atwood's costumes are the best a film adaptation of a popular book can buy. They rustle like nobody's business. The film itself is equal parts silk and polyester.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501216-movies-review-geisha,0,5751308.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somehow the movie that Rob Marshall has made from Golden's novel is a snooze. How did he and the screenwriter, Robin Swicord, let their subject get away from them?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?051219crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Trying too hard to grab our attention, he (Marshall) loses it. The art of the geisha prizes subtlety, stillness, grace. Why doesn't this movie?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/10414363/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It skips lightly over the surface of its rich material, more preoccupied with making pretty pictures than dipping below the surface so that you can experience the world through the eyes of its traumatized, yet increasingly savvy, heroine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2131913/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Swaddled in the posh vulgarity that passes for awards-season elegance, Memoirs is deluxe orientalist kitsch, a would-be cross between "Showgirls" and "Raise the Red Lantern," too dumb to cause offense though falling short of the oblivious abandon that could have vaulted it into high camp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0549,lim,70711,20.html</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a grand-looking, grandly empty pageant.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=491985&amp;reviewId=19726</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To its credit, the film's costume design is stunning. But unless you have a kimono fetish, there's no reason to pay a good dollar (or a yen, for that matter) on this junk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8315</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$57,010,853</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$85,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$682,504</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>