<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Miss Potter</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company / MGM</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Richard Maltby Jr.</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Chris Noonan</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Renée Zellweger</actor>
      <actor>Ewan McGregor</actor>
      <actor>Emily Watson</actor>
      <actor>Barbara Flynn</actor>
      <actor>Bill Paterson</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 29, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>In every way, Miss Potter is a very beautiful thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/01/05/DDG4HNC9SF1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's first-class entertainment for bookish lads and lasses of all ages - and for those who never have or never will crack a paperback's spine. And it might inspire today's nascent artists to open up their sketch-pads as well as their hearts and minds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.miss09mar09,0,2357333.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In addition to being a beloved author and illustrator, Beatrix is also presented as an early feminist and environmentalist who took control of her literary empire and saved vast acres of luscious farmland from greedy developers, eventually bequeathing property to Britain's National Trust.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0105/p11s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In many ways, a magical little movie in its own right, and a thoroughly pleasant experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/298430_potter05q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its lack of pretensions, Miss Potter is that rare breed of cinematic animal: a movie whose entire goal is to entertain and perhaps apply a gentle touch to the heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/m/miss_potter.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a lovely film for the holiday season, as well as afterward, and is reminiscent of "Finding Neverland," without the darker undercurrents.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-12-28-miss-potter_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Miss Potter, right to the end, is the definition of a "nice" movie, and that makes it a genuine oddball in a universe of increasingly distressed and uncivilized pop culture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20007965,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A very gentle-spirited picture, but it's not a self-consciously precious one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/12/29/potter/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director, Chris Noonan, doesn't play to our sentiments, he just lets them naturally evolve--even the animation of a few of her (Potter's) drawings doesn't feel especially forced. The result is an honorable and curiously winning film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1568455-4,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss/Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Endearing without being especially engaging.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284985&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe Miss Potter will be best appreciated on video when you will intuitively know when to turn it off. On the other hand, Potter's pastel illustrations, which often come to life to her and to the camera's eye, deserve the larger canvas. Tough call.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/485736p-408919c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At 92 minutes, the film has the economy of a Potter story, but not the shapeliness or the zip.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=787904&amp;reviewId=22046</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its tasteful palette and twee charm, Miss Potter is the china plate of movies, a Peter Rabbit collectible entirely suitable for mounting on the nursery wall.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070112.wpotter12/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A scenic, well-behaved account of Potter's life and times.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070105-movies-review-potter,0,7045976.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Miss Potter hardly deserves ridicule. It's sweet with lovely Lake District vistas and a heartfelt endorsement of land conservation. It will certainly play well with older audiences and the kind of adolescent girls who draw faces in their O's.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/26289/index.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pitched awkwardly -- neither for children nor cool young adults -- it's very sweet, very nice and just the thing for a girlie matinée with mum and nan.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=17079</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem confronting writer Richard Maltby Jr. and director Chris Noonan is that Potter lived a fairly uneventful life once you remove her success as an author.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=FLPF9j7JBcyTXC6StYhK0dS2Q3lypFClK2Y89lYW0jYNLfb1pkTS!-336171278&amp;&amp;rid=8562</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Renee Zellweger, in another Blighty role, struggles to make Beatrix credible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/awardcentral_review/VE1117932337.html?nav=reviews07&amp;categoryid=2352&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By most accounts, Potter was a serious workaholic monomaniacally devoted to the purity of her vision. Undaunted, Noonan and Maltby are determined to squeeze her life into a run-of-the-mill romance in which love heals all wounds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0652,taylor,75398,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is at once a flagrant piece of kitsch and an unexpectedly affecting story about an individual overcoming personal tragedy and brutally restrictive circumstances by talent and force of will.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-potter29dec29,0,376281.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Potter" periodically brings Zellweger's charming drawings to life in elegantly animated sequences that are as delightful and lyrical as the rest of the film is stilted and clumsy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/57101</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The immediate problem with making a movie based on Potter's life is that it doesn't seem to have been very interesting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9037</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This attractive, superficial stab at biography, with Renée Zellweger in the title role, is more concerned with a lonely woman's quest for acceptance and love than with an author's worldly achievements.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This much sweetness and light in a movie is all very well. But there's a reason that recipes for cake and cookies call for a pinch of salt. In Miss Potter, there is only a grain or two -- not enough to dilute the sugary overload. The film is the cinematic equivalent of a delicate English tea cake whose substance is buried under too many layers of icing.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/01/05/movies/05pott.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The twee romance was too much for me, though the movie's first half follows in fascinating detail the innovations Warne introduced to popularize illustrated picture books for children.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30920_MISS_POTTER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zellweger is certainly likable as Beatrix, but as an upper-class English lady of a century ago, she enunciates her words as if sucking a lemon -- you almost start to wonder if you've stumbled into a satire of "Masterpiece Theatre."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1124664&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zellweger dusts off her Bridget Jones accent - and a constellation of annoying vocal and facial tics - for Miss Potter, an unrelentingly mediocre, TV-movieish biopic of beloved children's author Beatrix Potter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01052007/entertainment/movies/potter_putters_then_sputters_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Miss Potter is, in the end, a confection, a trip through the imagination on gossamer wings. Enchanting, perhaps, but a long, long way from meaningful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A430981</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Miss Potter is a grave disappointment, because it never listens out for that note. It is a soft, woolly film about a smart, unsentimental woman who did constant battle with her frustrations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/articles/070122crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,005,605</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$30,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,653</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>ewan mcgregor</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>