<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Miss Pettigrew Lives for a Day</name>
   <company>Focus Features</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Magee</author>
      <author>Simon Beaufoy</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Bharat Nalluri</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Frances McDorm</actor>
      <actor>Amy Adams</actor>
      <actor>Ciaran Hinds</actor>
      <actor>Shirley Henderson</actor>
      <actor>Lee Pace</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 7, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frothy and exuberantly entertaining - in part because of the sexual innuendoes - it's the best romantic comedy so far this year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/03/07/DDO2VDT1L.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adams shines brightly, reinforcing the image she projected in Junebug and enhanced in Enchanted and Charlie Wilson's War. At this time of the year, it's tough to find a more diverting way to spend 90 minutes in a multiplex.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/m/miss_pettigrew.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Based on the 1938 novel by Winifred Watson, it's a deluxe romance that most of the time plays like farce.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0307/p12s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an unusual and engaging romantic comedy because it's mostly about how these women ready each other for real love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.pettigrew07mar07,0,3539320.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching McDormand navigate that transformation is the kind of thing that can keep your hope in movies, and in actors, alive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/03/07/miss_pettigrew/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sustains itself through terrific forward momentum and two glorious star turns by gifted actresses Frances McDormand and Amy Adams.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=J6r2HKvbG2YwccnKqSTVfnYNGcGJkSbL7m1nKrqnV1dlmQh3TcyJ!-401086537&amp;&amp;rid=10744</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Style is a tricky, elusive thing, and this film doesn’t so much have it as strive for it, constantly. But something in Watson’s story endures: The wish-fulfillment truly satisfies. And with the war clouds gathering by story’s end, the fairy tale acquires a bittersweet edge, nicely cutting all that whipped cream.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-miss-pettigrew/326510/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Looks and sounds great, and is at its best when it isn't trying too hard to have fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/miss-pettigrew-lives/review/291862</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A good farce is hard to find. Particularly one that holds up for the entirety of the story and keeps us engrossed, while smiling. Miss Pettigrew Lives for a Day is a particularly effective and cheeky example.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-03-06-miss-pettigrew_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only thing missing from this winsome, madcap throwback set in London on the eve of World War II is an actual Brit in the title role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/445394.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A jubilee for McDormand and jolly good fun for most everyone else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080306_McDormand_sparkles_in_Miss_Pettigrew.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plays like a breeze and ends before we know it. In the current state of cinema, all we can hope for is one like this per year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10833</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bharat Nalluri directs with a light touch and a great eye for costumes and sets, which are gorgeous enough to make up for any contrivances in the plot. It's pure romantic fantasy, and you won't believe it for a minute. But it's fun to watch Miss Pettigrew and Miss Lafosse live for a couple of hours.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-pettigrew7mar07,0,6460726.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's flaws are nothing compared with the pleasures it offers, chiefly in its unapologetic pursuit of old-fashioned sweetness and romance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1145032&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>How light is this movie? So buoyant that even an air raid warning, signaling that this whole world is about to crumble under the blitz, can’t dampen its giddy spirits.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/03/07/movies/07pett.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>McDormand's performance slowly builds a solid integrity, and contrasts well with Adams' more flamboyant turn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936353.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is lovely to look at -- so overflowing with lavish furniture, jewelry and interiors that it's almost like a visit to Paris' Musée des Arts Décoratifs. If you're a fan of such things, "Pettigrew" is worth seeing solely for its sets.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/354002_miss07q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's left to the ideally cast McDormand to keep everything on track and, as expected, she weathers every tonal change with competence, confidence and a perfectly stiff upper lip.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/03/07/2008-03-07_amy_adams_overdoes_it_in_miss_pettigrew_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adams, of course, is a peach. Her sparkle requires only minor character adjustment and twinkle recharging from her recent triumph as the old-fashioned modern heroine in "Enchanted."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20182341,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In trying to recapture the spirit of classic '30s screwball comedies, the film too often mistakes manic energy for wit, and it ends on a note of gloppy sentimentality that wouldn't have held water in Old Hollywood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/miss_pettigrew_lives_for_a_day</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although McDormand's performance is consistently focused -- one would expect no less from the actress -- the movie itself can't settle on whether Miss Pettigrew is Mary Poppins minus the sugar spoonful or just plain Carrie Nation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4440/miss-pettigrew-lives-for-a-day.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes Watson's novel a delight is its guilelessly homoerotic subtext. By downplaying that, the movie argues the case for Watson's innocent sensuality--and against its own worldly update.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0810,354607,354607,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This was shot at the legendary Ealing Studios, but I hesitate to call it a British comedy: its two stars are American, it currently has no UK release date, and its innocuous naughtiness seems pitched at grandmothers who watch BBC America.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32851_MISS_PETTIGREW_LIVES_FOR_A_DAY.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I adore Frances McDor mand, but she's seriously miscast  in a title role Emma Thompson could play in her sleep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03072008/entertainment/movies/ms__mcdormand_misses_as_pettigrew_some_100746.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The comedic success of this pair of dramatic archetypes, the radiant flibbertigibbet and the gray, lumpen elder spinster, in a lightweight bit of piffle such as this is a testament to both Adams' and McDormand's smarts. It's tough to play dumb when you're not and even more difficult to dial down your own innate brilliance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A598628</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's polished-looking, yet dull.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2008/03/07/its_polished_looking_yet_dull/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At least Miss Pettigrew Lives for a Day has the good grace to go wrong quickly, you don't have to sit there squirming with doubt.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120485307946918309.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$12,313,694</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$2,490,942</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>535</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>