<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Mister Lonely</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Harmony Korine</author>
      <author>Avi Korine</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Harmony Korine</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKFranceIrelandUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Diego Luna</actor>
      <actor>Samantha Morton</actor>
      <actor>Denis Lavant</actor>
      <actor>James Fox</actor>
      <actor>Melita Morgan</actor>
      <actor>Anita Pallenberg</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 2, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>112</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is damn near a masterpiece. Let’s hope we don’t have to wait so long to see what Korine will do next.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10840</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Korine's latest film, Mister Lonely, is no different, but this film has a sweetness that has rarely, if ever, been present in his previous work.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/363261_mister16q.html</url>
         <critic>Travis Nichols</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What to make of it all? Hard to say. Just to take in the fact that its soundtrack is made up of music by both J. Spaceman and Sun City Girls is to understand that this is a picture that's divided against itself in a way that's perhaps too hermetic to be comprehended.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4548/mister-lonely.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Korine is finding his way toward artistic greatness by searching his soul. It's possible that the man in the mirror is him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11278</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mister Lonely, self-enclosed though it may be, nonetheless demonstrates that Mr. Korine, who showed his ability to shock and repel in earlier films, also has the power to touch, to unsettle and to charm. This is undoubtedly a small movie, but it's also more than that: it's a small, imperfect world.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/05/02/movies/02lone.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What engages us is Korine's revolutionary way of telling stories. It's as though he's downloading his dreams directly onto the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1144919&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film may be Korine's most accessible as a director, featuring characters, images, and situations that are stirring and unforgettable – even if they don't add up to a complete narrative or visual whole.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A631283</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like so many lovely cinematic dreams, Mister Lonely inevitably descends into nightmare, with an unsettlingly grim conclusion that, again, seems more imagistic than idea-driven.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-mister-lonely/434895/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not all of the movie works - in fact, huge portions don't - but there are enough striking moments to make a lasting impact. How ironic: In this fairy-tale of arrested development, Korine has created his most mature movie yet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/05/02/2008-05-02_short_takes_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it's full of arresting, indelible images, Mr. Lonely remains mostly on the level of abstraction. You get it but you don't always feel it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-lonely9-2008may09,0,5046357.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Less outre than "Gummo" and "Julien Donkey-Boy," Korine's most lavishly produced pic to date begins as a sweet-tempered tale of social misfits-turned-celebrity impersonators, but falls short of its ambition to say something meaningful about the obsessive nature of celebrity culture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117933877&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'm glad Korine has pulled himself together, but the film is pretty ramshackle, full of obvious group improvisations that fail to spark and an overdose of bathos.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/46460/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Co-written with his brother Avi, Mister Lonely is startlingly straightforward compared to his earlier work. But, like that work, it stands or falls on each single, self-contained scene.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0818,mister-lonely-ha,427331,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Decidedly loopy and nonlinear, Mister Lonely is precious and artsy, but there are moments when Korine's, er, unique vision brings something bold and beautiful to the table.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080509_Mister_Lonely__.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a work of entertainment, as a cohesive narrative and as an artistic whole, there's no way to call it anything but an on-balance average effort. Yet there's nothing remotely average about the movie's warm spirit, its imaginative and arresting cinematography or its handful of unique, brilliant scenes and shrewd, bizarre performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/05/22/DDDS10QBQK.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As in Korine's other movies, characterization is often just amplified weirdness.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33198_MISTER_LONELY.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An odd, desperate film, lost in its own audacity, and yet there are passages of surreal beauty and preposterous invention that I have to admire. The film doesn't work, and indeed seems to have no clear idea of what its job is, and yet (sigh) there is the temptation to forgive its trespasses simply because it is utterly, if pointlessly, original.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080529/REVIEWS/805290302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has its moments of wonder and beauty, but the film is obscure by design, and meant to appeal to those who favor the alternative canon of directing greats: the one that includes the likes of Alejandro Jodorowsky, David Lynch, Crispin Glover, John Cassavetes, Claire Denis, Abel Ferrara, and Vincent Gallo.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/mister_lonely</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is really little more than an array of sometimes imaginative images.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/mister-lonely/review/293331</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some films, like some people, wear their artsy pretensions on their sleeve, and there really isn't much going on beneath – it's just a posturing armband wrapped around a plain arm. Welcome, then, to the emptiness of Mister Lonely, a movie that goes to extraordinary lengths to say ordinary things.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080529.wlonely30/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Occasionally there is a striking image or a moment of wounded sweetness, but mainly the film provides ample proof that it's possible to be bizarre and boring at the same time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05022008/entertainment/movies/mister_lonely_109021.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>None of the faux icons comes close to being a character. Instead, they are contrasted with a group of nuns who skydive without parachutes. Could this possibly be a metaphor for Korine's filmmaking? It certainly goes splat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20196672,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$165,831</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$16,769</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>