<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Mist, The</name>
   <company>MGM</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Frank Darabont</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Frank Darabont</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Thomas Jane</actor>
      <actor>Marcia Gay Harden</actor>
      <actor>Andre Braugher</actor>
      <actor>Laurie Holden</actor>
      <actor>Toby Jones</actor>
      <actor>William Sadler</actor>
      <actor>Frances Sternhagen</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey DeMunn</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 21, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>127</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Good and creepy, The Mist comes from a Stephen King novella and is more the shape, size and quality of the recent “1408,” likewise taken from a King story, than anything in the persistently fashionable charnel house inhabited by the “Saw” and “Hostel” franchises.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-mist/254942/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a horror film SHOULD be - dark, tense, and punctuated by just enough gore to keep the viewer's flinch reflex intact.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/m/mist.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What is surprising is how he (Darabont) rebounds from his weak, awkwardly compressed opening to produce one of the scariest King films since Stanley Kubrick's "The Shining."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_mist</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a grim modern parable to be read into the dangerous effects of the gospel-preaching local crazy lady Mrs. Carmody (brilliantly played by a hellfire Marcia Gay Harden) on a congregation of the fearful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20160213,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the parlance of the kids today, the movie totally goes there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/reviews/</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Criminally overlooked in the States, this is one of the best horror movies of the last few years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135642</url>
         <critic>Tom Ambrose</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I think this one of the first King movies to legitimately give me the creeps.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10426</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it's riveting throughout, The Mist is a bit bloated.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/21/DDNNTFLFC.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best, The Mist just wants to make you jump.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=985810&amp;reviewId=22780&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a B-movie with A-list aspirations, and it's at its best when it's not trying to be something it isn't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/314524.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Darabont doesn't match the sly cultural commentary of "The Host," a recent Korean import that also revamped the giant-monster genre, but his grocery-store survival drama, dominated by Marcia Gay Harden as a shrill fundamentalist, serves as a crude but effective allegory for post-9/11 America.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32482_MIST.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The scenes that really work are the ones that take place outside the supermarket, in the beginning and at the end of the film. In fact, the "Twilight Zone"-inspired ending nearly makes up for all that comes before.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/340455_mist21q.html</url>
         <critic>Andy Spletzer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike King, Darabont ends this story with a drop kick to the cerebellum, a change from the original that shocks the viewer and leave little doubt that Darabont thinks we're all headed to hell in a hand basket.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A560656</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More thought-provoking than frightening. Its stubbornly cynical attitude makes it worth watching, more than the monsters or the impenetrable mist (which looks spewed from a fog machine) engulfing a small town in Maine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-11-20-the-mist_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has a monster problem -- the more you see of them, the less scary they are -- most of the characters are standard-issue types, and Harden seriously overdoes the pious psycho bit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/mist/review/290414</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This one aims for bleak and hits it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4268/the-mist.html</url>
         <critic>Eric Alt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More political allegory than horror movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1138125&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Mist is itself a supermarket of B-movie essentials, handsomely stocked with bad science, stupid behavior, chewable lines of dialogue, religious fruitcakes, and a fine display of monsters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/11/26/071126crci_cinema_lane?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Much nastier and less genteel than his best-known Stephen King adaptations ("The Shawshank Redemption," "The Green Mile"), Frank Darabont's screw-loose doomsday thriller works better as a gross-out B-movie than as a psychological portrait of mankind under siege, marred by one-note characterizations and a tone that veers wildly between snarky and hysterical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935387.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Less horrific than it is horribly didactic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=10200&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you have seen ads or trailers suggesting that horrible things pounce on people, and they make you think you want to see this movie, you will be correct. It is a competently made Horrible Things Pouncing on People Movie. If you think Frank Darabont has equaled the "Shawshank" and "Green Mile" track record, you will be sadly mistaken.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071120/REVIEWS/711200306</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Until the director Frank Darabont decides that he’s saying something important instead of making a nifty horror movie, The Mist isn’t half bad.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/21/movies/21mist.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The brutally ironic ending, I might add, won't make anybody very happy about having chosen The Mist for their evening's entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/21/2007-11-21_the_mist_based_on_stephen_king_story_is_.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A pretentious left-wing monster movie with about 15 minutes of alarming creatures and a whole lot of bickering, is a pre-9/11 story which Stephen King wrote eons ago. It operates in the post-9/11 era about as well as a Studebaker at the Daytona 500.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11212007/entertainment/movies/the_mist_630424.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Mist contains nary a dollop of wit and irony. As adapted and directed by Frank Darabont, there's no ambiguity either.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.mist21nov21,0,6134339.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Mist doesn't provoke further thought; it provokes active annoyance at being punished in the service of a pulp morality tale with pretensions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9985</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wouldn't say this is laugh-out-loud risible, but there are definitely moments. Still, you might want to consider sitting through the uneven thing just to get to the ending, because that's quite something. You may love it, you may hate it, but forget it you won't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071122.wmist23/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A derivative horror picture that somehow rises to the level of a primal scream. The premise is simple, by which I mean both easy to understand and feeble-minded.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/41278/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lumbering and depressing movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0747,wilson,78410,20.html</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$25,593,755</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$13,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$12,861,800</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,423</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>