<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Mongol</name>
   <company>Picturehouse</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sergei Bodrov</author>
      <author>Arif Aliyev</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sergei Bodrov</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Germany</origin>
      <origin>Kazakhstan</origin>
      <origin>Russia</origin>
      <origin>Mongolia</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tadanobu Asano</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 6, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>120</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mongol is a throwback to a more respectable tradition. The largeness of its scope arises naturally from the material, not the budget. The movie earns its stature.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0607/p25s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This Central Asia-set historical epic from Russian helmer Sergei Bodrov ("Nomad") boasts breathtaking landscapes, dazzling cinematography, bloody battles and unique traditions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2478&amp;reviewid=VE1117934756&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Alissa Simon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mongol -- or, as I prefer to think of it, "Genghis Khan: The Early Years" -- is a big, ponderous epic, its beautifully composed landscape shots punctuated by thundering hooves and bloody, slow-motion battle sequences.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/06/movies/06mong.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I don't know the Mongolian word for panache, but Mongol's got plenty of it. The battle scenes are as notable for their clarity as their intensity; we can follow the strategies, get a sense of who's losing and who's winning. The physical production is sumptuous.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121271272126950681.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, we're about a third of the way through the great Khan's life; he hasn't even begun to take down the cities of Cathay or spread his seed. That suggests two sequels. I, for one, can't wait.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1113089&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mongol is quality escapism: an exotic saga that compels, moves and envelops us with its grand and captivating story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-12-mongol_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a visual spectacle, it is all but overwhelming, putting to shame some of the recent historical epics from Hollywood. If it has a flaw, and it does, it is expressed succinctly by the wife of its hero: "All Mongols do is kill and steal."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080619/REVIEWS/944262138/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mongol is great cinema, great fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080620_Genghis_Khan__the_early_years__Part_1_of_a_fierce__fun_epic.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proves eye-opening in two ways: Sweeping, bloody battles will make your orbs pop, and you'll re-evaluate this supposedly “uncivilized” man who unified quarrelsome Central Asian tribes to create one of the largest empires in history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/entertainment/story/686975.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The casting also works. As the Khan, Japanese actor Tadanobu Asano ("Zatoichi") is all effortless charisma, and Chinese actor Honglei Sun (as his best friend-turned-enemy) and Mongolian actress Khulan Chuluun (as his faithful wife, Borte) are just as effective.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/367684_mongol20q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Quite grand, quite exotic, David Lean-style epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20204732,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Full of stunning views of China, Mongolia and Kazakhstan and showing an unexpected side of Genghis Kahn, Mongol feels like an old-fashioned epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-mongol6-2008jun06,0,65614.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Last year's Academy Award nominee from Kazakhstan for Best Foreign Film, Mongol is purportedly the first in a multi-film saga on the wrath of Khan; as such, it's probably the last thing you'd expect--great fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0823,mongol,458814,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its breathtaking landscapes, bloody battles, bitter betrayals and an aching love story, Mongol is a sumptuously crafted epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135609</url>
         <critic>Will Lawrence</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In general the film is so impressive that we can't leave the theater without wanting more.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/19/DDH7115QHE.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even at the movie's most ridiculous (and Mongol is not without its ridiculous moments), this is a picture you laugh with more than laugh at.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8626</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a violent, romantic, beautifully shot and performed film -- with brutal battle scenes and charisma-bomb performances by Asano as the future Khan and Honglei Sun as a rival chieftain and brother-in-arms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/06/review_mongol_rides_the_range.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oliver Stone tried encapsulating Alexander's life into one movie, only to discover the task was impossible. Bodrov knows better, using Mongol -- the first of an intended trilogy -- to center on Genghis Khan's formative years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/583854.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>My only problem with Mongol is that--how often in life do you get to write this sentence?---Genghis Khan is a little too nice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2193043/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As an epic action movie, Mongol is satisfying enough. Think "Braveheart." Think "300." Just don't think too much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080605.wmongol06/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason McBride</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While rich in ethnographic detail, the film ultimately recalls nothing more than pulp fictions like Robert E. Howard’s "Conan the Barbarian," which validate their worship of ubermensch-ian brawn by way of sad tales of childhood victimization.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/mongol/review/292307</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A grandly kitschy rendering of Genghis Khan's early years.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-mongol/463113/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Every performer is tough and charismatic, especially Honglei Sun, who, as Jamukha, gives so many neck-cracks, guttural howls and conspiratorial smiles he's like a Chinese Marlon Brando.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/06/2008-06-06_short_takes_more_movies_out_this_week-1.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mongol really isn't worth leaving your yurt for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06062008/entertainment/movies/sweet_mongolia__how_genghis_got_his_hord_114158.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sergei Bodrov's Mongol relates the story of Genghis Khan's early years in a plodding, uninspired fashion that doesn't bode well for the next two entries in a planned trilogy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=p8YLLPTDpBhx8prv32B2GBSQLvnD8pCfzB1nKK3qTxt91By22gvZ!1702622283&amp;&amp;rid=11240</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time the film's abrupt conclusion arrives, you realize you've been watching a love story and not, as some might hope, "The Lord of the Rings: The Asian Edition."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A637770</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inert, inept epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11066</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$5,705,761</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$135,326</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>