<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Monster House</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Animation</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dan Harmon</author>
      <author>Rob Schrab</author>
      <author>Pamela Pettler</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Gil Kenan</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Steve Buscemi</actor>
      <actor>Nick Cannon</actor>
      <actor>Maggie Gyllenhaal</actor>
      <actor>Jon Heder</actor>
      <actor>Kevin James</actor>
      <actor>Jason Lee</actor>
      <actor>Sam Lerner</actor>
      <actor>Spencer Locke</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 21, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kenan directs with a zingy sense of kids, comedy, fright, and visual perspective. But the movie also shimmers and shakes in all its motion-capture animated beauty with the slyly deep sensibilities of executive producer Robert Zemeckis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1216691_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kenan never loses sight of the wonderment that children (and adults) experience when the inanimate becomes animate. Anthropomorphism is basic to the art of animation. So is a good story, and Kenan has that, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0721/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most imaginative and delightful computer-animated movie of recent years outside of the Pixar brand, Monster House is a Halloween ghost story by way of monster-movie adventure.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/278297_monster21q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Monster House makes its intentions clear: It wants to wrap you in a thick, warm blanket of 1980s nostalgia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1153351551121590.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the best movies of the year, and a great accomplishment for Messrs. Harmon and Schrab. Maybe now we’ll get a feature length "Robot Bastard" movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9184</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smaller kids might find the movie too intense at times, especially when DJ, Chowder, and Jenny find themselves literally in the belly of the beast. But everyone else should enjoy a good, goosebumpy scare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2969</url>
         <critic>Sara Brady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Easily the best computer-animated feature to come from Hollywood in a long while, Monster House is also one of the weirdest. A creepy-crawly, freak-show Halloween yarn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/special_packages/summer_movies/15083426.htm</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Becomes one of those wonderfully weird adventure stories beloved of children who don't mind getting a good old-fashioned case of the heebie-jeebies. It's kind of a blast for adults too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14064/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unpretentious, smartly written and a lot of fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/07/21/movies/21mons.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a return-to-innocence sweetness that recalls some of the work of another of its executive producers - Steven Spielberg. Kids may grow up too fast today to embrace the film's familiar message of the virtues of an unhurried adolescence, but it's nice to be reminded of the possibility.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-monster21jul21,0,2764179.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A scary, sharp, funny movie, this is the best kids’ flick of the year so far.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=10518</url>
         <critic>Ian Freer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I was a little disappointed by the cop-out ending, in which debut director Gil Kenan gives up the film's frightening elements and comforts the audience with comedy and superficial emotion.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=F513FDEFEDA01BA856537AAFBB56DEB2.prodapp14_ae_01?id=643999&amp;reviewId=21142</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, what happens with the house is not only entertaining, but a marvel of what animation can accomplish in this day and age.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=643999&amp;reviewId=21159</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Monster House may be the first true horror film for children.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-07-20-monster-house-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Scott Bowles</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Monster House is in no way groundbreaking, it's an enjoyable way to spend 90 minutes, and is suitable for all but the youngest children.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/m/monster_house.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The house itself - which walks down the street in one impressive scene - is memorably voiced by Kathleen Turner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/prime_real_estate_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A captivating piece of visual wizardry. The house, which eventually frees itself from its moorings and chases after our trio of tweener heroes, is a genuine original.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/436901p-367967c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Monster House was designed as a family movie and a scary movie. It may scare children, but it won't terrify them. So it's no scarier than it should be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/07/21/DDGHTK1F471.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's missing is what Pixar never fails to provide: The kind of storytelling heart that is inseparable from imagination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.monster21jul21,0,6051581.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Set around Halloween, Monster House manages to cull bits and pieces from Hammer, Hitchcock and the old-dark-house genre of 19th Century literature and early 20th Century stage and film.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060721-movies-review-house,0,4318707.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Gil Kenan has a feel for dizzying "camera" work, and the screenplay  combines witty gags with a sweet, albeit familiar, suggestion that kids shouldn't be in any great hurry to be anything but kids.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/50661</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Constant shock cuts and souped-up music and sound effects will keep small fry in a state of moderate petrification, while the trio of tweeny leads plus attitude-redolent cohorts will make teens feel welcome.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931010?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie might be scary for small kids--but good scary, with goose-bump-inducing frames, witty repartee, and three resourceful kid protagonists.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/17661/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The three neighborhood kids who venture inside this toothy trap are wittily conceived (as are other characters, like a goth babysitter), but though the overall conception suggests Hayao Miyazaki's "Howl's Moving Castle," the frenetic pacing seems as American as an apple pie in your face.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#30001</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly enough, puberty-stricken J.D. and Chowder actually sound like real teenagers, but the cartoony look will probably alienate real-life kids that age, and the man-eating house might be downright terrifying to younger kids.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=280222&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A serviceable story served up as a large animation experience for kids.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v4/sub/MarketingPage?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2Fstory%2FLAC.20060721.MONSTER21%2FTPStory%2FTPEntertainment%2FMovies%2F&amp;ord=1153499425378&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;force_login=true</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The voice work is exceptional, with a special nod to Maggie Gyllenhaal as a toxic-tongued baby sitter and Jason Lee as her raunchy-to-the-point-of-depraved boyfriend. Kenan is a talent to watch, even in a flick that doesn't know when to quit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6823696/rid/10905090/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Monster House is the first horror comedy made exclusively for fourth-graders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7614</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Monster House benefits from strong graphic design and lovely lighting, but the script is nothing to write home about.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The coolest thing about Monster House is that Kathleen Turner's face was actually motion-captured to create the house's movements, but actual human beings on-screen might have ratcheted up the tension, of which there is none.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0629,thompson,73909,20.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Equal parts Ray Bradbury and rickety carnival spook show, this animated tale of a carnivorous, haunted house and the band of neighborhood kids who decide to put it out of commission feels maddeningly unfinished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A388037</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A grisly, often cynical piece of work whose joyless, aggressive spirit is made even less appealing by its soulless visual style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1097339&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$73,661,010</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$75,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$22,217,226</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,553</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>