<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Motel, The</name>
   <company>Palm Pictures / ImaginAsian Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Kang</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael Kang</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jeffrey Chyau</actor>
      <actor>Sung Kang</actor>
      <actor>Jade Wu</actor>
      <actor>Samantha Futerman</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Chen</actor>
      <actor>Alexis Chang</actor>
      <actor>Jackson Budinger</actor>
      <actor>Conor J. White</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>76</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kang's marvelously assured feature debut is a subtle adaptation of Ed Lin's acclaimed novel "Waylaid."</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=47024&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the best independent films, The Motel realizes that life is made up of minor pleasures and tiny epiphanies, not sweeping character arcs or big dramatic moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/49909</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There were half a dozen occasions, maybe more, when I roared out loud with laughter. This just may be a filmmaker with great things in him; this one's pretty damn good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/06/29/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Kang's small, perfectly observed portrait of Ernest Chin (Jeffrey Chyau), a Chinese-American boy who lives and works in a dingy downscale motel operated by his mother, captures the glum desperation of inhabiting the biological limbo of early adolescence.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/06/28/movies/28mote.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike so many indie films, Michael Kang's gently empathetic debut embraces eccentricity without drowning in its own hip irony.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/431305p-363364c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Michael Kang makes an impressive feature directorial debut with The Motel. But the person to keep an eye on is Jeffrey Chyau, a student at the Bronx High School of Science, who is a delight in the lead role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/the_motel_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Kang's first feature and it suffers from rocky moments and an unsure eye, but his sense of detail is rich with prickly contradictions and he resists tidying up the story.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/283374_limited01.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pleasant and surprisingly hard-edged coming-of-age indie film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/20/DDGFFLRTLJ1.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>G. Allen Johnson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kang balances the uproariously comic with the profoundly sad, and the two tones amplify each other with subtlety.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7623</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indie coming-of-age dramas are not exactly an endangered species, but Michael Kang's debut drama is an admirably intelligent and modest example of the genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002765230</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By not romanticizing its despairing yet humanistic outlook, The Motel presents a moment-by-moment emotional recap of almost anyone's formative years while simultaneously issuing a stinging reminder on the impossibility of fully outgrowing adolescence's uncertain searching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14107/</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A well-worn coming-of-age tale enlivened by pungent detail and a sharp visual sense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-motel28jul28,0,7121395.story</url>
         <critic>Sam Adams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The backdrop of this seedy motel is just the perfect place to illustrate the awkward times of early teen life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=6796</url>
         <critic>Eric Campos</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Motel offers a fresh take on characters and conventions, and compels interest with shrewd, sympathy-inspiring storytelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117926269&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;False&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's little originality in the joy rides, first kisses, and clashes with bullies, yet this 2005 debut feature by writer-director Michael Kang captures the small triumphs of a boy becoming a man.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/27638_MOTEL_KANG</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Motel, Michael Kang's modest Sundance applause reaper, doesn't deserve to be shotgunned for the sins of 30 other movies. But the underwhelming syncopation of make-nice clichés is too familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0626,atkinson,73671,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$51,540</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$11,565</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>true</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>