<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Mr. Bean&amp;#039;s Holiday</name>
   <company>Universal Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Rowan Atkinson</author>
      <author>Robin Driscoll</author>
      <author>Simon Mc</author>
      <author>Burney</author>
      <author>Hamish Mc</author>
      <author>Coll</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Steve Bendelack</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Rowan Atkinson</actor>
      <actor>Steve Pemberton</actor>
      <actor>Preston Nyman</actor>
      <actor>Sharlit Deyzac</actor>
      <actor>Francois Touch</actor>
      <actor>Emma de Caunes</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 24, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Atkinson's goofball grotesquerie never lets up -- right through to the inspired finale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20052854,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Since Mr. Bean rarely speaks a complete sentence, the effect is of watching a silent movie with sound effects. This was also the dramatic ploy of the great French director-performer Jacques Tati, who is clearly the big influence here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0824/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Either you'll find the man hilarious -- or he'll seem like one of those awful, tedious comedians who only THINKS he's hilarious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9209</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're not a die-hard "Bean" fan, this is probably no place for you. But it's mercifully short (87 minutes), the French scenery is pleasant, a handful of the routines are hilarious and -- with its G rating -- you can definitely bring the kids.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/328797_bean24q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A former Bean hater, I've been converted by Holiday, Atkinson's second, and far superior film version of his TV hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20070824_Mr__Beans_French_trip_is_sweet_fun.html</url>
         <critic>Tirdad Derakhshani</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the comic stars of the silent era, Mr. Bean's character transcends language barriers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070823.wbean24/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kids at my screening loved it. Besides, at its heart, Mr. Atkinson’s movie, a huge hit overseas, speaks in an international language.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/08/24/movies/24bean.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Andy Webster</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beautifully worked out, and the movie's final sight gag, set to Charles Trenet's shimmery seaside masterpiece, "La Mer," is a gracefully orchestrated bit of silliness that's a visual love sonnet to Chaplin, Lloyd, Keaton and, yes, Tati.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/08/24/mr_bean/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Do you Bean? If you do Bean, rejoice. Bean is back. If you don't Bean, here's a chance to start. Bean now, or forever hold your peace.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1126147&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may be a stretch to call this mugging moron sympathetic, but it’s surprising how enjoyable Mr. Bean can be when he’s actually given a hint of humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-mr-beans-holiday-closing-escrow-the-last-legion/17092/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Atkinson remains an expert clown, and there are sufficient numbers of gags to ensure that Bean fans worldwide will be kept fairly happy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8966&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a thoroughly Euro bedmate to the 1997 "Bean," with the Gauls rather than the Yanks as the butt of Bean's bumblings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933137.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=%22Mr%2E+Bean%27s+holiday%22</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie gets full marks for earning its G rating: no violence, no cursing, no sex or nudity, no drugs, not even a rogue cigarette blotting the landscape. It's easier to achieve this rating when your hero barely speaks and has little consciousness of the adult world, but "Holiday" proves it can be done-and should be more often.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=935229&amp;reviewId=22638&amp;startDate=08%2F24%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Mr. Bean's Holiday is hardly a memorable vacation, Atkinson proves an agreeably silly tour guide.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/118789530833260.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>David Germain</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A very cute movie. Unfortunately, cute is rarely funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/mr_beans_holiday</url>
         <critic>Amelie Gillette</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only intermittently funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/08/24/DDBSRNBBS.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a guilty-pleasure quality to watching Atkinson at work even when Mr. Bean has overstayed his welcome. The film's lightness makes you wish you were the one headed to the beach.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-bean24aug24,0,1089678.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Steve Bendelack and writer-producer Simon McBurney aim for the comedy of Chaplin, Keaton, and Tati, relying heavily on sight gags and their star's pratfalls and facial contortions, but they vititate the comic payoffs by allowing scenes to run too long.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31998_MISTER_BEANS_HOLIDAY.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ruthlessly skilled as Atkinson is, the Bean persona of generic, maniacally grinning ineptitude owes most of its appeal to seeing just how far an actor can pull a face without pulling a muscle.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070824-movies-review-bean,0,7620732.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are certain elements in life that you either have a taste for, or you don't. Like coffee. Cats. And Mr. Bean.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/08/24/2007-08-24_this_bean_dish_isnt_for_all_tastes.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This time, it's not because mainstream movie-goers in this country lack taste but because the film isn't worth buying a ticket to see. Mr. Bean's Holiday is no vacation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/m/mr_beans_holiday.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you like the character – his tooty yellow Mini, his busily working beetlebrows, his tendency to point and grunt and eat shellfish whole – then you will be rewarded with 90 minutes of such.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A526166</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Picks up steam when it finally arrives in Cannes just in time to wreak yet more havoc at the big film festival, but getting there is pretty tedious. A little of the wildly mugging Atkinson goes a long way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08242007/entertainment/movies/hes_a_has_bean.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are certainly some laughs to be had in Holiday (mostly of the "so dumb it’s funny" variety), but not much else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4025/mr-beans-holiday.html</url>
         <critic>Natalia Cuevas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you've been lobotomized or have the mental age of a kindergartener, Mr. Bean's Holiday is viable comic entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-08-23-mr-beans-holiday_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An excruciating series of gags aimed at kids old enough to think it's funny when a grown-up acts like a small child.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=290029&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$33,302,167</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$25,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,889,780</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,714</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>