<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Nanking</name>
   <company>THINKFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Bill Guttentag</author>
      <author>Dan Sturman</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Bill Guttentag</director>
      <director>Dan Sturman</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>ColorBlackandWhite</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Woody Harrelson</actor>
      <actor>Mariel Hemingway</actor>
      <actor>Jurgen Prochnow</actor>
      <actor>Stephen Dorff</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 12, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>88</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not only is the film a powerful historical record and a warning for future generations, it is an essential reminder to people, including many in Japan today, who might deny that this massacre ever occurred. As such, Nanking honors the highest calling of documentary filmmaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8717&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>James Greenberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I have rarely, if ever, seen a documentary reconstruction of a historical event that is so rich in firsthand (and well-preserved) photographic material.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1700218,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thorough and sadly engrossing documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9924</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Guttentag and Sturman gain in dramatic immediacy, however, they lose when it comes to historical context, and the chance to offer insight into why such things occur in the first place -- and continue to happen today -- is lost.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/nanking/review/289328</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nanking, directed by Bill Guttentag and Dan Sturman, does justice to this tragedy even though it makes the mistake of mixing the testimony of actual participants with staged readings from actors subbing for real people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0111/p15s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nanking both calls attention to a horrifying set of war crimes that remains little known in the West and crafts an impossible-but-true hymn to the power of the individual conscience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/btm/2007/12/13/kite/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The horrific 1937-38 massacre of more than 200,000 Chinese during the early days of the Japanese occupation gets a polished presentation in Nanking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2007&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=berlin&amp;nav=RBerlin&amp;articleid=VE1117932520&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes the film bearable is the knowledge that a few people did what they could to hold the line against humanity’s worst instincts. The voices in Nanking speak for the persistence of good in times and places where a moral crevice opens to reveal a vision of hell on earth.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/12/movies/12nank.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everyone knows about the Holocaust, but few today have heard about what was infamous as the Rape of Nanking, when 200,000 residents of what was then China's capital were massacred by invading Japanese troops.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12122007/entertainment/movies/nanking_658827.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is the devastating testimony from survivors themselves that leaves the most indelible impression.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/14/2007-12-14_short_takes_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The stories are harrowing, and because they are delivered by living, breathing witnesses, they move us in deep ways that the archival footage, for all its horror, cannot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/11/DDHNUC130.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever the numbers, testimony cited in Nanking portrays the episode as a horrifying chapter in man’s renowned inhumanity to man.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-nanking/294705/content</url>
         <critic>Sid Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While at times the film begins to feel like a laundry list of bad deeds, the first-person accounts pack a wallop.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9689</url>
         <critic>Jeremy Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the footage and survivors of Nanking are gray and decaying, its unbearable story is not something out of the past; the evil and ignorance it describes are alive and thriving today.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0750,various,78583,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michelle Orange</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A handsome documentary on a brutal subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/349528_limited01.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Individually these elements are powerful, but they fail to mesh or collide with one another in any satisfying way, and the movie's score only exacerbates the problem.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32699_NANKING.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$161,182</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$11,603</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>