<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Neil Young: Heart of Gold</name>
   <company>Paramount Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
      <genre>Musical</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jonathan Demme</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Emmylou Harris</actor>
      <actor>Ben Keith</actor>
      <actor>Neil Young</actor>
      <actor>Pegi Young</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 10, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>103</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The concert film has never looked or sounded classier than Jonathan Demme's superbly crafted Neil Young: Heart of Gold.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929377?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The mesmerizing, heart-tugging concert film Heart of Gold confirms Neil Young's stature as a national treasure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-02-09-heart-gold-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to film icons like Young as anything BUT icons, but Demme's film gets past the legend, zooming in on Young's aged, heroic face and finding an artist as human as the rest of us.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45433</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At the film's intimate best, it gives a guitar's perspective of the troubadour. He plucks his instrument as he plays our heartstrings. It's movie and music bliss.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=544274&amp;reviewId=20158</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Heart of Gold feels like an ample slice of the real America, the one truly worth caring for. And it's such a rare thing in this benighted age that the simple clarity with which it's presented feels like nothing less than a miracle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1140551708180420.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a performance film that conjures a vision of American life as moving, funny and rueful as John Ford's Young Mr. Lincoln.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.young10mar10,0,464858.story?coll=bal-movies-storyutil</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All in all, a visual and musical feast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0217/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jonathan Demme's superb film of Neil Young's 2005 performance at Nashville's Ryman Auditorium is as fervent a musical homage as was Demme's bubbly tribute to the Talking Heads, Stop Making Sense (1984).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12621&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This immaculate filmmaking creates an engaging documentary that makes you forget that you're missing the energy of a live show because it's a completely cinematic experience with its own special energy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8436</url>
         <critic>Jeremy Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Demme is in such perfect sync with Young's music that even the painted prairie backdrop (and the painted farmhouse interior screen, complete with hearth, that slides in front of it) only makes you roll your eyes in retrospect.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/15702/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In one sense, Neil Young: Heart of Gold is just a simple concert film -- no cutaways during the music for interviews, no cameras swooping and soaring on giant booms. But simplicity in this case also means no barrier between us and the people on stage, as they sing some of the most soul-stirring pop songs I've seen performed in a very long time.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the record of a life, a musical and spiritual autobiography, and as directed by Jonathan Demme it taps into the kind of unashamed, unsentimental emotion that's become increasingly rare in films of any kind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-neil10feb10,0,597851.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this sushi age of methamphetamine concert DVDs and dysfunction junction music tell-alls, Jonathan Demme dreams us back to the golden age of performance films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A347621</url>
         <critic>Raoul Hernandez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That film remains an electrifying testament to pop music as a communal creative act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8691</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pretty-near pure gold.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060217-movies-review-neil,0,4016265.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is more than a movie, it's a privilege.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/8855959/rid/9249496/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its varied close-ups and wide shots of the performers and a series of interviews with several of the musicians as they prepare to perform, Heart of Gold is a traditional concert film. But a traditional concert film starring Neil Young brings a layer of emotion to the medium that's rarely seen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2550</url>
         <critic>Ann Donahue</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bracing cover of Ian Tyson's "Four Strong Winds," performed by no fewer than seven acoustic guitars, rounds out the set, but be sure to stick around for the credits.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46732</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Young, wizened yet valiant, his voice still braying at the moon, delivers these songs of aging and loss as if caught in a beautiful dream of what lies waiting for him on the other side.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1157690_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At one point, during one of his occasional verbal rambles, he (Young) says half-jokingly, half-defensively that he's got some love songs left in him. This film, which is at once a valentine from one artist to another and a valentine from a musician to his audience, is surely proof that he does.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/10/movies/10gold.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This smart, aesthetically understated concert film from Jonathan Demme will transport Young's legions of baby boomer fans back to the future, as 1969 re-invents itself in 2005 for Young.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001919479</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One might call Neil Young: Heart of Gold soothing, even becalmed, but mellowness and ripeness, when they exist at this high level of craft, should have their season, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060213crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Recaps and effectively mythologizes this nugget of modern folklore in brief interviews with Young and a band of old reliables, including Spooner Oldham, Grant Boatwright, and Ben Keith.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0606,charity,72090,20.html</url>
         <critic>Tom Charity</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Given what Young charges for concert tickets, all his organs could be gold. So I was even more grateful for this documentary of his August 2005 shows at the fabled Ryman Auditorium in Nashville, expertly directed by Jonathan Demme.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29315_NEIL_YOUNG_HEART_OF_GOLD.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Demme is smart and sensitive enough to sit back and listen to the music without attention-getting intrusions. The tunes are subtly compelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118101&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This remarkable concert film, beautifully shot by director Jonathan Demme over two days last summer, is all about legacy, a more-or-less conscious exercise in myth-making on the part of a musical giant facing his own mortality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060210.NEIL10/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Kate Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A snapshot of a fabled career that's of little interest to anyone outside Young's fans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/10/DDGK8H57OP1.DTL#flick2</url>
         <critic>Joel Selvin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dropping in amusing anecdotes and tender memories, a deeply reflective Young revisits - and often reinterprets - both his recent and classic work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/390159p-330844c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Heart of Gold is a sweet, gentle picture, if not a particularly exhilarating one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/10/young/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It works as a wistful coda to suggest that the song will go on long after the show is over.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/259817_young17q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shows the famed songwriter's performance and work off with reverance, and a faithfullness to the live experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134409</url>
         <critic>Ross Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A schmaltzy filmed record of a Nashville concert given by the legendary former rocker, who has morphed into the new Kenny Rogers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/63267.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,828,069</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$53,908</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>jonathan demme</oscar_winning_director>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>