<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Next Day Air</name>
   <company>Summit Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Blair Cobbs</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Benny Boom</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Donald Faison</actor>
      <actor>Mike Epps</actor>
      <actor>Wood Harris</actor>
      <actor>Omari Hardwick</actor>
      <actor>Emilio Rivera</actor>
      <actor>Darius McCrary</actor>
      <actor>Cisco Reyes</actor>
      <actor>Mos Def</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 8, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a script that snaps, characters that pop, a blaze of streetwise attitude and enough firepower to pulverize a significant chunk of South Philadelphia, Next Day Air nears neo-blaxploitation perfection. Good things come in strange packages.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/05/08/movies/08next.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A very pleasant surprise, Next Day Air is the rare crime comedy that does justice to both sides of the equation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/next-day-air,27729/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bloody screwball comedy, a film of high spirits. It tells a complicated story with acute timing and clarity, and gives us drug-dealing lowlifes who are almost poetic in their clockwork dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090506/REVIEWS/905069991</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Benny Boom and screenwriter Blair Cobbs pull off the tough trick of investing profoundly stupid characters with humanity, while cinematographer David Armstrong plays gleefully with the grime-o-vision palette of '70s blaxploitation flicks.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34363_NEXT_DAY_AIR.html</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>He may be a first-time feature ­director, but music video master Benny Boom clearly knows how to pull a midlevel movie ­together.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/05/08/2009-05-08_mos_def_in_next_day_air_delivers_rowdy_action_comedy.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Benny Boom built his reputation directing music videos and commercials, and his first feature, Next Day Air, falls somewhere between the blunt-force visuals of the former and the focus-grouped formulas of the latter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/2009-05-07/film-tv/movie-reviews-adoration-julia-little-ashes/2</url>
         <critic>Michelle Orange</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Next Day Air is sort of bracing, though it isn't very good: Its total lack of dramatic and comic bearings, to say nothing of a point, keeps you wondering about the next fatality, in a half-interested way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-tc-mov-next-day-air-0506-050may08,0,2508711.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ensues is an uneasy mix of farcical slapstick and comedy of errors with a violent, blood-soaked tale of inner-city crime.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1035968.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Predictable, and stereotypical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/Next-Day-Air</url>
         <critic>Rob Calvert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Next Day Air can't decide whether it's a broad stoner comedy or a gritty Tarantino-esque action flick. The humor is there, but violence brings the laughter to an abrupt halt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-05-07-next-day-air_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Routine stuff, but things move quickly, with several offhand funny moments. Mos Def is hilarious in a cameo as another delivery guy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05082009/entertainment/movies/next_day_air_168131.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The right combination of goofy character behavior, action set pieces, and narrative drive to keep the movie from ever being boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/day-air/review/297385</url>
         <critic>Perry Seibert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a serious miscalculation when the lighthearted hijinks suddenly give way to a climactic scene of brutal violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-next-day-air-1003971082.story</url>
         <critic>Stephen Farber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An altogether bumbling excuse for an action-comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940210.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wished Next Day Air were funnier. In the end, it's a fitfully amusing, sloppy comedy that doesn't work very hard for your 10 bucks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/next-day-air,1156481.html</url>
         <critic>Dan Kois</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>None of these characters provides more than a smattering of laughs, but Def is the one guy we might like to see more of, if only because his role is small and better executed than it deserves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/05/08/comedy_or_drug_drama_air_fails_to_fly_either_way/</url>
         <critic>Janice Page</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That's about all Next Day Air can muster by way of invention, trying to slap a new face on a gaggle of rote gestures in a vain attempt to cover its own uselessness. But no matter how big the guns it draws, every shot is a dud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-nextday8-2009may08,0,109462.story</url>
         <critic>Sam Adams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie could really use an Avon Barksdale, but even actor Wood Harris, who played drug kingpin Barksdale in "The Wire," seems a bit lost.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/05/07/MVD417FPNE.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the movie doesn't even care about its characters, then how can we?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20277908,00.html</url>
         <critic>Adam Markovitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Might make a terrific double bill with the equally inane (but considerably more entertaining) "Con Air," with the French electonica duo Air chirruping in the background. But, you know, only if you're stoned out of your head.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A776070</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$10,027,047</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$4,111,043</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,138</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>