<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Nick and Norah&amp;#039;s Infinite Playlist</name>
   <company>Screen Gems (Sony)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Lorene Scafaria</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Peter Sollett</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Michael Cera</actor>
      <actor>Kat Dennings</actor>
      <actor>Ari Graynor</actor>
      <actor>Jay Baruchel</actor>
      <actor>Rafi Gavron</actor>
      <actor>Aaron Yoo</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 3, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>So much goes down on Nick and Norah's one enchanted evening that the best advice is to enjoy the ride -- the actual ride -- around this vibrant new New York.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20230109,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the movie rambles in the middle, it gets back on track when Nick and Norah have a sweet encounter in an unexpected place. The soundtrack is an excellent counterpoint to the film's quirky scenarios.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-10-02-nick-norah-infinite-playlist_N.htm?loc=interstitialskip</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is filled with wonderful music, memorable characters and rich, quotable dialogue.  But what makes the picture really soar is the way it reminds you what it feels like to fall in love -- and the endless, countless possibilities a new romance brings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/709834.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though these two really grow on you, what's almost more remarkable than Nick, Norah or their playlist (which may not be infinite, but really does include some great music) is the quirky, melting-pot world director Peter Sollett creates around them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=95310446</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If we must have teen movies, let them all be as sweet and seductive as Sollett's smartly observed romance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/161207</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bright little screwball comedy that speaks for the vitality of new movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122298339529899629.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is a teen romantic comedy that largely fits the familiar template but is also fleshed out with atmosphere, a nice blend of broad goofiness and sophistication, and two appealing leads who bring it to life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-playlist3-2008oct03,0,6190536.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Ordona</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Let's call this "High Fidelity Nano." It's a little bit less in every way, lighter and cuter than its archetypal elder, but it might just fit your present lifestyle all the better. Who needs to go back to the polysyllabic spree of John Cusack channeling Nick Hornby when you have Michael Cera making awkward emo look so lovable?</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/381531_nick03q.html</url>
         <critic>Travis Nichols</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some movies skate by fast on slick action. Others snap with crisp dialogue. Nick and Norah springs high on the bounce of its hugely likable leads, Michael Cera and Kat Dennings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20081003_Their_talk_is_like_music_to_the_ear.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Geared more toward teens, although that won't prevent older viewers with an affinity for romance from appreciating the vibes it gives off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1352</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sollett works easily and well with Cera and Dennings, and lends a touch of awkward realism to what, from a screenwriting perspective, is pure formula.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-nick-and/640355/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sollett's working with stale material, clearly. He genuinely likes people, though, and his fondness revives "Nick and Norah" and sets it spinning with camaraderie and hope.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11273</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fantasy of one night in New York City and all its insanity, grossness, romance, and glamour.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4760/nick-and-norahs-infinite-playlist.html</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's title proves to be not entirely a case of bait-and-switch. The film really is a homage to vintage Hollywood comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081003.wnick03/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Peter Sollett (Raising Victor Vargas) and cinematographer Tom Richmond transform nocturnal New York into a soft-focus wonderland for their sweet but screwball courtship.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33611_NICK_AND_NORAHS_INFINITE_PLAYLIST.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though this Nick and Norah have a lot more angst, they're just as worth watching, admiring and cuddling up to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1844565,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the mix tapes that obsess its main characters, Nick &amp; Norah's Infinite Playlist builds into something of infectious joy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=%20%20%201144918&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Regards its characters with affectionate detachment, and assures its audience that no great calamities or revelations are in store. Instead, there are a series of small crises and tiny epiphanies, all adding up to a story that courts triviality in its pursuit of charm.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/10/03/movies/03play.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's the journey that matters, however, and sometimes the film doesn't seem to know where it's going.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/nick_and_norahs_infinite</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The conceit here is that if a boy and a girl love the same music, that means they're in love. Who am I to argue with such poetic whimsy?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1004/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It has a dogged all-night charm and a sense of who its audience is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10032008/entertainment/movies/wry_fidelity_to_a_genre_131871.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has been designed to make gentle hearts soar beneath neo-grunge exteriors. It's a mixture of high-SAT humor and high-jinks so crude they're really low-jinks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.nick03oct03,0,5226000.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Every generation deserves its ultimate high school romance, and Nick &amp; Norah's Infinite Playlist clearly aims to take the slot currently open. Despite a valiant attempt, though, it doesn't quite make the grade.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/10/02/2008-10-02_nick__norahs_infinite_playlist_isnt_a_ke.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie itself seems to be locked in a kind of adolescence; it never quite blossoms into maturity, into a fully rounded whole.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/10/03/nick/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So slight it's almost diaphanous--an hour after seeing it, what the movie leaves behind is not so much a memory as a mood. Still, it's a fine mood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2201449/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sollett, hoping for a "Before Sunrise/Before Sunset" vibe, sadly settles for a soggy aftertaste.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/18264868/review/23356408/nick_and_norahs_infinite_playlist</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Within the realm of a mildly good time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/10/02/DDHV139MCA.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the kind of sparsely plotted comedy that depends on compelling characters, but it stars two young actors defined by ironic detachment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938211.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Nick+and+Norah%27s+infinite+playlist</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lacks some of the idiocy of your average teenage rom-com. But it doesn't bring much to the party. It sort of ambles along, with two nice people at the center of a human scavenger hunt. It's not much of a film, but it sort gets you halfway there, like a Yugo.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081002/REVIEWS/810020305</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lest anyone think this soils Cera's record, the movie actually highlights his unique gifts; his easygoing chemistry with co-star Kat Dennings is practically the only thing about this picture that isn't pathetically contrived.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/10/movie_review_nick_norahs_infin.html</url>
         <critic>Stan Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All I can seem to muster, post-screening, is a modicum of fondness and a probably impermanent relief that the film isn't anywhere near as awful as it might have been in less capable hands.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A679348</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plays like something crafted in a lab by 54-year-old hucksters trying to sell shit to the kids under the cheerless guise of "alternative." The only thing it's an alternative to? Good.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-10-01/film/nick-and-norah-s-infinite-playlist-about-a-boy-and-not-much-else/</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$31,487,293</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$10,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$11,311,751</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,421</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>