<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Night Listener. The</name>
   <company>Miramax Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Mystery</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Armistead Maupin</author>
      <author>Terry Anderson</author>
      <author>Patrick Stettner</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Patrick Stettner</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Robin Williams</actor>
      <actor>Toni Collette</actor>
      <actor>Sra Oh</actor>
      <actor>Rory Culkin</actor>
      <actor>John Cullum</actor>
      <actor>Joe Morton</actor>
      <actor>Bobby Cannavale</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 4, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This unconventional psychological drama weaves a fascinating tale, and Collette and Williams give two of the summer's best performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-08-03-night-listener_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A topical study of writers' deceptions, which also explores issues of identity and the blurred lines between fantasy and reality, The Night Listener is intriguing, thought-provoking and harrowing by turns, with fine central and supporting performances and a richly satisfying feel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134257</url>
         <critic>David Hughes</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie adapted from a novel inspired by a person who probably never existed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1154557520210580.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Night Listener is by no means an example of perfect filmmaking, but it is the kind of movie that stays with you.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/n/night_listener.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pacing and staging of the later scenes could use a little more electricity and momentum, and a little less restraint. Yet The Night Listener keeps you watching. And listening.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060805-movies-review-night,0,5629420.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Williams delivers a solid, twinkle-free (though closed-off) performance, but the film as a whole can't decide what it wants to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/51227</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plays like an Alfred Hitchcock thriller but is nevertheless a movie of ideas. It bristles with intriguing thoughts about the realm of fiction, how one loves, issues of identity and questions concerning how one transfers a real-life incident into big-screen fiction. This is a film that can crawl inside your skin.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001882942</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even when the script overstates the obvious, Stettner mines every nuance of unease from the head games between Williams and the unnerving Collette, who embodies the moment passive aggression stops being passive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0631,ridley,74064,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's unlike anything else out now, and Williams, to his credit and our immense relief, has for the moment foresworn his usual giddiness in favor of a muted, hunched acting style that befits both the character of Noone and the overall tone of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A391618</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is not so much suspenseful as intriguing.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=7CBF3E9593D89F26D3621A613FC642C1.prodapp15_ae_01?id=666597&amp;reviewId=21246</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fundamental problem with The Night Listener is the manner in which the boy, Pete, is depicted. Rory Culkin gets the tricky job of bringing the role to life, and he does it well, but it's still a trick. Or is it?</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=666597&amp;reviewId=21241</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where the hero of Maupin's novel learns some valuable lessons about love and faith, the film strikes a darker, even angry tone that's far more understandable and, in the end, far more convincing.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=281260&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a narrative, it has serious problems -- holes so gaping that they're all but unavoidable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.night04aug04,0,5983664.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's also a terrific performance from Collette, who, in only a handful of scenes, wonderfully communicates the unusual resourcefulness of a demented woman who has spent her life assuming a succession of physical handicaps as a survival technique.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/280001_night04q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The experience of watching The Night Listener didn't make me feel "real" at all, only stuffed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/08/04/night_listener/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's suggestiveness gives way to a certain thinness and lassitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30103_NIGHT_LISTENER.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film has its creepy, suspenseful moments -- but it shrinks a rich, strange story to the dimensions of an anecdote.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/08/04/movies/04list.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Casting Williams in this thriller, adapted from Armistead Maupin's novel, was a bigger mistake than the actor's performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/08-04-2006/entertainment/col/story/440718p-371051c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Is The Night Listener a wintry drama with a few schlocky jolts, or an underdone psychological thriller straining for some dramatic heft on the side? Hard to tell, but either way, the movie doesn't cohere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1222151_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a performer, Robin Williams has a wonderfully volatile range; as an actor, he commutes uneasily between over-sincere and over-sinister. Both modes are on full monochromatic display in this stolid noir thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14156/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aiming for unsettling atmosphere over character definition, the dawdling mystery thriller manages to flatten two protagonists that had far more depth in the novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;head=sundance&amp;nav=RSundance&amp;articleid=VE1117929305&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes the film such a guilty pleasure is how Williams's righteous self-pity is perfectly matched to Collette's nuttiness and despair.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8918</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On their accounts (Williams/Collette), The Night Listener is compelling viewing-but on their accounts only.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=666597&amp;reviewId=21244</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A movie with lots of heart but no heartbeat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/08/04/DDGH3KA1BI1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It should be a better, more authentic movie, considering that screenwriters Maupin and his ex-partner, Terry Anderson, are retelling parts of their own story here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060804.NIGHT04/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somehow the movie ends up feeling like a museum piece or, worse still, a work of fiction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=3004</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Something happens to Robin Williams in serious roles. He becomes so drab that it's almost as if he's trying to efface himself from the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0804/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aiming to blur the distinctions between truth and illusion, it simply blurs its own effectiveness by relying on predictable and not particularly convincing mystery-thriller formula.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1121189&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time the credits rolled I was bored rather than stunned by the revelations within the movie and I just want these type of reversal/twist movies to get better, or go away.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8437</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This Sundance dud is a turgid gay soap opera with a limp twist, showcasing Robin Williams at his maudlin worst.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/neither_ear_nor_there_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Depressed and depressing drama.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,836,393</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$4,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,554,134</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,367</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>robin williams</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>