<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Nim&amp;#039;s Island</name>
   <company>Fox Walden</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Levin</author>
      <author>Jennifer Flackett</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Mark Levin</director>
      <director>Jennifer Flackett</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jodie Foster</actor>
      <actor>Abigail Breslin</actor>
      <actor>Gerard Butler</actor>
      <actor>Alphonso McAuley</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 4, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Exhilarating and enchanting family picture. It's the best I've seen this year and highly recommended for girls and for boys, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/04/03/DDK1VQBL8.DTL&amp;typ=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's hard to imagine kids not enjoying the good-hearted, lovingly shot fantasy of it all, and Breslin is charming, though most viewers past puberty will likely yearn to be voted off the Island.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20188978,00.html</url>
         <critic>Leah Greenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its limitations, the film still looks terrific. Flawless CGI and forays into animation keep things visually lively, and Nim’s enviable life is likely to hook kids into the story early and keep them entranced.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-nims-island/363870/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some nice scenery, an unexpectedly funny performance by Jodie Foster and a unflaggingly spunky Abigail Breslin make for above average family entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/nims-island/review/293094</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This family comedy adventure from Walden Media is likable in a scruffy way. Its characters, especially the youngest one, are engaging, and few adults are immune to childhood fantasies about secluded tropical isles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=BJNkH13Qd3vKL3xCJKbFM2M7FSzTv8tZNBlJ27pr44s4fTdYwqH1!-783599429&amp;&amp;rid=10913</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even as the derivative roots of Nim's Island are clearly visible, kids will no doubt vicariously enjoy Nim's adventures and Edenic existence. And how refreshing, for once, to see a girl embark on derring-do that, in Nim's own words, makes her the hero of her own story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1142883&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boys adventure stories are a dime (store novel) a dozen, but girls adventure tales are rare things indeed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A607275</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An entertaining, diverting adventure saga that offers excitement and a relatable heroine for children, and also will remind their parents of favorite classics from their own youth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-04-03-nims-island_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you're an elementary schooler or someone who finds Gerard Butler irresistible even when fully clothed, Nim's Island may be a treat to watch. If not, it's likelier to be a chore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/364/story/564696.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Breslin, so memorable in "Little Miss Sunshine," suffers the most. Skilled and reactive with humans, she doesn't quite muster the same engagement with her finned and flippered costars here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080404_Plucky_Nim_needs_human_interaction.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing especially wrong with Nim's Island, but there's not a lot right about it either.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/n/nims_island.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>8- to 12-year-olds will have a good time, and you'll have a good time watching them have a good time. Otherwise, the film's an oddity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10504</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smarter than it sounds and carried by a very funny performance by Foster, this is a kids’ movie that’s bearable for adults too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135239</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its formula and flaws (chief among them Foster’s sitcom-campy performance), Nim’s Island is a perfectly pleasant, agreeably innocuous ’tweener adventure film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/movie-reviews-forever-my-blueberry-nights-my-brother-is-an-only-child/18645/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Strictly for the 8-and-under crowd.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04042008/entertainment/movies/indiana_jodie_and_the_temple_of_product__104884.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Such an air of dumbness hovers over the movie, and it's all played so broadly that nothing about it is remotely believable.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/357624_nims04q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sweet but ho-hum adaptation of Wendy Orr’s novel, a comedy-adventure that never quite finds its tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/04/04/movies/04isla.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Foster seems to be having real fun, twitching and skittering around, that steel jaw of hers comically tense. But this family movie shouldn't be about a shut-in trying to get from A to B; it needs to be about an unconventional girl growing up and helping an equally unconventional grownup cut loose on a volcanic island. Sadly, Nim's Island is a missed opportunity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/04/04/2008-04-04_nims_island_is_a_little_missfire.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directors Jennifer Flackett and Mark Levin deliver some eye-catching fantasy sequences in the early scenes, but the film grows more mundane and the tone more uneven as it goes on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/nims_island</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The premise, from the book by Wendy Orr, is terrific, but the execution seems designed to make all but the youngest viewers fling copies of the book at the screen in frustration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-nim4apr04,0,7582696.story</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Three stories in one. This might be two stories too many.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/04/review_an_overstuffed_nims_isl.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You begin yearning for more cuteness from the anthropomorphic animals: a pelican, a sea lion and, best of all, a bearded dragon lizard. They're a lot more amusing than Foster, who pours on the angst.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.nims04apr04,0,6204456.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A picturesque adventure-comedy that quickly capsizes under the weight of its obnoxious slapstick, pedestrian dialogue and general unwillingness to rise above stock ideas and situations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936697.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's dated, stereotypical comedy often contradicts its wholesome intentions, coming across as laboriously cutesy and occasionally perverse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080404.wnim04/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$48,006,762</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$37,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$13,210,579</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,513</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jodie foster</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>