<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>No Impact Man</name>
   <company>Oscilloscope Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Laura Gabbert</director>
      <director>Justin Schein</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Colin Beavan</actor>
      <actor>Michelle Conlin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 11, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>93</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>At once noble and naive, earnest and a tad obnoxious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090925_The_nitty-gritty_of_living_an_eco-correct_life.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It all seems like a stunt, especially since Beaven has also written a just-published book about his experiences, but he and Conlin are an engaging pair who don't let zealotry get in the way of humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0911/p18s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The value of No Impact Man, a compelling and suitably exasperating documentary about one family’s attempt to not harm the environment for a year, is that it forces viewers to reflect on their own casual consumption and waste.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/no-impact-man,32718/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, it's an instructive and entertaining examination of both the overlooked environmental costs of everyday life and the possibilities for change.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/10/movie_review_no_impact_man.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is a hilarious, riveting must-see about a family as it breaks down almost all the way and then reinvents itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/09/11/no_impact/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To sum up Beavan’s message, he’s not saying you should give up toilet paper. But you should give up what you can. Help any way you can. Do all you can.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11510</url>
         <critic>Scott Knopf</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may not be the greatest of cinematic exercises, and it often feels contrived, but this documentary somehow is enlightening, ridiculous, foreboding and funny at the same time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/09/17/MVEK19N1LF.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>David Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Succeeds as both advocacy and entertainment by focusing on the family.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/A87E60057D9D862B86257641006DB0CF?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s like Sinatra said: If you can make (do without) it there, you can make (do without) it anywhere. The movie leaves it up to you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/10/02/off_the_grid_with_no_impact_man/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You know what they say: Behind every successful, self-flagellating environmental activist is a woman. And that's what saves both Beavan and the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/no-impact-man,1157934/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gabbert and Schein keep the focus on their subjects, interpreting their struggles through the ups and downs in the couple's relationship as they grapple with increasingly difficult issues. This character-driven approach draws viewers into the couple's struggle and prompts consideration of similar lifestyle changes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/no-impact-man-film-review-1003992011.story</url>
         <critic>Justin Lowe</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Goes down far easier than, say, an all-natural, fiber-enriched peanut butter sandwich without a glass of soy milk. It's that rare doc (these days) that could go theatrical, largely because it's a film about a couple, more than a movement.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939373.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=no+impact+man</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's even harder being the semi-supportive wife, which is what generates most of the electricity in this slight but entertaining documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=112447407</url>
         <critic>Mark Jenkins</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie gives off a stranger vibe. Beavan is both a hero and a figure of fun, a man whose ideals are in constant collision with the habits of modern life.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/58859/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film ultimately is more practical than profound, a slightly smartened-up "Dummy's Guide to Green Living," which, as you learn, most of us probably know a good deal less about than we imagine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-impact-man11-2009sep11,0,215112.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes this documentary work is that the Beavan family is so relatable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A899946</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film makes little sense (the couple refuses to ride subways, but Metro-North is OK), but it's a diverting conversation piece/freak show.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/movies/organically_groaning_B3BI5cH7w9fNK46Ua405mM</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I can’t, in the end (all appearances to the contrary), judge Mr. Beavan or this film too severely. Making an impact is easy. Making a difference is hard.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/09/11/movies/11impact.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We could all do better, definitely, but how much can we possibly glean from a guy whose idealism can be measured with a calendar?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-09-08/film/no-impact-man-tests-limits-of-man-s-carbon-footprint-wife-s-patience/</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The efforts of Beavan's clan are so extreme that they spark some interest, but their environmental commitment feels a bit too self-serving to have the impact that's clearly desired.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/09/11/2009-09-11_short_film_reviews_9_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eventually runs out of gas--or rather, pedal-power--as the filmmakers grope for how to cap the Beavans’ story.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/78392/no-impact-man-film-review</url>
         <critic>Nicolas Rapold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The boring, humorless pair do nothing to refute the image of eco-worriers as preening, puritanical douchebags addicted to symbolic gesture and allergic to cost-benefit analysis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?oid=1129489</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$100,028</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$15,215</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>