<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ocean&amp;#039;s Thirteen</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Brian Koppelman</author>
      <author>David Levien</author>
      <author>George Clayton Johnson</author>
      <author>Jack Golden Russell</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Steven Soderbergh</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Brad Pitt</actor>
      <actor>George Clooney</actor>
      <actor>Matt Damon</actor>
      <actor>Elliott Gould</actor>
      <actor>Al Pacino</actor>
      <actor>Don Cheadle</actor>
      <actor>Shaobo Qin</actor>
      <actor>Casey Affleck</actor>
      <actor>Scott Caan</actor>
      <actor>Bernie Mac</actor>
      <actor>Carl Reiner</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 8, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>122</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a world ruled by process, is compassion still real? Or is it just another scam? In Ocean's Thirteen, it is deviously, and merrily, both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20041402,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most enjoyable thing about the "Ocean's" movies is that nobody involved seems to take them seriously. The star wattage is immense but the stars themselves are refreshingly self-deprecating, almost satirically so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0608/p11s03-almo.html?page=1</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Ocean's 23," oops, Ocean's Thirteen, is also a gas; it's lighter than air, prettier than life, a romp, a goof and an attentively oiled machine.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/movies/08ocea.html?em&amp;ex=1181361600&amp;en=aa075f6d194e6c82&amp;ei=5087%0A</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pleasure here, as before, comes from watching skilled professionals team up for a job well done.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/oceans_13</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As smooth as a good mojito, as stylish as an Armani suit and as meaningful in the grand scheme of things as yesterday's Las Vegas betting odds, Ocean's Thirteen"continues the breezy good times of the first two series entries without missing a beat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117933755.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You can beat the house and you can break the bank, but sequels always get long odds on defeating the law of diminishing returns – yet Ocean's Thirteen just about pulls it off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133168</url>
         <critic>Chris Hewitt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's so money! It's so fun!</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/32866/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An over-the-top celebrity cartoon of cool and a tilt-a-whirl of fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10063</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's skillfully rendered fun, but don't expect to remember much the next day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06072007/entertainment/movies/its_reigning_men_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The lack of explosions and gunfire makes this an atypical summer thriller, but its breezy brand of unforced and occasionally self-referential entertainment is a lot more fun than pirates, webslingers, and green ogres.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/o/oceans13.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A satisfying story of a grand-scale swindle, but it also retains the impishness and charm of "Ocean's Twelve." Even better, it solves the Roberts problem in the most thorough and economical way possible: She's not in the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/06/07/DDGDBQ9JN913.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sleek, stylish and ephemeral as a fireworks display, Ocean's Thirteen is the definition of light, but not totally brainless, entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/oceans-thirteen/review/285360</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As frothy and smooth as a chilled margarita on a hot Vegas night.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-06-07-oceans-thirteen_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Breezy humor and a dazzling heist keep 'Ocean' franchise in the money.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9004</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A glittering, beautifully made goof, and the bulk of its fun comes in watching so many talented people chasing after such trivial, disposable pleasures on such a large, big-budget scale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/231/story/131473.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overplayed by a toupeed'n'tucked Pacino, Bank is made up to resemble Hollywood mogul Robert Evans, who produced Pacino in The Godfather. It's an inside joke for outsiders. As are the many references to the Corleone family saga.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20070608_Cool_stars_keep_film_afloat.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the caper reaches its conclusion in a swirl of turnabouts and twists -- you'll never guess in whose favor all of them go -- Thirteen delivers more than enough gaming satisfaction for one such picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3859/oceans-thirteen.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brad Pitt doesn't really act in Ocean's Thirteen, he just glides through the third chapter in Steven Soderbergh's heist-flick annuity on the magic carpet of his own unimpeachable cool. Don't knock it. Genuine star power is rare. Pitt has it in spades -- all aces.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/9569549/review/15010264/oceans_13</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ocean's Thirteen has a pleasingly casual, raffish quality -- it's enjoyable to watch, particularly if you've got nothing better to do.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/06/08/oceans_13/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Ocean movies aren't about plot, logic, or character development. They're spa experiences, two-hour-long immersions in a warm tub of Vegas (and Vegas-movie) nostalgia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2168023/fr/flyout</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This one is all about the boys. But as glad as we are to see them, watching the third installment is like attending a college reunion too soon after the last one: after the initial welcome, there's not all that much to say.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18986985/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This time, in a clever script by Brian Koppelman &amp; David Levien (who wrote the poker drama "Rounders"), the heist is for friendship.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9279</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Passingly enjoyable summer fluff, but if you can find a more genial, less edgy caper movie, you might want to own it as a pet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/06/07/2007-06-07_clooneys_flimsy_whimsy.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ocean's Thirteen proceeds with insouciant dialogue, studied casualness, and a lotta stuff happening, none of which I cared much about because the movie doesn't pause to develop the characters, who are forced to make do with their movie-star personas.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070606/REVIEWS/706060301</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Ocean's Thirteen were compared to a gem, it would have to be considered something of a flashy fraud: Initially impressive for cut and colour, it lacks either clarity or weight.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070607.woceans08/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Better than the fiasco that was "Ocean's Twelve" (how could it not be?) but not as engaging as "Ocean's Eleven."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-oceans8jun08,0,773906.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its attempts at wrinkles and surprises and sleight-of-hand, Ocean's Thirteen is too direct and plain and pleased with itself to ever feel like a thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1181166914234290.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pleasures of Ocean's Thirteen are so slight as to be eminently forgettable. Most of the "twists" in the plot are of the ho-hum variety; it's not that one sees them coming, but that they don't amount to much when they show up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.oceans08jun08,0,683334.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Three films in, and Soderbergh's Ocean's franchise has settled into a kind of hipster equanimity – happy to live in that loosely defined territory where art meets commerce and story blends seamlessly with cool.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A481177</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ocean's Thirteen is too complicated for its own mediocrity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1132629&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Predictably adolescent and smarmy, with the mix of sentimentality and cynical flippancy that's becoming Steven Soderbergh's specialty (even when he's pretending to make art films), this is chewing gum for the eyes and ears, and not bad as such.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31684_OCEANS_THIRTEEN.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Soderbergh ends the movie with a few jokes, which is casual and neat but leaves you wondering whether the practice of making enormous movies about nothing isn't a little mad.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/06/11/070611crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All told, this thing has to be one of the dullest caper movies ever made.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/318723_oceans08q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The director, Steven Soderbergh, and his large, cheerful cast have managed to make the least possible movie that still resembles a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118125770736228406.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The line between cool and cold is a thin one, however. Cool isn't the word for "Thirteen"; it's just smug.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070608-movies-review-oceans,0,487746.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Now, Soderbergh has made a movie so cool it's practically comatose. Sputtering along from one half-cocked gag line and self-satisfied in-joke to the next, Ocean's Thirteen is as slapdash and slipshod a three-quel as any in this summer's box-office sweepstakes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/oceans-thirteens-con-job/16574/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>See it if you must, but don't forget to pack the Air Wick. These breezy doings are mustier than a Glitter Gulch casino at 4 a.m.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0723,hoberman,76869,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$117,144,465</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$85,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$36,133,403</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,565</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>al pacino</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>steven soderbergh</oscar_winning_director>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>2</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>matt damon</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>brad pitt</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>