<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Off the Map</name>
   <company>Holedigger Studios</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Joan Ackermann</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Campbell Scott</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>J.D. Hawkins</actor>
      <actor>Joan Allen</actor>
      <actor>Amy Brenneman</actor>
      <actor>Valentina de Angelis</actor>
      <actor>Sam Elliott</actor>
      <actor>J.K. Simmons</actor>
      <actor>Kevin Skousen</actor>
      <actor>Jim True-Frost</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 11, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scott has the courage to let the imaginative story unfold at its own leisurely pace, and it's not surprising that the acting is excellent, considering that he's among the very best American screen actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0311/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A small masterpiece of tone and form.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3308&amp;Sumbit.x=51&amp;Sumbit.y=15</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of those sweet, intelligent, nicely made films.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050310-movies-review-mw-map.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Off the Map is visually beautiful as a portrait of lives in the middle of emptiness, but it's not about the New Mexico scenery. It's about feelings that shift among people who are good enough, curious enough or just maybe tired enough to let that happen.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050310/REVIEWS/50301004/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rambles without apparent purpose, and yet it blooms in emotional impact as it goes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=4090</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's sense of place is hypnotic, but there's more to it than gorgeous images -- Campbell Scott's astute direction; Joan Allen's beautifully laconic performance; a sense of lively, if occasionally pretentious, inquiry into the wellsprings of art.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a collective scintillation about its rich, distinctive characters, narrative serendipity and ineffable magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A23678-2005Mar10.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps the most evocative movie of the new year, Campbell Scott's Off the Map, moves at the pace of a Southwestern sunset and ends before you're quite ready to let it go.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/03-11-2005/entertainment/col/story/288928p-247278c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The funny and heartbreaking Off the Map, directed with a poet's eye and a keen ear for nuance by Campbell Scott, resonates with something rare in today's movies: simplicity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6156785?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a character study more than a forward-moving drama, plopped down with exquisite photographic care in a beautiful New Mexico desert, and starring good actors who make a feast of their flavorful roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1038448_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directed with an easygoing grace by Campbell Scott, has the feel of a coming-of-age novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=116355&amp;reviewId=17546</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The people are just a little too calculatedly quirky in Off the Map, an otherwise engaging comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.map25mar25,1,2488377.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's well-written, well-cast and skillfully directed in every scene, and, at the same time, it doesn't come together with enough impact to be hugely memorable.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/219213_map08q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A joy to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A25638-2005Mar10.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a director, screenwriter and star who have deep roots in the theater, Off the Map is more than anything an actor's film.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/03/11/movies/11map.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It takes a rugged survivalist mentality to sit through 108 minutes of Off the Map, a self-consciously loopy and mystical drama about a family that lives off the map, off the grid, off the land and mostly off their meds in the mangy desert of New Mexico.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules11mar11,2,6341122.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot is minimal, but the film is essentially an acting showcase. Allen is excellent.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/25387_OFF_THE_MAP</url>
         <critic>Patrick Z. McGavin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Any minor flaws Off the Map has are easily forgiven by great acting and beautifully shot landscapes. Campbell Scott does a great job of adapting a stage play (by screenwriter Joan Ackerman) to film as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=4016</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Off The Map feels peculiar and remote, strangled by an air of arty disengagement. The most vivid characters are the earth and the sky, and they both give stellar performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theavclub.com/review_pop.php?review_id=8283</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Campbell Scott's latest foray behind the camera most excels as a subtly observed study of how the dynamics within a close-knit family can shift over time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2003&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117919874&amp;categoryid=1273&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately the film manages a warm, offbeat appeal despite its flaws, and it has real heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A264518</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simmons plays it understated, conveying a sad-sack quality that's more relatable than Charley's irrational catatonia. The movie should have been about him instead.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/issues/2005-03-24/film/film6.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly, it works: The overwhelming natural expanse of the New Mexico desert is perfectly balanced by the psychic space Charley and Arlene create - the space where all the real action takes place.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=45979</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of those American independent films with two chief points to recommend it: the earnest good will of its creators and its determination to be unlike any studio film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1113473155308701.xml</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A beautifully acted if fairly poky coming-of-age story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/40923.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a disconnected, implausible story that aims for a tone of magic realism and falls short on both counts.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=116355&amp;reviewId=17691&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Were it not so soporific, Off the Map could easily drive you off your nut.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0510,hoberman2,61874,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its story meanders and doesn't build, and the pace is deadly.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,310,368</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$50,865</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>10</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>