<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Oswald&amp;#039;s Ghost</name>
   <company>Seventh Art Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robert Stone</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert Stone</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors/>
   <release_date>November 30, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Oswald's Ghost, his vast chronicle of the JFK assassination and its cultural aftermath, Stone uses little-seen footage to assemble the events of Nov. 22, 1963, with a fascinating present-tense density.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20164496,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Veteran conspiracy buffs probably won’t find much of Stone's material particularly new, but Stone’s film does serve as a neat summary for the rest of us while offering a number of intriguing insights into how conspiracy theories work and what they say about specific cultural and political climates.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=291395&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though we had just heard the name Lee Harvey Oswald, I believed he had done it alone. I still do, even more so after watching Robert Stone's meticulously researched, seemingly unbiased summary of the killing and the major conspiracy theories.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/30/2007-11-30_short_takes_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oswald's Ghost impresses as a concise, intelligent and rigorously well-researched piece of work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935467.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Late in the film, Stone interviews Norman Mailer, a one-time conspiracy-believer who eventually wrote a book that tried to get inside Oswald's head, explaining how Oswald's story is America's story. In less than a minute, Mailer describes the documentary Stone should've made.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/oswalds_ghost</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The documentary Oswald’s Ghost initially plays as yet another primer on the assassination of John F. Kennedy and the vilification of Lee Harvey Oswald.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/30/movies/30oswa.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lee Harvey Oswald's guilt or innocence or accomplices are not the point of the film; Stone is more interested in the fact that much about the Kennedy murder is now so shrouded in myth and mystification as to be permanently unknowable, and that that fact alone has gnawed away at the self-confidence of middle-class white America ever since.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/btm/2007/11/29/savages/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While trying to establish whether a conspiracy took place, the film attempts to solve the enigma that was Lee Harvey Oswald.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/10/12/DDP1SNPCP.DTL#flick4</url>
         <critic>Leba Hertz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Riveting yet ultimately unsatisfying documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0748,fox,78475,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a history lesson, Oswald's Ghost is valuable, but don't go expecting any new revelations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11302007/entertainment/movies/gunshots_in_dallas_still_echo_563842.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never really decides whether it wants to concentrate on providing information or sociological analysis, with the result that it fails to fully satisfy on either level.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=YzFtHhdMwzQ1cWrjhQMRQKYrSzsm5phQwYpXd8G7nDBhRndlGp5F!482841917&amp;&amp;rid=10288</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stone covers territory all too familiar to most Americans old enough to remember the JFK assassination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules7dec07,0,5582244.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only obvious question that Oswald’s Ghost raises is: how come Mort Sahl wasn’t in the movie? (If you don’t get that joke, you need to brush up on your Kennedy conspiracy lessons.)</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10438</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,796</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$1,796</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>