<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Over Her Dead Body</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jeff Lowell</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jeff Lowell</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Eva Longoria Parker</actor>
      <actor>Paul Rudd</actor>
      <actor>Lake Bell</actor>
      <actor>Lindsay Sloane</actor>
      <actor>Jason Biggs</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 1, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>95</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This madcap paranormal love triangle is charming on its own terms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/dead-body/review/292187</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the tale may fall short on imagination, the principal actors make Over Her Dead Body livelier than one would expect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-01-31-dead-body_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ensues may be predictable, but the slapstick performances of Rudd and Bell are anything but. They court, they spark, and a few times they catch comic fire.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080201_Here_comes_the_ghost_bride.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Many a comic potentiality is underworked, and the film's prevailing tone is obnoxiously erratic -- surely the supporting eccentrics (Jason Biggs and Lindsay Sloane) aren't supposed to be so off-putting? -- but it rests safe when entrusted to the charisma of its principals.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/caramel-over-her-dead-body-tre-and-more/18261/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Nick Pinkerton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The slapstick is crudely executed. And the movie never makes up its mind regarding how nasty the ghost of Kate is going to play her revenge tactics.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-over-her/294771/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Consider for a moment how this movie might play if it took itself seriously. Would it be better than as a comedy? I suspect so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080131/REVIEWS/801310301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In her imperfectly beautiful way, Bell suggests Carole Lombard. As a comedian, Bell is enough of a distraction that you can forgive all the inanities around her. And there are many.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1142961&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result, while not horrifically bad, is as mediocre a motion picture as you're likely to find in a multiplex this season. It's tough to hate the movie because it doesn't generate enough emotion for that kind of passion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/o/over_her.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For what it is -- a romantic comedy about the rivalry between a jealous ghost and a flaky psychic for the love of a veterinarian -- Over Her Dead Body is not bad.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/02/01/movies/01body.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's said that opposites attract, but for the brief period they're onscreen together in the dire comedy Over Her Dead Body, Eva Longoria Parker and Paul Rudd are one of the more bizarrely mismatched couples in recent memory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/over_her_dead_body</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A stiff of a supernatural comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/349548_overher01q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To be fair, Rudd and Bell are cute and funny in their scenes together, and Rudd salvages a few laughs with his deadpan line readings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/120174450847810.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rudd's talents as a thinking woman's charmer are wasted -- as are those of amiable Jason Biggs in a weak variation on the pop theme of being a gal's gay best friend.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20176575,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For what is essentially a screwball comedy, Over Her Dead Body is surprisingly uninspired, a frothy concept that offers little satisfaction in the way of execution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-over1feb01,0,5257838.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Playing a competitive schemer not unlike her "Desperate Housewives" character, Parker doesn't generate much heat, while Rudd is squandered in a bland role.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/nextweek/32693_OVER_HER_DEAD_BODY.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rudd is an underappreciated comic actor, and his line readings are the best thing in the film, but the bland role barely taps his talent. Amid the rest of the cast's one-note posing, his scenes with a parrot have a spontaneity and wit otherwise in short supply.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=bDHMHvQF3dnQM5LL5TydnsCqQ2SWHlhR7kSk13kD64F2JNJ5t5LD!1690619683&amp;&amp;rid=10576</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even the weakest "Desperate Housewives" episode packs more heat than this tepid romantic comedy-fantasy, whose basic plot gimmick has been done as far back as "The Ghost and Mrs. Muir."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936003.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At some point, this movie must have been a screenplay. But it's an enigma why anyone would bet tens of millions of dollars that people would laugh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02012008/entertainment/movies/longoria_days_journey_into_blight_920935.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Back to Wisteria Lane, Eva, and stay there until we call you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/02/01/2008-02-01_body_doesnt_stand_a_ghost_of_a_chance.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The silver lining in the film is Paul Rudd, who brings some nuance to his character that, given his past work, you can assume was all his doing. Jason Biggs, in his role as Ashley's gay best friend and catering partner, carries out an interesting, if somewhat left-field plot twist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4385/over-her-dead-body.html</url>
         <critic>Cortney Rock</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I like Longoria Parker on "Desperate Housewives" and truly believe she could have a career on the big screen if she promises to never again work with writer-director Jeff Lowell, who perpetrated this offense of a ghost comedy on her and on her otherwise gifted co-stars Paul Rudd and Lake Bell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/14584680/review/18723267/over_her_dead_body</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seriously lacks both romance and comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/02/01/DDJGUP13A.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A hopeless pastiche of timeworn plotlines, hackneyed dialogue and stultifying direction; to call it amateurish is a slap in the face to amateurs everywhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.dead01feb01,0,7664583.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not quite true to say that death is preferable to sitting through Over HerDead Body, but it's a safe bet that if you struggle through this witless romantic comedy the lure of being six feet under will cross your mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/400570.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Few things are more painful to watch than a botched comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080201.wbody01/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kindest context in which to put Over Her Dead Body, which was written and directed by Jeff Lowell, is that of a training film, a public display of people trying to master their craft. The best way to see it is not at all.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120182249396933545.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Where Over Her Dead Body should soar with blistering verbal gymnastics, it limps with empty sass about weight gain and skin blemishes; where it should race with inventive comic set-pieces, it slogs with extended flatulence sequences and gags about lifting overweight dogs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid:585460</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Over Her Dead Body is to romantic comedy what Spam is to meat. But at least with Spam, you get cool packaging.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10988</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>May be the worst romantic comedy I've ever seen, although I hesitate to make such a resolute pronouncement about a movie that's so barely even THERE.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/02/01/over/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,570,127</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$4,025,115</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,977</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>