<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Perfume: The Story of a Murderer</name>
   <company>DreamWorks SKG</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Andrew Birkin</author>
      <author>Bernd Eichinger</author>
      <author>Tom Tykwer</author>
      <author>Patrick Süskind</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Tom Tykwer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>GermanyFranceSpain</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ben Whishaw</actor>
      <actor>Dustin Hoffman</actor>
      <actor>Alan Rickman</actor>
      <actor>Rachel Hurd-Wood</actor>
      <actor>John Hurt</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 29, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>147</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a dark, dark, dark film, focused on an obsession so complete and lonely it shuts out all other human experience. You may not savor it, but you will not stop watching it, in horror and fascination.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070104/REVIEWS/701040301</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most horror movies try to show us the man inside the monster, so we'll empathize with his moral dilemmas or feel his suffering. Perfume: The Story of a Murderer shows us a man who is all monster, whose colossal amorality makes him a potential Messiah or menace to humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=763174&amp;reviewId=22034&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whishaw's oddly charismatic performance makes the despicable Grenouille into an almost sympathetic antihero. The rather astonishing finale will likely have audiences either howling in derision or ardently dissecting afterward. And it must have given the bluenoses at the MPAA fits.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1167875731323660.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is downright repulsive in places, and otherwise pushes the envelope for an art film, but it's a dazzling piece of filmmaking that wins us over with its boldness and artistry.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/298434_perfume05q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The odd conclusion renders it somewhat oblique, but Perfume is a feast for the senses.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134261</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tykwer makes of all this murder and madness a concoction of improbable beauty and rare artistry. "Perfume" is not just the finest film of his career but easily one of the past year's most accomplished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9552</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is to director Tykwer's credit that, although you never come close to understanding Jean-Baptiste, you don't turn your nose up at him, either.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=763174&amp;reviewId=22054</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume is sure to annoy as many moviegoers as it entertains, but at least even the naysayers would find it difficult to argue that film is nothing if not a departure from the ordinary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3362/perfume-the-story-of-a-murderer.html</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a crazy, gorgeous, disturbing, darkly comic horror story about an early-18th-century Frenchman born in a Paris fish market without any odor of his own but with a sense of smell that would make a pack of bloodhounds wail with envy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/483372p-406870c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume: The Story of a Murderer, crosses over from thriller into magic realism for a lavishly staged climax that's a bit much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12272006/entertainment/movies/what_he_nose_can_kill_you_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume misses some of the subtler base notes of Süskind's creepier, more self-aware original, but Whishaw and Tykwer blend the movie into something quite heady in its own bottle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1573720_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Long regarded as unfilmable, Patrick Suskind's 1985 novel "Perfume" has finally reached the screen in a blockbuster production that succeeds reasonably well in achieving what many said was beyond the scope of cinema: conveying the world of scent and smell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=560</url>
         <critic>Bernard Besserglik</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The seductive, sensory prose of Patrick Suskind's bestseller, "Perfume," reaches the screen with loads of visual panache but only intermittent magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931761.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A memorable and outrageous movie, but one more likely to be remembered as a massive folly than a whopping success.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/12/21/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deeply flawed though it may be, Perfume is a challenging motion picture, and one whose impressions are not easily shaken.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/p/perfume.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film, though admirably ambitious, is resolutely earthbound, mired in ick and slime and never more wooden than in the delirious climax.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=285208&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume is a pitch-black period epic of squalor and enterprise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9098</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a noble experiment in pushing the limits of cinema, but Tykwer never achieves true profundity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0652,halter,75392,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ed Halter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume is ultimately an unmistakable failure, but there's a strange majesty to its epic overreaching. It can be faulted for many things, but not for lacking the courage of its convictions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/57069</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Weaves a sensual spell of extraordinary delicacy, then sustains it -- up to a point.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Tom Tykwer (Run Lola Run) and cowriters Andrew Birkin and Bernd Eichinger preserve some of the novel's storytelling flair, and Dustin Hoffman does a swell turn as the antihero's Italian mentor. But despite a fairly spectacular climax, the material's generic limitations eventually catch up with the plot.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30926_PERFUME_THE_STORY_OF_A_MURDERER.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the time Perfume arrives at its ridiculous mass orgy, staged at the gallows where Grenouille is supposed to meet his end, you really would rather see him meet his end than endure a ridiculous mass orgy.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070105-movies-review-perfume,0,4853411.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's simultaneously arty, arcane and nasty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1107106&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Tom Tykwer's lavish and lively screen adaptation of Perfume: The Story of a Murderer is certainly not a stinker, there is something decidedly off about it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070104.perf05nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are sniff movies and there are snuff movies, but Perfume: The Story of a Murderer is both. It has the bouquet of balm and blood. Imagine "Fragrance of the Lambs."</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=763174&amp;reviewId=22045</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tykwer's camera can assault the audience with the rankest of imagery, but not even once does it come close to distilling the actual aroma of the abattoir that was 18th-century France. And for that, I suppose, we should all be thankful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A430972</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's missing is less a sense of the protagonist's inner nose (which is very well-trammeled) as a sense of his inner life, motivation or desire.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-perfume27dec27,0,5252398.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Try as it might to be refined and provocative, Perfume: The Story of a Murderer never rises above the pedestrian creepiness of its conceit.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/12/27/movies/27perf.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This isn't pleasant to watch. Neither is it amusing, intellectually engaging, whimsically fascinating, coldly satirical or painfully poignant, though at any given moment in this erratic film director Tom Tykwer might be trying for one of these conflicting tones.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/01/05/DDG8RNCDRE1.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perfume offers eau de crud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.perfume05jan05,0,4422349.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$2,223,293</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$63,700,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$57,445</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>dustin hoffman</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>dustin hoffman</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>