<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Pray the Devil Back to Hell</name>
   <company>Balcony Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Gini Reticker</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Janet Johnson Bryant</actor>
      <actor>Etweda Cooper</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 7, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This illuminating film by director Gini Reticker and producer Abigail Disney is a much-needed attempt to put the spotlight on a moment of history that still inspires, especially because that moment led to Taylor's exile and to Liberia's election of Africa's first female head of state.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/12/11/DD5R14MQ6P.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If this were a fictional Hollywood movie, it would be criticized for being too upbeat. But sometimes truth is not only stranger than fiction, it's also a whole lot better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1108/p25s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pray the Devil Back to Hell is at once inspiring and horrific.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20081126_Women_of_Liberia_pray_an_end_to_a_war.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gini Reticker's simply made, affecting documentary Pray the Devil Back to Hell reveals how these heroic ordinary women prodded the factions to peace and literally brought down Taylor, a leader of sociopathic cruelty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20237778,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gini Reticker's lucidly impassioned film, filled with strong, eloquent spokeswomen, garnered Tribeca's docu award.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937034.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Pray+the+devil+back+to+hell</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Powerful enough to make even the most cynical believe in the ability of ordinary people to induce political change.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=nk21JWYQz7N06pQ1y1JzfTP7f0t8M9JqZG2nJgJvttQppbsHZ4Jx!-710515805&amp;&amp;rid=11930</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Without their guns, the men prove surprisingly helpless. And when a representative of a larger pan-African community tells them that if they want the women to stop treating them like children, they must behave responsibly, you sense a corner has been turned.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=96534452</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fleet, gripping documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#34038</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the truly heartening international political stories of recent years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-pray14-2008nov14,0,3214898.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gini Reticker's embracing documentary Pray the Devil Back to Hell shows how Taylor got his comeuppance from a coalition of tenacious Christian and Muslim women armed only with matching T-shirts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11072008/entertainment/movies/liberia_doc_fitting_to_a_t_137453.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The longer the film goes on, the more you crave a vaster history of modern Liberia, originally a colony founded by former slaves from the United States.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12559</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overly conventional as a documentary, but it's inspiring as a rebuttal to the declining state of the world at large. It's encouraging to know that the endurance of institutions like marriage and family could hold the key to keeping civilization intact.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/pray_the_devil_back_to_hell</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Peace is a process, not an event," one unnamed activist says toward the end. Amen, sister.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/pray-the-devil-back-to-hell,1151348.html</url>
         <critic>Neely Tucker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reticker offers perhaps a too-narrow focus on this historical moment, but Pray the Devil remembers the golden rule of moviemaking--rather than tell, it shows, and what it shows is quietly affecting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-11-05/film/pray-the-devil-back-to-hell/</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Uplifting, disheartening, inspiring, enraging -- the mind reels while watching the documentary Pray the Devil Back to Hell, even as the eyes water, the temples pound and the body trembles.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/11/07/movies/07pray.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$78,986</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$8,227</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>