<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Premonition</name>
   <company>TriStar Pictures / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Bill Kelly</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Mennan Yapo</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sra Bullock</actor>
      <actor>Julian McMahon</actor>
      <actor>Shyann McClure</actor>
      <actor>Courtney Taylor Burness</actor>
      <actor>Nia Long</actor>
      <actor>Marc Macaulay</actor>
      <actor>Kate Nelligan</actor>
      <actor>Amber Valletta</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 16, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The star and the more overwrought aspects of the plot are mainstream but the philosophical implications will not appeal to those who prefer easily digestible cinematic portions. It's also true that the more deeply one considers the movie's themes and structure, the less sense it makes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/p/premonition.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This slick exercise about a housewife whose spouse might or might not be dead is effective until a downright maudlin close.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933030.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As Premonition zigzags toward its solution it loses its head completely, packing a risible final reel with left-field religious disquisitions and heartfelt warnings against infidelity.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070316-movies-review-premonition,0,2909327.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Had it been easier to comprehend at the beginning, there's no telling how bad Premonition might have been.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/premonition</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At times, Bullock seems as confused by the plot as we are. Even if you cut the writer Bill Kelly and the director Mennan Yapo a lot of slack, there are plot holes galore. May I suggest that it's time to declare a moratorium on movies about time?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0316/p11s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Premonition is both dreary and absurd, suffering from a lack of intrinsic logic and terrible pacing, a one-two punch that kills off any chance of entertainment value.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-03-15-premonition_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With her tetchy screen persona, Sandra Bullock is well served by brainteasers like "The Lake House" and this passable thriller about a woman who seems to be bouncing between two alternate realities.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31246_PREMONITION.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bullock is so good, working hard to pull off the transition from grief-stricken wife and mother to reluctant time traveler, you want to pull for her. So it's possible - not easy, but possible - to overlook the script's inconsistencies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.premonition16mar16,0,2928839.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A supernatural thriller that keeps your attention while failing to hold you in its grip.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/03/16/DDGIGOLBIH1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once Bullock's character clears her head at the top of the thrill ride, Premonition becomes inescapably dull because it is her mental health, not her purposefully dull husband's fate, that interested us.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070316.PREMO16/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Premonition is actually more daring than you might expect. Not bold enough to be memorable, maybe, but just enough to keep you from falling asleep in front of the TV.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/231/story/42196.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Premonition is an odd little thing, with a protagonist in a protracted fugue state and a plot that doesn't know whether its coming or going. Or maybe it does.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=829603&amp;reviewId=22341</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One piece of advice in trying to make sense of it all: Follow the sleepwear, since Bullock cycles through a few garments that clarify which day is which. Another suggestion? Ignore the two-bit psychological and spiritual doggerel with which screenwriter Bill Kelly tries to deepen the meaning of the game.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20014967,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sandra Bullock is a disheveled, grumpy, adorable mess in Premonition,  a psychological thriller that was no doubt pitched as "Medium," only longer and brunette. Or maybe "The Eternal Sixth Sense of the Spotless Groundhog Day."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1127324&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Had the film maintained a tone of kooky, Kafkaesque tragicomedy, narrowing in on Linda's wacko wrestling match with the laws of physics, we might really have had something here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0711,lee,76053,20.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The usually likable Bullock, obstructed by glaring continuity problems and often baffling character motivation, comes across as unsympathetically dazed and confused here, giving the viewer little reason to care about this desperate housewife's puzzling predicament.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8903</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Premonition doesn't know when to stop. The picture can't decide between cheap scares or deep thoughts, so it goes for both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/03/16/premonition/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We never get a sensible explanation for Linda's bizarre double life, or uncover any reason - any reason at all - why Bullock would pick this lazy, patchwork script out of all the ones she surely receives every year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/03/16/2007-03-16_lets_not_do_the_time_warp.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When you awake, it may all seem like a bad dream - but why is your wallet missing $11? Scary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03162007/entertainment/movies/never_mind_the_bullock_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although Premonition is not a frightening movie, it is aimed squarely at an audience of frightened souls.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/03/26/070326crci_cinema_lane?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>They only want us to play that tiresome guessing game: Is it all a dream or is it really happening? Instead, you may find yourself asking: Is this cinema or merely Cinemax?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews-premonition-i-think-i-love-my-wife-and-others/15913/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sloppy, absent-minded Premonition is a giant step backward for Ms. Bullock.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/16/movies/16prem.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a much dumber movie than "The Lake House." In fact, the script is an ungainly mess and ultimately a shaggy-dog story.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/307656_premonition16q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script's vague, silly "explanation" for Linda's experiences -- nature abhors a spiritual vacuum, so weird stuff happens to the faithless -- is the icing on the irritation cake.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286407&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pumped up sound effects play like an overplayed laugh track on a sitcom that just isn't funny and only draws more attention how ineffective the filmmaking is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3591/premonition.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Warren</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a movie only a psychic could love, since a psychic would know to stay home or see "Zodiac" instead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9143</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only Bullock could have foreseen how bad Premonition would turn out to be, she would have spared herself (and us) a lot of agony.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A455701</url>
         <critic>Steve Davis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its biggest failing -- and the ultimate one for a lightweight entertainment such as this -- is that it's a deadly bore from start to finish.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-premonition16mar16,0,1370869.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pay real money to see this feeble fiasco only if you're in the mood for "Groundhog Day" without the laughs.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The real horror here is watching Sandra Bullock drop her big Miss Congeniality smile to A-C-T! She does this by not smiling. What happened to the range she showed in "Crash" and "Infamous?"</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/10311247/review/13826549/premonition</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$47,852,604</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$17,558,689</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,831</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>