<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Prestige, The</name>
   <company>Newmarket Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jonathan Nolan</author>
      <author>Christopher Nolan</author>
      <author>Christopher Priest</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Christopher Nolan</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Hugh Jackman</actor>
      <actor>Christian Bale</actor>
      <actor>Michael Caine</actor>
      <actor>Scarlett Johansson</actor>
      <actor>David Bowie</actor>
      <actor>Rebecca Hall</actor>
      <actor>Andy Serkis</actor>
      <actor>Piper Perabo</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 20, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>128</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>To talk more about the movie's layers is to risk giving away too much. I'll say only that this film confirms Nolan's status as the director whose work I look forward to more than any other.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=F14384751E507FEEF2A1C36FB27845C0.prodapp15_ae_01?id=726275&amp;reviewId=21646</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's prestige is a doozy, both dazzling and preposterous, but if you're watching closely -- as Cutter advises in the film's first few minutes -- it's flawlessly set up.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=283579&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nolan directs the film exactly like a great trick, so you want to see it again the second it's over. I'd call that wicked clever.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/9387671/review/12087204/the_prestige</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A visually stunning, startlingly clever sleight of hand that will have audiences pondering well after the lights go up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-10-19-review-prestige_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Prestige isn't art, but it reaps a lot of fun out of the question, How did they do that?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1547545_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stuffed with hard-working actors, sleek effects and stagy period details, The Prestige, directed by Christopher Nolan from a script he wrote with his brother Jonathan, is an intricate and elaborate machine designed for the simple purpose of diversion.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/10/20/movies/20pres.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Prestige does more than focus on magicians. It is so in love with the romance, wonder and ability to fool of stage illusion that it becomes something of a magic trick in and of itself</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-prestige20oct20,0,1454799.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bale and Jackman inject their reliable charisma into two otherwise very cold fish. Okay, I'll say it: If you see only one magic-at-the-turn-of-the-century movie this year, make it this one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1121124&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Prestige is utterly without pretense. It doesn't want to explore epistemological questions about the nature of perception and memory; it just wants to mess with our heads. And as a wily, slightly sadistic chess game of a movie, it succeeds quite nicely.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2151861</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Take the movie's first words to heart: watch closely. You'll be well rewarded.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15338103/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the film's murky misdirections, it is very enjoyable. That's because Nolan's recreation of the illusionists' backstage world is so marvelously detailed, including as it does revelations of how some of their best tricks are accomplished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1548716,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Prestige traces the course of their bitter feud, as their respective acts of sabotage become ever more deadly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=10967</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Christopher Nolan's The Prestige has just about everything I require in a movie about magicians, except ... the Prestige.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070906/REVIEWS/709060303</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a gorgeous, strange little piece -- but I did find myself wishing it poked fewer aces out its sleeve after urging us to pay such close attention.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1161212108133161.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nolan, who has become an assured, stylish filmmaker in the span of only a few films, keeps the complicated plot spinning.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=726275&amp;reviewId=21643</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has its moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1020/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, there's enough movie magic in The Prestige to keep you guessing, even after the film's over.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.prestige20oct20,0,2496456.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's like "The Illusionist" crossed with a really hard Sudoku.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8875</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>[Nolan is] back in the fine engineering business, crafting a story as intricately designed as a magician's lock, tightly packed with tumblers of deception and issuing a fun challenge to any volunteers in the audience: Just try to pick it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061020.PRESTIGE20/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a lopsided yet absorbing movie in which the director is less drawn to his main characters than to those on the periphery.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0642,foundas,74759,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all its surface dazzle, The Prestige shares with this year's earlier "The Illusionist" a certain core hollowness. Maybe that's a natural consequence of even the best magic shows: You can't help but feel duped.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/54268</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If The Prestige is something of a let down as a magic trick, it's more successful as a tale of obsession. The rivalry between the magicians is brutal and bloody and Bale and Jackman do their best work when they're plotting each other's downfall.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3202/the-prestige.html</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By describing the structure of a great trick in a movie about a great trick, The Prestige makes a promise it can't keep. Its third act is about as convincing as a photo of a cow jumping over the moon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/10-20-2006/entertainment/col/story/463517p-389823c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Many, I suspect, will fall for The Prestige and its blend of one-upsmanship and science fiction. I prefer "The Illusionist," the movie that got here first.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061020-movies-review-prestige,0,4032522.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On the M. Night Shyamalan scale of stupid endings, The Prestige isn't as bad as "The Village" but it's comparable to "Unbreakable."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10202006/entertainment/movies/slight_of_hand_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's plenty going on but never any real magic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/p/prestige.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you can forgive some woeful casting and a plot that is as creakingly thin as an old staircase, you can enjoy director Christopher Nolan's The Prestige.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/289315_prestige20.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Audiences might enjoy this cinematic sleight of hand, but the key characters are such single-minded, calculating individuals that the real magic would be to find any heart in this tale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003254756</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When all is said and done and you get the full explanation of what meant what and who did what to whom, it's not fulfilling at all. It's a magic trick that's all showmanship and craft, but lacking true whimsy, ultimately failing the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9378</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"The Illusionist" also centers on a 19th-century magician, and the elegant contours of its story are even more impressive compared with Nolan's clutter of double and triple crosses.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30473_PRESTIGE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jonathan and Christopher Nolan's adaptation of this novel by Christopher Priest offers three acts of exasperating muddle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/movies/15801020.htm</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Prestige is a trick box with too many false bottoms. Ultimately, the last one simply gives way -- leaving us with a hole, and a little residual darkness, but not much else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/10/20/the_prestige/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The tit-for-tat scenario ought to be wildly entertaining, but the magic is crude, the characters flyweight, and the story protracted and unpleasant.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/23143/index2.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Truth itself is little more than a word in The Prestige, a film that both celebrates the wonder of being fooled and the foolishness of wanting just that.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A411561</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Clearly, director Nolan is aiming for something else. But the delight in sheer gamesmanship that marked his breakout "Memento" doesn't survive this project's gimmickry and aspirations toward "Les Miserables"-style epic passion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931858?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thus, we find ourselves watching an ice-cold movie about competition that contains not a shred of rooting interest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/20/DDGFFLRSBN1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$53,089,891</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$40,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$14,801,808</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,281</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>michael caine</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>