<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Pride</name>
   <company>Lionsgate</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Kevin Michael Smith</author>
      <author>Michael Gozzard</author>
      <author>J. Mills Goodloe</author>
      <author>Norman Vance Jr.</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sunu Gonera</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Terrence Howard</actor>
      <actor>Bernie Mac</actor>
      <actor>Kimberly Elise</actor>
      <actor>Tom Arnold</actor>
      <actor>Bron Fobbs</actor>
      <actor>Alphonso McAuley</actor>
      <actor>Regine Nehy</actor>
      <actor>Nate Parker</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 23, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>104</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pride doesn't have much surprise, but it's a formula picture of genuine feeling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20015579,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Howard, playing an inspirational and resourceful man up against long odds, really is an inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070323-movies-review-pride,0,1762786.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's about black athletes, and they swim. It's as reassuringly uplifting as its predecessors, but the African-American and aquatic elements set it pleasantly apart.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=835358&amp;reviewId=22350&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Inspired by the true story of Ellis, has Hollywood formula practically stitched to its Speedo. But the characters and the actors who play them are so captivating, we're too entertained and charmed to notice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1124602&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether this is all a case of life imitating art or vice versa matters little. Few of these movies aspire to art. What counts is the trajectory of uplift.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0323/p11s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As exasperating as it is conventionally satisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/308625_pride23q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are formulaic moments aplenty in Pride, the "inspired by a true story" tale of Philadelphia swimming coach Jim Ellis, but in its first scenes, at least, it deserves some credit for doing the unexpected.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/pride</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's called Pride, and, while it's neither as socially urgent as "Freedom Writers" nor as danceable and soapy as "Stomp the Yard," it's better acted and tougher to resist</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8988</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A measured, magnificently understated and intense performance by Academy Award nominee Terrence Howard (Hustle &amp; Flow, Crash) as Ellis gives Pride its fire and heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=0F37F84679F5C7090CC067FD88464C8E.prodapp12_ae_01?id=835358&amp;reviewId=22356&amp;startDate=03%2F25%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Worth seeing, not only because it shows how an ordinary man can do something extraordinary, but because it allows audiences the opportunity to watch an extraordinary actor in a performance that could have been rote, but instead is nuanced and intelligent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-03-22-pride_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie serves up the expected ratio of setbacks to triumphs and closes with video footage of the real Jim Ellis. But when sinewy young idealists glide through water to the tune of "I'll Take You There," the heart still leaps.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/22/movies/23prid.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite a second half that feels more routine than its first, Pride is a definite crowd-pleaser.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933100.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is familiar terrain jazzed up by unfamiliar voices--principally Terrence Howard and his high-pitched, singsong drawl. You don't quite know what he's thinking; he might even be demented. But he keeps you watching and guessing.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/29429/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If nothing else, Pride has the best sports-film soundtrack ever--Philly funk and soul, '70s style. And hell, that'll get ya wet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0712,film,76120,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Canned racial uplift and tear-streaked faces abound, though they're offset somewhat by a nicely funky blaxploitation vibe.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31290_PRIDE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sadly, the only aspect of this well-intentioned film that doesn't feel completely formulaic is its refreshingly unromantic picture of an inner-city neighborhood in the early '70s: Life in Nicetown is hard and very, very poor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286672&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pride has little to be proud about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/p/pride.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It follows exactly the same path as both "Glory Road" (except that was basketball) and "Gridiron Gang" (football).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03232007/entertainment/movies/diffrent_strokes_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That Pride ultimately gets to you is more of a surprise than the outcome because it's not very well-constructed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/03/23/DDGLJOPC081.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yeah, the story is corny and tired. But when you aren't rolling your eyes, you'll probably be wiping them dry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/03/23/2007-03-23_pooling_resources_in_pride.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One wishes the makers of Pride had stuck with non-fiction, because their movie reduces Ellis's story to the level of generic sports-flick hokum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070323.wpride23/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If only the screenplay had more going for it than hackneyed homilies and living-in-the-ghetto stereotypes. If only first-time director Sunu Gonera had a surer hand, a knack for something bolder, wilder, goofier.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20070323_Pride_lacks_pride_of_place.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Terrence Howard delivers another solid lead performance and competition swimming is a new arena for such films. Nonetheless, Pride is just plain trite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8926</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Howard seems to be in an altogether different and substantially more idiosyncratic film. When the story calls for him to be Patton, he plays Kurtz.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-pride23mar23,0,2203192.story</url>
         <critic>Sam Adams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Pride had concentrated on a gifted coach's teaching and training techniques, it might have been a contender. Instead, all the overheated melodrama evaporates our rooting interest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.pride23mar23,0,6704559.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pride's story was etched in stone ages ago by mysterious movie powers beyond our understanding, and all the Staples Singers' songs in the world won't keep it from its appointed rounds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A457632</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite Mr. Howard's best efforts in the role, though, the film rarely realizes its subject's potential.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,057,600</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$3,533,300</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,518</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>