<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Chronicles of Narnia: Prince Caspian, The</name>
   <company>Walt Disney Pictures, Walden Media</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>C.S. Lewis</author>
      <author>Stephen Mc</author>
      <author>Feely</author>
      <author>Christopher Markus</author>
      <author>Andrew Adamson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Andrew Adamson</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Georgie Henley</actor>
      <actor>Skar Keynes</actor>
      <actor>William Moseley</actor>
      <actor>Anna Popplewell</actor>
      <actor>Ben Barnes</actor>
      <actor>Peter Dinklage</actor>
      <actor>Warwick Davis</actor>
      <actor>Vincent Grass</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 16, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>140</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A glorious medieval war movie. It's about war as the ultimate pitch of conflict that tries men's souls, and women's, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.caspian16may16,0,1230645.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's pronounced split between violence and softness notwithstanding, Prince Caspian is finally a more polished effort than "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe" and squarely in the tradition of the kind of teenage movies the Disney organization used to make before teens discovered horror and gore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-narnia16-2008may16,0,915250.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even with all the CGI effects, this darkly emotional movie feels like the anti-"Speed Racer." Sure, it's a big-budget spectacle. But it's also the kind of grandly old-fashioned entertainment we don't get enough of anymore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/05/16/2008-05-16_fantasy_war_epic_prince_is_a_worthy_heir-1.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Several shades darker in tone than the previous edition -- which, to be fair, didn't carry the burden of expectation that a sequel must bear -- the return to Narnia still casts a transporting spell.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=11075</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Closer to a straight-ahead medieval battle picture than the fantastical, other-worldly journey depicted in "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe," this new entry is a bit darker, more conventional and more crisply made than its 2005 predecessor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937080.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As portrayed by William Moseley, Skandar Keynes, Georgie Henley and especially Anna Popplewell as Susan, the Pevensies still make for terrific tween protagonists, and Aslan, the majestic mythical lion voiced by Liam Neeson, is still a breathtaking manifestation of the Cat Upstairs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1143812&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exhilarating fantasy adventure marred only by its length and protracted climactic battle scenes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-05-14-prince-caspian_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An elaborately presented feast that will taste familiar to the 'tween and teen audience for whom it is served. The four courses are love, war, faith and humor, served in no canonical order, and sometimes, simultaneously.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080516_Wartime_theme_suits__Narnia_.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In this sequel, magic still reigns but suspending disbelief doesn't come as easily.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/363258_narnia16q.html</url>
         <critic>Athima Chansanchai</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, while not as strong in terms of plotting or character development, Prince Caspian is nevertheless a better cinematic experience than its predecessor, if only because it feels more confident and polished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/c/chronicles_narnia2.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In their refusal to be up-to-the-moment, the Narnia movies are bound to age beautifully, perhaps much more so than the two Shrek films Adamson directed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05162008/entertainment/movies/good_knight__and_good_pluck_111011.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Take away the storming music and grand vistas, and it's all a standard sword-and-sorcery adventure; director Andrew Adamson is more than a journeyman but much less than the visionary Peter Jackson is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8921</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Caspian has a fault, it's that viewers familiar with neither the books nor the first film may have trouble picking up the strands of the story in the early scenes… but in all honesty, how many Lewis neophytes will choose Caspian as their point of entry?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/chronicles-narnia-prince/review/292188</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Next time out, more dwarfs, more Aslan, and definitely more Reepicheep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0517/p25s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Prince Caspian is fairly good fun, and I'm trying to decide whether it was the capable swordplay or Ben Barnes's bedroom eyes that prompted a significant shift in brand loyalty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0820,prince-caspian-loses-some-magic,440998,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>They may make for clunky religious parables, but the Narnia books--and so far, the movies based on them--are wonderful as stories about childhood and its loss.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2191486/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Quite a bit darker than "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe," both in look and in mood. It is also in some ways more satisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/05/16/movies/16narn.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In total effect, Prince Caspian feels a lot more earthbound than "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20200264,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adamson's pulled a more morally nuanced rabbit (or badger, actually) out of his directorial hat this time out, and the result is a far more engrossing film than its predecessor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A623188</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a persistent surface level, one-off quality to the whole business that repels emotional involvement at every juncture and seems stylistically in keeping with Disney's reluctance to greenlight each new Narnia film until the last one has proven itself at the box-office.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4590/the-chronicles-of-narnia-prince-caspian.html</url>
         <critic>Ryan Stewart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Is it a bad thing that Disney has commercialized, denatured and inflated the story to make it indistinguishable from any handsome sword-and-sorcery epic? Perhaps not, for it IS handsome on its grand scale.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/625759.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is more somber and less wondrous in tone than the first film, especially since the lion Aslan (voiced by Liam Neeson), who would have been instrumental in leading the Narnians to victory, has disappeared.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1058/story/533904.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Junkies for dark humor should prep for going cold turkey, despite the efforts of director Andrew Adamson to spice things up with combat and a rivalry between Caspian and Peter (good on Moseley for showing some backbone) that Lewis never imagined.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/17033272/review/20818407/chronicles_of_narnia_prince_caspian</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Prince Caspian is elaborate filmmaking, all right. It's the magic of the human touch that's missing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/05/16/caspian/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Significantly better than the first film or, say, the first two Harry Potters, but we still can’t love it as much as we do the books. That said, if they keep improving at this pace, Dawn Treader should be a fantastic experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133186</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This fusty sequel lacks the narrative complexity of "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe" and squanders both its first-rate computer graphics and its sturdy international cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33162_CHRONICLES_OF_NARNIA_PRINCE_CASPIAN.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I can't condemn it outright, but damned if I can remember anything (aside from Izzard's performance) that would make me recommend it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10966</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The wee mousie is fun, all right, yet like the occasionally ragged editing, the fun just gets haphazardly wedged in.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080516.wnarnia16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Roughly the same as the first in terms of quality and style. It delivers without much visual dynamism, and with a determined emphasis on combat. In the 1951 novel the climactic battle between the good Narnians and the bad Telmarines lasted a few pages. The film version of the same battle feels like "The Longest Day."</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-chronicles/419339/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wish I could be more enthusiastic about Prince Caspian, an honorable and attractive adventure for children and families. But scenic beauty and spirited action can't conceal its dramatic defects.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121089374818396985.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The more obvious special effects are downright hokey, such as a weird swirling water creature who looks like something out of a toilet cleaner commercial. As the outcome of all the sword-flinging and catapult-launching is never in question, it's hard to stay engaged with the movie once the fighting begins.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/137013</url>
         <critic>Jennie Yabroff</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, it's an absence of personality that does the film in. The creatures remain beautifully designed and Narnia still looks like a colorful, inviting place, but it feels as lifeless as the fantastical anyworlds found on glittery unicorn posters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_chronicles_of_narnia_prince</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Such a clunkerama that it made me rethink all the nice things I wrote about its predecessor, "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Could the same people have made both films?</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47037/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Exactly one minute longer than its predecessor, but it's a dragged-out exercise, with no epic scale and no spirit worth talking about.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/05/15/DDIS10M921.DTL</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$141,621,490</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$225,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$55,034,805</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,929</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>