<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Proof</name>
   <company>Miramax Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Auburn</author>
      <author>Rebecca Miller</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>John Madden</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Gwyneth Paltrow</actor>
      <actor>Anthony Hopkins</actor>
      <actor>Hope Davis</actor>
      <actor>Jake Gyllenhaal</actor>
      <actor>Gary Houston</actor>
      <actor>Anne Wittman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 16, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>100</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paltrow gives the performance of the year, and perhaps of her career, in this extraordinary and powerful dissection of genius, jealousy, madness and serenity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7965</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extraordinary thriller... The film centers on two remarkable performances, by Gwyneth Paltrow and Hope Davis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050922/REVIEWS/509220307/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's so fluid and cinematic that it's hard to even envision how the piece worked on stage.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/241832_proof23q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proof is on the side of the lost, blessed souls. Paltrow, as alluring and reassuring as ever, emphasizes the blessedness in the isolation of genius, giving a new dimension to a complex role. New, true and thrilling--she is the Catherine that Proof was waiting for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1098933,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The material is intellectual, but the treatment is not. Proof is a stirring motion picture that challenges our views on a great many things about life, some of which we take for granted. And, by opening up the play, Madden has made it less talky and more cinematic without losing the quintessential elements that made it such a success on stage.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/p/proof2005.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tasteful, thoughtful fare that entertains without ever speaking down to the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/112738707736470.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But despite less-than-ideal casting of the male roles, and a tendency to soften the Pulitzer Prize-winning work's thorny humor with a more sober tone, director John Madden has woven together an elegant, intelligent drama of a breed increasingly rare in mainstream American movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928007?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>David Rooney</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Against considerable odds and despite a shaky start, Proof proves itself in every area.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-proof16sep16,0,3703352.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But at its highest level of ambition, Proof fails to deliver. The film becomes a psychological whodunit where Catherine is shown to be either a martyr to her father or else his intellectual equal. None of it is terribly convincing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0916/p11s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proof proves undeniably that the intimacy of a stage play can be re-created powerfully on screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-09-15-proof_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hopkins plays "Hopkins," and the buff, terribly miscast Gyllenhaal will be convincing only to viewers who've never set foot on a university campus. What makes it worth seeing, however, is the extraordinary chemistry between the atypically raw and unguarded Paltrow and Davis, a fabulously talented actress once again testing her range with a performance unlike any she's given in the past.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=45473</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Very, very faithful to Proof the play.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=415619&amp;reviewId=19096</url>
         <critic>Christine Dolen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once you get past that golden swag and curtain of hair, Paltrow's performance is devastating, cutting to the pith and marrow of parent-child relations. The other actors in this stagebound movie fare less well.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=415619&amp;reviewId=19076</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proof is proof that you can drain most of the juice out of a play and still have an enjoyable night at the movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=6032</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The source material has undergone some sentimental softening, though Hope Davis, as the heroine's sister, does a swell job of making sanity seem obnoxious.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28526_PROOF_MADDEN.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To play for an audience of one that is only a few feet away is different in concentration and shade from playing in the theater, and Madden, though the script lags a bit, has nonetheless helped his actors to render what were once theater scenes as film sequences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20051010&amp;s=kauffmann101005</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paltrow is pretty commanding, even if Madden pushes things toward airlessness by keeping the camera so tight.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/22/AR2005092202064.html</url>
         <critic>Nelson Pressley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its characters are complex and engaging, its central mystery pulls the action forward at a clip, and the performances by Paltrow and Davis are excellent. At the same time, it's a little too slick.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gwyneth Paltrow is triumphant in this somewhat derivative and overly stage-bound film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001022037</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hopkins' increasing disconnection with his fellow actors and the material nearly sabotages Proof, an otherwise-respectable adaptation of David Auburn's Pulitzer Prize-winning play.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/40658</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Engrossing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3552&amp;Sumbit.x=67&amp;Sumbit.y=7</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Proof, Paltrow plays yet another young woman who is being gnawed at by termites of instability, only this time out, her performance, rather than startling, is merely competent: earnest and overly familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1104943_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You never believe that Paltrow's character is insane, even when she herself does. She has too sturdy a core.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.proof30sep30,1,3019629.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Loses something in its translation to celluloid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A295907</url>
         <critic>Steve Davis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result, like so many stout travellers from stage to screen, is respectable. Stolidly, bloodlessly, yawningly respectable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050930/PROOF30/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who knew a drama about numbers could be so thrilling?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/346850p-295886c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proof will put a lot of viewers right back where they left off in 12th-grade calculus: asleep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/52732.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paltrow does an excellent job as the shy loner, affecting youthful, sulky mannerisms without resorting to stereotype. Anthony Hopkins, meanwhile, brings both gravitas and dark humour as Catherine's mentally ill father, while Jake Gyllenhaal makes for an effective, if buff, maths geek.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=132288</url>
         <critic>Anna Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A goopy Gwyneth Paltrow movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/23/DDG0MERFGA6.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Proof isn't just a movie about mathematics; it's a mathematical movie. The scenes may as well have been laid out by diagram.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/09/16/proof/index.html?sid=1389804</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Madden honors the play's roots; he has not made the mistake of opening it up with a lot of obvious visual expansions. But the story's genial unpretentiousness has been darkened and weighed down, and what's left is less than prime.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050916-movies-review-proof,0,4903937.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The image of Gwyneth Paltrow looking anguish-stricken has become such a cinematic meme that it hardly bodes well for Proof that it opens with this sight.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2285</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Madden directed Paltrow in the play on the London stage, but he does his "Shakespeare in Love" goddess no favors by filling the screen with big close-ups that betray the theatrical origins of the piece and drain the movie of life and urgency. Proof hasn't been filmed at all -- it's been embalmed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6142637?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ensues is a devout communal effort, tricked out with various hops through time and space, to make us forget that it was a piece of theatre in the first place. Needless to say, the attempt is in vain.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050919crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>John Madden's competent, monotonous film version, not exactly stagebound but hardly freewheeling, only underscores its mechanical nature.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0537,lim1,67755,20.html</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I wish I could report the arrival of an impressive movie, but this one, for all its ostensibly big ideas about mathematics and wounded minds, struck me as an elaborate pretext for a synthetic love story.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's funny how movies about smart people often play so dumb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/16/movies/16proo.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$7,535,331</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$193,840</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>2</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>gwyneth paltrow</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_actor>anthony hopkins</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>