<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Puffy Chair, The</name>
   <company>Roadside Attractions</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Mark Duplass</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jay Duplass</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Mark Duplass</actor>
      <actor>Kathryn Aselton</actor>
      <actor>Rhett Wilkins</actor>
      <actor>Bari Dahan</actor>
      <actor>Gerald Finnegan</actor>
      <actor>Julie Fischer</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 2, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>85</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ripe with characters and events reflecting the psychic travails of today's young adults.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/284214_limited08.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a film culture in which contrived tomfoolery and overinflated emotions stifle in their effort to provide comedy and romance, something as light and precise as The Puffy Chair feels like more than an exception; it feels like fresh air.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1149117945180610.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Puffy Chair is the funniest, saddest and most emotionally honest "romantic comedy" to come along in years, even if I've yet to encounter many over the age of about 35 who like the film, or even get it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13944/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all so goddamn realistic and reminiscent of real-life love (and how often does that happen onscreen?) that The Puffy Chair would be hell to watch if it weren't so funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A369893</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The scenes feel real and both Duplass and Aselton do a great job duking it out. The Puffy Chair combines great original comedy and solid acting to make a fun movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=6797</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A charming, if limited, romantic comedy that examines post-collegiate angst with easy, unself-conscious humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1108562&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A pointed and nicely observed screenplay that guides us on an often funny journey through familiar terrain made fresh by their off-center sensibility and three fine performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-puffy7jul07,0,2222573.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Under the cover of what seems like a charmingly slapdash style, the Duplass brothers have created a disarmingly shrewd movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/02/DDGJVJ5D911.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Combines a wise script with funky performances, especially by Aselton, who could give Jennifer Aniston a run for her money.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/laughter_on_a_road_to_recliner_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Billed as a dark comedy, brothers Jay and Mark Duplass' shaggy, ultra-low-budget tale of a tense New York-to-Atlanta road trip is more accurately a relationship-hell drama peppered with strangled laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=282296&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie may not amount to much, but the genial tone and exceptionally good performances from the three leads make for a winning debut by the Duplass brothers.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/28783_PUFFY_CHAIR</url>
         <critic>Reece Pendleton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Funny Ha Ha," Andrew Bujalski's casually raw 2002 faux–cinema vérité indie about a bunch of shiftless twentysomethings, The Puffy Chair uses simple, unadorned dialogue and intimate, off-the-cuff performances to get at the underlying issues.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0631,various,74043,20.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it would be accurate to call the film a comedy, the Duplasses are trying to wrestle something closer to Chekhov than to farce out of the lives of these semi-likable, highly recognizable people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/08/03/btm/index3.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ostensibly a road-trip farce, Chair really depicts the highway to man-child hell: The laughs come from the gulf between how mature the characters think they're being and what emotional toddlers they are.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7637</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enjoyable road movie that feels both comfortable and completely fresh.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060922-movies-review-puffy,0,1561603.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a slacker flick, it's a relationship pic, it's a road movie all under the same hood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20061208.wpuffy08/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its fidelity to its characters’ view of the world -- although they are presumably college graduates, they seem never to have read a book or expressed an opinion -- is more a liability than a virtue. The Puffy Chair is as modest as their ambitions and as narrow as their curiosity about the world beyond themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/08/04/movies/04puff.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$194,523</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$26,029</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>7</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>