<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Reader, The</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Hare</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Stephen Daldry</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
      <origin>Germany</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ralph Fiennes</actor>
      <actor>Kate Winslet</actor>
      <actor>David Kross</actor>
      <actor>Lena Olin</actor>
      <actor>Bruno Gan</actor>
      <actor>Alexra Maria Lara</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 10, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>123</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Winslet deserves an Oscar for her amazing performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/The-Reader</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kross and Winslet's intense performances and Daldry's deliberately placid control of tone make the material work as a love (and hate) story as well as a metaphor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_reader</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader is significant because -- like another film opening today, "Valkyrie" -- it asks us to see not just the Jews but the whole German people as victims of the Holocaust, and to view Nazism as more a product of explicable ignorance than inexplicable evil.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/393397_reader25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The crucial decision in The Reader is made by a 24-year-old youth, who has information that might help a woman about to be sentenced to life in prison, but withholds it. He is ashamed to reveal his affair with this woman. By making this decision, he shifts the film's focus from the subject of German guilt about the Holocaust and turns it on the human race in general.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081223/REVIEWS/812239989</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a sense of ambiguity at the core of The Reader that makes it all the more brutal, all the more honest in its deflowering of love and what one imagines love ought to be instead of what it too often is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A719066</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With this film Daldry, previously the director of "Billy Elliot" and "The Hours," proves himself the screen's reigning master at showing passion thwarted or repressed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20081223_The_story_of_a_an_entanglement_across_decades.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An immaculately crafted, splendidly acted drama with a message at its core of forgiveness and humanity. It's also blatantly manipulative, and, upon reflection, rather banal. In other words, it's the epitome of Oscar bait and almost serves as a step-by-step guide to creating such a beast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/12/crafty_stepbystep_manipulation.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This coming-of-age portion is the less interesting half, though it has the more interesting Michael. We have seen Fiennes play an emotionally detached introvert so often that he brings nothing new to the role, apt though he is.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/36897-review-the-reader</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fiennes brings to the role a shimmering subtlety.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1213/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader is closer to a near miss than a rousing success but, on balance, this is still worth seeing for those who enjoy complexity and moral ambiguity within the context of a melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1414</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Winslet's fierce, unerring portrayal goes beyond acting, becoming a provocation that will keep you up nights.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/23318567/review/24991176/the_reader</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the effort is uneven, it's a well-acted romance that becomes a less compelling courtroom drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-12-09-the-reader_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An engaging period drama. But German postwar guilt is not the most winning subject matter for the holiday season.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-the-reader-1003917714.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is only, frankly, the strength of Winslet's performance that rises above conventional surroundings and makes The Reader the experience it should be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-reader11-2008dec11,0,7585074.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The revelation that Winslet’s character is a war criminal is the centerpiece of The Reader, but surrounding the Holocaust morality play is another story that’s more modestly scaled and, in this age of unashamed romance between older women and younger men, more contemporary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/081225/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bernhard Schlink's highly regarded novel "The Reader" receives a graceful, absorbing screen adaptation by director Stephen Daldry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/the-reader,1154621.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is notable for its nice performances, its handsome photography, and its very active music. If the preceding praise sounds generic, so is the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20245348,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the script works in a couple of pages of collegiate-level ethical debate about "the question of German guilt," what the movie is really interested in is the question of German sex. So think of it as "Schindler's Lust."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12102008/entertainment/movies/death_camp_for_cutie_143454.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader doesn't do enough to explore the guilt and betrayal the adult Michael feels over the acts of his elders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/824509.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The epitome of middle-brow 'quality' drama -- admirable within its limitations, but Bernard Schlink's Oprah Winfrey Book Club-approved book wasn't exactly literature, as this isn't exactly cinema.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135209</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provocatively intentioned, The Reader is a movie worth seeing - the kind of film you'll think about for days afterward. But when all is said and done, you're likely to wonder why the impact wasn't greater still.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/12/10/2008-12-10_the_reader_worth_seeing_leaves_you_wanti.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is neither about the Holocaust nor about those Germans who grappled with its legacy: it's about making the audience feel good about a historical catastrophe that grows fainter with each new tasteful interpolation.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/12/10/movies/10read.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cast is superb: especially Kate Winslet, who transcends, by far, the limits of her character's narrow soul. Yet The Reader remains schematic, and ultimately reductive.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader can feel stilted and abstract: the film's only flesh-and-blood characters spend half the movie separated. But its emotional impact sneaks up on you. The Reader asks tough questions, and, to its credit, provides no easy answers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/171180</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Faithful both to the novel's plot and to its higher aspirations. This is not an entirely good thing. On the other hand -- and somewhat surprisingly -- it is not an entirely bad thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1865533,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So why, despite everyone's best efforts, does all this bigness seem so small and unfocused and simply not up to the task?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081211.wreader1212/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film made with high aspirations and more than the usual commitment but one that, after an arresting beginning, changes into a passive rumination.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/12/11/DD5P14LH3B.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like many narrative filmmakers who walk on their tippy-toes when dealing with the Holocaust, neither Daldry nor Hare seems eager to make the material his own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-12-10/film/winslet-and-fiennes-the-reader-takes-the-long-and-oscar-worthy-road-to-redemption/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader feels weighty, all right; but it's an unsatisfying kind of weight, and Fiennes' presence, as the grown-up Michael, doesn't help much.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/12/10/the_reader/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stephen Daldry's film is sensitively realized and dramatically absorbing, but comes across as an essentially cerebral experience without gut impact.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117939125.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether the source material or Hare's tinkering is to blame for the fact that the story keeps the viewer at arm's length, the end result is still the same: A film that's technically superb, yet still falls short of true greatness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/reader/review/296276</url>
         <critic>Jason Buchanan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Can a formidable actress redeem a pile of solemn erotic kitsch? Kate Winslet answers that one as honestly as she can in the film version of Bernhard Schlink's 1995 novel "The Reader."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-thereader-review-1225dec26,0,7333411.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After a sensuous introductory act, The Reader descends into a series of dismaying contradictions regarding the moral toxins of the Holocaust - which still pollute postwar Germany.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12629</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Reader is ponderously self-important and smugly Socratic, brimming with unfinished sentences and pregnant pauses; if a single character would only say what he thinks, the movie would be over in 30 minutes</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-li.reader25dec25,0,3693371.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For those who think of cinema as dramatic roughage, The Reader should prove sufficiently indigestible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/12/15/081215crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It appears that the filmmakers have taken Hannah Arendt's notion of the "banality of evil" way too literally.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/52914/index4.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slow-acting poison. For the first third of the movie, you'll experience a not-unpleasant tingling in the extremities, giving way to an encroaching torpor. An hour in, your pupils will have shrunk to pinholes, and by the time the closing credits roll, you'll be capable only of a dim longing for the defibrillation paddles. Who would have thought a movie about a beautiful, frequently naked female Nazi could be so dull?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2206513/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The shallowest "serious" film to be reeling this year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11426</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$34,192,652</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$33,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$179,970</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>