<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Redacted</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Brian De Palma</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Brian De Palma</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Kel O&amp;#039;Neill</actor>
      <actor>Ty Jones</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Stewart Sherman</actor>
      <actor>Izzy Diaz</actor>
      <actor>Rob Devaney</actor>
      <actor>Patrick Carroll</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>November 16, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Palma's screenplay is outstanding, and he draws wonderfully naturalistic performances from his youthful cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9704&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result of the film is shocking, saddening and frustrating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071115/REVIEWS/711150303/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>He intercuts documentary sequences from a French news crew and also includes Arab website footage of insurgents and YouTube confessions from soldiers who witnessed a barbarous act, which we also see, involving the platoon and a young Iraqi girl. The concept is audacious but the actors are too theatrical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1116/p15s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is by turns strident, obvious, righteously angry and inspired.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=291272&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Palma is extreme, visceral, usually in bad taste but almost always riveting. De Palma's Redacted, a no-budget fake documentary that imagines the circumstances behind a real rape and murder of a civilian girl committed by US troops in Iraq, is a piece of anti-war propaganda whose aims I don't agree with, but it jolted me nonetheless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/11162007/entertainment/movies/battle_scarred_600609.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Love it, hate it, but be sure to watch it, because this odd and disturbing picture is as different as the war it reflects, and that difference is vast enough to seem profound.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071116.wredacted16/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It isn't elegiac, but enraged. It doesn't look back with sorrow, but forward in dread. And it's made with a clear intention - to stop the Iraq war.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/16/DD9CTB7AB.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Redacted is a bristling act of protest that obliterates a target it isn't aiming for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.redacted30nov30,0,6578068.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Redacted is hell to sit through, but I think De Palma is bravely trying to imagine his way inside an atrocity, and that he’s onto something powerful with his multisided approach.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/11/19/071119crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Redacted pretty successfully sustains a dual level of hysteria (in its content) and disinterest (in its film-long framing devices). It's an amazingly vigorous work for a filmmaker who turns 67 on Sept. 11... The movie is a cry of national shame; for De Palma, it's a new badge of honor for a wily old vet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1658403,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone who sees the suffering faces of the victims in "Casualties" and "Redacted" knows that De Palma not only despairs over what he’s showing us but implicates his own medium--his own male gaze--in the crimes against nature.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/40643/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a manipulator of images and emotions, De Palma has few equals, and this is his most gripping film in at least a decade. Viewed simply as cinema and not as political rhetoric, it's often a kick in the guts -- even when it makes you roll your eyes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/119749841576860.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its shortcomings, Redacted is nevertheless a film brimming with spontaneity and fury, and in a season of often-ambiguous films about the war in Iraq, there is a lot to be said for this kind of combustible energy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A577014</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Under De Palma's cool disconnection is an anger, and it's this anger that drives his act of political theater.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/341590_redacted30q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like so many of his movies, Redacted is difficult to watch but queasily fascinating.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-redacted/251961/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Lions for Lambs," Redacted is more significant in its sense of purpose than its uneven execution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/11/16/2007-11-16_short_takes_more_movies_out_this_week-1.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brian De Palma's Redacted doesn't quite work as a movie. But it works as SOMETHING.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/09/10/toronto3/index1.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most authentic thing about Redacted is the rage with which it was made.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0746,hoberman,78319,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As an expression of from-the-gut anti-war rage, Redacted is admirable, but as art, it's undercooked.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/redacted</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deeply felt but dramatically unconvincing "fictional documentary" -- inspired by the March 2006 rape and killings by U.S. troops in Mahmoudiya, south of Baghdad -- has almost nothing new to say about the Iraq situation and can't make up its mind about how to package its anger in an alternative cinematic form.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934538.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>DePalma's movie offers its own doctoring and processing, without delivering an ounce of real humanity - good or bad - in the bargain.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071116_Redacted___.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It shows rare courage in protesting the widespread abuse of innocent Iraqis, but its pseudodocumentary form is full of awkward misfires (such as a protracted use of theme music from Barry Lyndon) and its acting is often terrible.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32428_REDACTED.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem here, which vitiates the picture's ingenuity and causes it, finally, to sink like a stone, is in the physical execution of the material.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4248/redacted.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>De Palma is incapable of making a dull movie, but poor performances and a see-sawing tone make this an unsatisfying experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135254</url>
         <critic>Ian Freer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>if you're trying to make us believe we're watching "reality" by using a faux documentary style, you need actors who never look like they are acting, and this is where Redacted stumbles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/41887</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its formal novelty aside, Redacted rarely hits the audience with a genuine shock or a clarifying insight. It churns through a set of ideas and emotions that are confusing and unpleasant, to be sure, but also, by now, dispiritingly familiar.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/11/16/movies/16reda.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all of De Palma's studious multimedia trickery -- a valid, even inspired idea -- Redacted is so naive it's an embarrassment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20162038,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's moral commentary is De Palma redux: same old Brian enjoying the peeping, bringing us into the guilt zone, then saying shame on all of us.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141221&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By any rational standard, this film is kind of a mess. Even if you agree with its politics, you will probably weep at the ineptitude of it all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-redacted16nov16,0,4199081.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Americans are portrayed with varying degrees of loathsomeness, but there's not much variety in the film. It's all an awful aberration.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119517337319395051.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$65,388</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$5,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$25,628</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>15</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>