<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Red Doors</name>
   <company>Polychrome Pictures LLC</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Georgia Lee</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Georgia Lee</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tzi Ma</actor>
      <actor>Jacqueline Kim</actor>
      <actor>Elaine Kao</actor>
      <actor>Freda Foh Shen</actor>
      <actor>Kathy Shao-Lin Lee</actor>
      <actor>Mia Riverton</actor>
      <actor>Jayce Bartok</actor>
      <actor>Rossif Sutherl</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 8, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Georgia Lee never leaves any doubt that the bonds of ethnic family devotion are a charm against any woe more serious than an engagement to the wrong white guy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1532067_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gentle, pleasant film about people you genuinely like.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/09/22/DDGUAL9FMJ1.DTL#flick3</url>
         <critic>G. Allen Johnson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A peppy if uneven charmer with a fetchingly wistful edge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14533/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Following Woody Allen, Ang Lee and any number of sitcoms, Georgia Lee constructs her well-shot, well-written film around three daughters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-capsules22sep22,0,6352586.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well-told and charming, debuting writer-helmer Georgia Lee's comedy-drama Red Doors is big on heart but never sappy. Without overdoing the quirk factor or the melodrama, Lee shows a sure feel for family dynamics, and her light touch brings out the best in the ensemble's lovely, understated performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001052677</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Packs five films' worth of drama, crises and revelations into one, and often lapses into sitcom triteness.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?tvobjectid=282747&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's enough affection and insight here to make Lee's next movie worth watching for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/450513p-379034c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Think of Red Doors as a promise, and hope that Georgia Lee keeps it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9285</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Everything you'd expect from a frosh-indie effort: stilted dialogue, oversimplified relationships, sitcommy goofiness, and cringe-inducing romances. And yet Red Doors is so well-meaning, with such obvious affection for its characters, that it pleases nonetheless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0636,levine,74390,20.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This agreeable, lightweight movie, written and directed by Georgia Lee, turns the malaises of a suburban family into bittersweet farce that teeters between cheeky humor and surface pathos.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/09/08/movies/08door.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Predictable but sincere.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/29584_RED_DOORS</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film about a family billed as "bizarrely dysfunctional" – is a pleasant enough experience. However, it probably could have used a little more of the bizarre or dysfunctional to spice things up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=7607</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lightly feminist, good-naturedly comic sketch of a Chinese-American family in crisis. But despite pic's earnestness and obvious good intentions, narrative elements, carefully set forth though they may be, fall back on overfamiliar, underdeveloped tropes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927154?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Ronnie Scheib</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script falls victim to the stereotypes and clichés so often found in movies about Asian-American families. Still, Lee shows talent, although it might take a feature or two before she finds her own voice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/entertainment/movies/red_doors_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ma, who portrayed the stone-faced General in the Coen brothers' comedy "The Lady Killers," once again plays his role largely silent. As the despondent Ed, Ma says more with a few facial expressions &amp; twitches than most performers could hope to with a three-page monologue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=3077</url>
         <critic>Scott Warren</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$97,848</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$35,050</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>