<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Religulous</name>
   <company>Lionsgate</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Larry Charles</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Bill Maher</actor>
      <actor>Jose Luis De Jesus Mira</actor>
      <actor>Steve Berg</actor>
      <actor>Andrew Newberg</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 3, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>101</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>He's a bombs-away provocateur, and in Religulous, Maher's blasphemous detonation of all things holy and scriptural, he doesn't really pretend to play fair. He's like Lenny Bruce with an inquiring mind and a video camera.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20230120,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You may very well hate it, but at least you've been informed. Perhaps you could enjoy the material about other religions, and tune out when yours is being discussed. That's only human nature.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081002/REVIEWS/810020306</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The results are often as surprising as they are funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.religulous03oct03,0,6687431.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a rare film that can simultaneously crack you up and send a chill down your spine. Worth seeing -- even for believers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135987</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What he does do finally in this funny, refreshing movie is assert how unrestrained religiosity could guarantee the "end days" many of his subjects admit to looking forward to.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/09/30/2008-09-30_religulous_is_bill_maher_at_his_best.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though fashioned as popular entertainment with laughs, light moments, and mostly humorous segments, Religulous is as serious as a disapproving Jehovah about its mission to upend our rote allegiance to blind religious faith.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A679774</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Those with a taste for irreverent humor and clear-eyed analysis will find it funny, enlightening and disturbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-09-30-religulous_N.htm?loc=interstitialskip</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maher's sense of humor deserts him in the end, though, when in an apocalyptic montage of fire and hate (bin Laden, Pat Robertson), he suggests all religions are equally bent on destruction of the Earth. It's fatuous to suggest that the Iraq war was launched because of religion or that belief in the Book of Revelation is the same as organizing terrorist attacks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10012008/entertainment/movies/omigod__131506.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maher can be a smartass, but his attempts to apply reason to religion are more a challenge than a threat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15506607/review/23356376/religulous</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stylistically, Religulous is very much like a Michael Moore documentary, in that most of the scenes have a comic structure, end with a punch line and are designed to make Maher-the-interviewer look sane and rational while his subject comes off as a complete fool.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/381532_relig03q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To the film's credit, Maher never engages in Michael Moore-style gotcha tactics, but rather asks questions that raise more questions, in the form of a Socratic dialogue. To believers expecting a blind hatchet job, this will prove both thought-provoking and a bit disarming; skeptics may be surprised (as Maher is) by the occasionally smart replies to his queries.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938034.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Religulous</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As he delivered his climactic sermon in the Israeli desert, I murmured, "Amen, brother." Religulous is a religious experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/51152/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Was Maher afraid he might muddy his clownish jape if he actually brought into the mix a learned theologian?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1004/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a shocking anger and force.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/10/movie_review_religulous_1.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fairly entertaining bash, with a travelogue vibe established by director Larry Charles ("Borat"). It’s also smug as all hell.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-religulous/640392/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While even believers can support Maher's skepticism, when he denounces the faithful in sweeping absolutes at film's end, he sounds as absolutely certain as those he has mocked for the previous 100 minutes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20081002_Bill_Maher_demands_proof__What_he_gets_as_he_spans_the.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maher makes Michael Moore look incredibly likable in comparison.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/10/02/DDE81391L1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A major disappointment because here, unlike on "Real Time," Maher aims for laughs instead of insight--and aims low.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/081002/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the most part Mr. Maher is an equal-opportunity denigrator, but it's worth noting that humor fails him when the subject is Muslim fundamentalism. It's hard to make light of what frightens us.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122298339529899629.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By focusing so narrowly on religious fundamentalists and bigots while ignoring any spiritual dimension to religion, the film is not only being disingenuous but limits its audience to non-believers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11607</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with the movie, whose title compresses "religious" and "ridiculous" into a single word, isn't that it milks more than one sacred cow but that it does so with minimal subtlety and intelligence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1350</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bill Maher's one-man stand-up attack on religious fundamentalism is a dog that has more bark than bite--a skeptical, secular-humanist hounding of the hypocrites, amusingly annotated with sarcastic subtitles and clips from cheesy biblical spectacles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-10-01/film/bill-maher-makes-an-adolescent-case-against-religion-in-religulous-muslim-comics-play-it-safe-in-allah-made-me-funny/</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Much of Mr. Maher's film is extremely funny in a similarly irreverent, offhanded way. Some true believers -- at least those who have a sense of humor about their faith -- may even be amused. But most will not.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/10/01/movies/01reli.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The bulk of Religulous is a passionate but misguided attempt by Maher to stimulate the 16 percent of the American population who deem themselves non-religious into standing up and being counted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/709847.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More rant than rollick, it's just ain't funny enough.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081003.wreligulous03/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The lack of insightful commentary keeps the spotlight focused on Maher. That's not restraint; it's a missed opportunity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4759/religulous.html</url>
         <critic>Eric Kohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film has a habit of cutting away from interviews for Maher's commentary during the drive to the next location. You can see him trying to work the car for a laugh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11384</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maher's too smart to make a movie this dumb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/religulous</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though he claims to be a seeker, someone who "has to find out" why believers believe, Maher sets out not after answers but cheap laughs that preach, so to speak, to the converted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-religulous3-2008oct03,0,1002859.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the rules of satire is that you can't mock things you don't understand, and Religulous starts developing fault lines when it becomes clear that Maher's view of religious faith is based on a sophomoric reading of the Scriptures and that he doesn't understand that some thoughtful people actually do believe in some sort of spiritual life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=%20%20%201142445&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Neely Tucker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>His scattershot and ad hominem attacks against many different forms of religious hypocrisy don't add up to a coherent critique, and he's not qualified to provide one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2008/10/02/maher/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$13,011,160</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$2,500,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$3,428,633</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>502</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>