<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Reno 911!: Miami</name>
   <company>Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Ben Garant</author>
      <author>Thomas Lennon</author>
      <author>Kerri Kenney</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ben Garant</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ben Garant</actor>
      <actor>Thomas Lennon</actor>
      <actor>Kerri Kenney</actor>
      <actor>Niecy Nash</actor>
      <actor>Mary Birdsong</actor>
      <actor>Cedric Yarbrough</actor>
      <actor>Danny DeVito</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 23, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>84</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is not high art. It might not qualify as low art. But it is 90 minutes or so during which people can put their brains on the shelf and enjoy a few laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070223-movies-review-reno,0,3623059.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Esposito</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This low-rent, nonsense cop business filled me with a nostalgic twinge. I didn't know I wanted the "Police Academy" series resurrected with a lot more hilarity, but I'm glad somebody did it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9500</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reno 911's anti-heroes are doomed, deluded losers, but they engender a strange sympathy all the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/59019</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever the final analysis, Reno 911!: Miami is a welcome breath of fresh air in a year that's already forced audiences to endure the likes of "Norbit."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9802</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The characters are perfectly evolved screwups and the premise has potential. It lacks only the discipline of a 30-minute episode -- or a YouTube video.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20013556,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By film's end, you've enjoyed a middle-of-the-road episode of the series, basically. And as usual, Deputy Trudy and Lt. Dangle are getting the best lines while about one-third of the jokes hit their marks.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1172102124209170.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The gags vary - a tattooed-breast mystery kinda sags - but there are lots of laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/02232007/entertainment/movies/flatfooted_fun_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's longer running time means more dead spots and the more elaborate stunts demand tighter scripting and less room to improvise, which is a shame since improvisation is the Reno's gang real strength. Forgiving fans, however, won't care a whit.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286041&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Often mildly amusing but rarely laugh-out-loud funny, the film works best in scenes with a distinct Miami flavor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-reno23feb23,0,4671675.story</url>
         <critic>Alex Chun</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It probably cost less than the catering budget of average Adam Sandler comedy and, in its own hit-and-miss scattershot fashion, it's about as funny. At least when it hits.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/304750_reno23q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Moviedom is littered with the wreckage of ill-conceived small-to-big-screen adaptations, but Reno 911!: Miami is not the disaster it could have been. Fans of the TV show need not shudder. You will not see sacrilege.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1127606&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Dan Zak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Recommended only for die-hard fans of the TV show. Others are advised to wait until this is available in a smaller format.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/r/reno_911.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While several members of the cast valiantly fill the void where they can, these fish out of water could have made a greater high-definition splash if they had been thrown an occasional line or two rather than counting on inspiration to wash over them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=FpZ0JQRjmcDjkhGvDPbvvwpCGjSdpGbNd6P2J31pdQLT0j9mqzJ7!-1407640441&amp;&amp;rid=8843</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Come to think of it, 84 minutes isn't much of a sacrifice for a few laughs, even if the material is almost as hit-or-miss as our heroes' shooting skills.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/499863p-421506c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The humor is lowbrow, but the screenwriters and performers have a sense of pride that makes them strive for stupid jokes that haven't been done before.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/02/23/DDGDNO8O2I1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About 45 minutes worth of funny stuff awkwardly stretched to 84 minutes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070224.RENO24/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What feels amusingly anarchic on the small screen feels underdeveloped and disjointed on the big screen, perhaps because instead of commercials gluing the jokes together there’s dead air.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/02/23/movies/23reno.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of which goes to demonstrate that while it's easy enough to slap a colon on a lowbrow cable TV show, additional punctuation by itself isn't sufficient to actually transform it into a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932883.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The TV show excels with its short squad-car bursts of random inanity; here, the plot -- stretched out to 84 minutes -- feels like a dime bag tossed aside by a fleeing perp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0708,film,75862,20.html</url>
         <critic>Brian Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The filmmakers assume familiarity with the show's documentary premise and in-jokes (e.g., deputy Garant giving all his commands in French), which will make the movie even less accessible to novices.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A448419</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is mostly a listless hodgepodge of half-improvised whatever, the seven lead characters so flatly conceived they're like the Keystone Kops (without the chops).</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31165_RENO_NINE_ONE_ONE_MIAMI_RENO_911_MIAMI.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Very, very low-brow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134969</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$20,342,161</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,273,477</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,702</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>danny devito</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>