<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Rescue Dawn</name>
   <company>MGM</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Werner Herzog</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Werner Herzog</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Christian Bale</actor>
      <actor>Steve Zahn</actor>
      <actor>François Chau</actor>
      <actor>Jeremy Davies</actor>
      <actor>Craig Gellis</actor>
      <actor>Zach Grenier</actor>
      <actor>GQ</actor>
      <actor>Pat Healy</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 4, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>126</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a sweet collision is Rescue Dawn: the American psycho meets the German kook.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/07042007/entertainment/movies/fliers_work_movies_.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An old-fashioned prisoner-of-war movie that becomes much more because of writer-director Werner Herzog's admiration for the remarkable true story of its protagonist, Dieter Dengler.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/07/13/DDGAEQUS911.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Out of a harrowing story set in a foreign thicket, Herzog has found American beauty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20044587,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That such a masterful depiction of American heroism and can-do spirit has been created by a German art film director known for considerably darker visions of obsession is an irony Herzog no doubt finds delicious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1128063&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aside from a riveting adventure story that Herzog tells in all of its terrifying, stripped-down simplicity, Rescue Dawn is a fascinating study of human particularity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-rescuedawn4jul04,0,6238847.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Christian Bale plays Dieter Dengler and this is one of the actor's most complex and compelling performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=gfyJGJ4BjLqJ8RFxy211d03q4w2f2rJQBsFYl01JB7bQvkdmh53R!-862252910&amp;&amp;rid=9452</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog outdoes himself with Rescue Dawn, making his most popularly accessible film yet and proving at the same time that he is among the most daring of all filmmakers and capable -- like his characters -- of almost anything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A506339</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bale is extraordinary, grinning like a kid, displaying wily intelligence, sinewy resolve and spirit - and a bit of craziness, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20070713_Survival_tale_that_is_worth_telling_again.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is, indeed, perhaps the most believable that Herzog has made. For a director who gravitates toward the extremes of human behavior, this film involves extreme behavior, yes, but behavior forced by the circumstances.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070712/REVIEWS/70620008</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The question remains: Why would Herzog want to dramatize what he has already captured as nonfiction? To better control the material, I think, and to bring it in line with his own obsessions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9563</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is filmmaking that's as rousing as it is strange.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3927/rescue-dawn.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To better capture the extremity of Dengler's ordeal, Bale once again underwent the kind of dramatic weight loss that shocked audiences of "The Machinist," but he's downright plump next to the emaciated Davies, who looks like Charles Manson in the end stages of a hunger strike.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/rescue-dawn/review/288831</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Their bond lends this more or less conventional POW escape film resounding emotional depth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/rescue_dawn</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The scenes between Dengler and Duane, between a force of nature and a force of reason, are the real heart of the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.rescue27jul27,0,1769891.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As far as establishing a sense of period goes, Herzog cleaves to a refreshing less-is-more philosophy. This may be the first Vietnam-set film in history not to feature a bar of Jimi Hendrix, the Rolling Stones or indeed any other rock music on its soundtrack.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117931546.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=%22Rescue+dawn%22</url>
         <critic>Leslie Felperin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rescue Dawn is a tale of heroism untainted by political skepticism. In an age when U.S. soldiers are seen as villains or victims, the movie offers a GI who bravely, or madly, simply refuses to die.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1640413,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But like much of Herzog's work, it's essentially apolitical, focusing on a man at war with his environment -- and no one plunges into the foliage like he does.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#31830</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You can't watch this exciting movie without rooting for little Dieter, but decoding the lessons of his ambiguous story will take a lot longer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/07/05/btm/index1.html?VERSION=5</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As taut and exciting as many edge-of-your-seat Hollywood escape movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/19491327/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Christian Bale continues to amaze with his ability and range.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/r/rescue_dawn.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although nothing beats seeing and hearing the real story, Herzog has done a fairly compelling job of blending staged action with docudrama authenticity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0706/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Christian Bale loves to suffer on-screen. Werner Herzog loves to make people suffer on-screen. Rescue Dawn is proof they were made for each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=233132C496F97EB1F1F8EA9C1D37943D.prodapp14_ae_01?id=918521&amp;reviewId=22579&amp;startDate=07%2F27%2F2007</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's never any question how Rescue Dawn will end, but as conventional and straightforward as the movie is, it's easy to understand why Herzog was driven to tell this story twice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/231/story/182692.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In Bale, Herzog has found a talent who transcends the challenges of a brutal shoot. "Rescue" reveals new capabilities for an actor who's already proven himself in other intense and ever-focused performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10178</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the most part, Rescue Dawn is a marvel: a satisfying genre picture that challenges the viewer’s expectations.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/07/04/movies/04dawn.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film, Rescue Dawn, is so good it makes you wish that Herzog had gone Hollywood earlier in his career. His pet theme is here: man tested against nature, his sanity more precarious than his body.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/33977/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is honor, boldness, and grip in the new movie, but other directors can deliver those. Werner Herzog is the last great hallucinator in cinema, so why break the spell?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/07/09/070709crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rescue Dawn is the closest thing to a "real" movie that Herzog has ever made. The lone conquistador has joined the club. Rescue Dawn is a Rambo movie without the Man (who, if I remember my Rambology, was himself of German descent).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0727,hoberman1,77136,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The canniness of Bale’s performance (which may be the best of his young but brilliant career) is that he plays Dengler as a fundamentally kind and simple yet rather ingenious man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/rescue-dawn-air-america/16755/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is a great movie in Werner Herzog's Vietnam saga, Rescue Dawn. Unfortunately, it's about 30 minutes long.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/07/03/2007-07-03_flawed_movie_great_escape.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is all about escape. And as prison-break movies go, Rescue ranks among the best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-07-02-rescue-dawn_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Scott Bowles</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The strangely hybrid result, half Herzog and half Hollywood, plays like its own battleground. Sometimes, the tension is fascinatingly productive; other times, all we get is the worst of both worlds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070706.wdawn06/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rescue Dawn is Herzog's first English-language screenplay, and this is part of its problem: The hushed conversations between prisoners sound only fitfully idiomatic. Also--crucially--Herzog can't find a way to make his own big finish feel authentic, even if things did happen roughly this way.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070713-movies-review-rescue,0,2257229.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog’s planted rather too firmly in his discomfort zone, but Bale once again confirms himself as one of our most intense, committed and watchable actors.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133123</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Herzog's drive to bring Dengler's story to a wide audience might have paradoxically caused him to do what he seems normally to abhor: compromise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/118540236260000.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a well-acted but rote and strictly by the book "war movie."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/323437_rescue13q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$5,490,423</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$10,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$167,872</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>true</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>