<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Revolutionary Road</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Richard Yates</author>
      <author>Justin Haythe</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sam Mendes</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Leonardo DiCaprio</actor>
      <actor>Kate Winslet</actor>
      <actor>Michael Shannon</actor>
      <actor>Kathryn Hahn</actor>
      <actor>David Harbour</actor>
      <actor>Kathy Bates</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 26, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>119</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Indeed, all of the performers in the film truly shine, and all of them can probably thank Sam Mendes for creating an ideal environment.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.tvguide.com/revolutionary-road/review/292570</url>
         <critic>Perry Seibert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best American film of 2008.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/01/02/DDG0152444.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film is so good it is devastating.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081230/REVIEWS/812309997</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The results are being billed as a reunion of the "Titanic" star team, but anyone expecting a similarly gushy romantic idyll is in for a shock: it is an uncompromisingly dreary view of two self-deluded people incapable and unwilling to understand one another.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/394335_road02q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There isn't a banal moment in Winslet's performance--not a gesture, not a word. Is Winslet now the best English-speaking film actress of her generation? I think so.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/52914/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Revolutionary Road is a fine motion picture, but it's not a good choice to lighten a burden or brighten a night. It rewards in the ways that only tragedies can.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1432</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>DiCaprio is in peak form, bringing layers of buried emotion to a defeated man. And the glorious Winslet defines what makes an actress great, blazing commitment to a character and the range to make every nuance felt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/15858060/review/24991187/revolutionary_road</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Winslet (Mendes' wife) once again demonstrates why she's one of the best actresses working today.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12262008/entertainment/movies/50s_way_to_leave_your_lover_145924.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best thing about Revolutionary Road, a cool-blooded and disquieting adaptation of Richard Yates' 1961 novel about a powerfully unhappy Connecticut couple, is that it doesn't end with that rote vision of bourgeois anomie. It only begins there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20248901,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Encouraged by Mendes' artful direction, his gift for eliciting naturalness, the core of this film finally cries out to us today, makes us see that the notion of characters struggling with life, with the despair of betraying their best selves because of what society will or won't allow, is as gripping and relevant now as it ever was. Or ever will be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-road26-2008dec26,0,2435136.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As a whole, Sam Mendes' film of Revolutionary Road comes close but falls short of capturing Richard Yates' terrific novel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/12/24/2008-12-24_beauty_is_in_the_details_of_leonardo_dic.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of losing myself in the story, I often felt on the outside looking in, appreciating the craftsmanship, but one step removed from the agony on display. Revolutionary Road is impressive, but it feels like a classic encased in amber.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/171185</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A near-perfect case study of the ways in which film is incapable of capturing certain crucial literary qualities, in this case the very things that elevate the book from being a merely insightful study of a deteriorating marriage into a remarkable one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117939047.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I couldn't escape the fact that Revolutionary Road seems like a really, really good episode of "Mad Men." There's smoking, drinking, cheating and like the excellent TV show, the lure of a bigger better deal always rules the day. But the film differs in many ways once you get beyond surface appearances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11434</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fully exploits the drama, with scenes, dialogue, and even key visuals pulled from the text.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#33994</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Handsomely done and beautifully acted, just slightly wanting in a screenplay that leaves questions unanswered about what's behind these unhappy people. And it's ultra-depressing...</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135013</url>
         <critic>Angie Errigo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>However sterling the craftsmanship, the film adaptation inflates the meaning and buffs the atmospheric surfaces of Yates' story, rather than digging into its guts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-adv.hd.acmovies1jan02,0,1528389.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When the tobacco is extinguished what comes between April and Frank Wheeler is bigger, colder and more formidable than the iceberg that sundered Kate and Leo in "Titanic": shattered hope.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20090102_Uncoupling_in_the__50s_suburbs.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Revolutionary Road is a less stringent work than Yates's book, it also feels like a more tolerant and humane one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090101.wrevolution0102/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Sam Mendes makes '50s suburbia a persuasively suffocating place — he did the same for '90s suburbia in "American Beauty," remember.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=98659285</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not quite up to the caliber of Richard Yates' novel, which is deeply nuanced and rich in subtext. But the performances are superb, and the film is beautifully shot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-12-25-revolutionary-road_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both director and cast keep the familiar journey intense, but after capturing the death of love in those opening moments, the rest of the film too often feels like a study in dissection.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/revolutionary_road</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Revolutionary Road isn't a great movie -- it lacks the full, soul-crushing force of the novel -- but what works in it works so well, and is so tricky to pull off, that you can't help but admire it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-12-24/film/winslet-and-dicaprio-awake-to-yates-s-revolutionary-road/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a sourness, a relentlessness about the movie which borders on misanthropy. In both the social and the personal scenes, the conversational tone veers between idiotic pleasantries and fathomless bile, with nothing in between.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/12/22/081222crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shannon is monstrously good – unpredictable where the other actors are clipped and careful – and he steals the whole picture in two short, shattering scenes. When Shannon exits the film, the air gets sucked out again, and you realize the pretty artifice extends to more than just the Wheelers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A723262</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Leonardo DiCaprio and Kate Winslet do exactly what’s asked of them as Frank and April Wheeler, who may be ironically named: They spin emotional wheels constantly but get nowhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/37671-review-revolutionary-road</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Maybe it's a cheap shot to call Revolutionary Road "American Beauty" without the laughs, but it gets to the heart of the problem.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10539</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Revolutionary Road isn't emotionally engaging or moving; it's awfully similar in theme to Winslet's 2006 movie "Little Children."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/Revolutionary-Road</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a textbook example of a well-crafted movie, beautifully shot, impeccably acted, and structured like an elegant three-act play. So why does the movie feel as pleasantly deadening as the midcentury Connecticut suburb where it takes place?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2207404/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mendes has extraordinary gifts, but he has leveled them at the Wheelers like a firing squad. Strangely, he evinced no particular moralizing agenda when making films about the mob or the military. But put ordinary people in his sights and he's venomous. It's unbecoming -- and it should be worked out in private, not in a movie theater.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/01/movie_review_revolutionary_roa.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sad experience, but the sadness has no emotional heft because its people have none. This movie hasn't earned its funk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1226/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An impeccably shot, studiously staged, passionately acted bore, one of those curious fizzles in which everyone seems to do everything right, but the film simply refuses to take off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/833127.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is that Revolutionary Road is a hard movie to love. Plenty of people will appreciate the hopelessness, but they might wish for a little less emptiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/revolutionary-road,1147370.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a movie about two people in pain; the last thing they need is for Mendes to turn his cool camera on them. But that's all Mendes knows how to do. He's a clinical director, and whatever feeling he puts into a movie is measured out in careful quarter-teaspoon increments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/12/25/revolutionary_road/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Revolutionary Road" is the kind of great novel that Hollywood tends to botch, because much of it takes place inside the heads of its characters, and because the Wheelers aren't especially likeable and because pessimism without obvious redemption is a tough sell.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/12/26/movies/26road.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In "Virginia Woolf," George and Martha are locked into a symbiotic, disturbingly needy relationship that absolutely feed off their acidic battles. But for Revolutionary Road's Frank and April Wheeler, you wonder: Why don't they just get a divorce?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-revolutionary-road-1003897431.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is stifling, all right, and depressing in the bargain.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123015087021633387.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Revolutionary Road isn't just a failed literary adaptation. It's a failure of the worst kind: It doesn't even make you want to read Richard Yates' deservedly legendary book.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.revolutionary09jan09,0,4546525.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$22,911,480</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$189,911</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>kathy bates</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>sam mendes</oscar_winning_director>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>kathy bates</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>true</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>