<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Right at Your Door</name>
   <company>Roadside Attractions</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Chris Gorak</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Chris Gorak</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Mary McCormack</actor>
      <actor>Rory Cochrane</actor>
      <actor>Tony Perez</actor>
      <actor>Scotty Noyd Jr.</actor>
      <actor>Max Kasch</actor>
      <actor>Jon Huertas</actor>
      <actor>Will McCormack</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 24, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are no zombies to distract from the plausibility of Right at Your Door. And that's what makes this smart, coolly horrifying American indie thriller one of the scariest movies you're likely to see all year — a post-9/11 nightmare about terrorism, panic, and paranoia with real, waking-life implications.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20052851,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately a story about the American mindset post-9/11, Right at Your Door is also a much more personal tale, as it forces all of us to consider what we would do if the chips were down.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8364</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is frightening stuff, ably helmed (by writer/director Gorak, art director on the nerve janglers Fight Club and Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas), viciously acted, and altogether horrific in ways George A. Romero could imagine only through the lens of the darkest sort of fantasy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A526258</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While this is admittedly not lighthearted mainstream fare, the subject matter is interesting and is handled in a manner that offers a compelling and sometimes unsettling 95 minutes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/r/right_at.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Grounded hard by some terrific smoking-skyline special effects and by Cochrane and McCormack's intensity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0734,wilson,77564,20.html</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The two actors are solid, never overplaying scenes and capturing well that slow realization that their lives are never going to be the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=1001884299&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>McCormack and Cochrane can't transcend the clichéd, meandering dialogue, so Brad and Lexi's dilemma never feels like anything but a didactic contrivance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=290033&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has an ironic and unpredictable ending, but it doesn't wash away the sour taste of Brad's behavior.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/08/24/2007-08-24_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As frightening as it intends to be, but not enjoyably so.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08242007/entertainment/movies/right_at_your_door.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film, especially in its resolution, feels a bit like a “Twilight Zone” episode and might have been better at that length, but the acting’s pretty good, and the cinematography keeps things lively.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/08/24/movies/24door.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Neil Genzlinger</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The characters devolve into boring narcissists. And the movie devolves into a broad-brush dark satire of emergency bureaucracy that feels a lot sillier than the post-9/11 panic attack of the first half-hour.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1187834152262960.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Grows more and more incredible leading up to a twist ending worthy of an O. Henry short story that is as appropriate as it is ridiculous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/08/24/DD19RNENK.DTL#flick4</url>
         <critic>Pam Grady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chris Gorak grabs the viewer by the throat in the first few minutes, but quickly fritters away involvement by concentrating almost exclusively on two characters who are both annoying and boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929356.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>First-time director Chris Gorak is no Rod Serling, and in his hands the enterprise tends toward the lurid, especially after his nifty third-act twist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139666&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This doomsday scenario takes up the first third of the movie, after which the tension dissipates badly and the husband and wife, now separated by plastic sheeting, wait for help to arrive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/2007/070824/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A dumb twist can be excused, however, if your characters keep the thing afloat, which makes perhaps the most unforgivable sin of this claustrophobic terror scenario the fact that we have to spend it with arguably the two least interesting people in Los Angeles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-capsules24aug24,0,4656460.story</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is low budget but puffed with self-importance, and it offers proof that Hollywood filmmakers should probably steer clear of topics that actually matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10592</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$64,802</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$32,452</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>20</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>