<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Rocky Balboa</name>
   <company>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Sylvester Stallone</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Sylvester Stallone</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sylvester Stallone</actor>
      <actor>Burt Young</actor>
      <actor>Antonio Tarver</actor>
      <actor>Geraldine Hughes</actor>
      <actor>Milo Ventimiglia</actor>
      <actor>Tony Burton</actor>
      <actor>A.J. Benza</actor>
      <actor>James Francis Kelly III</actor>
      <actor>Talia Shire</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 20, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>102</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The acting in the film is grade-A, with Stallone bringing the more mumbled Rocky from the first film spliced with some rousing inspirational monologues when the moment is right (not forced, not preachy… just perfect).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9498</url>
         <critic>Mark Bell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not so much a sequel or even a remake for a new generation of moviegoers as it's a retranslation for the old one: an irresistible statement that "Yo, life ain't over till it's over."</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/296465_rocky20q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What gives Rocky Balboa its unexpected pathos is the titanic humility of Stallone's performance, the earnestness with which he plays a man knocked down (but not out) by the ravages of time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/15267/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stallone doesn't pander to audiences with unearned sentiment. He believes in his story, in the inspirational element that has sent thousands of folks running up the steps of the Philadelphia Museum of Art over 30 years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/mld/charlotte/entertainment/movies/16274555.htm</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie itself, defying all odds, comes close to a knockout.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-061220-movies-review-rocky,0,4978667.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After the widely reviled "Rocky V," it was just as unlikely for there to be a satisfying conclusion to the Rocky saga, but Rocky Balboa fits the bill.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/3345/rocky-balboa.html</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rocky Balboa is not as good as "Rocky," but it allows us to forget the other four sequels, none of which was memorable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/r/rocky_balboa.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is much to poke at in Rocky Balboa, yet the movie, with its amusingly updated ''Gonna Fly Now'' montage and its very niftily staged climactic bout, summons just enough incredulous wit about just how often Rocky has been around this particular block to let Sylvester Stallone earn his nostalgia.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1569422_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deep and astonishingly authentic streak of melancholy runs through this fifth sequel to the 1976 sleeper that made both struggling actor Sylvester Stallone and hard-luck slugger Rocky Balboa international stars.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=281740&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Better than decent. But if Stallone (who wrote and directed the flick) had pulled a few punches to the heart, it could have been truly worthy of that first, glorious movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12192006/entertainment/movies/rock_of_ages_packs_punch_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly Rocky Balboa, is no embarrassment. Like its forerunners it goes the distance almost in spite of itself. It's all heart and no credibility except as a raw-boned fable.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/12/20/movies/20rock.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does Rocky Balboa deliver? Weirdly enough, it does: I was jumping out of my seat during Rocky's bout. If you close your eyes and try to halve your IQ--aim for something between a baboon and a lemur--you might even think it's a masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/25634/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Defies all expectations with a low-key, technically stripped-down production that really does come close to capturing the heart and soul of the original.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=FGvtQHLHtQkR3LWdjhqwLDxTspxd9Cf1Vptj18JkB7dLn5MTDn1z!13192026&amp;&amp;rid=8554</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It matters because this boxer taps into something deeper in our collective souls than the desire for entertainment. It's the hope that one day we're going to win big, too, after everyone's given up on us. It's as hokey as it's true.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/12/19/AR2006121901614.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the character of Rocky, it's got heart to spare, and is by turns one of the sweetest of the sweet-science pictures as well as one of the most doleful. Fighters fight, it's what they do. And Balboa, god bless him, fights on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A428375</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As written, directed and, of course, acted by Sylvester Stallone, this film provides more insight into the character and his psyche than previous films, which were much more about the punches thrown.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-12-19-rocky-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Think you're too tough for a sentimental comeback story? Well, a few minutes with Rocky Balboa might just knock the cynic out of you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/481763p-405212c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rocky Balboa scores a split decision: A familiar start, some flat-footed middle rounds and a solid, flailing finish. And since Stallone has promised to throw in the towel on the franchise, we'll add an extra half star in honour of his diligence in the gym.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20061220.ROCKY20/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just when you're ready to puke, the old Bill Conti theme ("Gonna Fly Now") kicks in -- are you feeling it? -- Stallone steps in the ring and every day is Christmas. All together now: Rock-ee! Rock-ee!</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/8912323/review/12812463/rocky_balboa</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rocky Balboa is far from essential, and there are moments in it bad enough to make you wince. But I dare you not to feel at least a tiny little rush when that opening bell rings, and Rocky starts swinging one final time.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=776347&amp;reviewId=21971&amp;startDate=12%2F19%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's touching about Rocky Balboa, the sixth chapter in the saga of Philadelphia's lord of the ring, is the small-scale stuff. Not the spectacle of the has-been, now 60, connecting with a punch. But the sight of an actor connecting with a character.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=776347&amp;reviewId=21969</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The time away from the ring has done Rocky and the franchise some good, although it takes pic a good long while to gather momentum and clout before a surprisingly satisfying third-act heavyweight bout.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932317.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rocky Balboa, effortlessly reflexive and patently, even proudly, absurd, is a tough movie to dislike -- and believe me, I've tried.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0651,nelson,75348,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even as Sylvester Stallone's long goodbye to the heroic underdog who made him famous descends from pathos into silliness, and from fairy tale into hallucination, you can't help liking the big galoot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/12/20/rocky_balboa/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you hear the Rocky theme and think '118 118', you might wonder what all the fuss is about. For the rest of us, this is a reminder of why we fell in love with the character in the first place.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=17086</url>
         <critic>Ian Freer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Against all odds this panoply of punishment is almost thrilling, even though it's raging bull of a different kind.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As usual with Stallone's Rocky sequels, the schmaltz is unbearable, but the fight is plausibly handled, and Stallone's sincere sadness at growing older makes this an unexpectedly satisfying conclusion to the series.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/30875_ROCKY_BALBOA</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Stallone likely hopes to go out with a bang, this small, manipulative movie doesn't have any real punch to it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/116656711040130.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The original Rocky would have found a way to ground that encounter in reality, to engender honest emotion and give audiences an Everyman hero both noble and believable. This film is too busy worshiping its hero to bother.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.rocky20dec20,0,2571184.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is no corporate project made to squeeze a few more dollars from a fading cash cow. No one else has been asking for another "Rocky," other than maybe Burt Young . No, this is a rarer beast -- an auteur sequel -- and it's so wrapped up in its maker's personal mythology and psychic needs that it becomes a hall of mirrors to which we're given a slack-jawed ringside seat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8710</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching Rocky Balboa go through the usual paces does trigger a few helpless waves of nostalgia, especially once Bill Conti's famed score kicks in and Stallone sticks it to a few sides of beef. But audiences needn't be responsible for helping an over-the-hill actor through his midlife crisis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/56843</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anyone who appreciates Sylvester Stallone or enjoys the "Rocky" movies will find moments to enjoy in Rocky Balboa and will leave the theater reasonably satisfied. It's just good to see the guy, and it's good to revisit the character. And that's everything good to be said for the experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/12/20/DDGM0N26KH1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Above all this is a film for gluttons for punishment, for those who never ever can get enough of Sylvester Stallone. Everyone else, please leave the building.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-rocky20dec20,0,6069810.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$70,269,899</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$24,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$21,851,382</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,017</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>sylvester stallone</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>