<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ruins, The</name>
   <company>DreamWorks Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Scott Smith</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Carter Smith</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>AustraliaUSA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jonathan Tucker</actor>
      <actor>Laura Ramsey</actor>
      <actor>Jena Malone</actor>
      <actor>Shawn Ashmore</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 4, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>In order to appreciate The Ruins, one has to be a die-hard fan of horror or bloody thrillers. Those in that category will discover that The Ruins delivers the goods.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/r/ruins.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprisingly effective little horror nightmare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10277</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>First-time feature director Carter Smith, working with resourceful cinematographer Darius Khondji, pulls off the neat trick of using the wide screen to claustrophobic effect. And the actors give such a convincing display of starvation-fueled fear that they deserve their own private craft-service table.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/movie-reviews-forever-my-blueberry-nights-my-brother-is-an-only-child/18645/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Ruins is, with one major caveat, about as good an adaptation of Scott Smith's bestselling novel as Hollywood was ever going to make.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/224/story/481063.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The characters never evolve past mere functionality, and the adherence to certain tried-and-true horror tropes -- the good girl who doesn't want to go but does, the generic naughty kids who get it first -- feels workmanlike, robbing the story of any real suspense or surprise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-et-ruins5apr05,1,4902920.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, the gimmick is too risible and its effects on the characters too forced to sustain either suspense or horror.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=3QZFH2wDkXtxqLN28xTK9QN2bL4fP9CHyGBY9GVf5qk0QycRRk32!2044029123&amp;&amp;rid=10925</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Carter Smith suffers from another, more common problem: In trying to squeeze every plot point from the book into a 90-minute movie, he failed to capture its chilling essence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_ruins</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Smith has changed a few plot points around to keep readers who already know the secret of the ruins guessing, and to some extent the strategy works. There was, however, no reason whatsoever to change the book's perfect endings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/ruins/review/293093</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Ruins is lumpish, static, and obvious. It's a gringos-go-home cautionary fright flick done in the spirit of a cheap '50s horror movie, except that it leaves you longing for the competence of grade-Z studio-system trash.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20188997,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are a handful of intense sequences and a few scenes of squirm-inducing gore in The Ruins, but not much else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10893</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slick, sick stuff, but save the odd squirm, a killer-plant horror that doesn’t grow anywhere.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135241</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More disgusting than scary, The Ruins is the latest in a long line of horror films about upper-middle-class travelers being terrorized in unfamiliar environments.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/04/05/movies/05ruin.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately less dependent on suspense or even scares than on squirm-inducing grossouts, this tale of Yank hardbodies vs. carnivorous creepers should flower briefly in hardtops, then spread like an invasive weed in ancillary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117936708.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie doesn't do anything with these viney bastards. There's no back story, no satire, no allegory, no implications beyond what's happening on the pyramid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04052008/entertainment/movies/killer_ivy_leaves_film_in_ruins_105041.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As it stands, The Ruins is about as interesting as a pile of old stones and a monkey-dumb yanqui falling prey to the horrors of globalization. And that's pretty dumb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A607277</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$17,432,844</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$25,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$8,003,421</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,812</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>