<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Saw II</name>
   <company>Lions Gate Films Inc.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Darren Lynn Bousman</author>
      <author>Leigh Whannell</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Darren Lynn Bousman</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Donnie Wahlberg</actor>
      <actor>Shawnee Smith</actor>
      <actor>Tobin Bell</actor>
      <actor>Glenn Plummer</actor>
      <actor>Dina Meyer</actor>
      <actor>Emmanuelle Vaugier</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 28, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jigsaw is a wickedly fun villain, if you can put aside the implausibility of a guy who likes to saunter away from his deathbed to kidnap younger, stronger people and devise medieval torture chambers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/56278.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Saw II, despite the swift turnaround time, improves on all of the first film's problem areas, while leaving intact everything that was good about the concept.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-10-27/film/film5.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The killer himself takes a far more prominent role in this edition, and as played by the superb Tobin Bell he's quite a memorable creation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001349216</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For the most part the film succeeds in producing a frightening Halloween weekend experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-saw28oct28,0,1007178.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The contest is close, but Saw II is just barely a better B flick than "Saw."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1123047_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's an honesty to the film that elevates it a cut above standard slasher fare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.saw28oct28,1,5039705.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Morally dubious it may be, but this gory melange of torture, terror and darkly humorous depravity appeals to the sick puppy within us all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=132340</url>
         <critic>Alan Morrison</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's clear this sequel (directed by Darren Lynn Bousman) doesn't have the same smartness (I speak relatively) of the original. Nonetheless, "Saw" fans can still look forward to involuntary incineration, wrist and throat slashing, bullets through brains and the bashing of someone's head with a nail-festooned club.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1107684</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It all adds up to a sequel that is, against all odds, not a total waste of your serial-killer dollar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/113040909014110.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Mike Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Basically, this is a really good movie until the last part, where director and co-writer Darren Lynn Bousman ruins so much so fast that you'll wonder if his actions are deliberate -- or if the studio interfered.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/10/28/DDG17FEJ0A1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's fully apparent that this sequel is more trick than treat and doesn't really compare to its fine predecessor - though it still manages to be eye-opening (and sometimes positively nauseating) in itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/28/movies/28saw.html</url>
         <critic>Laura Kern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, that imagination flags early in the first sequel to the grisly 2004 sleeper hit, though the bang-up ending nearly makes it all worthwhile and it opens with a set piece worthy of its predecessor.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46480</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the overall effect feels a little anemic compared with its predecessor, the ads promise blood, and - oh yes - there is blood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/10-28-2005/entertainment/col/story/360054p-306583c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>New pic lets the air out by divulging the startling mystery that concluded the original. Add this to problematic juggling of police procedural and group-in-distress storylines, and Lions Gate has what looks like a sequel rushed for Halloween.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928622?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are some surprises to be had amid the cruelty (inflicted by both Jigsaw and his test subjects), but this time around the ordeal is less grueling than simply distasteful.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/246180_saw28q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To its credit, the film rockets toward its conclusion with scant downtime. It's come and gone before you even know it, and, like death, that's a good thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A303132</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stripped down to the barest genre essentials, Saw is a spring-loaded killing machine, packed with sadistic little deathtraps and ludicrous macabre twists, and its quickie sequel offers more of the same, which should again appease viewers who enjoy being jerked around.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41979</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the drawbacks to rushing your sequel to theaters is that there's not a lot of time to hone dialogue and performances.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=8112</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The explanation for all this mayhem eludes me, and even a lame last-minute twist isn't enough to cover the fact that Jigsaw ain't as clever as the movie thinks he is.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=447228&amp;reviewId=19394&amp;startDate=10%2F28%2F2005</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether we're talking this go-round, the original or the second sequel the finale seems to promise, I'd rather try standing drunk on a see-saw (though maybe not over dirty syringes) than see Saw.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-10-27-saw2_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's worth noting is how much greater deliberation was given to the marketing than the screenplay of this cursory dud, rushed to theaters exactly a year after its amusing predecessor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0543,tracking10,69448,20.html</url>
         <critic>Benjamin Strong</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Saw II repels, morally and aesthetically, and while some -- including the filmmakers, perhaps -- may take this as a compliment, it isn't intended as one. Let the game stop. Please.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3633&amp;Sumbit.x=44&amp;Sumbit.y=12</url>
         <critic>Christopher Orr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Vilely violent, Saw 2 is the Phnom Penh of splatter movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=447228&amp;reviewId=19371&amp;startDate=10%2F27%2F2005</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not a film, it's an excuse to show victims bleeding at the mouth, or getting shot in the eye, or plucking out their own eyeballs. Most gruesome of all, the sequel oozes dialogue that is best described as "functional."</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501028-movies-review-saw,0,5232676.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't look for logic here. But if gore is your game, a motherlode awaits.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051028/SAW28/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Finally, a horror movie for the reality TV generation. Saw II feels like an episode of "Fear Factor" or "Big Brother" with Rob Zombie at the helm, and if that doesn’t scare you away from this ridiculous movie, well, feel free to indulge your questionable tastes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2357</url>
         <critic>Ryan Devlin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The product of immaturity. It approaches suffering with a meaninglessness that must be a luxury for anyone who has never lost anyone, or is incapable of empathizing with someone who has.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7415</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Comes to life only when it reprises elements from the original movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/movies/archives/2005/1005/051028.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$87,025,093</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$5,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$31,725,652</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,949</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>