<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Screamers</name>
   <company>Maya Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Carla Garapedian</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>John Dolmayan</actor>
      <actor>Daron Malakian</actor>
      <actor>Shavo Odadjian</actor>
      <actor>Serj Tankian</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 8, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>89</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Armenian-American quartet have taken it upon themselves to teach their fans about what happened to their families in that now-forgotten time, a deeply personal mission that has proven effective in politicizing their audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=284146&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fans are, obviously, most likely to appreciate the concert footage that's woven throughout the film. But the most powerful moments come offstage, when we see young audience members burn with the fresh outrage of the newly enlightened.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/491887p-414337c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film offers true insight into the patterns of war crimes, even if the songs sound disquietingly close to a call to violence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20010415,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So many documentaries about genocides play art-house theaters that it can be easy to get jaded, but combining one with tour footage from the most innovative metal band in the world is genius, banging the viewer's head before he realizes it's being filled with awareness too.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/15172/</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The piece is intelligently made, although the director often doesn't establish place or time, leaving the viewer unmoored.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-screamers8dec08,0,2021257.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Ordona</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film paraphrases a quote from Hitler before he invaded Poland in 1939 (a quote still in hot dispute): "Who still speaks nowadays of the extermination of the Armenians?" This documentary does. Whatever its flaws, that alone makes it worth seeing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1132871&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Richard Leiby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This film has provocations to spare; it just hasn't been made provocatively. It's a mess, actually.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9708</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Part rockumentary, part howl of outrage, Screamers would have benefited from less concert film and more historical background.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/25/movies/26scream.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A committed piece of agit-prop, which benefits from the passion of its protagonists. Followers of the band will need no introduction to the subject matter, which is referenced in their musical repertoire. The film also should play well with those interested in liberal causes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=F1PQBBR6TYf6ZB4PW2Qd8DsnsLqbyxsJ1DGCrvgs8Zp7CJ8N3YCQ!-110099270&amp;&amp;rid=8529</url>
         <critic>Richard James Havis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The band is sincere, and many of its followers are just as sincere, but there's always a danger that too much "screaming" can turn a meaningful statement into an inarticulate din.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/57882</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A noble cause does not a good movie make. Pic repeatedly drowns its impassioned message with music, creating an awkward hybrid between history lesson and concert documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117932271.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A commendably brave piece, but less focused and powerful than you'd like. In the end, Garapedian might have been better off concentrating her energy on the 1915 Armenian story--which has been told on film various times (for example, in "Forty Days of Musa Dagh" and Atom Egoyan's "Ararat"), but never with the power of, say, "The Pianist" or "Schindler's List."</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070209-movies-review-screamers,0,2612607.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most of the screen time goes to American-Armenian hard rock band System of a Down, whose grating concert footage trivializes Garapedian's message.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31084_SCREAMERS_GARAPEDIAN.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Margasak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If this sounds intriguing, we should add that System of a Down is a lousy live band. And director Garapedian, for all her public-minded zeal, isn't capable of corralling her interviews and opinions into a coherent polemic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070607.wscreamers08/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Screamers, one of the most bizarre documentaries you'll ever not see.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/01262007/entertainment/movies/say_genocide__and_armenia_it_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$52,034</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$23,609</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>