<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>September Dawn</name>
   <company>Black Diamond Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
      <genre>Western</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Christopher Cain</author>
      <author>Carole Whang Schutter</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Christopher Cain</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jon Voight</actor>
      <actor>Trent Ford</actor>
      <actor>Tamara Hope</actor>
      <actor>Jon Gries</actor>
      <actor>Huntley Ritter</actor>
      <actor>Lolita Davidovich</actor>
      <actor>Dean Cain</actor>
      <actor>Terence Stamp</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 24, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>110</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most significant and contrary to the Mormon Church's ongoing position, the film depicts Young as present when the plot is hatched to slaughter the emigrants. Needless to say, this workmanlike but unflinching film won't be playing in Utah anytime soon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/september-dawn/review/285942</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cruel simplicity of the atrocity is made needlessly chaotic by artless camerawork that swishes rapidly back and forth across the action, to the accompaniment of a syrupy soundtrack.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/328801_dawn24q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cain has crafted a modest picture, filmed in Canada, that too often feels like a very elaborate episode of "Gunsmoke."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=nYnmGTpLvqrNZDmyyXQRhTFCnd7RHJ4Bwp5n7SryS4077vn6Tn2h!-1904077233&amp;&amp;rid=9671</url>
         <critic>Luke Sader</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn't THAT bad -- it's just made-for-TV historical treacle that has somehow found its way to the big screen (and barely that; if you want to be moved or outraged by the film, you'll have to travel to Danvers or Revere).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10248</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A rare case in which one can't help but wish the film were somehow worse than it is, for it would then be easier to dismiss outright. Jon Voight's turn as a fictional local Mormon leader and, in particular, Terence Stamp's performance as Brigham Young have a strange, unnerving conviction about them, and give the film an oddly engaging pull.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-september24aug24,0,6554750.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shot in a style that might be termed Americana gravitas, September Dawn has the ham-fisted lyricism of political ads and pharmaceutical commercials. The schematic script is further burdened with heavy ironies and hackneyed dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0734,hoberman,77559,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The didactic presentation, grim speechifying and tacked-on love story all signify a less-than-healthy regard for the audience's intelligence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934474.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>September Dawn, written by an evangelical Christian, may be the worst historical drama ever made.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/08/24/2007-08-24_westward_woe_in_1857_utah.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Filmmaker Christopher Cain has turned a national tragedy into a teen romance, and not in a grand, entertaining, "Titanic" way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/story/212437.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A ham-fisted cautionary tale of religious fanaticism that would have been hooted out of even 19th-century theaters as melodrama of the most lurid kind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.september24aug24,0,1683668.story</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The villainous turns by Jon Voight (as a hard-hearted Mormon bishop) and Terence Stamp (as a bloodthirsty Brigham Young) would have been more fun if they weren't part of such a clumsy campaign to lay this tragedy at the church's doorstep.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31999_SEPTEMBER_DAWN.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a soap opera posing as moral outrage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1135868&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its complete lack of empathy for early Mormons and simplistic rendering of historical figures, September Dawn is that rare movie that actually deserves whatever condemnation might come from religious groups.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/september_dawn</url>
         <critic>Steven Hyden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The audience gets the message (religious fanaticism: bad), but nothing we see is convincing on its own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20053801,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Muddled, sloppy, and obfuscating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A526168</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Succeeds completely at failure; the unified incompetence of its writing, directing and acting suggest a man who manages to be on fire and drowning at the same time, just as the bus runs him over.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08242007/entertainment/movies/pulpit_massacre_has_whiff_of_p.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The maudlin, grotesque western September Dawn, about the massacre on Sept. 11, 1857, of about 120 settlers by Mormons (and their Paiute Indian mercenaries), apes "Schindler’s List" in hopes of creating a Christian Holocaust picture.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/08/24/movies/24dawn.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Matt Zoller Seitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a strange, confused, unpleasant movie this is. Two theories have clustered around it: (1) It is anti-Mormon propaganda to muddy the waters around the presidential campaign of Mitt Romney, or (2) it is not about Mormons at all, but an allegory about the 9/11/01 terrorists. Take your choice. The problem with allegories is that you can plug them in anywhere. No doubt the film would have great impact in Darfur.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070823/REVIEWS/70823001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$901,857</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$10,100,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$901,857</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>857</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jon voight</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>jon voight</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>