<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Seraphine</name>
   <company>Music Box Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>War</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Martin Provost</author>
      <author>Marc Abdelnour</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Martin Provost</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>France</origin>
      <origin>Belgium</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Actress Yole Moreau</actor>
      <actor>Ulrich Ukur</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 5, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>125</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>What makes Seraphine, directed and co-written by Martin Provost, so exceptional is that it neither condescends to nor romanticizes its subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-seraphine5-2009jun05,0,31221.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The scene is so emotionally ravishing that it breaks you apart. The peacefulness that finally descends on Séraphine in the film's final moments is more than a balm. It's a benediction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0612/p17s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It "explains" nothing but feels everything. It reminds me of two other films: Bresson's "Mouchette," about a poor girl victimized by a village, and Karen Gehre's "Begging Naked," shown at Ebertfest this year, about a woman whose art is prized even as she lives in Central Park.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090617/REVIEWS/906179991</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Moreau is bewitching -- she simply breathes her role, without a hint of vanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20282755,00.html</url>
         <critic>Adam Markovitz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Among the best of its kind, thanks in no small part to the utterly believable, vanity-free performance of Yolande Moreau in the title role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/08/movie_review_seraphine_capture.html</url>
         <critic>Stan Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Séraphine is one of the most evocative films about an artist I've ever seen--and in its treatment of madness one of the least condescending.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/57041/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provost and cowriter Marc Abdelnour explore the mutable boundaries between spirituality, naivete, genius, and madness, showing how the two outsiders and polar opposites cultivated a mutual understanding.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#34491</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The rare movie that manages to convey the inner soul of an artist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090717_A_beautiful_portrait_of_a_painter.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Moreau does with this role is as inscrutably moving as anything Séraphine Louis painted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/07/31/sraphine_offers_a_slowly_drawn_portrait_of_art_and_madness/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With exquisitely simple images and minimal dialogue, Seraphine is both haunting and humane.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/8640B47920D816FA862576170072DD80?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The line between madness and genius is thin. Not to mention more than amply explored in any number of films about tortured artists. But to look at the almost religious ecstasy on Moreau's face is to feel the artist's passion and be inspired by it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/seraphine,1156566.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extraordinary performance by vet thesp Yolande Moreau in the title role.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938316.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;query=seraphine</url>
         <critic>Eddie Cockrell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Séraphine's dependence on her patron--a cultivated but emotionally detached homosexual, who knew a fellow outsider when he saw one but came and went in her life without warning--is almost as unbearably moving as her inevitable unraveling--when money and fame cut the artist off from her creative wellsprings and drove her over the edge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-06-03/film/s-eacute-raphine-lyrical-biopic-stirred-the-french-public/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The mystery of Séraphine de Senlis -- who died in a mental hospital in 1942 and whose work survives in some of the world’s leading museums -- is left intact at the end of Séraphine. Rather than trying to explain Séraphine, the film accepts her.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/05/movies/05sera.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Moving historical drama brings a fascinating chapter of art history to life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/film-review-seraphine-1003980517.story</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Martin Provost tells much of Seraphine's true-life story without words, lingering here on the process by which she makes paints, there on the obsessive single-mindedness she brings to her art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=104880202</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yolande Moreau's most impressive costars are the extraordinary compositions of Seraphine Louis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11917</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A genuinely moving portrait of the artist as a young(ish) scullery maid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A890557</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a movie about a scrubwoman who paints - so don't expect lots of sex scenes or car chases. Just expect a great performance by Moreau, who will convince you that she painted every one of those paintings - and lived them all before she painted them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/07/16/MVA818JTPA.DTL</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>We don't get a good look at a painting until 35 minutes into the film biography of Séraphine de Senlis, the early 20th-century French painter discovered by German art collector Wilhelm Uhde. The film Séraphine is not about paintings.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/sraphine/article1221407/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is an actors' showcase, without being showy, and Moreau and Tukur reveal radically different personalities with just enough in common to make things interesting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-0619-seraphine-reviewjun19,0,4985726.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Séraphine is far more powerful when it lingers on Louis at work.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/seraphine,28818/</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$883,270</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$38,637</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>