<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Shorts</name>
   <company>Warner Bros. Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robert Rodriguez</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Robert Rodriguez</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
      <origin>UnitedArabEmirates</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jon Cryer</actor>
      <actor>William H. Macy</actor>
      <actor>Leslie Mann</actor>
      <actor>James Spader</actor>
      <actor>Jimmy Bennett</actor>
      <actor>Kat Dennings</actor>
      <actor>Trevor Gagnon</actor>
      <actor>Leo Howard</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>August 21, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>89</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>More zippy, diverting fun from Robert Rodriguez's family filmmaking factory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940794.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fast and funny, and grown-ups will not suffer sitting through it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1194074.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rodriguez, is a hack in the best sense of the term, often serving as producer, director, writer, shooter and composer – all of which come into play for Shorts .</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/shorts/article1258893/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Magic vies with technology in this exuberant adventure comedy, which unfolds achronologically in a series of zany, effects-laden vignettes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?oid=1123465</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adult actors pretty much let the youngsters upstage them. The two leads, Bennett and Vanier, do a nice job holding the center of gravity while the film goes nuts around them. Best of all, Shorts is short, finishing before you can truly get tired of all those wishes gone wrong.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/shorts-film-review-1004001590.story</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rodriguez’s technical wizardry is less showy here than in his other recent outings, which helps Shorts connect with kids on a basic human level.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A820181</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Jumanji," Shorts runs out of momentum before it's half over. That leaves it treading slapstick and killing time until its strained and preposterous big finish.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090821_The_story_of_a_dorky_kid_and_a_wish-granting_rock.html</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fast-paced, imaginative and often cute, Shorts is slight but enjoyable family fare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-08-20-shorts-review_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A satisfying dose of wild imagination and unbridled silliness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/08/robert_rodriguez_shorts_like_t.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provides just enough smart, silly fun for families desperately seeking an easy (and air-conditioned) escape from hazy August humidity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/08/21/2009-08-21_shorts_fun_in_a_falling_rock_zone.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A preachy parable of suburban discontent, Shorts probably has enough kid-oriented slapstick to please the under-12 set. But it's not likely to rival writer-director Robert Rodriguez's "Spy Kids" series in long-term appeal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=111959848</url>
         <critic>Mark Jenkins</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A cute and mildly clever fantasy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-08-18/film/robert-rodriguez-s-cgi-overload-shorts/</url>
         <critic>Aaron Hillis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More like a summer-camp theater project than a studio movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20299477,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'm not sure if parents will be counting out each of Shorts 89 minutes or not, begging for it to end, but I'm guessing 8-year-olds will absolutely love it, because Rodriguez isn't talking down to them or using pop-culture references in place of actual gags; he's making what might be called eye-level children's entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/08/movie_review_a_magic_stone_gat.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's more of a burst pinata than a story, a wild, kinetic jumble of images, ideas and flying-candy-bar product placement that would offend if it weren't so forthright.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/08/20/MVI319APUM.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Amy Biancolli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If parents feel like they've seen much of Shorts before, its celebration of mayhem and restless, thrill-seeking vibe will absorb young viewers, especially as the boredom of late summer begins to set in.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/shorts,1060771/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Soon becomes tiresome, but it’s emblematic of a film that is dancing as fast as it can to entertain.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/08/21/movies/21shorts.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem with Shorts is in the execution. The blown-up plot line at times derails even the little ones, the many fine comedic grown-ups are mostly squandered, and the "message" part of the movie feels like it was thrown together during detention, resulting in a wrap-up that is rushed and cloyingly PC.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-shorts21-2009aug21,0,4654389.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jon Cryer and Leslie Mann have a couple of sly moments as overworked career people, and Spader again proves he learned a lot by working with William Shatner for so long. But the bottomless slapstick and silly effects quickly grow wearying, as does a cast of young actors whose work can politely be called energetic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/shorts,31963/</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Props should be given to Rodriguez’s breathless “let’s put on a show” inventiveness. Plus, Macy and the booger--kick ass!</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/77682/shorts-film-review</url>
         <critic>Keith Uhlich</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Be warned, though: This is the multiplex equivalent of ADD.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/08/21/shorts_is_long_on_hyperactive_energy/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is as lumpy and misshapen as a giant booger.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/08212009/entertainment/movies/youll_get_short_shrift_if_you_go_to_this_185526.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$20,919,166</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$6,410,339</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,105</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>