<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Sir! No Sir!</name>
   <company>Balcony Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Zeiger</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>David Zeiger</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Troy Garity (narrator)</actor>
      <actor>Edward Asner</actor>
      <actor>Jane Fonda</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 7, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>85</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sir! No Sir! is far from a dry rehashing of what may seem for some like ancient history. Driving guitar rock and lively editing add to the film's urgency. The voices of the veterans alone, however, make this an important and poignant film that can speak to any generation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/04/07/DDG5UI43FV1.DTL#flick3</url>
         <critic>John McMurtrie</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zieger's thoroughly researched film is a vital reminder that beginning in the mid-'60s, a few conscience-stricken military individuals -- including dermatologist Dr. Howard Levy, sickened by cynical attempts to win Vietnamese "hearts and minds" through medical treatment, and Navy nurse Susan Schnall, who wore her uniform to a civilian antiwar demonstration -- actively and openly voiced peace sentiments.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46050&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A riveting documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=465049&amp;reviewId=20951</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of these soldiers were valiant in their efforts to not fight in a war they felt was a deceitful practice in government fraud, and they succeeded through all the hardships.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8937</url>
         <critic>Felix Vasques Jr.</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zeiger's superb documentary about the Vietnam War era's GI protest movement is jammed with incident and anecdote and moves with nearly as much breathless momentum as the movement itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13430/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A powerful documentary that uncovers half-forgotten history, history that is still relevant but not in ways you might be expecting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-sir5may05,0,6346624.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film provides a window into the conversations and debates that occurred among soldiers on military bases and while in country, opinions shaped and altered by first-hand experiences and knowledge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A284767</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sir! No Sir! honors those who fought, then questioned the morality of that fight, then joined the national protest.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060609-movies-review-sir,0,7767892.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is powerful stuff, offering us not only a new look at the past, but to the unavoidably relevant insights into the present.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/410753p-347371c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sir! No Sir! is a documentary about an almost-forgotten fact of the Vietnam era: Anti-war sentiment among U.S. troops grew into a problem for the Pentagon.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060608/REVIEWS/606080304/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ffor all its clumsiness, Sir! No Sir! movingly captures the raw excitement of grunts discovering their power and their voices in their ability to resist.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47544</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zeiger's movie is a timely salute to the risky and brave men and women who had the temerity not only to think for themselves but to speak their minds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9195</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In his smart, timely documentary about the G.I. Movement, Sir! No Sir!, Mr. Zeiger takes a look at how the movement changed and occasionally even rocked the military from the ground troops on up.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/19/movies/19sir.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1145419544-wxb49N07IqReoPATqkwMtw</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It will change your understanding of the Vietnam era, even if you were alive then.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/20/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Narrated by Troy Garity, whose mother, Jane Fonda, candidly discusses her involvement in the movement that seems to have faded from the collective conscience in the intervening years, the film does a commendable job in providing enlightenment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000973218</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Because it's bolstered by proud memories of Vietnam vets who turned against the war, Sir! No Sir! rings with an exultant, even elated tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927681?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As it is, this one is compelling enough, a potent mix of outrage, residual anger, and sorrow that speaks not just to the legacy of our misadventures in Vietnam, but to the entire uncertain future of a nation at war.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0616,gallo,72911,20.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I expected to emerge depressed by how long these stories have gone untold, but the speakers' courage and humanity are a shot in the arm.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#29892</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Winter Soldier," Sir! No Sir! will surely reopen old wounds, as the Vietnam War -- like the Civil War 100 years before -- refuses to die. But hawks and doves alike should be grateful to Zeiger for preserving a fascinating piece of American cultural history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1114742&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Informative and swiftly paced documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060721.SIR21VAN/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sir! No Sir! doesn't make a lot of sense, but it does have some fascinating footage of Jane Fonda, both as a dippy young protester and today, when she remains dazzled by her own legend.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64659.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$116,944</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$7,547</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jane fonda</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>