<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Snow Angels</name>
   <company>Warner Independent Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>David Gordon Green</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>David Gordon Green</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Sam Rockwell</actor>
      <actor>Kate Beckinsale</actor>
      <actor>Michael Angarano</actor>
      <actor>Griffin Dunne</actor>
      <actor>Amy Sedaris</actor>
      <actor>Olivia Thirlby</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 7, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>106</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>David Gordon Green's captivating winter-chill tragedy, is a tale that encompasses murder, divorce, adultery, alcohol abuse, mental breakdown, and the disappearance of a small child. In other words, it's downbeat enough to make the recent Oscar-nominated films look like party games.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20182342,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Green is a rare bird in American filmmaking: a humanist who knows how to tell a story.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-snow-angels/345196/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result feels less like selling out than growing up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1206577517172440.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a deep understanding of his characters, Green has crafted a film that's devastating and uplifting without sounding a false note.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9697</url>
         <critic>Jeremy Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>All of these actors are incredibly fine, and as a confirmed Beckinsale non-fan, I'm obliged to say that she really knocked me out here.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4443/snow-angels.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Disturbingly good. The writing and the performances are such that as things go from bad (sad motel-room affairs) to worse (a 4-year-old gone missing), the film's characters get inside your skin, your soul. It's enough to make you want to cry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080328_Life_worsening_in_a_disturbingly_good_film.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Emotionally harrowing and gentle by turns, this well-acted winter's tale is a more narrative-driven experience than Green's more lyrical Sundance entries, "George Washington" and "All the Real Girls."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117932497&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Few filmmakers these days are as capable and assured with the fumbling ambivalence of human conversation as Green is; his ear for the half-truths, misapprehensions, and long-simmering defensiveness of everyday dialogue is a wonder to behold.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A607595</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Revelatory as well as unsettling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/03/20/DD0LVMPKG.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For all the misery and emotional mess of Snow Angels, Green finds resilience and hope in the kids and even in some of the grown-ups.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/355810_snow21q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the foibles that have affected his films, the dramatic image has always been important to Green, who has developed quite a cult following and deserves it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1138933&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's success is due in large part to actors who are both faithful to all the social minutiae and seductive enough to keep you watching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1720367,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Snow Angels succeeds because of the depth of its well-drawn characters. With no cinematic sugarcoating, it's an organic story that draws us in to these people's lives, as flawed and destructive as they may be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=8654</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What saves this heavy, heavy material from sinking into the chill, familiar turf of the Small-Town Midwinter Tragedy is Green's practiced ear for verbal idiosyncrasy and off-kilter conversation rhythms.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0810,350975,350975,20.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A power­ful drama, but if I didn’t know Green had directed it I probably wouldn’t have guessed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/moviereviews/080320/</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In spite of strong performances and a characteristically vivid sense of place, the film feels disjointed and heavy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/snow_angels</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It does give Sam Rockwell another opportunity to creep us out, and Kate Beckinsale a new shot at believability. Too bad the movie around them meanders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/03/07/2008-03-07_sam_rockwell_ups_chill_factor_in_snow_an.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thoughtfully crafted but ultimately lugubrious, Green's latest only really connects when the director sticks to the small stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080320.snow21nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Frankly, Snow Angels is a downer. This isn't inherently a negative - after all, some of the cinema's most powerful motion pictures are downbeat. However, in this case, there's no emotional force behind all the gloom - just a sense that something's missing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/s/snow_angels.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Green knows how to convey a mood visually and develop tension with his camera. He just doesn't give people enough interesting things to say or know when to shut them up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/574827.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite all-around wonderful performances and excellent dialogue, the story never quite coheres narratively. Instead it moves toward a hopelessly bleak -- and I mean bleak -- climax that's more traumatic than dramatic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-snowangels14mar14,0,3784107.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film full of murder, jealousy and fatalism, Snow Angels feels curiously small and anecdotal, and its impact diminishes as it nears its terrible conclusion.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/03/07/movies/07snow.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Beckinsale tackles the downscale role manfully, but Rockwell is nearly unrecognizable as the pudgy, suicidally depressed, chronically inept Glenn, who's acting out a half-convincing portrayal of himself as a born-again Christian.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2008/03/06/paranoid/</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kate Beckinsale is too good for any of the guys in Snow Angels and too good for this movie. Her inventiveness exposes just how puny this movie is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.snow11apr11,0,7576123.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I left as frustrated as that band teacher is at the beginning of the movie. Enough with these meek, banal exercises, David Gordon Green. Hit me with the sledgehammer in your heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9937</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scene by scene his (David Gordon Green’s) new film, Snow Angels, isn’t terrible. Parts of it are amusing, and there are wintry images that eat into the mind. But it’s one of the most disjunctive things I’ve ever sat through.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/44751/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Green and his regular cinematographer Tim Orr have a feel for the sad, generic landscape of small-town America, but rather than adding to an overarching melancholy it only reinforces an already drab, at times bizarrely comic tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/snow-angels/review/292346</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An intriguing and somber tale of disintegrating and disappointing relationships fused with a coming-of-age story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-03-13-snow-angels_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$402,858</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$14,247</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>