<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Somersault</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Cate Shortland</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Cate Shortland</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Australia</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Abbie Cornish</actor>
      <actor>Sam Worthington</actor>
      <actor>Lynette Curran</actor>
      <actor>Nathaniel Dean</actor>
      <actor>Erik Thomson</actor>
      <actor>Leah Purcell</actor>
      <actor>Hollie Andrew</actor>
      <actor>Paul Gleeson</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 21, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>106</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cornish's raw, nuanced performance and Shortland's sympathetic but unsentimental portrayal of Heidi's fumbling steps toward maturity are underscored by Sydney-based band Decoder Ring's catchy, angst-ridden score.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46392&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Showcases a brilliantly realistic performance by Abbie Cornish as Heidi. She's a provocative mix of naivete and ripe, unbridled sexuality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/67352.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somersault faces the difficulty of representing a girl's unspoken desires and anxieties, a challenge Shortland rises to with terrific skill and aplomb.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106955&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This beautifully understated feature (2004) revolves around sex, but it's neither erotic nor puritanical; its young characters are governed by their urges, but the experience itself seems as neutral and mysterious as sleep.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#29805</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This remarkable film from Australia, the debut feature of writer-director Cate Shortland, moves to the lyrical rhythms and unhurried pace of a 1970s road movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13252/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Dreamy and creepy, tender and terrifying, Somersault is a frank and visceral film that at the same time exudes an unexpected innocence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-somersault21apr21,0,7561039.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somersault, which the Australian Film Institute garlanded with 13 awards, including best film, director, actor and actress (for Ms. Cornish's astonishing performance), is a movie about the looks on people's faces and the disparity between the surface and the roiling chaos beneath.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/21/movies/21some.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With Somersault, filmmaker Cate Shortland has expertly served up a vivid and touching tale, one told many times before, but in this well-realized mounting, one that sparkles with fresh awareness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000514346</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching the Australian coming-of-age film Somersault is a little like watching a fluffy white bunny hop through a minefield, one tiny spring away from becoming tonight's rabbit stew.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47546</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shortland's script takes some unnecessary turns, mostly with Joe's drinking and sexual insecurities. But as long as it's focused on Heidi's predicament, it is riveting drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/04-21-2006/entertainment/col/story/410786p-347370c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has more style than depth and it's sometimes in danger of confusing the two.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8195</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the kind of small filmmaking that leaves a big impression.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/05/19/DDGVQITKKO1.DTL#flick2</url>
         <critic>G. Allen Johnson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The character can be a dolt, but Cornish is a marvel, exuding a reckless hunger and prowling with a sexuality of potent directness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1190462_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Erotic, poetic and light on its feet. It's a portrayal of a runaway teenager's sexual initiation, and though it comes close to being exploitive, it keeps dancing away.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060512-movies-review-somersault,0,7942927.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'm sure some people will be driven mad by the deliberate ambiguities of Somersault, and by its characters' near-total inability to understand themselves or express themselves. But to me, that makes it uncannily true to life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/04/20/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sexual compulsion accelerates adolescent angst in the arty Down Under drama, but while Shortland shows a notable eye for detail, her distracted approach to narrative and an attitude to her characters that's cold as the movie's snowfields make pic most likely to be embraced by serious-minded fest auds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=cannes2004&amp;content=review&amp;reviewid=VE1117923896&amp;categoryid=1724&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Russell Edwards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ms. Shortland has announced her presence as a new filmmaker to be taken seriously, while her star, Abbie Cornish, gives a performance that starts impressively, and gets even better as it goes along.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cornish, in her first film seen stateside, is astonishing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A365985</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The annoying shaky-cam style so common to such indie dramas is toned down to a dreamy sway and the image drifts in and out of focus in scenes of heightened emotions. It's like waking from a daze and getting your bearings; the effect is both unsettling and calming.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/269880_somersault12q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Shortland frames the story against the apt grey, off-season ski town, but her attempt to match it with deliberate pacing just makes the film feel chilly and too long, just like Heidi's depressing routine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2753</url>
         <critic>Jessica Letkemann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are lots of ways to grow up. The method offered in this Australian drama is to do something awful and then flee from it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0616,levine,72927,20.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$92,214</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$21,566</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>