<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Son of Rambow</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Garth Jennings</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Garth Jennings</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Bill Milner</actor>
      <actor>Will Poulter</actor>
      <actor>Jules Sitruk</actor>
      <actor>Jessica Stevenson</actor>
      <actor>Neil Dudgeon</actor>
      <actor>Anna Wing</actor>
      <actor>Ed Westwick</actor>
      <actor>Eric Sykes</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 2, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>96</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Perhaps the most ingeniously imaginative element in Son of Rambow, a film exploding with imagination (some of it scrawled directly over the film in animated expressions of Will's private world), is its very conceit.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/362301_rambow09q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funny and sweet and guaranteed to flood you with good feeling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A623720</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In many ways, Son of Rambow plays like a pint-size, even cheekier version of the recent Michel Gondry film "Be Kind Rewind." Both are stories about people making movies not because it's their job but because doing so brings a vast sense of play into their lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10249</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching skinny-armed little Will pretend to be the spawn of Sly Stallone in a series of botched feats of derring-do is a treat, as is much of this film.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/05/review_the_young_eccentrics_of.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jennings's film, with its missing fathers, sometimes threatens to become cloying, but it's almost always righted by a healthy dose of slapstick or the spectacle of little kids posing as muscle-bound killers.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#33134</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This year’s diamond in the rough, a small movie that is big in heart and promises to be big at the box office.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9621</url>
         <critic>Jamie Tipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A quirky charmer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/son-rambow/review/293339</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don't be put off by the title. This is no sequel, but a surprisingly charming British comedy that is only tangentially associated with "Rambo."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-05-01-rambow_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A quirk-heavy comedy that tonally reads almost exactly like "Millions," as executed by amateur actors having the time of their lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-son-of/408070/content</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As is the case with many English comedies, some of the film's slang is hard to understand. But Jennings' sprightly films proves that although England and America are countries divided by the same language, they are united by slapstick comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080509_Childhood_reveries__suffused_with_Stallone_visions.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Few movies have captured the intoxicating effect of pop culture on kids better than Son of Rambow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080509.wson09/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For much of its frolicsome, rambling running-time, Son of Rambow is like a guarana-spiked soft drink: It goes down easy and delivers a kick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.rambow16may16,0,4789141.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is filled with scenes about scrappy, cut-and-paste filmmaking, and the movie-within-a-movie that drives the plot also ends up as the centerpiece of the hugely affecting final scenes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/533905.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gentle story that involves a great deal of violence, but mostly the violence is muted and dreamy, like a confrontation with a fearsome scarecrow that looks horrifying but is obviously not real --- or real enough, but not alive.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080508/REVIEWS/805080302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Son of Rambow bristles with the anarchic energy of late childhood and a genuine respect for the life-changing power of movies--even (or especially) the schlocky ones.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2190376/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A crowd-pleasing combination of buoyant spirit and occasionally dark humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1135871&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A likable, lightly sticky valentine to childhood, the 1980s and the dawning of movie love, Son of Rambow was written and directed by Garth Jennings and produced by Nick Goldsmith, the duo behind the underappreciated fantasy "The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy."</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/05/02/movies/02ramb.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its most likable, Son of Rambow evokes the rush of discovery that turns budding cinephiles into lifers--that delight in finding a film that seems to express or coalesce some inchoate yearning, including a yen to share.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0818,new-blood,427333,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>My only regret is that the film could not somehow take a leap forward to 1988. I would love to have seen what Lee and Will could do with "Die Hard."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0502/p25s13-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The resulting tale of friendship and family touches plenty of crowd-pleasing buttons but comes across as more than a little derivative.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/s/son_rambow.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An endearing, well-acted trifle with lovely intentions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/151/story/635649.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sweetly raucous adventure. Widely quoted comparisons to "Billy Elliot" and Tim Burton overstate the case for what is really a modestly eccentric entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117932571&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Luckily, Son of Rambow, a comedy that's part kid-buddy flick, part valentine to filmmaking - and full of heart - has both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/05/02/2008-05-02_greenhorn_beret_action_in_son_of_rambow.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The team who made "The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy" display plenty of whirligig energy, if not much control or lightness of touch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20196647,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The shooting of the movie-within-a-movie offers the brightest moments in Son Of Rambow, a testament to the innocence of the boys' creative impulse and the sheer unlikely pleasure of their friendship.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/son_of_rambow</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A hodgepodge of popular kids' elements crammed into a mishmash of a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=8696&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Duane Byrge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An '80s coming-of-age comedy with more energy than ideas.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/05022008/entertainment/movies/soldier_boyhood_109018.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The super-hip style is groovy but doesn't mask the fact that Son of Rambow doesn't really go anywhere special or say anything much. For a film about falling in love with the movies, its insights on them are next to nil.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-son2-2008may02,0,2130455.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If it happens to hit you right - that is, if you happen to catch its wavelength of tear-and-a-smile whimsicality - the movie will speak to you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/05/08/DDGA10IJ8S.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,785,505</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$2,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$53,789</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>5</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>