<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Sorry, Haters</name>
   <company>IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jeff Stanzler</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jeff Stanzler</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Robin Wright Penn</actor>
      <actor>Abdel Kechiche</actor>
      <actor>Élodie Bouchez</actor>
      <actor>Aasif Mvi</actor>
      <actor>Sra Oh</actor>
      <actor>Remy K. Selma</actor>
      <actor>Josh Hamilton</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 1, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>83</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>So long as Sorry, Haters stays ambiguous and sticks to long, winding conversations between Penn and Kechiche, the movie rolls along and builds momentum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45851</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that begins in intrigue, develops in fascination and ends in a train wreck. It goes spectacularly wrong, and yet it contains such a gripping performance by Robin Wright Penn that it succeeds, in a way, despite itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060316/REVIEWS/60314006/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A well-acted little thriller of the sort sometimes called a "twisty" -- I wouldn't call it a great movie, but it'll keep you guessing about its characters and it has an intriguing mean streak.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/02/23/btm/index2.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An audacious, highly contemporary psychological thriller, Sorry,Haters is the kind of audience provoker certain to elicit at least as many haters as admirers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001180511</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's all about the performances. Kechiche is reserved and superbly troubled, but Wright Penn, her stardom-crippling reserves of bitterness and bile rising to the surface, is a scary monster in full bloom, and her habitation of this wacky role makes the movie worth its weight in pixels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0609,atkinson,72350,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is cross-eyed with fuzzy thinking; it's also an interesting, if wacko, artistic response to world events.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1173449_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stanzler's ideas about the psychic legacy of 9/11 are so confused -- that by the time he unveils the final plot twist, his film has lost every shred of credibility.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46756</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Penn looks bewildered in a role that simply doesn't track, but Kechiche rises to the occasion. Stanzler's helming, shot blandly in digital vid, amounts to point-and-shoot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;head=berlin&amp;nav=RBerlin&amp;articleid=VE1117928516&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A preposterous screwball psychological drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060317-movies-review-haters,0,3965765.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This rancidly exploitative movie is redeemed only by canny performances by both leads, as well as Sandra Oh in a supporting role as Phoebe’s friend.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film-reviews/12916/film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Sorry, viewers" is more like it.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29397_SORRY_HATERS.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfolds with such utter looniness that the horrible final moments are more likely to inspire laughter than shock. Casually insulting our emotions and intelligence, Mr. Stanzler seems to have shaped his film with one goal in mind: to prove that audacity and recklessness are acceptable substitutes for craft and common sense. Needless to say, they're not.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/01/movies/01hate.html</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So misguided as to be genuinely mystifying, Jeff Stanzler's queasily blended political psychodrama isn't simply a lousy movie. It's also a lousy movie that boldly exploits the events of 9/11.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/396245p-335862c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not even Sandra Oh, as Phoebe's boss, and Elodie Bouchez ("The Dreamlife of Angels"), as Ashade's sister-in-law, can keep Sorry, Haters from becoming a sorry mess.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64560.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a well-meaning but ultimately feeble and misguided attempt to say something profound about the aftereffects of the 2001 attacks on New York.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/17/DDGERHOUMQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$6,364</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$3,589</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>