<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Stealth</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>W.D. Richter</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rob Cohen</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Josh Lucas</actor>
      <actor>Jessica Biel</actor>
      <actor>Jamie Foxx</actor>
      <actor>Sam Shepard</actor>
      <actor>Richard Roxburgh</actor>
      <actor>Joe Morton</actor>
      <actor>Ian Bliss</actor>
      <actor>Ebon Moss-Bachrach</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 29, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>117</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stick it out through the first ten incoherent minutes or so, and Stealth is an invigorating reward, especially the tense final half-hour.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2221</url>
         <critic>Sara Brady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While you're in the theater, it's actually -- heaven help me -- pretty fun to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1122544915215390.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you like hard bodies and hot engines, if you want to feel like you're inside a cockpit or a video game with someone else working the joystick, you'll find decent escape from the summer doldrums in Stealth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.stealth29jul29,1,3522042.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This giddy summer extravaganza does deliver aerial thrills with eye-dazzling visuals and ear-smacking (though beautifully designed) sound.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=368674&amp;reviewId=18630&amp;startDate=07%2F29%2F2005</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If the Navy is looking for splashy recruiting tools, it could do worse than Stealth, a zillion-dollar action movie stuffed with futuristic jet fighters, glamorous carrier pilots and an overload of explosive, mostly digital derring-do.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-07-28/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A slick piece of summer entertainment that is counting on elaborate special effects to make its derivative, convoluted story line all but irrelevant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-stealth29jul29,0,2430667.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On one level, Stealth is technically breathtaking, viscerally thrilling action cinema of the highest order. On another, it is slavering, state-of-the-art war porn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=10241</url>
         <critic>Simon Braund</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Makes a serviceable summer shoot-'em-up, but it's surprisingly trashy and rather stupid, and its efforts toward being a gripping military drama in the Tom Clancy tradition are fairly pathetic.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/234383_stealth29q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it's loaded with visceral thrills, it never rises above the level of an extended video game or an advertisement for the military.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28301_STEALTH.html</url>
         <critic>Joshua Katzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though Stealth's strengths are obvious -- high-tech marvels and a good cast -- so are its flaws. At its worst moments, a mad robot seems to have taken over the movie, too.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050728-movies-review-stealth,0,3861179.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sort of retarded "Top Gun," Rob Cohen's Stealth revisits the world of cocky fighter pilots and war games turned real, but it has some serious moral quandaries on the brain, and too much thinking gets it into trouble.</snippet>
         <url>http://redesign.theonion.com/avclub/node/25075</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even Cohen can't dull the loony romanticism of the movie’s finale and, to his credit, stages one truly spectacular bit of action midway through, when Biel bails out behind enemy lines and narrates each harrowing moment of her earthward plummet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3488&amp;Sumbit.x=45&amp;Sumbit.y=6</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stealth, a dregs-of-summer knockoff, is too ponderous and inept to serve a comparable function now, yet the film's lack of thrust may be related to an absence of conviction about its own war-is-a-videogame clichés.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1087402_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plays like a slapdash assemblage of the greatest hits of conspiracy-minded action cinema.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A281284</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hollywood's latest virtual movie, features impressive action sequences -- all created through technology -- a thin story, cardboard characters and snicker-inducing dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000999942</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aiming to join the Jerry Bruckheimer/Michael Bay school of American movie war games, Stealth is just too dumb to make the grade.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927778?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stealth is an offense against taste, intelligence and the noise pollution code -- a dumbed-down "Top Gun" crossed with the HAL 9000 plot from "2001."</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050727/REVIEWS/50713001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flimsy and forgettable, but it does have a few worthy action and special-effects sequences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/07-29-2005/entertainment/col/story/332487p-283995c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Stealth were a recruitment film for aircraft-carrier duty, one would be tempted to say, "Mission accomplished." As a feature film, it's a washout.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=368674&amp;reviewId=18637</url>
         <critic>David Hiltbrand</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Plastic characters, chaotic camerawork, lots of things blowing up, and an incredibly dumb screenplay. In short, it represents a great time at the movies for anyone who has recently undergone a frontal lobotomy.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/s/stealth.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The dialogue is often drowned out by engine noise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/28/AR2005072800595.html</url>
         <critic>Michael O&amp;#039;Sullivan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's interesting about Stealth isn't its nitwit story... No, what's interesting about this movie - and many others of its kind - is that it continues the love affair Hollywood, that hotbed of liberalism, has long had with militarism.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/29/movies/29stea.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brought down by repeated bursts of high absurdity.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The scene where a pilot bails out in Stealth is so over-painted with CGI that it doesn't look as real as the sequence starring Shepard that inspired it in "The Right Stuff," a movie made with model airplanes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/50562.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's astonishing what little impact even the most imaginatively choreographed and well-filmed aerial escapades can have when they're presented as neither an expression of a character's personality, nor in the context of a compelling mission.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/07/29/DDGIHDUSB815.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cohen (The Fast and the Furious, xXx) is no stranger to cornball excess but Stealth is his chef-d'oeuvre, a movie so audaciously preposterous and jingoistic it plays like a parody of the genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050729/STEALTH29RVT/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stealth is basically the kind of movie a 13-year-old boy given an infinite budget and creative freedom might cook up between Xbox games.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=368674&amp;reviewId=18656</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its action sequences, more geeky than thrilling, fail to rescue the laughable plot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0531,halter1,66467,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ed Halter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even by the degraded standards of dim-witted summer blockbusters, this is sorry stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46185</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a movie to pretend, in the face of the deaths of tens of thousands of Iraqi men, women, and children directly or indirectly caused by our presence there, that we can wage war without anyone really getting hurt isn't naive, or wishful thinking, or a jim-dandy way to spend a Saturday night at the movies. It's an obscenity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=6024</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's not new. It's not interesting. I wish it would go away.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/28/AR2005072802248.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$32,116,746</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$138,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$13,251,545</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,495</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>jamie foxx</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>