<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Stick It</name>
   <company>Buena Vista Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jessica Bendinger</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jessica Bendinger</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jeff Bridges</actor>
      <actor>Missy Peregrym</actor>
      <actor>Vanessa Lengies</actor>
      <actor>Tarah Paige</actor>
      <actor>Maddy Curley</actor>
      <actor>Kellan Lutz</actor>
      <actor>John Patrick Amedori</actor>
      <actor>Mio Dzakula</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>105</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A spry teenage comedy that gets everything right, Stick It takes the usual batch of underdogs, dirt bags, mean girls and bimbos and sends them somersaulting through happy clichés and unexpected invention.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/28/movies/28stic.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A sports empowerment fantasy of the best kind.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/268266_stick28q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Other than flubbing the dismount, Stick It is smarter and funnier than it has any right to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1146092111298530.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Much of the honest dialogue has the same feel as John Hughes' and Cameron Crowe's movies during their best years, while there's a half-serious hipness that recalls the first eight episodes of "The O.C."</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/04/28/DDGI2IFU0H1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deliriously, defiantly unfocused headrush, Stick It is primarily an exercise in exercise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1188878_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Subversively funny, Stick It sees gymnastics as a microcosm of teen life.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=586465&amp;reviewId=20644</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Peregrym's performance as fiery, troubled teen Haley Graham is a triumph of charisma over technique.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/04-28-2006/entertainment/col/story/412762p-348941c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bendinger pulls out all the stops visually, using bold set design, frantic editing, extreme angles and computer image multiplying that turns what begins as a Busby Berkeley exercise in synchronized movement into a kaleidoscopic infinity of handsprings and back flips.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46808&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the familiar story arc and MTV visuals, Bendinger puts this across with a certain amount of pizzazz, and the competitive gymnastics are often spectacular.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29570_STICK_IT.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spends an inordinate amount of time ogling the tight, lithe bodies of its young female characters. Thus, what might have appealed only to teen girls might well have crossover appeal to leering young boys as well.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002424506</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bridges gives the movie its only genuine pulse as a gym coach known for his hard and manipulative ways.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930346?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stick It uses the story of a gymnast's comeback attempt as a backdrop for overwrought visual effects, music videos, sitcom dialogue and general pandering. The movie seems to fear that if it pauses long enough to actually be about gymnastics, the audience will grow restless.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060427/REVIEWS/60421004/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Peregrym is like a secondhand Hilary Swank. She has a looser presence and might be a better actor, but since we already have Swank, finding out is not a priority.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8836</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bridges actually does a fine job in an uninteresting role. But this chick flick is all about the attitudinal teenagers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-04-27-stick-it-review_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The final meet felt eternal to me, but little girls may love it all, and even if they don't, they're almost sure to practice their handstands when they get home.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13307/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So along with being fake punk-rock, Stick It is also a fake protest movie. That leaves the only traces of genuineness to Bridges, who plays the coach with a fatherly patience that earns him a paycheck, but not the better film he deserves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/47874</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stick It reels from its own frenetic pace. The music is loud, the camera cuts are incessant and everything seems geared toward distracting us from what's going on onscreen. Which is not much.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060428-movies-review-stick,0,2282488.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like "Bring It On," Stick It is so much better than most of its insipid teen-movie peers yet like her earlier movie, Bendinger's new one is also not all it might be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A360492</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Peregrym is a fresh-faced beauty and Bridges is enjoyably cranky, but the film is as bland as an Afterschool Special.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0428/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even though William Safire doesn't fit in the target demographic, Stick It is more valuable as a survey of modern American teen argot than as a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060428.STICK28/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Jason Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Another rah rah girl power film, is your formula sports film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8954</url>
         <critic>Felix Vasques Jr.</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script fights well against the cliche-ridden plot but this is very average all round.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133288</url>
         <critic>Simon Braund</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film strives for some type of a girl-empowerment message that equates trading one type of conformity for another with self-determination but muffs the dismount and stumbles on the landing. In other words, it fails to Stick It.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-stick28apr28,0,1372883.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of gold-medal-winning, last-minute heroics, the movie weirdly becomes about the scandal of arbitrary gymnastics judges. Is it a movie or an episode of "Real Sports"? It veers into fresh territory but not dramatically satisfying territory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1111711&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rarely is a sports movie so inept that it can't even make its central figure likable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/67692.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$26,910,736</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$20,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$10,803,610</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,038</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>