<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Stolen</name>
   <company>International Film Circuit</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rebecca Dreyfus</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Blythe Danner</actor>
      <actor>Campbell Scott</actor>
      <actor>Harold J. Smith</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 21, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Poe-like atmosphere in Stolen is such a chilling success that when Mashberg says that Gardner would have cracked this case herself, it's impossible to imagine that she isn't out looking for those paintings right now.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9135</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's easy to understand why so many people have been obsessed with this story for so long. When the paintings are finally found, the story will make a great Hollywood movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/67349.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But in the end it all comes to naught: Tantalyzing though the leads are, the paintings remain elusive.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46887&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stolen is about a puzzle that's resisted solution for more than 15 years, but that doesn't stop it from being a fascinating, adventurous documentary with a lively and eccentric cast of characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-stolen3nov03,0,7299661.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever the outcome of all this hugger-mugger, as yet unresolved, Stolen gives us hints about a special sort of muscle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060515&amp;s=kauffmann051506</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Little turns out well in Rebecca Dreyfus's Stolen, a haunting and expansive documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16701/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Provides a treasure trove of outrageous characters, rampant speculation, personal obsessions and a glimpse into the rarefied world of art collecting. Instead of spinning off in so many directions, the film actually pulls together into an engrossing meditation on the value of art in our lives.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000973501</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A documentay  that should appeal not just to the legion of Vermeer fans, but to lovers of good mystery.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926475?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's like racing through a detective novel, only to find the last page has been torn out.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/04-21-2006/entertainment/col/story/410763p-347375c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A captivating documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=620146&amp;reviewId=21066</url>
         <critic>Marta Barber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite the soft-spoken Smith, a type-A British liaison self-named the Turbocharger, and the apparent involvement of the IRA, the doc prioritizes flash over facts, leaving you pining for the New Yorker exposé it could've been.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0616,atkinson,72923,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rife with conspiracy and colorful characters, this globe-trotting intrigue has the makings of a splendid thriller, but Ms. Dreyfus has fashioned only a middling documentary, failing to locate a compelling structure or rhythm in the material.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/04/21/movies/21stol.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, we're treated to an overture of possibilities rather than a satisfying film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1120662&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Deyfus' haphazard filmmaking dissipates a potentially fascinating mystery into one long diversion.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/275866_limited30.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stolen owes its persuasiveness less to its substance than to the visual craft of Dreyfus and her celebrated cinematographer, Albert Maysles. In telling the story of an unsolved crime, they use every trick available to awaken and prolong suspense before a payoff that never comes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/09/01/DDGM4KS9JQ1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Baker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Several potentially compelling narratives jockey for breathing room in this disappointing documentary about the unsolved 1990 heist of 13 paintings (valued at $500 million) from Boston's Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/14926/</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$132,596</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$10,271</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>