<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Stoning of Soraya M., The</name>
   <company>Roadside Attractions, MPower Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Cyrus Nowrasteh</author>
      <author>Betsy Giffen Nowrasteh</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Cyrus Nowrasteh</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Shohreh Aghdashloo</actor>
      <actor>Jim Caviezel</actor>
      <actor>Mozhan Marno</actor>
      <actor>Ali Pourtash</actor>
      <actor>Navid Negahban</actor>
      <actor>David Diaan</actor>
      <actor>Parviz Sayyad</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 26, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>116</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Stoning of Soraya M. goes well beyond its angry didacticism and its specific indictment of men's oppression of women to achieve the impact of a Greek tragedy through its masterful grasp of suspense and group psychology, and some superb acting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-stoning26-2009jun26,0,6554858.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a powerful, shocking piece, and the denunciation of a system in which an accused woman has to prove her own innocence (while in the case of a man, his guilt has to be proven by others), is strong and clear and unforgettable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11676</url>
         <critic>Peter Brunette</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Stoning of Soraya M.”has such a powerful stoning sequence that I recommend it if only for its brutal ideological message. That the pitiful death of Soraya is followed by a false Hollywood upbeat ending involving tape recordings and silliness about a car that won't start is simply shameful. Nowrasteh, born in Colorado, attended the USC Film School. Is that what they teach there?</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090624/REVIEWS/906249978</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The sum is difficult to watch. But this isn't a film against Islam or religion in general: A clear distinction is made between Allah's more vicious followers and the mercy of Allah himself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/06/25/MVS918DBAH.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Amy Biancolli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A timely story, given the political upheaval in Iran, it is emotionally explosive. It also is profoundly compelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-06-25-stoning-of-soraya_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Stoning of Soraya M.'s drawn-out torture sequence is harrowing and lurid.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20288863,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Based on a French true-crime best seller, this gory, ham-fisted hybrid of social-issue picture and horror film exerts a crude but undeniable power.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34516_STONING_OF_SORAYA_N.html</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This broadside against sharia law lacks the finesse of an import, but it's effectively melodramatic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/A41EBD8F74FD26DE862575F4007299EB?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The last thing I want to do is represent The Stoning of Soraya M. as entertainment, summer or otherwise. This is classic tragedy in semimodern dress that means to horrify, and does so more successfully than any film in recent memory.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As with so many message movies, this one trades ­nuance for naked outrage. The filmmakers'heartfelt intent is admirable, but right now they’re competing with a more compellingly told reality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/06/26/2009-06-26_short_takes_film_reviews_in_brief_including_afghan_star_and_surveillance_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A slow, inexorable slog to the titular event -- a public execution so inconceivably violent and brutal the movie practically dares you not to look away.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1133704.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though The Stoning of Soraya M.'s heart is in the right place, its head is lost in storm clouds of anger.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/the-stoning-of-soraya-m/article1221368/</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film oddly mirrors "The Passion of the Christ," as a show trial leads inexorably toward an almost sadistically filmed public execution (it doesn't hurt that Jim Caviezel plays the reporter). Like that movie, it gets its point across with all the subtlety, sorry to say, of a rock upside the head.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/07/stoning_a_tale_of_injustice_in.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It also gives another black eye to Iranian fundamentalists. It is most unfortunate, then, that the film isn't better.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06262009/entertainment/movies/executioners_wrong_176120.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is basically self-congratulatory fare for people who feel more "politically conscious" when reminded that women in the Islamic world can have it rough. Right now, you're better off just watching the news.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-06-24/film/a-particularly-appaling-application-of-sharia-law-in-stoning-of-soraya-m/</url>
         <critic>Vadim Rizov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Nowrasteh seems to think the only way to save lives is to sensationalize death. You could trek to the theater and have this movie whack you upside the head. You could also just mail a check for $10 to the human rights group of your choice.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/06/26/8216the_stoning_of_soraya_m8217_doesn8217t_hold_back_anything/</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thoroughly blurs the line between high-minded outrage and lurid torture-porn.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/26/movies/26stoning.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nowrasteh constantly overplays his hand, not realizing that some horrors speak for themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/the-stoning-of-soraya-m,29671/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Iranian American director Cyrus Nowrasteh, co-writing with wife Betsy Giffen Nowrasteh, has amplified the basic elements of Suraya's story into the worst kind of exploitive Hollywood melodrama, presented under the virtuous guise of moral outrage.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/the-stoning-of-soraya-m.,1156567.html</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A classic case of preaching to the choir, since it’s doubtful the film will reach many of the minds that need changing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A815643</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$655,871</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$115,053</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>27</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>