<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Sugar</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Anna Boden</author>
      <author>Ryan Fleck</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Anna Boden</director>
      <director>Ryan Fleck</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Algenis Pérez Soto</actor>
      <actor>Rayniel Rufino</actor>
      <actor>Andre Holl</actor>
      <actor>Michael Gaston</actor>
      <actor>Jaime Tirelli</actor>
      <actor>José Rijo</actor>
      <actor>Ann Whitney</actor>
      <actor>Richard Bull</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 3, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>120</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is both sad and hopeful, but the film's sorrow and its optimism arise from its rarest and most thrilling quality, which is its deep and humane honesty.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/04/03/movies/03suga.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In its unhurried fashion, Sugar can take its place with the best baseball movies. Where most focus on the grand slam, this one's about the life that surrounds the game and everything that comes after.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/04/10/sugar/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This one slice of the American experience amounts to one of the best films of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-tc-mov-sugar-0415-17apr17,0,2295042.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sugar is that sweetest of films: A sensitive and memorable story that surprises at every turn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-04-16-sugar-review_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As the film plays out its melancholy story, we realize that what we are watching is far rarer than the usual sports flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0413/p17s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A baseball movie, a stranger-in-a-strange-land movie, a movie about real people facing real challenges in the real world, Sugar is all that and more.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20090424_Story_of_a_Latino_player_in_the_U_S__has_big-league_charm.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film of rare intelligence, beauty and compassion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/sugar,1098106.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A moving, surprising and provocative baseball flick that rises immediately to No. 1 with a bullet on my personal list.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/04/03/sugar/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is raw and riveting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/17578414/review/27182503/sugar</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Algenis Perez Soto plays the character so openly, so naturally, that an interesting thing happens: Baseball is only the backdrop, not the subject. This is a wonderful film.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090415/REVIEWS/904159997</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sugar is a near-great movie with qualities more unusual than some all-time classics. It resists cliche at every turn and puts something solid in its place: raw yet controlled observation that gives the film the form of a flexing muscle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.sugar15may15,0,7364580.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's quality, wit and emotion throughout.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/04/review_land_of_milk_honey_and.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Instead of hitting all the usual beats, Sugar just moseys in a mostly delightful way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/sugar,26068/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's style is so ''objective'' it's a bit subdued, yet this is a sports drama of total originality, as well as the most authentic inside view of the immigrant experience the movies have given us in quite a while.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20269305,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Without a trace of didacticism, Boden and Fleck portray the insidious details of exploitation and hollow American maxims.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-04-01/film/boden-and-fleck-s-sugar-sidesteps-sports-clich-eacute-s-finds-the-sweet-spot/</url>
         <critic>Melissa Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sympathetic, genial and exceedingly wholesome, it's a film that, once seen, will permanently and favorably influence the way viewers regard the characters' real-life counterparts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2471&amp;reviewid=VE1117935902&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most remarkable thing Sugar does is give American viewers a sense of how our country must seem to a newly arrived immigrant, without caricaturing or condescending to either guest or host.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2215241/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As good as it is because of the care and skill writer-directors Anna Boden and Ryan Fleck bring to it, gifts that were visible in their first film, "Half Nelson," which earned a lead actor Oscar nomination for Ryan Gosling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/la-et-sugar3-2009apr03,0,6078801.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The filmmakers have mostly cast from Dominican playing fields rather than from acting studios -- Algenis Perez Soto, the accomplished first-time performer who plays Miguel Sugar Santos, was himself a teen ballplayer -- so game and practice sequences have an easy authenticity from the start.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=102832593</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a drama of shifting values and compromised ideals, arriving at a view of life that's wise, complicated, and tinged with melancholy.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34289_SUGAR.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mainly, though, the film's strength is reportorial, sensitively exploring a theme that has grown ever more prominent with the globalization of sport.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090416.wsugar0417/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gripping look at the immigrant experience, with small moments as important - and visually arresting - as any on the baseball diamond.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/04/09/DDP916V7AG.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Curiel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The price of the production's integrity is a leisurely pace -- but it's a worthwhile one. Though Sugar demands patience, it deserves attention.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123870443126983769.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoughtful drama about guys who have a moment in the big time before returning home to an odd reflected glory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/04/03/2009-04-03_short_takes.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Algenis Perez Soto was a baseball player in real life, which helps to explain his sensitive, understated performance as Sugar. But he's let down by a manipulative script recycled from dozens of sports and immigrant movies. At least it dispenses with a Hollywood ending.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04032009/entertainment/movies/baseball_days__unsweetened_162587.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sugar is a curiosity – too somber for a picaresque, too arm's-length for much emotional effect – and while it's interesting, it's never truly absorbing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A776218</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,081,922</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$60,140</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>11</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>