<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Talk to Me</name>
   <company>Focus Features</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Michael Genet</author>
      <author>Rick Famuyiwa</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Kasi Lemmons</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Don Cheadle</actor>
      <actor>Chiwetel Ejiofor</actor>
      <actor>Mike Epps</actor>
      <actor>Martin Sheen</actor>
      <actor>Cedric the Entertainer</actor>
      <actor>Vondie Curtis-Hall</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 13, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>118</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A rowdy, richly offbeat biopic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20045727,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Talk to Me has a great subject and a great actor working in tandem, reminding audiences that once upon a time media personalities used to fight The Man, not be The Man.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070713-movies-review-talk,0,669334.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Someone like Petey Greene made a difference and made a mark, and broadcasting is better because of his transparent honesty. He helped transform African-American stations more, probably, than their mostly white owners desired. And talk talents like Howard Stern, whether they know who he was, owe him something.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070712/REVIEWS/70620007</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As Greene, Don Cheadle - explosive because you've never before seen this model of actorly restraint - is a one-man fireworks show in Talk to Me, Kasi Lemmons' rollicking, resonant portrait of the real-life ex-con who improbably became a civic icon.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20070713_Talk_testifies_to_power_of_unity.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No matter what character Don Cheadle has played in his 23-year career, he's always seemed to be holding something back...Until Talk to Me.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=894056&amp;reviewId=22597&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hughes' push for Greene to succeed confronts the nettlesome issues of racial identity that most films vigorously avoid. The worthiness of Talk to Me will be proved if it gets us talking to each other.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/325259_talk27q.html</url>
         <critic>Gianni Truzzi</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once Greene achieves fame, neither he nor the screenplay quite knows what to do; the first half-hour of Talk to Me is the most fun. But a vibrant feel for its era and a genuine affection for its characters make the whole thing a solid evocation of a time and a life worth remembering.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1185404157118820.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kasi Lemmons' movie is called Talk to Me, but what it really does is sing to you, in the argot and cadences of soul, jazz, rock and rhythm and blues.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.talktome13jul13,0,268239.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Cheadle's fearlessly robust performance absolutely galvanizes Talk to Me, it's not the only thing that makes Kasi Lemmons' third feature such a pleasure to take in.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9406&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a movie that offers uplift without phoniness, history without undue didacticism and a fair number of funny, dirty jokes.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/07/13/movies/13talk.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A vital entertainment that struts confidently between comedy and drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/19762054/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Eventually you may come to think of Talk to Me as a true movie rarity -- a very honest yet curiously affecting experience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1643422,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Talk to Me speaks powerfully to audiences with its potent blend of extraordinary performances and engaging soundtrack.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-07-12-talk-to-me_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Talk to Me is a welcome reminder of a time when radio truly listened to the people instead of just shouted at them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/231/story/182693.html</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Especially wonderful is Taraji P. Henson as Petey's longtime girlfriend Vernell , a vision in Foxy Brown period clothes with a pixie smile, lollipop legs, and a filthy mouth. After "Hustle &amp; Flow ," this is at least the second movie Henson has stolen, and will Hollywood please do something about it?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10051</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cheadle and Ejiofor are riveting together; they have the kind of apparently effortless chemistry that makes every scene they share a delight. With a dynamite soundtrack under their feet, the two of them rock the house.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/talk/review/285626</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Talk to Me, with two great actors, tells that story, and it makes you feel not only the joy people experienced in the wash of Greene's raucous, truth-saying humor, but also his wisdom and calm. And many mourned his death at 55 in 1984.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1134222&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With its R&amp;B soundtrack and footage of civil unrest, Talk to Me might seem to cover familiar ground. But as an intimate portrait of the complex, fruitful and extremely volatile friendship between trailblazing African American men whose daring came to redefine an industry, it's fresh and revelatory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-talk13jul13,0,3425142.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An imperfect picture that's alive every minute, a movie that perfectly captures the vibe of a person, a place, a time and a way of being, and even gets, indirectly and without a whiff of sanctimoniousness, to the heart of what being an American ought to mean.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/07/13/talk_to_me/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A poignant reminder of why people used to actually listen to their radios.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10166</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>From James Brown to Sam Cooke, the songs set a mood that lingers for some time after.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A509496</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The problem is, the last section of the movie doesn't follow the career path of Greene: It traces the blander character of Hughes. Cheadle, who galvanizes the first half of the film, fades from view, and the best part of the conversation in Talk to Me goes with him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070727.wtalktomerevu0727/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite being abandoned in the late going by his director, Cheadle gives one of the year's most fully realized performances, and Henson is a revelation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/07/13/2007-07-13_cheadles_righton_as_a_60s_dj.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Don Cheadle has a fine time jiving through Talk to Me - accent, please, on the middle word. It's a black "Good Morning, Vietnam."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/07132007/entertainment/movies/boogie_mikes_movies_kyle_smith.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Alternates too deliberately between jaunty comedy and serious message-making.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933973.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie always teeters on the verge of something deeper, and Cheadle’s rendering of Greene’s stubborn refusal to be domesticated is funny, exhilarating and then quietly tragic. But Lemmons keeps pulling back into jive-talking shtick, and for much of the time -- I felt as though someone had trapped me in a time-warped episode of "The Jeffersons."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/talk-to-me-shock-jockery/16814/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There’s terrific chemistry between the leads, but an episodic structure set over 20 years is too sprawling to really allow for a connection.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134091</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, that story isn't particularly well told, and after a while, the strength of the two leads' work and the popping soundtrack can't hide the fact that Lemmons doesn't really have much to say about the material.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/talk_to_me</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever brought Greene down was far more complex than this film allows for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0713/p16s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The early scenes of Greene misbehaving on the air are pretty funny, thanks mainly to Martin Sheen as the apoplectic station manager. But I was bummed out by the movie's trite VH1 cartoon of the black power era--especially coming from Kasi Lemmons, who made her directing debut with the hauntingly ambiguous "Eve's Bayou."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/31831_TALK_TO_ME_CHEADLE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The banality of Talk To Me is only half disappointing; at least it babbles clichés with conviction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0728,lee,77209,20.html</url>
         <critic>Nathan Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A potentially great movie winds up buried inside a just OK one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/07/13/DDGAEQV0OB1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a movie that celebrates the power of speech, Talk to Me is oddly tongue tied. Its dialogue, equal parts uptight honky and jumping jive seems, particularly in the early stretches, to have been generated by a computer.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118428191638465246.html</url>
         <critic>Joanne Kaufman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$4,526,759</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$402,000</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>33</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>