<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Then She Found Me</name>
   <company>THINKFilm</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Helen Hunt</author>
      <author>Vic Levin</author>
      <author>Alice Arlen</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Helen Hunt</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Helen Hunt</actor>
      <actor>Bette Midler</actor>
      <actor>Colin Firth</actor>
      <actor>Matthew Broderick</actor>
      <actor>Ben Shankman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 25, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>100</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A smart, subtle and seriously funny dramedy bound to find favor with sophisticated auds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934911.html?categoryid=2850&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With the screenwriters Alice Arlen and Victor Levin, Hunt adapted the story from a 1990 novel by Elinor Lipman, and has turned the material into a fine, tense, unpredictable comedy of mixed-up emotions and sudden illuminations.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/05/05/080505crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A strength of Then She Found Me, from Elinor Lipman's novel, is its straightforward, uncomplicated storytelling that keeps the threads untangled and blends the everyday and the absurd with natural ease.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-then-she/396980/content</url>
         <critic>Sid Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While there are plenty of laughs, Hunt doesn't play this for farce. Even Midler gives perhaps the most restrained, and arguably the most winning, performance of her screen career.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04252008/entertainment/movies/hunt_for_a_wombmate_107947.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hunt's movie-directing debut frequently crackles with nice gags.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20192234,00.html</url>
         <critic>Clark Collis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Hunt's show, and she delivers a strong performance that captures all the seriousness and absurdity of the avalanche of circumstances that comes crashing down on April's head. To say she's only half the director she is an actress is actually paying her quite a complement.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/then/review/293338</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The new movie shrieks of motherhood - raising hot-button issues like biological clocks running down, the rights of birth mothers and whether to adopt or give artificial insemination a shot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/05/01/DDII10E0F3.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With subtle laughs but solid emotional thrust, it will play very well with older audiences.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?&amp;rid=9776</url>
         <critic>John DeFore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Then She Found Me, a serious comedy, is more impressive for what it refuses to do than for its modest accomplishment.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/04/25/movies/25foun.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's something about Hunt's put-upon persona that grates, and it would be nice to see her for once in a role that doesn't call on her to be so angry, short-tempered and disappointed all the time...Still, all in all, Then She Found Me is a warm, entertaining and well-made little movie and an auspicious debut for Hunt the director.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-found25apr25,0,4850884.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While Hunt's directing debut is promising, if understated, it's her performance as schoolteacher April Epner that impresses the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/361411_found02q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Some may dismiss Then She Found Me as a mere "women's film," but it's really a more honest and mature take on sex and the city.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A620086</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What ought to be a bittersweet movie about a woman's momentary unraveling feels like a workout class: Cardio melodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=11089</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are some wise observations about parenting. Hunt draws some good performances from the cast and wisely chose a low-key personal story for her directorial debut.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-05-08-then-she-found-me_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot, as hinted, goes strictly by the "How April Got Her Groove Back" book, but it must be said that the performances push it a notch above pedestrian.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/05/review_helen_hunts_then_she_fo.html</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This whole movie has zero chemistry. Broderick and Hunt are a match made in hell; Firth and Hunt are a match made in limbo.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.found09may09,0,3563492.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The material is so charged that it threatens to electrocute any who would touch it. Yet from the moment that Bette Midler, as Bernice the bio-Mom, appears, she becomes the instrument of its emotional release, catharsis teetering on high heels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080502_Mother-daughterhood_movie_tests_limits_of_maternal_bond.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No, there isn't anything wrong with comfort entertainment. Then She Found Me could have, should have been something special - a "Knocked Up" for weary boomers. The only hitch is that it isn't all that entertaining. Nor comforting for that matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080425.wfound25/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Stephen Cole</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's a quirky, honest movie struggling to emerge from Then She Found Me (April's Jewish heritage is refreshingly portrayed, and there are lovely, scattered moments when the characters surprise you), but Hunt, in her directorial debut, can't seem to decide whether she'd rather make a spicy ethnic dish or bland comfort food.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/133797</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In short, it's the kind of film that only a mother, which is to say my mother, would love.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0817,then-she-found-me,419645,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With Midler missing in action much of the time, the film drowns in a sea of thudding earnestness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/then_she_found_me</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has some nice moments, but it feels very much like a first film. The pacing is off, and the cast members appear to be acting in completely different projects.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/04/25/2008-04-25_helen_hunt_goes_off_track_with_then_she_.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hunt's crabby performance weighs on the film, though it's nothing compared to Colin Firth's scenery-chewing turn as her self-lacerating new beau.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33088_THEN_SHE_FOUND_ME.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Suffers from, if anything, a lack of pure confidence in the story, the actors or the audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1143523&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is the sort of movie that gives "chick flicks" a bad name. It's a cross between inept melodrama and a bad sit-com.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/t/then_she.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Overall, the film is lost and never found. In her first shot as director, Hunt seems direction-less.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10921</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A bizarre, overcooked broth that combines a broad sitcom style (the banter goes rat-tat-tat like a steam drill) with a preposterous succession of plot complications, plus solemn questions of identity, adoption and the nature of happiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120908724598943787.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,735,717</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$72,594</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>9</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>helen hunt</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>