<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>There Will Be Blood</name>
   <company>Paramount Vantage</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Paul Thomas Anderson</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Paul Thomas Anderson</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Daniel Day-Lewis</actor>
      <actor>Paul Dano</actor>
      <actor>Ciaran Hinds</actor>
      <actor>Kevin J. O&amp;#039;Connor</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 26, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>158</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>There Will Be Blood is ferocious, and it will be championed and attacked with an equal ferocity. When the dust settles, we may look back on it as some kind of obsessed classic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/74407</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There Will Be Blood is, in fact, not a historical saga; rather, it's an absurdist, blackly comic horror film with a very idiosyncratic satanic figure at its core.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4316/there-will-be-blood.html</url>
         <critic>Glenn Kenny</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Daniel Day-Lewis stuns in Paul Thomas Anderson's saga of a soul-dead oil man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=9935&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>John DeFore</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enthralling and powerfully eccentric American epic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2007/12/17/071217crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Boldly and magnificently strange, There Will Be Blood marks a significant departure in the work of Paul Thomas Anderson.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117935281.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a story that's all about the harnessing of fateful chthonic forces, Paul Thomas Anderson has dug deeper than ever before, and struck black gold.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2180466</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For bleakness, the movie can't be beat -- nor for brilliance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20168259,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is above all a consummate work of art, one that transcends the historically fraught context of its making, and its pleasures are unapologetically aesthetic. It reveals, excites, disturbs, provokes, but the window it opens is to human consciousness itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/26/movies/26bloo.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This may be an extremely bold statement to make, but there hasn’t been such an amazing character study in film since “Citizen Kane.” I honestly can’t praise it enough. From the opening to the ghastly ending, this film will sit in the depths of your stomach for some time to come.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10472</url>
         <critic>Zack Haddad</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is truly a work of symphonic aspirations and masterful execution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0752,hoberman,78696,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Daniel Day-Lewis's portrayal is not just the performance of the year -- there will be injustice if he doesn't win an Oscar -- but a creation of awesome proportions.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119880937547154683.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anderson's uncompromising masterpiece will continue to resonate as a harrowing cautionary warning to a country with oil pumping through its veins, clouding its judgment and coarsening its soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/there_will_be_blood</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the most wholly original American movies ever made.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1698168,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Day-Lewis... the role of a lifetime.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-there-will/276085/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A searing, apocalyptic and finally breathtaking drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139949&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With There Will Be Blood, Paul Thomas Anderson has taken a stab at making The Great American Movie -- and I daresay he’s made one of them.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film/there-will-be-blood-is-andersons-citizen-kane/17975/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An unusual, visually hypnotic, American Gothic historical epic that traces the rise and tragic fall of a Western mining magnate of the Gilded Age.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/345931_blood04q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There Will Be Blood" is anti-state of the art. It's the work of an analog filmmaker railing against an increasingly digitized world. In that sense, the movie is idiosyncratic, too: vintage visionary stuff.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10610</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anderson’s fearless, bighearted filmmaking is an antidote to the toxic cloud of Manifest Destiny. He has made a mad American classic.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/42087/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In terms of excitement, imagination and rule-busting experimentation, it's a gusher.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/14710093/review/17925481/there_will_be_blood</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fact that that character happens to be so repellent -- and yet so endlessly fascinating -- is one of the film's many strokes of genius.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/story/373712.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There Will Be Blood is not a movie that disappears quietly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A581507</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Uncompromising, intelligent and searing cinema. Along with The Assassination Of Jesse James... and No Country For Old Men, this is the best batch of Western-set dramas in decades. John Huston would have been proud.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133232</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's first-rank filmmaking, through and through, even if it struggles to find closure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/119984190761940.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sprawling yet cramped, There Will Be Blood may not be the best movie of the year, but it's certainly the strangest. It evokes passing comparisons to everything from "Giant" to "Citizen Kane" but it's impossible to pigeonhole.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0104/p12s04-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's important to remember that Sinclair was as much a committed socialist as a novelist, someone who probably wrote for political purpose more than for dramatic effect. So while Day-Lewis' gorgeous acting largely disguises it, the people in "Blood" tend to be schematic and the film as a whole has a weakness for the didactic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-blood26dec26,0,7809173.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A searingly intense and artful tale that grabs hold of the viewer from its jarring and wordless opening scenes and doesn't let go.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-25-there-will-be-blood_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Just a few barrels short of being a masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20080104_A_daunting_Day-Lewis__pumping_oil_and_blood.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That's not to say that There Will Be Blood isn't something exceptional; it's just that the movie is jarringly erratic, ranging from moments of delicacy to majesty to over-the-top bombast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080103.blood04nat/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The kind of film that is easily called great. I am not sure of its greatness. It was filmed in the same area of Texas used by "No Country for Old Men," and that is a great film, and a perfect one. But There Will Be Blood"is not perfect, and in its imperfections we may see its reach exceeding its grasp. Which is not a dishonorable thing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080103/REVIEWS/801030301/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With a grating symphonic score by ­Radiohead's Jonny Greenwood and the constant sense of danger following Plainview, "Blood" does not release its grip on the audience until its last, bizarrely crazy minutes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/26/2007-12-26_drilling_deep_for_a_role_of_gold_in_ther.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Between D-Day, the sheer ambition of Paul Thomas Anderson's historical epic and Robert Elswit's dazzling cinematography, this is a must-see movie - even though its emotional temperature rarely rises above freezing and the climax goes way, way, way over the top.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12262007/entertainment/movies/oil_star_performance_818366.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, the film's final third is poorly focused and, while there is a clear conclusion, it feels strangely hollow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/t/there_blood.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ambitious, deeply flawed and studded with sequences that achieve pure, majestic greatness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/blood/review/291160</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's mostly a disturbingly believable portrait of a psychopath whose true depths of rage are buried where none but he can see. The ironically named Plainview does not come into plain view until the last scene, and the lupine, scowling Day-Lewis is mesmerizing in the role.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=1002916&amp;reviewId=22841&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This has loads of swagger, but for stylistic audacity I prefer Anderson's more scattershot "Magnolia."</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#32616</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anderson almost brings off a picture worthy of his grandiose ambition.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/01/04/DDVCU8QKP.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are epic impulses everywhere you look in There Will Be Blood; what's missing is character development, focused storytelling and, most significantly (apart from that terrific opening sequence), any sense of raw, intuitive drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/12/26/blood/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Anderson and Day-Lewis strip themselves of their natural talents for invention and poetry, as if any hint of romance, nobility or fun would soften the film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.blood11jan11,0,4686766.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$40,222,514</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$314,917</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>daniel day-lewis</oscar_winning_actor>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>true</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>