<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Thirst</name>
   <company>Focus Features</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Park Chan-wook</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Park Chan-wook</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>SouthKorea</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Song Kang-ho</actor>
      <actor>Shin Ha-kyun</actor>
      <actor>Kim Ok-bi</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 31, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>133</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Blending plot elements of "Double Indemnity" and "Natural Born Killers" with the ripe sensuality of Francis Coppola's take on "Dracula," the film should make audiences sit up in startled pleasure, as if they'd just received the most luscious neck-bite.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1914182,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A brilliant and gruesome work of cinematic invention as well as a passionate and painful human love story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/07/31/thirst/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gaudy, daring, operatic, and bloody funny provocation of a melodrama from Park Chan-wook.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20294559,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Be warned: Thirst is one of those pictures that tacks on another chapter just when you think it’s wrapping up.</snippet>
         <url>http://featuresblogs.chicagotribune.com/talking_pictures/</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Are you hungering for that rare vampire movie with serious intellectual heft, ravishing undead, biting passion and a healthy splash of irony as well as iron in all that spilled red blood? Wait no longer, Korean auteur Park Chan-wook's Thirst should satisfy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-thirst31-2009jul31,0,4326720.story</url>
         <critic>Betsy Sharkey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A terrific film. Loosely based on Emile Zola's novel "Therese Raquin."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11775</url>
         <critic>Nick Antosca</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thirst never picks up the momentum of Park’s best-known work. But its turgid pace creates a queasy fascination all its own, drawing viewers into an ever-darkening locus of sin and obsession where even the wish for redemption comes at a terrible cost.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/thirst,31090/</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The summer's most lip-smacking movie treat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/thirst/article1243529/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Movies exist to cloak our desires in disguises we can accept, and there is an undeniable appeal to Thirst.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090812/REVIEWS/908129983</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thirst is deliriously bonkers and keeps getting more so; you watch it holding your breath, waiting to see where Park will zigzag next.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/08/21/for_those_with_stomach_for_it_thirst_delivers/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, it is also less than the sum of its parts -- overly long, lacking in narrative momentum and too often choosing sensation over coherence.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/07/31/movies/31thirst.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stunning production quality and the story's extremity should arouse interest beyond the specialty Asian market.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/thirst-film-review-1003973508.story</url>
         <critic>Maggie Lee</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's evolution from somber spiritual torment to icky body horror to fetishistic sex to wild lyricism (vampires pogoing off buildings) to Grand Guignol splatter is exhilarating.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/58083/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The most intriguing aspect of Thirst is the steady erosion of Sang-hyeon's ethics, slackened from "do not" to "do not kill" to "do not kill the undeserving" by the lure of those O+ cocktails.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-07-28/film/park-chan-wook-gets-positively-trendy-with-thirst/</url>
         <critic>Jim Ridley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What the film is saying, so far as I can tell, is that, if cut, you will bleed. And bleed. As the vampire's kindred Seven Deadly Sinner, wild-haired Kim Ok-vin looks like she's having a high old time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0731/p17s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Forget "Twilight."  Fans of vampire movies are not likely to see anything more graphic, extreme or twisted than Thirst.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-07-30-thirst_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Do you dig the current vampire craze? Do you love "Twilight" so much you'd die for it? Then skip South Korean writer-director Park Chan-wook's violent, bloody Thirst, a genre-bending - if not genre-destroying - foray into the vampire myth.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20090828__Thirst__starts_with_much_promise__then_devolves_into_repetitious_violence.html</url>
         <critic>Tirdad Derakhshani</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thirst is good, insolent fun for about two-thirds of the way, before it stumbles and drowns in a pool of its own excess. Still, you can't help but admire a horror movie that prompts us to wonder how vampires with a surplus of blood got by before the advent of Tupperware.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/thirst,1150874.html</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I'll stick out my neck and say that Park Chan Wook's wildly gruesome Thirst is the most whacked-out version of an Emile Zola novel ever to reach the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/07/30/MVRN18VMOC.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Taken as a whole, Thirst meanders too far from the crossroads of life and death; it gets outright dull in spots, although they are few and far between.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A820695</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An overlong stygian comedy that badly needs a transfusion of genuine inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117940255.html?u=IMDB&amp;p=H2BE&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$318,574</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$55,889</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>