<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Tony Takitani</name>
   <company>Strand Releasing</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jun Ichikawa</author>
      <author>Haruki Murakami</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jun Ichikawa</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Japan</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Yumi Endo</actor>
      <actor>Rie Miyazawa</actor>
      <actor>Hidetoshi Nishijima</actor>
      <actor>Issei Ogata</actor>
      <actor>Shinohara Takahumi</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 29, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>75</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's underlying theme is the complex relationship between objects and memories, worked out through a taut, compelling story and superbly understated acting. Ryuichi Sakamoto composed the atmospheric score.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0729/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No adventurous filmgoer will want to miss Tony Takitani.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/50519.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a quiet dream of a movie, a vision of loneliness giving way to love, then to loneliness again; it's like "Vertigo" remade in a sedately haunted style of Japanese lyricism.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1089318_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exquisite film, as elegant and precise as an impeccably cut diamond. It's small in scale but wholly mesmerizing, holding us captive as it demonstrates how much enveloping richness can be conveyed with a minimalist style.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/turan/cl-et-takitani26aug26,0,3009008.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A visual poem.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/09/02/DDGPTEGBQN1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A haunting, melancholy fable, Tony Takitani is the kind of film that could seem tedious from a mere description. Approached with the right mind-set, however, it's a hypnotic mood piece on love and loss, one that knows -- at 75 minutes -- not to overstay its welcome.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/113459371535300.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The hues are so muted you may remember this as a black-and-white film, but its emotions are as vivid as primary colors.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#28609</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Movies can't exactly replicate the feeling of reading a book, but Jun Ichikawa's adaptation of Haruki Murakami's short story Tony Takitani comes remarkably close.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41078</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a film for specialized tastes, quiet, delicate. But it suits those tastes beautifully.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050930-movies-review-tony,0,3159731.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is one of those movies where you either give yourself up to its rhythms or give up entirely. It took me a few minutes to get used to it, but I found Tony Takitani absorbing and loaded with emotional power.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/08/11/btm/index2.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This gossamer work is one of the loveliest examples of minimalist cinema I've seen in a long time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3525&amp;Sumbit.x=50&amp;Sumbit.y=17</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A delicate wisp of a film with a surprisingly sharp sting.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/29/movies/29taki.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A marvelously moody meditation, beautiful to look at and beautiful to ponder as the camera slowly pans from one scene to the next, framing life as still life.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/10/13/AR2005101300513.html</url>
         <critic>Teresa Wiltz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It recommends itself best to viewers who can appreciate its novelty and roll with the risks it takes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A295574</url>
         <critic>Marrit Ingman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a quietly simple fable that hits you hardest after it's over.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/332479p-283981c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film itself is also a beautiful work of art, exquisitely framed and precisely envisioned.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7663</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tony Takitani, fablelike and beautiful, requires a certain amount of patience, but its small, peculiar charms work their way into your soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=410125&amp;reviewId=18985</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oneiric as it is, though, Tony Takitani conveys a powerfully tangible sense of loss and loneliness. In both concrete and existential terms, it's a film that dwells on what the dead leave behind and how the living carry on.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0530,lim,66261,20.html</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not many of us, I think, would want to see many films made this way, possibly not one more, but this one is an intriguing glance at the director-as-god, deigning to treat human frailty with imperial sway, assuming that his art justifies this slender material.</snippet>
         <url>http://tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20050815&amp;s=kauffmann081505</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This minimalist meditation on loneliness and loss is so spare and drained of color that it seems always on the verge of fading into invisibility.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46334</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, this is a striking-looking film -- consciously recalling the paintings of Edward Hopper in its architectural use of space -- which, like its protag, is a little short on real feeling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117924648&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You really have to be in the right mood to sit through Tony Takitani. You have to be ready to take in a thoroughly depressing story that moves...very...slowly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7012</url>
         <critic>Eric Campos</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$129,783</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$1,765</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>