<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>TransAmerica</name>
   <company>The Weinstein Company LLC / IFC Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Duncan Tucker</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Duncan Tucker</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Felicity Huffman</actor>
      <actor>Kevin Zegers</actor>
      <actor>Fionnula Flanagan</actor>
      <actor>Graham Greene</actor>
      <actor>Burt Young</actor>
      <actor>Elizabeth Peña</actor>
      <actor>Carrie Preston</actor>
      <actor>Grant Monohon</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 2, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>103</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Until it detours into dysfunctional-family comedy-drama, Transamerica rides cross-country without ever running low on bracing, cactus-spined surprises.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.trans27jan27,1,1446764.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Transamerica is a modern-day Sullivan's Travels.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8285</url>
         <critic>Elias Savada</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Impressively realized on all levels, this transgender spin on the road trip boasts an extraordinary central performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001137942</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Laugh-out-loud funny, tartly off-color and ultimately touching.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117926290?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Eddie Cockrell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This debut feature left me in a state of movie euphoria. Who could have guessed that such a discomfiting premise would blossom into a deadpan-hilarious and yet deeply affecting story about a singular glitch in the human condition?</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But the most impressive thing is how, a few minutes into the film, you stop noticing Huffman's external transformations and start to focus on the character. Not that the external stuff isn't impressive.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1137692,00.html</url>
         <critic>Joel Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A flawed but nevertheless endearing father-son road trip with a distinctive twist.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46517</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This drama offers a chuckle at every turn.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/12-02-2005/entertainment/col/story/370944p-315365c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's soul is with Huffman. Speaking in a low voice, her posture as stiff as her vocabulary, her eyes a pool of sadness and hope, she turns this small, resonant film into a cry from the heart.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/7264940?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Transamerica provides the frame and the occasion for one of the year's best performances, Felicity Huffman's as a woman trapped in a man's body who's passing for female while awaiting a sex-change operation.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/12/23/DDGSFGBLFG1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a fine, tender, delicate, funny, gender-bending-and-rebending performance this is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051223/TRANSAMERICA23/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Felicity Huffman brings to Bree is the newness of a Jane Austen heroine. She has been waiting a long time to be an ingenue, and what an irony that she must begin as a mother.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060119/REVIEWS/51214005/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a farce with heart, a meditation on identity, family and gender politics that has real faith in its characters - even when the characters themselves lack it.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=354465&amp;reviewId=19976&amp;startDate=01%2F27%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's debatable whether watching Huffman get dressed, take hormones, and learn to use a more feminine diction could sustain an entire movie, but the character is certainly a creation more original than a lot of the film itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8149</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A perfect example of an ordinary movie made unique by the powerhouse performance of its lead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1137637517132331.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite its subject matter, Transamerica is a surprisingly funny movie, because Tucker never lets the pathos overwhelm his sense of humor.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=354465&amp;reviewId=19966</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You might feel constrained when it comes to a standing ovation, but there's certainly enough substance and yuk here to go along for the ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-12-22/film/film5.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If Tucker's road map often feels a little too confining and the screwball comedy too contrived, he can take credit for introducing viewers to a character they have almost certainly never met before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1106158&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Farce born of sadly irreconcilable impulses: Bravo!</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2131264/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The real success of Duncan Tucker, who wrote and directed this debut feature, is that, through credible dialogue and sensitive performances, the basic idea overcomes its cleverness and is affecting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20051226&amp;s=kauffmann122605</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Transamerica itself does not always live up to its star, but it is touching and sometimes funny, despite its overall air of indie earnestness.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/12/02/movies/02trans.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Transamerica is about as sexual as "The Brady Bunch." It's about an intelligent woman in excruciating transition to a new body that will line up with an identity she's held all along.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/ink/06/02/film-taylor.php</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best, and perhaps the only, reason to see Duncan Tucker's Transamerica is for Felicity Huffman's touching, shape-shifting performance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/1202/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The unintended effect of all the melodramatic complications in Transamerica is, oddly, to distract attention from an understanding of exactly what that courage really costs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1136113_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It may not exactly be a traditional love letter to his wife but actor-turned-executive producer William H. Macy has given her a plum part as Bree in screenwriter-director Duncan Tucker's offbeat road movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/256326_transamerica20q.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Huffman is a woman playing a man playing a woman, which is easily the year's most complicated turn. She does a fine, nuanced job in bringing to life a character that could have become a caricature.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-12-01-transamerica-pluto_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As much heralded, "edgy" movies go, Transamerica fails to live up to expectations.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/t/transamerica.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is actually a very middle-of-the-road movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=133039</url>
         <critic>Olly Richards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Felicity Huffman is such a wonder, at once funny and brave, playing a pre-op male-to-female transsexual in the uneven comedy Transamerica that she sustains several lapses that might otherwise have sunk it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-transamerica2dec02,0,1250084.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An occasionally touching, more often clumsy variation on the formula of crusty oldster and problem child bonding on a road trip. The main reason to see it is "Desperate Housewives" star Felicity Huffman.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/capsules/28738_TRANSAMERICA</url>
         <critic>Martin Rubin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pleasant even without reaching much of a destination, Transamerica leaves the basic impression that it's not as self-satisfied as it could have been.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0548,kenigsberg,70465,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ben Kenigsberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never lets us forget that it's a nonmainstream story about a nonmainstream subject, when ideally, it should simply be a story about a person. The picture too often feels like a lesson in tolerance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/12/02/transamerica/index.html?sid=1418406</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Huffman intermittently rescues Transamerica from bathos with her brusque wit, swatting away the victimization elements that figure into most films about transsexuals.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/43287</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like a preoperative transsexual, Transamerica is neither one thing nor the other. It yanks at the heartstrings too much to qualify as an edgy comedy-drama, but it's far too bawdy to make it to the Hallmark Channel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/58770.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the way, the other thing that keeps Transamerica from being a mainstream movie is its obsession with penises: showing them, talking about them, placing us in bathrooms and trailers when they're in use.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=354465&amp;reviewId=19989&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writer-director Duncan Tucker does little to develop his narrative setup beyond the basic and obvious, and his film begins to feel more like an exercise than a fully realized story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A329000</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At its best, Transamerica made me laugh and feel for Bree. At its worst, it made me cringe at the potential creepiness of its central relationship.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060120-movies-review-transamerica,0,3984336.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$9,015,303</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$1,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$46,908</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>