<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Tyson</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>James Toback</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>James Toback</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Mike Tyson</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>April 24, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is an often-anguished monologue built on pride, despair and self-defense. Accuracy aside, Tyson does work hard to analyze his own, clearly complex character. So while we only get half the picture, it makes for consistently compelling viewing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/04/24/2009-04-24_short_takes.html?page=1</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A documentary with no pretense of objectivity. Here is Mike Tyson's story in his own words, and it is surprisingly persuasive.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090429/REVIEWS/904299976</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Toback has found a documentary subject as tragic and ridiculous, as bizarre and driven, as the heroes of his other films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/05/07/MVLL17E4QF.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What emerges is a fallen warrior's tale: the inside story of a man bloodied and bowed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.tyson15may15,0,1059348.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Toback's film, partly because it restricts itself to Mr. Tyson's point of view, offers a rare and vivid study in the complexity of a single suffering, raging soul. It is not an entirely trustworthy movie, but it does feel profoundly honest.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/04/24/movies/24tyso.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is as gripping as a title fight and as mesmerizing as a conversation with a cobra. You may not be happy with everything said, but you will not be bored.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-tyson24-2009apr24,0,1364931.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An extraordinary documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/193491</url>
         <critic>Allison Samuels</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By getting Tyson to open up as he has, Toback has succeeded in illuminating one of the most polarizing, complex and -- the film almost forces one to admit -- misunderstood figures of our time.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937153.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;query=tyson</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No filmmaker I know has gotten as close to a professional athlete as James Toback gets to Mike Tyson in his new documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/56142/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tyson is more like a particularly riveting therapy session, with Tyson as both analyst and patient.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-04-22/film/tyson-delivers-a-powerful-blow-fighting-is-down-for-the-count/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You won't know what hit you after watching Tyson. This power punch to the gut is one of the best movies of any kind this year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/20726171/review/27537995/tyson</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Terrifically compelling and, more than that, unexpectedly moving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/05/01/tyson_captures_ugly_paradoxes_of_fighters_life/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No other sporting figure has ever been afforded so much screen time for self-revelation: just another instance of Iron Mike's one-of-a-kind status.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/05/review_sparring_with_the_devil.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's so affecting about him in the film, though, is that he doesn't seem monstrous at all. To the contrary, Iron Mike, having meted out epic suffering in the ring and other venues, seems to be a man who has suffered genuinely, even terribly, in the course of a life that he never believed would last 40 years.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB124052480101050043.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The resulting portrait shows a seriously troubled man whose brutality was bred into him on the punishing streets of Brooklyn and whose modest wisdom seems as hard-won as any title. Tyson's fight career may be over, but his battle with himself has many rounds to go.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/34314_TYSON.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you’re not really interested in Mike Tyson as a boxer and a person, the film doesn't give you much to go on. This is a movie called Tyson and it is about Mike Tyson – and nothing else.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11538</url>
         <critic>Whitney Borup</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a sympathetic portrait of a complex man driven by an anger that still bubbles beneath the surface.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11104</url>
         <critic>Ray Bennett</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Very humane portrait of a potentially extremely unlikeable character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=136033</url>
         <critic>Damon Wise</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's brutal to watch the bigger-they-are-the-harder-they-fall tragedy of this once-great heavyweight. In fact, it's enough to make you cry.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A786020</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie humanizes Tyson and brings him down to the land of mortals, making his achievements loom larger. And if the boxer hasn't entirely made peace with his troubled soul, Tyson suggests the struggle is going his way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1091728.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An absorbing and not-too-uncomfortable experience, so long as you remember there's a camera lens and a big distance between you and the film's violent subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090507.wtyson0508/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gives a taste of what it might be like to live inside Mike Tyson's mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/04242009/entertainment/movies/in_tysons_corner_165863.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, this may be the closest we'll ever get to understanding how Mike feels about himself, and there's value in viewing that assessment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1604</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tyson does succeed in humanizing a deeply troubled individual who has been depicted as an almost animalistic stereotype of African-American manhood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/04/24/tyson/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie makes it clear that, for all his snarls and outbursts, he is intelligent, candid, and easily wounded; that he is by turns inordinately proud and inordinately ashamed and, above all, intensely curious about himself, as if his own nature were a mystery that had not yet been solved.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2009/05/11/090511crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tyson can be brutal with himself, but Toback's fawning documentary lets him off easy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/tyson,27062/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is flashy, but the meaning is a bit of a bob and weave.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20272455,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a movie that's thought-provoking without being intelligent and candid without being truthful. The same aesthetic choices that Toback seems convinced will set his documentary apart are also what diminishes its credibility.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2216787/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$887,918</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$85,046</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>11</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>