<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ultimate Gift, The</name>
   <company>20th Century Fox / Fox Faith</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Cheryl Mc</author>
      <author>Kay</author>
      <author>Jim Stovall</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Michael O. Sajbel</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Drew Fuller</actor>
      <actor>James Garner</actor>
      <actor>Ali Hillis</actor>
      <actor>Abigail Breslin</actor>
      <actor>Lee Meriwether</actor>
      <actor>Brian Dennehy</actor>
      <actor>Mircea Monroe</actor>
      <actor>Donna Cherry</actor>
      <actor>D. David Morin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 9, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>114</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a well-made little inspirational drama featuring both a familiar older star (James Garner) and a new one (Abigail Breslin).</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/306673_gift09q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's nothing wrong with the moral of The Ultimate Gift's story; in fact there's everything right about it. But director Michael O. Sajbel too often succumbs to movie-of-the-week sentimentality and starchy pacing. Still, Breslin's captivating performance reminds you why she was recently nominated for an Oscar.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1134080&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although cynics likely will reject The Ultimate Gift as warmed-over Capra-corn, this predictable but pleasant drama based on Jim Stovall's popular novel may be prized by those with a taste for inspirational uplift and heart-tugging sentiment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117933023.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Things may work out predictably, but The Ultimate Gift does not yank on the heartstrings so much as pluck them gently.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.ultimate09mar09,0,5576658.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Garner is good, and so is Brian Dennehy as a crusty ranch owner; Abigail Breslin, playing a leukemia patient, demonstrates that she was not a one-note wonder in "Little Miss Sunshine."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0316/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The message is clear almost immediately: charity not vanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9691</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>"Gift" comes across as a television-ready effort that would work perfectly for Hallmark.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=Lv2cF0hW1zgXv0ZhXGd0HzMJZP1w3ysJ7NS17cn1LHM2SVz9hTvW!-123830289&amp;&amp;rid=8890</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Kind of like a feel-good "Saw" for churchgoers, minus the sadistic games of death.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20014972,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film constantly teeters on the fulcrum of its own treacly good intentions and simplistic parable-like storytelling, and the extent that it stays balanced is largely thanks to its agile cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-gift9mar09,0,7711662.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directed with accomplished impersonality by Michael O. Sajbel ( One Night With the King), The Ultimate Gift means well, but in the end it's "The Pursuit of Happyness" made from the ivory tower looking down instead of from the street looking up.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0710,foundas,76005,20.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The plot, though of the made-for-TV ilk, makes for good discussion fodder if you're trying to impress life's lessons on children or others you love. That said, be prepared to be hit over the head by the message, edifying as it is.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-070309-movies-review-gift,0,7358606.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Louis R. Carlozo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This drama from Fox Faith Movies has a mercifully light hand in selling its Christian-values themes, but its plodding story about a spoiled young scion who must complete 12 tasks assigned him by his late grandfather is still a slog.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/503693p-424760c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>More watchable for secular audiences than the handful of earlier films released under the Fox Faith label, this one actually has a sense of humor, a politically progressive point of view and a solid cast including the ever-reliable James Garner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/03092007/entertainment/movies/gift_has_a_good_rap_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is message filmmaking so blunt you might be tempted to root for the parasitic reprobate over the saintly old man, and that's just not right.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/detail/movie.aspx?tvobjectid=286729&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reeking of self-righteousness and moral reprimand, Michael O. Sajbel’s Ultimate Gift”is a hairball of good-for-you filmmaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2007/03/09/movies/09ulti.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story, based on the novel by motivational speaker Jim Stovall, throws every emotional stimulus into the pot, and the result is a deep desire for those Hollywood execs to remember that Christian doesn't have to equal brain-dead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A452807</url>
         <critic>Toddy Burton</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$3,438,735</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$1,241,079</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>816</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>