<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ultraviolet</name>
   <company>Screen Gems Inc. / Sony Pictures Entertainment</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Kurt Wimmer</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Kurt Wimmer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Milla Jovovich</actor>
      <actor>Cameron Bright</actor>
      <actor>Nick Chinlund</actor>
      <actor>William Fichtner</actor>
      <actor>Sebastien Andrieu</actor>
      <actor>Ida Martin</actor>
      <actor>Ricardo Mamood</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>March 3, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>88</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>For this violent yet gore-free film, clearly designed for horny teenaged video game wizards, writer-director Kurt Wimmer stages a succession of fight sequences that pit V against helmeted thugs who appear to have raided the Star Wars storm trooper costume closet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film-reviews/12803/film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To her credit, Jovovich carries out her action-hero duties with swagger and conviction that never get out of control. Clearly, she's expecting a franchise out of this.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-ultraviolet6mar06,0,2712602.story</url>
         <critic>Gene Seymour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although it looks cool, appearances aren’t everything.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8826</url>
         <critic>Stina Chyn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amid every action cliche in the book, outmoded stereotypes, and a plot derivative of every futuristic drama made in the last fifteen years, Ultraviolet comes off as nothing more than a pale copy of better, more inventive films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2628</url>
         <critic>Jessica Letkemann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Wimmer is more concerned with fetishizing his heroine and patronizing his audience. The verdict? Ultrasilly.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/03/04/movies/04ultr.html</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Kurt Wimmer has an eye for jackboot chic (Equilibrium), and the images here have been digitally polished so that the characters' skin is smoother than porcelain. It's a cool effect--I spent most of this interminable actioner wondering if one could bounce a quarter off Jovovich's bare midriff.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29368_ULTRAVIOLET.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seems this is yet another puddle of futuristic sludge for us to blame on John Cassavetes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0610,nelson,72461,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is another one of those pointless action superhero movies that unfolds like a video game in which the viewer is unable to participate.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/u/ultraviolet.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film to be enjoyed only by science-fiction movie completists and middle school boys with extreme cases of attention deficit disorder.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/06/DDGRCHJ3MT1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Underdeveloped antagonist Nick Chinlund sums up the entire film during one of his rants about Jovovich's latest casual, offhand slaughter: "One woman against 14 men! It's ridiculous!" Well, yeah.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/46120</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultraviolet, unscreened for critics, is unfit for consumption.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/396538p-336109c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An all-but-incoherent mess whose main components are palpably fake-looking CGI effects, video-game-style action sequences and Milla Jovovich's admirably taut abdomen, Kurt Wimmer's film epitomizes just about everything wrong with post-MATRIX, comic book-/video-game-inspired, Hong Kong-action-style sci-fi thrillers.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46652</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jovovich is bad, and not in a good way. She turns in an epically expressionless performance (maybe she thought it was one of her modeling gigs?) but she sure looks great.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8732</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Perry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The latest entry in the "This film is so bad we're not screening it for critics" genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002115864</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Pic is hermetically sealed in a synthetic wrapping that's so total -- Sony's top-flight high-def cameras, visibly low-budget CG work, exceptionally hackneyed and imitative action and dialogue --that it arrives a nearly lifeless film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929842?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unengaging, uninspired and unwatchable. A criminal waste of time and talent.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133213</url>
         <critic>James Dyer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultraviolet, warns someone, ''Don't overthink it.'' Sage advice for anyone masochistic enough to watch this pile of poorly pixelated vampire poo.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1171071_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Scott Brown</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jovovich, who's shown sensitivity in her dramatic work, looks spectacularly bored as she power-kicks her way through one bloody pile-up after another. That boredom, like the mystery virus at the center of the film, is contagious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A343757</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A cut-rate ripoff of "Aeon Flux" with Milla Jovovich as a butt-kicking futuristic heroine in a midriff-baring bodysuit, is ultrastupid, ultra-incoherent, ultrasilly - and way, way ultraboring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/60532.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$18,522,064</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$30,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$9,064,880</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,558</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>