<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Unknown White Male</name>
   <company>Wellspring Media</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author/>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Rupert Murray</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USAUK</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Doug Bruce</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 24, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>88</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The extraordinary subject and the filmmaker's near total access make for a singular documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#29408</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The real subject of the film is Douglas Bruce sitting on two years of memories and told there is a 95 percent chance that another 30 years may return to him. A lot of people don't want to know when they're going to die. Maybe they wouldn't want to be reborn, either.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060309/REVIEWS/603090307/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Veers between mystery, comedy, philosophical inquest and medical/psychological drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/64097.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While I don't entirely rule out the possibility that Bruce is a hoaxster, it seems more likely that his story is one of those weird scientific anomalies that more frequently turn up as an Oliver Sacks case history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0303/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fascinating documentary by Bruce's longtime friend Rupert Murray, uses footage taken by both Bruce and Murray to document Bruce's harrowing, enlightening and occasionally hilarious experience. It's a wild ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-03-23/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Melissa Levine</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Equally fascinating and frustrating.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060310-movies-review-male,0,3168883.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Unknown White Male that Murray has made asks profound questions. They're just not necessarily the right ones.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7665</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A fascinating, somewhat frightening documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-24-2006/entertainment/col/story/394306p-334135c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's enough drama here to fill two hours. Whether or not that happens, Rupert Murray's account represents fascinating viewing, and the richness of the subject matter more than makes up for the crudeness of some of the visual elements.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/u/unknown_white.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Murray honors his buddy by presenting him as a sympathetic enigma - the puzzling center of this very human suspense thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/now-playing/12754/new-film-reviews/</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Crammed with friendly, sympathetic talking heads and pretty images of a stunned-looking Mr. Bruce, then 35, relearning life (he remembers how to walk but forgot family and friends), the film comes up frustratingly short when it comes to the particulars.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/24/movies/24male.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In terms of "narrative," the film keeps excellent pace, maintains your attention, and educates you on psychological ramifications of memory.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=7666</url>
         <critic>Stina Chyn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Given that this retrograde memory loss has cleansed Doug Bruce's perceptions and made him an altogether more open and emotional person, Unknown White Male suggests that amnesia could be the ultimate chicken soup for the soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyorkmetro.com/movies/reviews/16017/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bruce's efforts to retrace and recover his life after his memory loss contain all the drama and uncertainty of a fine psychological drama.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117926062?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An unexpectedly emotional, continually disconcerting film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-unknown24feb24,0,2436483.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unknown White Male is framed as a look at the mystery of identity, but there's a bizarre neutrality to the movie, since it makes Bruce's life just as detached and remote to us as it seems to him.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1162022_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While a fascinating subject, Bruce is a bit of a poseur, keenly aware of how he comes across on camera.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/263280_male17q.html</url>
         <critic>Bill White</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Intriguing, not-terribly-probing documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/114427950778660.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even if Rupert Murray's film does turn out to be a hoax, there's no denying the ingenuity involved in its making.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133561</url>
         <critic>David Parkinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film as a whole has the gravitas of a really thoughtful rock video.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unknown White Male has flashes of brilliance: Murray stretches out the dramatic tale of Bruce's first terrifying hours of recall, and Bruce's raw misery as he recounts those events is deeply affecting.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45645</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To call this story unbelievable is to say the very least. If it's a hoax, Bruce is a fantastic actor (but then, the movie suggests, so are we all). If not, you may wonder less about Bruce's personality than his condition.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0608,hoberman,72260,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Cushioned by money - which frees him from needing to work and allows him to fly around the world looking for his past - Bruce is attractive and well-spoken but not especially interesting, which leaves a yawning void at the story's center.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/Movie-Review.asp?MI=46387</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While the film raises simple but deeply puzzling questions about memory and identity, the hit-or-miss search for answers by the subject and assorted experts, family and friends is finally unsatisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/03/10/DDGKAHL0BT1.DTL#flick3</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fake or not, Unknown White Male doesn't live up to its tantalizing potential.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1108336&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Many are the times the viewer stares disbelievingly at the screen, furious with Murray for not asking follow-up questions or simply refusing to see the need to prove the veracity of the story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A349428</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$126,836</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$24,591</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>