<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Unmistaken Child</name>
   <company>Oscilloscope Laboratories</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Nati Baratz</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Nati Baratz</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Israel</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tenzin Zopa</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 3, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>102</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unmistaken Child stands above most others in offering us an intimate look at Tibetan Buddhism in action, with no external commentary or narration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/btm/feature/2009/06/06/unmistaken/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Its privileged glimpse deep into unfamiliar spiritual territory has the strength of revelation.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-child12-2009jun12,0,479581.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Films that address faith and love as eloquently as this moving 2008 documentary are rare.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?film=978100</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This documentary is only partly a story of the chosen one; mainly, and more intriguingly, it's a chronicle of the choosing one, of the nervous young monk charged with the job of leading the search party.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/unmistaken-child/article1308584/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unmistaken Child stands as a window on a beautiful and mysterious world. The questions it leaves hanging are for us to untangle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/07/17/in_unmistaken_child_the_making_of_a_spiritual_leader/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A compelling documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/06/25/MV1P18C4Q4.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I hope they have shrinks in remote Nepal, because this kid is going to need one. P.S.: The scenery is awesome.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06032009/entertainment/movies/zen_mastery_is_his_universe_172330.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baratz’s apparent willingness to accept everything at face value papers over some of the more troubling aspects of Tenzin’s mission, but Unmistaken Child allows the mysteries of the process to be preserved without judgment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/unmistaken-child,28820/</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unmistaken Child: adorable, moving, bewildering, sad and, ultimately, peaceful.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/unmistaken-child,1156569.html</url>
         <critic>Dan Zak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seldom has a film presented such a richly ambiguous juxtaposition of modernity (among the toys showered on the boy is a really cool radio-controlled helicopter), ancient mindset and, to be sure, possible miraculousness.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Baratz doesn't ask any of the obvious questions, preferring to observe uncritically, and if you can do the same, you may find Unmistaken Child worth seeing. I could not, and grew restless.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090722/REVIEWS/907229985</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Although the film is handsomely filmed and features a surprisingly frank view of the political machinations within the upper ranks of Tibetan Buddhism – even the Dalai Lama comes across as a bit of a wheeler-dealer – Unmistaken Child is more than a little disappointing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11760</url>
         <critic>Phil Hall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The beauty of the landscape and the monk’s sweetness, humility and good humor evoke a plane of existence, at once elevated and austere, that is humbling to contemplate.
That said, Unmistaken Child offers no scholarly perspective on Tibetan Buddhism and leaves fundamental questions unanswered.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/03/movies/03unmi.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is a drama of faith, a Tibetan monk's search for the reincarnation of his beloved master Lama Konchog.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-06-03/film/a-chinese-factory-reborn-as-condo-heaven-in-24-city/</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who knew reincarnation could be such a lovely snooze?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A815652</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$306,140</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$9,728</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>