<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Ushpizin</name>
   <company>Picturehouse Entertainment LLC</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Shuli Rand</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Giddi Dar</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>Israel</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Shuli R</actor>
      <actor>Michal Bat-Sheva R</actor>
      <actor>Shaul Mizrahi</actor>
      <actor>Ilan Ganani</actor>
      <actor>Avraham Abutboul</actor>
      <actor>Daniel Dayan</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 19, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does what the best movies can do: take viewers to what might be unfamiliar places, into a culture with unique customs and traditions, and show, through drama and comedy, how the fundamental truths of the human experience need no translation.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=463449&amp;reviewId=19419</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In addition to providing a fascinating, agenda-free look at an unseen way of life, the film presents a lesson that should be welcome among people of any faith or none at all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/113763390470950.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Marc Mohan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The unusual intimacy and authenticity can't be faked: The cast is peppered with nonprofessionals, most notably Michal Bat Sheva Rand.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1125312_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jew or Gentile, a good story well told is a thing to be cherished.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.ushpizin09nov09,1,1601996.story?coll=bal-movies-storyutil</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Israeli comedy Ushpizin begins something like Guy Ritchie's "Snatch" and ends like the Coen brothers' "Raising Arizona" – in between it's a wholly original movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A320918</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You need not be a believer to appreciate its humor and humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/11/23/DDGJOFS6GH1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ushpizin takes us to a fascinating place, and hands out the sort of brochure that tourists always need but seldom get -- the charming kind, fun to ponder and rewarding to browse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20051202/USHPIZIN02/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ushpizin may not turn out to be as popular as Miracle on 34th Street, but if you believe that miracles can happen, it is a perfect outing during the holidays.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=463449&amp;reviewId=19598</url>
         <critic>Marta Barber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The new Israeli movie Ushpizin, a film about man's clumsiness and God's grace, is a touching and amusing tale that expands our horizon and also should open our hearts.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501028-movies-review-ushpizin,0,229155.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On paper, Ushpizin (Aramaic for "holy guests") looks like a hard sell. It works, however, thanks to a witty script and believable performances from real-life husband and wife.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/29675.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's little difference between this joyful holiday film and the standard-issue yuletide-miracle movie, except that the holiday isn't Christmas.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46424</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gentle and affecting, it offers an introduction to a mostly unfamiliar world while touching on issues recognizable to all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/357797p-304686c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stylistically Ushpizin belongs to a classic tradition of raucous Yiddish comedy that is easy to enjoy if taken lightly. At the same time, it sustains a double vision of ultra-Orthodox life.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/10/19/movies/19ushp.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Holden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As directed by Gidi Dar, Ushpizin has a disarming folk quality.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0542,hoberman2,68957,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the charming comedy-parable Ushpizin, religious orthodoxy inspires not unbending dogma but humble, sometimes baffled spiritual striving by its embraceable, flawed characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001308023</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A warm, conciliatory entertainment.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3620&amp;Sumbit.x=58&amp;Sumbit.y=15</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A gently humorous fable about the power of faith and the possibility of change, Ushpizin not only takes place in Jerusalem's ultra-Orthodox Jewish community, it was filmed with that media-shy group's cooperation and followed religious law at all times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-ushpizin19oct19,0,1222410.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The ability of faith to reintegrate a damaged personality is one theme here, although the film doesn't strive for psychological realism; in its heartfelt embrace of religion as ethical path, it owes more to the bygone Yiddish drama than to psychodrama.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28815_USHPIZIN.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A charming comedy with a philosophical undercurrent that provides a fascinating glimpse of Jerusalem's ultra-Orthodox Jews, who live in a realm almost literally sealed off from outsiders. But the most remarkable thing about the film is that it exists at all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/10/27/btm/index.html?sid=1406602</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The picture has enough good feeling and chuckle to take it out of the parochial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20051107&amp;s=kauffmann110705</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A good-hearted movie aimed at Orthodox Jews who don't normally go to the movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://listings.dallasobserver.com/gyrobase/Film/ShowFilm</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enjoyable seriocomic tale of a poor couple whose holiday-time miracle becomes a test of faith.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117926334?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Jay Weissberg</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most revelatory here is Malli, who defies the stereotype of submission and subservience and emerges as a woman of self-possession and substance. (The earthily beautiful Bat-Sheva Rand infuses the character with a generous dollop of her own zaftig sensuality.)</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1112691</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ushpizin's effortlessly authentic depiction of Jewish orthodoxy--and the palpable, almost ecstatic sense of joy its characters take in it--ultimately tips the film's hand.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41987</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A flawed but fascinating (and frequently funny) insight into a culture seldom explored on film from an insider's point of view.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/ReviewComplete.asp?FID=133319</url>
         <critic>David Hughes</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,397,999</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$85,007</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>