<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>W.</name>
   <company>Lionsgate</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Stanley Weiser</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Oliver Stone</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Josh Brolin</actor>
      <actor>Elizabeth Banks</actor>
      <actor>Richard Dreyfuss</actor>
      <actor>James Cromwell</actor>
      <actor>Ellen Burstyn</actor>
      <actor>Thie Newton</actor>
      <actor>Jeffrey Wright</actor>
      <actor>Scott Glenn</actor>
      <actor>Ioan Gruffudd</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 17, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>Rated</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>W., a biography of President Bush, is fascinating. No other word for it.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081015/REVIEWS/810150285</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You'll be disappointed if you expect famed leftist Oliver Stone to apply a coup de grace to this man.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/32251-review-w</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seems a much more even-handed and thoughtful take on the man than anyone might have expected.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/383637_wreview17q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A measured and thoughtful meditation on a leader who, this terrific movie believes, inadvertently made the world as roiling as his soul.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/10/16/2008-10-16_oliver_stones_mission_is_accomplished_wi.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The pleasure of Mr. Stone's work has never been located in restraint but in excess, a commitment to extremes that can drown out the world or, as in this film, give it newly vivid, hilarious and horrible form.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/10/17/movies/17ston.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end, W. makes up in immediacy what it lacks in objectivity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/10/16/DDTD13HNU5.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An often compelling, tragicomic psychological analysis of Dubya, viewed through the prism of his relationship with an allegedly disapproving father.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10172008/entertainment/movies/poppys_seed_133917.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the end it depicts its subject as lost, and pitiable--like  Richard  Nixon, but more a pawn than a dark knight.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-w/687447/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performances are good (some scarily realistic), and the movie is enjoyable to watch. But as a probing analysis of the 43rd president, it falls short.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-10-16-w_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like Tina Fey's Sarah Palin, Stone's George Bush gets his best lines straight from the source.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2202430/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>W. is not a dispassionate biography; it is an interpretation of personality intersecting with history, and as a piece of drama it is persuasive and perfectly creditable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-w17-2008oct17,0,4439328.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When it works, W. can take your breath away. When it doesn't, you can feel Stone still working out his feelings toward the man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12103</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Passably interesting, occasionally riveting and largely superfluous. But it's certainly a worthwhile curiosity, and it's not what anyone expected. At the movies these days, that alone is worth something.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/727978.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever you think of Dubya, he has balls. The movie doesn't.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/22717752/review/23638454/w</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like all Stone movies, W. has energy and forward momentum--particularly in the pre-presidential sections, when Bush is in his loose-cannon phase. It's not boring, and Brolin is often remarkable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/163481</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>W. is the kind of film that demands discussion and only then can we start to decipher what Stone's intentions are towards our President.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11277</url>
         <critic>Don R. Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's when Stone engages in shameless editorializing -- when he lets his freak-flag point of view fly, rather than tempering it -- that W. is most entertaining and most vital. The rest of the time it feels too much like awards bait: stiff, arch and knowing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/10/17/w/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A surprisingly unsurprising film.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=95746285</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stone paddles down the giant river of Bush's life without exploring any of the tributaries; he passes by two or three dozen better movies along the way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/w</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The intrepid one is the outstanding Josh Brolin, who does such a phenomenal job in the title role that he carries every scene he's in to a place of subtlety and integrity far beyond what Stone needs to make his attention-grabbing noise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20233285,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In our age of 24-hour news coverage, this rehashing of current events doesn't just come off familiar but completely unnecessary. And, worst of all, prosaic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A688405</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In spite of Josh Brolin's heroic efforts, W. is a skin-deep biopic that revels in its antic shallowness.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122420113425542917.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Superficial, uninformative, and inert, this two hour snoozefest isn't even inflammatory enough to stoke a righteous anti-Bush brushfire. W. does for recent history what Oliver Stone's epic "Alexander" did for ancient times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1375</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unlike the filmmaker's previous stabs at presidential biopic-ing and conspiracy theorizing - "JFK" and "Nixon" - this one doesn't have the luxury of historical perspective.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20081017_Oliver_Stone_s__quot_W__quot__fails_as_satire.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a gutsy movie but not necessarily a good one. Its greatest strength is that it wants to talk about what's on our minds right now and not wait for historians.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=Q8yYLr8f620NXgSs7LJl5QlJH0s6fhwnQQKqjgfWyk4TvW5yXk7p!1819155073&amp;&amp;rid=11791</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film that could have been either a scorching satire or an outright tragedy, W. is, if anything, overly conventional, especially stylistically.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117938628.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>None of it is new, nor is the recycled stuff presented in a newly revealing context.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081016.wdubya17/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's most entertaining for its stunt casting of movie stars as the president's family and advisers.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33724_W_STONE.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Stone may think he's made a movie about the toxicity of the Bush presidency, but what we have instead is a cautionary tale of a decidedly lower order. As far as I can make out, the real message of W. is: Don't vote for anybody who talks with his mouth full of food.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1018/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>W. isn't gripping enough as drama or witty enough as satire. It's neutered.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/51391/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Richard Dreyfuss, hunching over and baring his teeth like a shark cruising off a Martha's Vineyard beach, does a wicked impersonation of Cheney. His relish for the part suggests that the movie should have been done not as an earnest bio-pic but as a satirical comedy -- as a contemporary  "Dr. Strangelove," with a cast of satyrs and clowns.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/10/27/081027crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=all</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Disappointing. Stone whipped this out in time for the US Presidential election, but it’s hard to see how it’ll make any significant impact on voters. Or why it even should.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135529</url>
         <critic>Helen O&amp;#039;Hara</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why this movie -- a rushed, wildly uneven, tonally jumbled caricature -- and why now?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/10/16/AR2008101601594.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A painful movie to endure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-10-15/film/oliver-stone-assigns-motive-to-dubya-s-m-o-in-w-but-at-this-point-who-cares-other-than-josh-brolin/</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is an X-ray of an invisible man -- by the film's end, the W. still stands for Who?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1849848,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie plays like a dunk-the-clown game at a carnival. Through intent or ineptitude, he sets up the Bush family and administrations as caricatures.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.wmovie17oct17,0,4714419.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$25,534,493</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$25,100,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$10,505,668</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,030</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>2</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>ellen burstyn</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_actor>richard dreyfuss</oscar_winning_actor>
   <oscar_winning_directors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_directors>1</num_oscar_winning_directors>
   <oscar_winning_director>oliver stone</oscar_winning_director>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>