<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Wah-Wah</name>
   <company>Samuel Goldwyn Films LLC / Roadside Attractions</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Foreign</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Richard E. Grant</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Richard E. Grant</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>UKFranceSouthAfrica</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Gabriel Byrne</actor>
      <actor>Mira Richardson</actor>
      <actor>Emily Watson</actor>
      <actor>Julie Walters</actor>
      <actor>Nicholas Hoult</actor>
      <actor>Celia Imrie</actor>
      <actor>Julian Wadham</actor>
      <actor>Fenella Woolgar</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 12, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both acidly funny and very moving.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-wah12may12,0,5782939.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An unforced, engaging and surprisingly incisive account of the disintegration of British rule in Africa.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=133816</url>
         <critic>David Hughes</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is so well acted -- by Byrne, who makes Harry's internalized agonies and continuously carried torch for his ex-wife touching, and by Watson and Hoult -- that its more cloying moments, including a staged version of the musical "Camelot" (which is too long), are a moot point.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/272448_wahwah02.html</url>
         <critic>Paula Nechak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wah-Wah has a sequence, based on old newsreels, in which the flag is lowered and the sun sets on another bit of the empire. Odd how many critics have felt the whole movie should be about this. I don't see why. The story is about people who lived closed lives, and a film about them would necessarily give independence only a supporting role.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060615/REVIEWS/60509006/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Grant is a fine actor ("Withnail and I," "Gosford Park") and, although he doesn't appear in Wah-Wah, his spiritedness as a performer carries through to some of the others in his cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0512/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thanks to Grant's script and direction, the exotic Swaziland location (a film first) and an engaging cast, this smartly crafted drama radiates a gently comic pulse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/417011p-352164c.html</url>
         <critic>Jami Bernard</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wah-Wah can't sustain the mastery of its superior first hour, but it maintains a core of truth that sets it apart from less-convincing depictions of boys becoming men.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/48577</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The fascinating aspect of the rambling and involving film is how Ralph and this no-nonsense dame who married Dad become confederates.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=588467&amp;reviewId=20881</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yet for all its studied snobbery and brittle entitlement, the film is never mean-spirited: even Ralph's monstrous parents are treated with more compassion than they deserve. Clearly, Mr. Grant's memories are more fond than bitter - even if the same probably can't be said of the Swazis.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/05/12/movies/12wah.html</url>
         <critic>Jeannette Catsoulis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Grant's unblinking but sympathetic depiction of this emotionally unhinged world makes the viewer feel like an illicit, enlightened gawker, and it has the enormous fringe benefit of fine performers, including Richardson, who puts endearing vigor into the adulterous Lauren, and Julie Walters, Ralph's aunt, who tells the boy her frequent tipsiness is a recurring case of "sunstroke."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1121260&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Veteran actor Richard E. Grant makes his writing and directing debut with Wah-Wah, a startling portrait of his own startling and unusual childhood, growing up in Swaziland in the waning days of the British Empire in Africa.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001178549</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Flavorsome performances by a seasoned cast, held in check by Grant's traditional but well-crafted, always cinematic direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/ac2006_review/VE1117927963?nav=reviews&amp;categoryid=1986&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Derek Elley</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Never less than good but it's also never quite great.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A375491</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wah-Wah's characters are wonderfully human and flawed and still capable of stirring empathy, which is appealing. But in the end, the film isn't saying much at all.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=588467&amp;reviewId=20876</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the raw material is juicy stuff, the details and the larger picture never come together and the cast is uneven.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46931&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though far from expert filmmaking - visual clichés fly thick and fast - the movie has a swooning feel for the stark beauty of the African kingdom in which it was shot.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13496/</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As in so many films directed by actors, there's a generosity shown to performance that results in many lifelike moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/114851139339370.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An overdeveloped coming-of-age potboiler.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1192891_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As coming of age stories go, Wah-Wah does little to distinguish itself.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/w/wah-wah.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>That the film is semi- autobiographical for caustic actor-turned-writer-director Richard E. Grant helps explain its severely, sometimes laughably bitter tone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0619,nelson,73174,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To label the parents in Wah-Wah dysfunctional doesn't adequately describe their wildly inappropriate behavior.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/05/26/DDGO2J1KBL1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>About as gripping as its title.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060602.WAH02/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There isn't enough heft to the story to pull everything together. Watching it is like trying to assemble a puzzle that's missing pieces.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060526-movies-review-wah,0,4360004.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a hokey, old-fashioned melodrama in which the actors scream more often than necessary.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29485_WAH_WAH.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story lacks focus. The senses blur as wives and ex-wives come and go, and Harry regularly falls off the wagon, only to reform the next day.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/68405.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$234,750</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$7,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$55,304</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>26</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>