<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Waist Deep</name>
   <company>Rogue Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Crime</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Vondie Curtis-Hall</author>
      <author>Darin Scott</author>
      <author>Michael Mahern</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Vondie Curtis-Hall</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Tyrese Gibson</actor>
      <actor>Meagan Good</actor>
      <actor>Larenz Tate</actor>
      <actor>The Game</actor>
      <actor>Henry Hunter Hall</actor>
      <actor>Kimora Lee</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 23, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>97</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes excessiveness and implausibility are virtues in disguise. Movies this enjoyable don't come about by accident.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/23/DDGP9JI45J1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Curtis Hall keeps slipping in surprising social and emotional flavorings rarely found in the genre.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1210248_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Gregory Kirschling</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Vondie Curtis Hall gives this virtually nonstop crime actioner, set against the mean streets of Los Angeles, pleasing noirish touches along with larger-than-life-size characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002726206</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The performances are pretty good--with the exception of the nauseatingly sweet H. Hunter Hall (the son of the director) as Junior and a one-note scowl from rapper The Game, who plays Meat--and the screenplay, by Hall and Darin Scott, has some genuinely funny moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060623-movies-review-deep,0,3033216.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Waist Deep packs considerable energy and style into its tale of an ex-con forced back into a life of crime to rescue his kidnapped son. Yet the kinetic direction and occasional sly humor can't disguise the tale's banal brutality or pump much excitement into its routinized pileup of shoot-outs and car chases.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930886?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>No, it's not a great movie. It is, however, an interesting one.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1118091&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Teresa Wiltz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By most of the ways movies are usually judged, pretty much of a mess. The camerawork is jerky and distracting, the dialogue is cliched and the story makes so little sense that the script seems to have been improvised by the actors as they went along.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/274979_waist23q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Billed as an action thriller, it plays out as an urban-fairy tale version of "Bonnie and Clyde," with an ending suitable for a Harlequin romance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/06-23-2006/entertainment/col/story/429135p-361732c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Gibson and Good deliver such emotionally honest performances that we wish them a happy ending, no matter how many movie clichés have to be trotted out to get there.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13839/</url>
         <critic>Chuck Wilson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unapologetically a B movie, its narrative premise whittled down to a mean little nub and placed carefully on the borderline between the wildly implausible and the completely absurd.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/06/23/movies/23wais.html</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As its plot thickens, Waist Deep gets more outlandish. The whole mess empties out into an overextended car chase through Los Angeles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-waist23jun23,0,7638112.story</url>
         <critic>Gene Seymour</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Waist Deep is a cynical excuse for the writer and director (and talented actor) Vondie Curtis-Hall to sock some money away for the kids' college tuition. It's as if he watched "Get Rich or Die Tryin' " and thought, "It needs more palm trees."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8701</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With an exciting way out, the audience would have gladly overlooked all the loose ends from earlier in the movie. But the way Hall plays it, he undermines the early style and intelligence of his all-black action movie, taking audiences for the wrong kind of ride in the end.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=218FBC9808228C09E69459798F4D6A18.prodapp14_ae_02?id=633950&amp;reviewId=21029&amp;startDate=06%2F23%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Peter Debruge</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A deep waste is more like it.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46814&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For its ever shifting attitudes toward men, women, and murder, Waist Deep is one of the sloppiest movies ever to reach the screen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0626,gallo,73684,20.html</url>
         <critic>Bill Gallo</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The lengths to which a parent will go to save a child can be gut-wrenching stuff, but Waist Deep rarely hits you in the pit of your stomach. Blame it on the lame screenplay, which unwisely (and badly) gravitates more toward the crime-spree elements of "Bonnie and Clyde" than the fierce parental instincts of, say, "Kramer vs. Kramer" or "Lorenzo's Oil."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A377839</url>
         <critic>Steve Davis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like the forgotten blaxploitation schlock it often resembles, the film aspires to nothing but cheap thrills, but while it's plenty cheap, it's far from thrilling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/49912</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The cast, especially The Game, does a fairly good job with this meager material, but it's like trying to make chateaubriand out of Spam.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=6216D670BE740645311419442DCADB66.prodapp12_ae_02?id=633950&amp;reviewId=21033&amp;startDate=06%2F23%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To be fair Deep does have one thing going for it. While the movie never seems to end, and when it does… oh man. Think "Aquaman" meets "Training Day."  It proves that sometimes a crappy drama is sometimes just a comedy in disguise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2911</url>
         <critic>Monica A. Reyhani</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Slow-witted and occasionally unintentionally hilarious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/total_waist_of_ones_time_movies_lou_lumenick.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's about as much fun for the viewer as being dropped into a virtual-reality version of a highway-safety crash film. Hall writes and directs with the finesse of a rusty hatchet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.deep23jun23,0,1317934.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Vondie Curtis-Hall has managed to top (or should I say "bottom"?) his last theatrical release, Mariah Carey's "Glitter," with a movie that offers not one praiseworthy moment: not a scene, not a performance, not a technical achievement, not even a line of dialogue.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html;jsessionid=D50FA0EBDBAC3ADBED1228D04A0FB405.prodapp12_ae_01?id=633950&amp;reviewId=21044&amp;startDate=06%2F23%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$21,344,312</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$9,404,180</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1,004</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>