<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>WALL-E</name>
   <company>Walt Disney Pictures, Pixar Animation Studios</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Animation</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jim Capobianco</author>
      <author>Andrew Stanton</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Andrew Stanton</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Fred Willard</actor>
      <actor>Jeff Garlin</actor>
      <actor>Sigourney Weaver</actor>
      <actor>John Ratzenberger</actor>
      <actor>Kathy Najimy</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 27, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>103</running_time>
   <rating>G</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that's both breathtakingly majestic and heartbreakingly intimate.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0826,wall-e-robots-in-love,478491,20.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The visual design of Wall-E is arguably Pixar's best. Stanton, who wrote the script with Jim Reardon from a story he concocted with Peter Docter, creates two fantastically imaginative, breathtakingly lit worlds.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=stXDLjWG25pv31dwl2yynPgffjhWyvSk96w52TwNp9jZphdLSkRG!-209288430&amp;&amp;rid=11329</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While I may argue with the little guy's taste in musicals, it's remarkable to see any film, in any genre, blend honest sentiment with genuine wit and a visual landscape unlike any other.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-wall-e/474605/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A charming, hilarious robot love story aimed at the entire family.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06262008/entertainment/movies/bot_stuff__117307.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At once futuristic, funny and fantastical.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-25-wall-e_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's Pixar's most daring experiment to date, but it still fits neatly into the studio's pantheon: Made with as much focus on heart as on visual quality, it's a sheer joy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/wall_e</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It whisks you to another world, then makes it every inch our own.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20209111,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first 40 minutes or so of Wall-E -- in which barely any dialogue is spoken, and almost no human figures appear on screen -- is a cinematic poem of such wit and beauty that its darker implications may take a while to sink in.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/27/movies/27wall.html</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first half hour of WALL-E is essentially wordless, and left me speechless. This magnificent animated feature from Pixar starts on such a high plane of aspiration, and achievement, that you wonder whether the wonder can be sustained. But yes, it can.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121451823921608769.html?mod=2_1168_1</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It can hardly be called a children's film, but a masterpiece of feature-film animation for all ages.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/wall-e/review/292190</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The idea that a company in the business of mainstream entertainment would make something as creative, substantial and cautionary as WALL-E has to raise your hopes for humanity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/06/26/AR2008062604139.html#</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is a beautiful movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/583632.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie does work, spectacularly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.walle27jun27,0,2645987.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The best American film of the year to date.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9749</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mixing Chaplinesque delicacy with the architectural grandeur of a Stanley Kubrick film, director Andrew Stanton recycles film history and makes something fresh and accessible from it without pandering to a young audience.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080627.wwall27/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Daring and traditional, groundbreaking and familiar, apocalyptic and sentimental, Wall-E gains strength from embracing contradictions that would destroy other films.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-walle27-2008jun27,0,2063836.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It works; this is Pixar's most enthralling entertainment since "Nemo."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1813964,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Once again, the Pixar wizards have pushed the animation envelope in unexpected directions and come up with a winner. Wondrously inventive, funny and poignant, WALL*E is part sci-fi adventure, part cautionary fable, part satire and part love story, which may be the best and most improbable part of all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newsweek.com/id/143466</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You leave WALL-E with a feeling of the rarest kind: that you've just enjoyed a close encounter with an enduring classic.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/19457927/review/21542030/walle</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The new Pixar picture Wall-E is one for the ages, a masterpiece to be savored before or after the end of the world.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/daily/movies/2008/06/walle_pixar.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To call WALL•E Pixar's best film would potentially denigrate films that deserve no scorn. But this is their most ambitious undertaking since "Toy Story" and storytelling of such charm and visual wit that it can stand proudly alongside the studio’s best. Absolute heaven.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=134838</url>
         <critic>Olly Richards</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story line for WALL-E is probably too convoluted for small kids, and sometimes it suffers from techie overload, but it's more heartfelt than anything on the screens these days featuring humans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0628/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A charmer of a film and a delightful piece of storytelling.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/368528_walle27q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first hour of Wall-E is a crazily inventive, deliriously engaging and almost wordless silent comedy of the sort that Charlie Chaplin and Buster Keaton used to make.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=91894500</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Apparently, the movie has caused annoyance in some quarters because it criticizes the American way of life. This it does, and with suavity and supreme good humor. WALL-E is a classic, but it will never appeal to people who are happy with art only when it has as little bite as possible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/07/21/080721crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=2</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A thoroughly enjoyable film, and ranks with Pixar's best.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11053</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Pixar's finest and most emotionally powerful film yet, and it draws on a wealth of cinematic resources that run the gamut from Chaplin's best to Buster Keaton, Jacques Tati, and even Martin and Lewis.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A639250</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A potent environmental message wrapped up in an irresistibly cute romance between robots.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/434/story/686983.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Succeeds at being three things at once: an enthralling animated film, a visual wonderment and a decent science-fiction story.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080626/REVIEWS/963071290</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Put simply, WALL-E is about as charming as movies get.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1153</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a justifiably G-rated film, but parents may have some 'splainin' to do.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2008/06/review_walle_dazzles_with_sile.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rotates around a rusty little robotic hero who's built, as the movie is, with such emotion, brains and humor that whole universes exist in his whirring tones and binocular eyes.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/27/2008-06-27_pixars_whimsical_walle_is_summers_cutest.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's first half is largely free of dialogue, playing like silent comedy, while the second act offers a breathtaking tour of the cosmos.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33284_WALL_E.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Walks a fine line between the rarefied and the immediately accessible as it explores new territory for animation, yet remains sufficiently crowd-pleasing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/VE1117937536.html</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wall-E is an improbable delight, a G-rated crowd-pleaser.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2194322/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In the moment, it's intermittently transcendent, heartrending and beautiful ... and busy, repetitious and boring.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/26/DDI011F0KL.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With rich, detailed, cinematic animation and terrific sound effects, WALLE pulls this unlikely love story off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20080627_Nuts-and-bolts__high-tech_love_story.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When it works, it really works, but it's debatable whether its target audience will really enjoy anything more than the nifty robots. Which is fine, too. Robots are pretty cool.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4631/walle.html</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The picture feels weirdly, and disappointingly, disjointed, something that starts out as poetry and ends as product.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/06/27/wall_e/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$223,808,164</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$180,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$63,087,526</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,992</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>