<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>War Within, The</name>
   <company>Magnolia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Ayad Akhtar</author>
      <author>Joseph Castelo</author>
      <author>Tom Glynn</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Joseph Castelo</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Ayad Akhtar</actor>
      <actor>Firdous Bamji</actor>
      <actor>Samrat Chakrabarti</actor>
      <actor>Sarita Choudhury</actor>
      <actor>Aasif Mvi</actor>
      <actor>Kamal Marayati</actor>
      <actor>Mike McGlone</actor>
      <actor>Nana Sen</actor>
      <actor>Varun Sriram</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>September 30, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>90</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Of all the feature films and documentaries to emerge since 9/11, few have been as bold, perceptive or as downright chilling as this thriller.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46490</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An utterly convincing portrait of the sort of person willing to strap ordnance to himself and decimate scores of strangers in pursuit of his religious and political ideals.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/1129805747180870.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>One of the strongest--and sure to be controversial--films of the year, The War Within goes places that other films wouldn't dare go.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-10-06/film/film6.html</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A few plot details strain credibility, but the characters (particularly the friend's sister and little boy) are persuasively depicted.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/28646_WAR_WITHIN.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's thanks to Akhtar's standout performance that The War Within is as electrifying as it is.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A298960</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film is highly critical of America's counterterrorist efforts, and not at all subtle in making the point that our stupidity and Nazi-like methods have helped create -- and vastly acerbate -- our problems.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/244513_war14q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What goes on inside the mind of a terrorist who is willing to blow himself for the cause? The War Within is one of the few films that attempts to deal with this subject in a nonexploitative way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0930/p14s03-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A portrait of a mild-mannered zealot, one that seeps under the skin and unsettles the nerves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/10/13/AR2005101301911.html</url>
         <critic>Teresa Wiltz</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not entirely free from an aura of didacticism or contrivance, but the film by and large functions as a taut thriller. A drastic act late in the film on the part of Duri seems somewhat implausible, but that does not deter The War Within from emerging as a mostly well-wrought and timely tragedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-war7oct07,0,3682.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Thomas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The War Within plays effectively off our voyeurism, yet it has such a cloistered, American-eyed view of the nightmare of terrorism that I kept searching for the profound explanation beneath its piecemeal ones.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1114283_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hampered by a mopey leading man.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8432</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The War Within is dark and somber, adjectives that describe both the film's look and its message.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=426315&amp;reviewId=19631</url>
         <critic>Marta Barber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes too pat and sometimes ragged with omissions and confusions, but it's still a fascinating look outside of that familiar world and into a harsher one.</snippet>
         <url>http://avclub.com/content/node/41310</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The War Within succeeds only as a thriller with some wartime overtones, rather than as a character study that thrills.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/09/30/movies/30war.html</url>
         <critic>Janet Maslin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chillingly realistic but deeply repellent, The War Within is a film that should not have been made.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/53188.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite an admirable effort to explore topical concerns, both director and actor are obviously overwhelmed by the immensity of the subject matter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/351086p-299353c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tries too hard to be even-handed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/10/14/DDG7VF7E3U1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Walter Addiego</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The War Within has within it a war of its own, one between docudramatic truth and familiar melodrama, however low-keyed.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-0501007-movies-review-war,0,1824800.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mired in noir cliché, the movie manages to be simultaneously overwrought and undercooked, with the Bambi-eyed Akhtar giving such a relentlessly inscrutable performance, one wants to poke him with a stick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3595&amp;Sumbit.x=40&amp;Sumbit.y=8</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An honorable but failed attempt to dramatize the dynamics that propel a basically good man to become a suicide bomber, The War Within contains provocative points inside a dull package.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117928412?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Does a fairly good job of laying out the basic political motives behind Islamic terrorism. Unfortunately, as a drama, it has its narrative peak in the middle and quickly runs out of story afterward.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001096962</url>
         <critic>Richard James Havis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shot in DV by Lisa Rinzler, Joseph Castelo's modest drama struggles for verisimilitude, but it wears clichés like concrete boots, down to the cycle-of-intolerance-and-violence message that we hear every day on NPR.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0539,atkinson2,68228,20.html</url>
         <critic>Michael Atkinson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$73,789</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$7,540</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>1</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>