<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Water Horse: Legend of the Deep, The</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Adventure</genre>
      <genre>FamilyKids</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Dick King-Smith</author>
      <author>Robert Nelson Jacobs</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Jay Russell</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Emily Watson</actor>
      <actor>Alex Etel</actor>
      <actor>Ben Chaplin</actor>
      <actor>David Morrissey</actor>
      <actor>Brian Cox</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 25, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>111</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Personally, I wouldn’t take a toddler (unless he was the son of Tarantino) to this intermittently, legitimately terrifying tale of a boy and his Loch Ness monster. But everyone else should blow off "Alvin and the Chipmunks" and show up for the best kiddie picture of the season -- and, along with "Ratatouille," of the year.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/movie-reviews-the-bucket-list-persepolis-the-great-debaters/17936/?page=2</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Well-told fanciful tales aimed at children but appreciated by adults are a rarity, and The Water Horse should be savored for the exuberantly entertaining ride it offers.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2007-12-23-water-horse_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like most British family films, Water Horse doesn't dumb down its young characters or insult the intelligence of the audience. It has a lot of sly humor about what we know, or have heard, about the Loch Ness monster.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071224/REVIEWS/712240302</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Combining the best of fantasy and somber reflection, The Water Horse is a lovely ride.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1139143&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ffamily-friendly escapist fare that should enthrall, without insult, fantasy-minded viewers of any age.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/12/25/movies/25wate.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Laura Kern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An enchanting tale of friendship and evolvingrelationships, The Water Horse: Legend of the Deep" engagingly grafts coming-of-age movie chestnuts onto Scottish folklore.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-water25dec25,0,4654260.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It declines to take itself seriously, yet manages, sometimes simultaneously, to be exciting, instructive, cheerfully absurd and genuinely affecting.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While it boasts a lower profile than many other Christmas releases, it might catch on with parents who want to take their kids to a movie that the entire family will actually enjoy. Nifty special effects and a first-rate British cast elevate this production.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=T2qWHh4WhZyDzL8vQlymgkkfvXPTw2JhD4Xj1MChCSXJHTw6CTTq!1932153867&amp;&amp;rid=10350</url>
         <critic>Stephen Farber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though it strikes some predictable coming-of-age notes, this moving, well-wrought adventure should appeal to fans of "E.T." and Carroll Ballard.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117935642.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Consider it "Free Willy" with the Loch Ness Monster. It's that kind of family-friendly movie - one that focuses on the friendship between a lonely boy and an animal.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/w/water_horse.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's adapted with charming dispatch from the Dick King-Smith story, and served up by the same CGI wizards who animated the critters in "The Lord of the Rings" and "The Narnia Chronicles."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20071223.horse24/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Few kid films manage to assemble this much ambition alongside this much sincere, sweet emotion.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_water_horse_legend_of_the</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The period detail is evocative, Watson and Etel are particularly good, and baby Crusoe -- a computer-generated image seamlessly woven into the live action -- is a slippery little star in his own right.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/water-horse/review/291771</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A solidly made wish-fulfillment fantasy set during World War II.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/12/25/DD04U1E8N.DTL</url>
         <critic>Steve Winn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like many fairy tales, this handsome family film concerns a child coming to terms with his fears and the death of a parent.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/32581_WATER_HORSE_LEGEND_OF_THE_DEEP.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Predictable but entertaining kid movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/344498_water25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A family film in the best sense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A573328</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a little corny and somewhat overlong, but a sweet sensibility and stirring adventure scenes make The Water Horse: Legend of the Deep a welcome gift for anyone looking to keep kids entertained over the holidays.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/12/25/2007-12-25_water_horse_good_family_entertainment.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>First, a few things The Water Horse is not: revolutionary, controversial or challenging. What it is: a sweet, familiar story, beautifully filmed and lovingly told.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-the-water/271189/content</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If you want to take the kids to a cockle-warming tale of humans and computer-generated critters, do yourself a favor: Skip the singing rodents and head for the baby Loch Ness Monster in The Water Horse: Legend of the Deep.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9185</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Emily Watson, looking at home in her '40s frocks, plays Angus' mother - coping not only with her son's obsession with what she believes to be an imaginary friend, but also with her own worry and grief about her husband at war.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071224_It_s_a_hard_time_for_young_Angus_MacMorrow__His_dad_is_off_NO_HEAD_SPECIFIED.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Likeable stuff despite being slow paced and rather sentimental.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=133915</url>
         <critic>Anna Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adults will sniff out a general air of phoniness - the period detail isn't particularly convincing, and the Scottish factor is overcooked to the point where the script starts to resemble the national cuisine.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12252007/entertainment/movies/wary_ness_mess_587514.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Parents can trust that none of their wee ones will ask for a stuffed water horse for Christmas. The star of this Scottish fable, about the mythical Loch Ness monster, looks like a raw chicken breast with teeth when he hatches.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20165813,00.html</url>
         <critic>Karen Valby</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$40,412,817</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$16,797,265</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,772</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>true</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>