<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Wedding Crashers</name>
   <company>New Line Cinema</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Steve Faber</author>
      <author>Bob Fisher</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>David Dobkin</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Owen Wilson</actor>
      <actor>Vince Vaughn</actor>
      <actor>Rachel McAdams</actor>
      <actor>Christopher Walken</actor>
      <actor>Jane Seymour</actor>
      <actor>Isla Fisher</actor>
      <actor>Will Ferrell</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>July 15, 2005</release_date>
   <running_time>119</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Funny, ungirdled romp - a buddy picture about buddies who actually know what women want.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1082768_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sometimes a movie comedy just clicks. Welcome to one of those times.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6151233?pageid=rs.ReviewsMovieArchive&amp;pageregion=mainRegion</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The flick brings two hours of great big sloppy buck-wild laughs by morphing into a cross between "Meet the Parents" and "Some Like It Hot."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/49823.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Head, shoulders, funny bone and brain above the competition. It's the best comedy I've seen this year.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Vince Vaughn and Owen Wilson are enormously funny in this farce.</snippet>
         <url>http://spacefinder.chicagoreader.com/movies/critic.html#28271</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Lung-bloatingly funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/14/AR2005071402102.html</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wedding Crashers may be the most optimistic Hollywood comedy of the year, because it restores at least some dim hope that directors, writers and actors with actual brains in their heads can somehow triumph over unimaginative studio execs. In that way, Wedding Crashers isn't just the life of the party, but its pulse.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2005/07/15/wedding_crashers/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The script by Steve Faber and Bob Fisher is one of those high-speed, ping-pong-banter marvels in which you're still laughing from the last great line when you're hit by the next.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2122745/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Not since the breakthrough days of Jim Carrey, Adam Sandler and the Farrelly brothers have two hours of movie comedy simultaneously felt so wrong but oh so right.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/Reviews.asp?Id=7733</url>
         <critic>Rick Kisonak</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Witty, unhinged and fearless, it's exactly the kind of movie we need now.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/chocano/cl-et-wedding15jul15,0,7472373.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Hopelessly raunchy, helplessly romantic, and wickedly, wickedly funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=353834&amp;reviewId=18504</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Good, indecent fun starring two of the most amiable comedy actors around.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/327832p-280226c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wedding Crashers is unashamedly profane and, for its first two acts, very funny, a classic guilty pleasure that revels in its basest elements.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.crashers15jul15,1,1882499.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Chris Kaltenbach</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Tom Cruise might have saved his family from apocalypse. But Owen Wilson and Vince Vaughn have just saved our summer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7241</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The first twenty minutes of Wedding Crashers are rabid with simple pleasure.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?050725crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Here's a tip: When Vaughn and Wilson are outed as impostors and forced to leave Walken's estate, grab your stuff and walk out. You'll think you just saw a comedy masterpiece.</snippet>
         <url>http://dallasobserver.com/Issues/2005-07-14/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Robert Wilonsky</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The two key roles are wonderfully cast with Owen Wilson and Vince Vaughn and the gross-but-not-too-gross humor will score with young moviegoers. But Wedding Crashers is still a letdown. The film never quite lives up to the promise of its premise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000975596</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It parades a screen chemistry rarely seen since the original Butch and Sundance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1081369,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprisingly flabby, with lazy writing and some final-act lurches into unironic rom-com that seem at odds with the bizarro premise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/112133548791280.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's little doubt a person can get a little pent-up looking for a good romantic comedy -- but you might want to save yourself until something better comes along.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/TPStory/LAC/20050715/WEDDING15/TPEntertainment/Film</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It’s an uneven outing from the Frat Pack, and an equally sad commentary on the state of American comedy: This run-on mess is the funniest film of the last six months.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2214</url>
         <critic>Sara Brady</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A showcase for Vince Vaughn's rantings and Owen Wilson's standard but affable chum act.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2005-07-14-wedding-crashers_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Watching Wedding Crashers is like stuffing yourself with raw cookie dough. It's a guilty pleasure that goes down easily, but you can't help wondering what it would've tasted like if someone had finished the job.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=353834&amp;reviewId=18495&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Reasonably enjoyable until its guys are forced to grow up. Because bad behavior is usually more fun to watch than good, the movie is especially fine during the preliminaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2005/07/15/movies/15wedd.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Vaughn can motormouth like a machine gun, spraying men, women and children with manic, rat-a-tat outbursts of toxic insincerity. It's often dirty, yes. But it's also manic and inspired.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/07/14/AR2005071400439.html</url>
         <critic>Desson Thomson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite flashes of nudity, crudity and mockery of women's raging hormones at the first sight of a trousseau, at its core it's just a big pushover with the heart of a chick flick.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117927584?categoryid=1920&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wedding Crashers doesn't quite live up to its promise, but through no fault of its off-the-wall cast.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.co.uk/site/incinemas/ReviewInFull.asp?FID=11230</url>
         <critic>Nick De Semlyen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Most of the time Wedding Crashers is more genteel than it is outrageous (or funny), playing like an only slightly less benign spin on the tiresome fish-out-of-water farce that fueled the two Meet the Parents movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film/film_results.php?showid=3472&amp;Sumbit.x=49&amp;Sumbit.y=9</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Each star has his moments, and the supporting cast is good, especially Walken, playing one of his less extreme characters; Jane Seymour as his promiscuous wife; and the stunning Rachel McAdams as their daughter and Wilson's love interest.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/232603_wedding15q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Delivers 90 minutes of riotously funny raunch; unfortunately, its running time is closer to two hours.</snippet>
         <url>http://tvguide.com/movies/database/showmovie.asp?MI=46311</url>
         <critic>Angel Cohn</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There are a few good laughs, but not nearly enough clever ideas to keep things hopping for two hours.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0715/p14s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>David Sterritt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Explosively funny in spots -- this is easily Vaughn's best work since "Swingers" -- but it comes wrapped in a package so sweet and sugary, so tediously moral and conventional, it sabotages the laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=353834&amp;reviewId=18515</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After a promising beginning, this movie crashes and burns.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/w/wedding_crashers.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Walken is an odd choice for a D.C. power player, wasting his creepiness on this straight, respectable role.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-050714-movies-review-wedding,0,7212693.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In spite of its cast and seemingly can't-miss premise, Wedding Crashers is at its best a succession of mild chuckles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theonionavclub.com/review.php?review_id=8694</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amiable and hollow.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0528,winter,65804,20.html</url>
         <critic>Jessica Winter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You know all those horror stories about a cigar-chomping producer who screens a movie and says they need to lose 15 minutes and shoot a new ending? Wedding Crashers needed a producer like that.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050714/REVIEWS/50708002/1001</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unfortunately, the inspired concept is coupled with weak screenwriting, and the movie turns out to be much more fun to think about than it is to watch.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/07/15/DDG5SDNIES1.DTL&amp;hw=wedding+crashers&amp;sn=002&amp;sc=973</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A stiff drink or maybe some pharmaceutical assistance might have made me overlook the film's sour tone, or the unremarkableness of its direction.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A278995</url>
         <critic>Kimberley Jones</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$209,218,368</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$40,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$33,900,720</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,925</number_of_screens>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>2</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>owen wilson</highest_grossing_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actor>christopher walken</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>