<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>When a Stranger Calls</name>
   <company>Screen Gems Inc.</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Jake Wade Wall</author>
      <author>Steve Feke</author>
      <author>Fred Walton</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Simon West</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Jake Wade Wall</actor>
      <actor>Tommy Flanagan</actor>
      <actor>Tessa Thompson</actor>
      <actor>Brian Geraghty</actor>
      <actor>Clark Gregg</actor>
      <actor>Derek de Lint</actor>
      <actor>Kate Jennings Grant</actor>
      <actor>David Denman</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>February 3, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Designed to capitalize on the title and premise of the original but offers little to those who fondly remember it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001957331</url>
         <critic>Frank Scheck</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A modestly clever concept gets indifferent execution in When a Stranger Calls, another bigger-yet-blander remake of an allegedly "classic" '70s shocker.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117929471?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Joe Leydon</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>After an hour of red herrings, in which Jill investigates creepy corridors or opens rattling closet doors with no results, the only real danger is that we'll become bored to death.
For real thrills, rent the original, turn down the lights and scare yourself silly.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/02-04-2006/front/story/388416p-329471c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ironically, for all of Stranger's faults, director Simon West has probably made a perfect date movie: just suspenseful enough to keep you arm-in-arm with your beau or belle; but silly enough that you'll both laugh about it afterwards.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2536</url>
         <critic>Channing Joseph</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jake Wade Wall's screenplay does deserve a word of praise. It has managed to incorporate the advent of cellphones, the *69 command and caller ID, which could have easily made the entire story impossible.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/02/04/movies/04stra.html</url>
         <critic>Anita Gates</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie ends with a bizarre and unsatisfying denouement. The epilogue, which is designed either to set up a sequel or lampoon "Halloween 2," plays like a sour last note. I suppose someone thought it was clever, but it doesn't work.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/w/when_stranger.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This version is a thin, protracted study in shifting Hollywood strategies. The original, while dramatically spotty, was an almost experimental concoction of horror and thriller. The 2006 model, in contrast, is straight-up formula.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0606,singer,72109,20.html</url>
         <critic>Matt Singer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When a Stranger Calls never manages to convey the primal, almost atavistic terror that has earned John Carpenter's movies and the "Scream" franchise their places in the teen horror canon. The most lasting psychological effect of this pulp non-classic will most likely be limited to a deep pathological fear of Architectural Digest.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/02/03/AR2006020302975.html</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Loud, noisy, flashy but too rarely chilling.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/incinemas/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=11176</url>
         <critic>Kim Newman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rather than remake the entire original movie, Simon West and screenwriter Jake Wade Wall have taken only that now-classic first act and padded it out into a dull, filler-filled feature that's remarkably void of any new ideas.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46645</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This remake takes an alternate tack from the original feature, expanding the story of "The Sitter" to a full 83 minutes, but the result is dull and painfully generic.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29259_WHEN_A_STRANGER_CALLS.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Amounts to an assault of jarring music cues and peek-a-boo scares that starts off mechanical and ends up utterly desperate.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12570&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Tim Grierson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Droopy remake.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-stranger6feb06,0,1051063.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The original should have been a short film; the new version shouldn't exist at all.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/45234</url>
         <critic>Scott Tobias</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>When a Stranger Calls is ba-a-a-a-c-k, in frightless form, updated for the age of anytime minutes and caller ID.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1157693_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even the element of surprise isn't enough to save this film, which has too many slow parts and features an ending that's extremely tepid by 21st century horror movie standards.</snippet>
         <url>http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/03/DDGDVH0E7T23.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Peter Hartlaub</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ineptly directed by Simon West, the scare-free When a Stranger Calls is the worst of the seminal horror movies from the late '70s and early '80s that have been getting the remake treatment lately.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/59741.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Even by the lowest standards, this is a frightless, cynically made movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=8227</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's an inferior remake (of a movie that wasn't that great to begin with), it's poorly acted, and it's yet another in an unending string of PG-13 "horror" movies that do nothing to build even the most rudimentary sense of real dread.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8611</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Long distance information? Get me Hollywood, USA: I’ve got a rusty ice pick to bury in the gullet of whoever greenlighted this pointless exercise in masturbatory tedium.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A333042</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$47,860,214</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$15,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$21,607,203</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>2,999</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>