<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Who Killed the Electric Car?</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Chris Paine</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Chris Paine</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Martin Sheen (narrator)</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 28, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>92</running_time>
   <rating>PG</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who Killed the Electric Car? makes you angry, and also sad, to live in a country where innovation could be contrived into an enemy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1210262_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The only question his movie doesn't ask is "What do you want your next car to run on?"  That's up to you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=9094</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>They were fast, they were sexy, they were clean, they were the future -- and they're already gone.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/115334976578510.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who Killed the Electric Car? makes you feel that no good idea, let alone good deed, goes unpunished. Only the exuberance of the moviemaking keeps your spirits high.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.who01sep01,0,898254.story?coll=bal-movies-utility</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A potent hybrid of passion and politics fuel this energetic and highly compelling documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002729006</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Chris Paine's documentary makes an unapologetic case for the car and an unofficial indictment of the forces allied against it.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1205348,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Who Killed the Electric Car? is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/06/28/movies/28kill.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Above all, the film is an extended love letter to the EV1, a sleek GM electric marvel that, by Paine's reckoning, marks the single greatest innovation in human technology since the wheel.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/49916</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paine doesn't hide his liberal mind-set, but he lets all sides - from GM suits to Ralph Nader - have their say. By the closing credits, there's little doubt who killed the electric car.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/oils_not_well_that_ends_well_in_jolting_doc_movies_v_a__musetto.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the end of the film, you actually come to mourn the passing of the EV1, a well-intentioned soul that was in the right place at the right time, but was surrounded by the wrong people.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2923</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In a sad twist of technological birth and infanticide, General Motors - with assists from the oil industry, the Bush administration, cowardly California energy officials and apathetic consumers - doomed the future car to the literal scrap heap of history.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/431326p-363376c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A balanced examination of the reasons for the electric car's disappearance, reasons that include corporate collusion and greed, governmental spinelessness and oil company propaganda -- but also consumer indifference and the limitations of the vehicles themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/07/07/DDGP1JQ0OM1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Shaped just like the murder-mystery its title promises, the documentary Who Killed the Electric Car? introduces us to the victim, then rounds up the suspects most likely responsible for its demise.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=597941&amp;reviewId=21191</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As efficient and zippy as its subject.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=597941&amp;reviewId=21148&amp;startDate=07%2F28%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There is an element of murder mystery and an edge of conspiracy thriller to Chris Paine's documentary about the rise and fall of General Motors' EV1 (Electric Vehicle 1).</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/277481_electric14q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nihilistic greed was the major factor when GM terminated the car in 2001, though Paine is also careful to note the passivity of the general public.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29967_WHO_KILLED_THE_ELECTRIC_CAR.html</url>
         <critic>Jonathan Rosenbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Oil companies aren't the only ones profiting from a spike in prices at the gas pump. It's likely also to boost the prospects of Who Killed the Electric Car? a likable if partisan post-mortem on the now-defunct auto.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117930452?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1&amp;s=h&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a laudably complicated, if emotional and a little comic-book goofy, story of how a confluence of forces - industry skepticism, trained-seal lobbyists and, last but not least, consumer reluctance - undermined the future of a quiet little bean of mobile metal that the anointed few who could afford to lease it passionately adored.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13887/</url>
         <critic>Judith Lewis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>So who did kill the electric car? There are many suspects, and as it turns out, most of them are guilty.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8463</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the end of Who Killed the Electric Car? you'll be worked into a lather one way or another. Paine crams in more theories, ideas and arguments than the movie can easily hold, but that's OK with me.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/06/29/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fascinating documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/printedition/calendar/cl-et-electric28jun28,0,153280.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who Killed the Electric Car?, a fascinating feature-length documentary by Chris Paine, opens with a mock funeral, then follows the structure of a mock trial in which multiple suspects are found guilty.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You’ll leave the film wondering why you've never seen a TV ad for an electric car, or why GM is all about selling Hummers these days.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A389988</url>
         <critic>Marjorie Baumgarten</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Paine does offer something of a heroine in Chelsea Sexton; the attractive EV1 sales specialist was laid off in 2001, became an EV1 activist and is now executive director of Plug In America.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060714.ELECTRIC14/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Jennie Punter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Impassioned, unwieldy and padded with celebrity interviews.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=47025&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=0&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A story that deserves to be heard, but like the EV1, it’s a quiet achievement that should have been much louder.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=134216#Scene_1</url>
         <critic>Sam Toy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A lot of the film is illuminating; a lot of it is pointless.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1122593&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The real question is why this purportedly impassioned documentary investigation of a great subject--the culture's conspiratorial dismissal of eco-friendly alternatives to the gas-guzzler -- would assume such massive viewer disinterest that it coats the pill with C-list celebrity NutraSweet, including Martin Sheen voiceovers -- that would sound unforgivably hackneyed even on basic cable.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0626,nelson,73665,20.html</url>
         <critic>Rob Nelson</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,678,874</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$58,526</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>8</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>true</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>