<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Why We Fight</name>
   <company>Sony Pictures Classics</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Documentary</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Eugene Jarecki</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Eugene Jarecki</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>William Solomon</actor>
      <actor>Karen Kwiatkowski</actor>
      <actor>Anh Duong</actor>
      <actor>John McCain</actor>
      <actor>William Kristol</actor>
      <actor>Richard Perle</actor>
      <actor>Gore Vidal</actor>
      <actor>John S.D. Eisenhower</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>January 20, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>98</running_time>
   <rating>Not</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's impossible to imagine anyone, right-leaning or left, coming away from this hugely important documentary unshaken by its representation of the United States and its military establishment.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html?id=465126&amp;reviewId=20204</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a topical, iconoclastic documentary with the warmth and pace of a first-rate personal essay.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.fight17mar17,0,2510259.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jarecki is no glib ideologue thumbing his nose at power.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1150081_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Picture sets the gold standard for political documentaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=sundance2005&amp;nav=reviews&amp;content=reviews&amp;reviewid=VE1117925968&amp;categoryid=1865&amp;cs=</url>
         <critic>Robert Koehler</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why We Fight deserves high praise for making it that much tougher to wear blinders.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6823996/rid/9166284/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An agit-doc of unusual depth. It has a point -- that the primary business of America over the past half-century has been waging war -- and it supports that point with nuance, research, and a willingness to hear the other side of the argument.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=7672</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's plenty of ammunition here for liberal conspiracy theorists, which surely will limit the audience to those already in Jarecki's political camp. Which is too bad, for it is a sobering history lesson as well as a political polemic on foreign policy and the growth of war into America's biggest business.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/258970_fight10q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A film that stands out for its passion, ambition and clarion-call sincerity, even amid the contemporary onslaught of political documentaries.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/01/19/btm/index.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Memo to left-wing anti-Bushies: Stories like this work. Don't lecture. Tell stories! Much better!</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1108335&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Canny and somewhat overwhelming documentary.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A345777</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's no denying the particular political slant of Why We Fight, but Jarecki's thoughtful, nonconfrontational approach makes it absorbing viewing, regardless of whether or not you buy his arguments.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html?id=465126&amp;reviewId=20161</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The strength of this documentary lies in its balance, or at least the careful appearance of balance.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060217.WHY17/TPStory/TPEntertainment/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A somber polemic that presents a convincing case against using war as an economic booster -- although, Jarecki argues, that is precisely what the United States has been doing under every president since Truman.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/02/10/DDGK8H57OP1.DTL#flick</url>
         <critic>Neva Chonin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Why We Fight attempts, somewhat sketchily, to connect the dots between Ike's Cassandra-like warnings and current events.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/113944292376500.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result isn't quite a Michael Moore movie without the hubris, but it's reasonably close. It's thoughtful, and you have to take it seriously and with respect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-01-19-why-we-fight_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Mike Clark</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a deeply provocative piece of filmmaking.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/movies/database/ShowMovie.asp?MI=46631</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether we've reached the critical mass of "misplaced power" is the gist of the current national debate, and Why We Fight is a useful tool in that argument.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/01-20-2006/entertainment/col/story/384178p-326092c.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ultimately, Why We Fight reveals itself as yet another leftie doc with an anti-war agenda. But the mere fact that it takes time to ask questions and listen to opposing viewpoints sets it apart from the pack.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/44528</url>
         <critic>Keith Phipps</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In addition to the usual pontificators like Gore Vidal, whose world weariness has assumed Olympian proportions, the director provides interviews with such right-wing counterparts as Richard Perle and William Kristol. Nobody is allowed much time to develop an argument.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0120/p14s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The long line of recent muckraking documentaries that has preceded Why We Fight does nothing to diminish its force.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-fight20jan20,0,136863.story</url>
         <critic>Kevin Crust</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jarecki says that his film doesn't precisely answer the question in his title. He is mistaken.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20060213&amp;s=kauffmann021306</url>
         <critic>Stanley Kauffmann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Adding to the film's underlying sense of urgency and unease is composer Robert Miller's haunting score, so reminiscent of Philip Glass' music for "The Fog of War."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-02-09/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Jean Oppenheimer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Jarecki's film forcefully argues that the much abused word FREEDOM cannot paper over the conflicts between capitalism and democracy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0603,hoberman,71721,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite Jarecki's varied success in bringing these six people's stories to life, their stories personalize our current geopolitical predicament and remind us that in a democracy no one can shrug off responsibility for the war.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/movies/archives/2006/0206/060217.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This scary, eye-opening documentary looks back from a post-9/11 vantage point to see how Ike’s prophecy has come horribly true.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/10857739/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Unconvincing and ineffective; the many patches of ideological montage, growing like kudzu throughout the film, weaken the impact of its best moments.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060123crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Jarecki forcefully, if not with wholesale persuasiveness, argues that our business is specifically war.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/01/20/movies/20figh.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A pretty entertaining case against our current war and question the integrity of our president, but more than that, these docs manipulate imagery, music and sound bites to work their audiences into a frenzy.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060217-movies-review-fight,0,6158298.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Allison Benedikt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie tells us nothing we haven't heard before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rogerebert.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060216/REVIEWS/602160303/1023</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There may not be two equal sides to every argument, but in giving such little credence to those who might oppose him, Jarecki makes us wonder what exactly it is he’s so afraid of.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/index.php?option=com_lawcontent&amp;task=view&amp;id=12438&amp;Itemid=9</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This rehash of familiar pacifist arguments offers neither heat nor light. It's "Fahrenheit: Room Temperature."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/61847.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mr. Jarecki undercuts his own case -- not just undercuts but carpet-bombs it -- by using the same propaganda techniques he professes to abhor.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$1,880,863</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$53,571</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>6</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>