<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Wrestler, The</name>
   <company>Fox Searchlight Pictures</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Robert D. Siegel</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Darren Aronofsky</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Mickey Rourke</actor>
      <actor>Marisa Tomei</actor>
      <actor>Evan Rachel Wood</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>December 17, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>109</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler is like "Rocky" made by the Scorsese of "Mean Streets." It's the rare movie fairy tale that's also a bravura work of art.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20245338,00.html</url>
         <critic>Owen Gleiberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rourke creates a galvanizing, humorous, deeply moving portrait that instantly takes its place among the great, iconic screen performances. An elemental story simply and brilliantly told, Darren Aronofsky's fourth feature is a winner from every possible angle.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938197.html?categoryid=2863&amp;cs=1&amp;query=the+wrestler</url>
         <critic>Todd McCarthy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rourke is getting tons of press and award nominations, but Marisa Tomei kicks ass too. Not only does the one-time Oscar winner look amazing and perform her own pole tricks, but she effectively humanizes what could be just another naked chick in a movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/Review/Movies/The-Wrestler</url>
         <critic>Jenni Miller</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler is a character study, no more and no less, yet it's open-ended enough to function as many things.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=12579</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie has the simplicity and confidence of a Johnny Cash song.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/12/24/DDEJ14U023.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is Rourke doing astonishing physical acting.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20081223/REVIEWS/812239985</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An emotional smackdown. Rourke's never been better, and the change of pace and texture suits Aronofsky perfectly. "The Raging Bull" of wrestling movies? Oh, go on then.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/review.asp?FID=135272</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a raw and honest film, and it keeps its feet firmly on the ground, even as The Ram flies through the air to deliver -- or receive -- another beating in the squared circle of life.</snippet>
         <url>http://blog.oregonlive.com/madaboutmovies/2009/01/movie_review_rourke_grapples_w.html</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Ram is sometimes--often, even--a manipulative, self-pitying man, but Rourke and Aronofsky paint his portrait with a rigorous dignity.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2206966/</url>
         <critic>Dana Stevens</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like its hero, the movie has a blunt, exuberant honesty, pulling off even its false moves with conviction and flair.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/12/17/movies/17wres.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Rourke offers us, in short, is not just a comeback performance but something much rarer: a rounded, raddled portrait of a good man. Suddenly, there it is again--the charm, the anxious modesty, the never-distant hint of wrath, the teen-age smiles, and all the other virtues of a winner.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/12/15/081215crci_cinema_lane</url>
         <critic>Anthony Lane</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Aronofsky's directorial style is simple and spare. There are no flourishes or attempts to convince us that he is a master of his craft.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1422</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler offers something to pretty much everyone in the audience. Much like "The Sopranos," it creates a world that might make you feel utterly at home or exhilarated by strange horrors. Maybe both.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/12172008/entertainment/movies/we_love_new_rourke_144623.htm</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler presents a fascinating peek at the workings of the pro wrestling industry (the tenderness and humor the athletes share backstage is the complete opposite of the ferocity they display in the ring).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/854071.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler works for the same reason "Rachel Getting Married" works. The way they're acted, shot, edited and scored, both films deploy a loose, rough-hewn documentary style to great dramatic advantage. The corn isn't hyped. The performances click without going for the jugular.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-wrestler-review-1225dec26,0,2737864.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a haunting, scary, funny, sad portrayal from Rourke.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20090109_Mickey_Rourke__art_imitating_life.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>You watch The Wrestler (with a superb title song from Bruce Springsteen) in a state of pure exhilaration. A great actor in a great movie will do that to you.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/19744444/review/24616363/the_wrestler</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film's a little more accessible than "Requiem for a Dream" and a lot easier to understand than "The Fountain," but its low-key grunginess may restrict its appeal to people who have liked professional wrestling and/or Rourke.</snippet>
         <url>http://events.charlotteobserver.com/reviews/show/38634-review-the-wrestler</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's bleak, credulity straining and often stomach-turning, but it definitely works as a heart-tugging character study, and Rourke's performance as the has-been title character is golden.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/395287_wrestler09q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mostly though, the movie feeds off Rourke, who plays a genuinely decent guy who never lets his dawning self-awareness interfere with his responsibility to give the fans a show.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_wrestler</url>
         <critic>Noel Murray</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Both Rourke and Tomei bring a tender, lived-in honesty to their sad roles.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/12/16/2008-12-16_mickey_rourke_earns_oscar_buzz_with_role.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Bolstered by a career-best performance from Mickey Rourke and outstanding work by Marisa Tomei and Evan Rachel Wood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=11602</url>
         <critic>Stephen Farber</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director, Darren Aronofsky, and the writer, Robert D. Siegel, have turned the story of this washed-up faux gladiator into a film of authentic beauty and commanding consequence.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122963414294619431.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>He looks like a truck ran over him, but at 52 he's still ripped enough to get away with the role; in the end the movie is about Rourke's indomitability more than the character's.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33692_WRESTLER.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As far as I'm concerned, you can keep your Sean Penns and your Brad Pitts and your Frank Langellas; if there's any justice in the world, this year's best actor Academy Award will be going home with Rourke.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A723023</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The story has its clichéd and sentimental moments. It's no "Raging Bull," more like "Rocky" shot with a handheld camera. But Rourke's wounded tough guy is undeniably captivating.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-12-16-the-wrestler_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The excesses are easy to forgive, both for the humour and charisma of Rourke's outsized performance and Aronofsky's canny low-key direction, which make for a combination that is irresistible.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081223.wwrestler1224/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As good as Rourke is, and as willingly as he throws himself on the figurative hand grenade, his performance constantly begs the question of whether the story would be worth telling without him. Marisa Tomei, as Cassidy the pole dancer, delivers a courageous performance, one nearly as ego-battering as Rourke's.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/the-wrestler,1154622.html</url>
         <critic>John Anderson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler could have been a groundbreaking drama, one that upturns the sensational genre roots from which it stems. With Rourke in such form, it could have been character-driven to the core – if only Aronofsky trusted his character enough to resist screenwriter Siegel's contrived plot thrusts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11428</url>
         <critic>Matthew Sorrento</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Present in every scene, if not each shot, Rourke gives a tremendously physical performance that The Wrestler essentially exists to document.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-12-17/film/mickey-rourke-and-darren-aronofsky-both-make-visceral-comebacks-in-the-wrestler/</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whatever Aronofsky did -- or didn't -- do, Rourke's performance comes off beautifully. The Wrestler may not be the "best" Aronofsky movie in any technical sense. But the director clearly feels a great deal of tenderness toward his lead character.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/10/10/wrestler/index.html?CP=IMD&amp;DN=110</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A heavy dose of corn syrup. Director Darren Aronofsky's herky-jerky, hand-held camera stylistics have a veneer of verity, but don't be fooled. This pastiche, written by Robert Siegel, is purest Hollywood.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/1220/p25s01-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This movie has an aura of forced tragedy, like a fourth-generation version of "Requiem for a Heavyweight."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.wrestler16jan16,0,5705523.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn't as world-shattering as those bouts: It's a regretful-old-warrior weeper.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/52914/index3.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Rourke does strong, sensitive work here, which will cheer his old-time admirers and win him new fans...But the movie itself is pretty bad.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1866615,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The Wrestler doesn't add up. It's constructed with great care around a lead performance that is everything it could possibly be, but the picture itself is off-putting and disappointing.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/movies/la-et-wrestler17-2008dec17,0,2680168.story</url>
         <critic>Kenneth Turan</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$26,236,603</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$6,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$288,220</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>4</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>