<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Wristcutters: A Love Story</name>
   <company>Autonomous Films</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Drama</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Romance</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Etgar Keret</author>
      <author>Goran Dukic</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Goran Dukic</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Patrick Fugit</actor>
      <actor>Shannyn Sossamon</actor>
      <actor>Shea Whigham</actor>
      <actor>Tom Waits</actor>
      <actor>Will Arnett</actor>
      <actor>Leslie Bibb</actor>
      <actor>Sarah Roemer</actor>
      <actor>Abraham Benrubi</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 19, 2007</release_date>
   <running_time>91</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Wristcutters: A Love Story is a lousy title for a lovely-loony picture about an afterlife for suicides. It's an off-road "road movie" about people who off themselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.wristcutters09nov09,0,1242162.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film about suicide, Wristcutters is agreeably loopy and game. Dukic is bitterly funny rather than maudlin, and his carefully plotted grunge chic, in addition to being cheap, lends the film a great deal of Jim Jarmusch grime to go with its unmistakable Jim Jarmusch quirk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/wristcutters_a_love_story</url>
         <critic>Tasha Robinson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The whole film is cracked, but in a stylish, downtown way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20152840,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This delightful piece of whimsy uses its simple premise effectively to gain and keep our attention and to remind us simply that, while this world appears ordinary, it is still unbounded by reality.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/337718_wrist02q.html</url>
         <critic>Gianni Truzzi</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has an offbeat, absurdist charm that turns a potentially creepy conceit into an odd, touching adventure.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/10/19/movies/19wris.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is wholly original, sort of like "The Wizard of Oz" as filtered through the sensibilities of Emir Kusturica, the cult filmmaker and musician.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/10192007/entertainment/movies/getting_their_slit_together.htm</url>
         <critic>V.A. Musetto</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>For a film about suicides, Wristcutters: A Love Story is strangely life-affirming. This film about slackers stuck in limbo between life and death is upbeat in an offbeat way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/philly/entertainment/movies/20071109_A_story_of_suicides__yet_not_grim.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Turns out to be a sweetly grim lark: a road film through Limbo. It takes the self-pity associated with ending one's life and uses it for the purposes of mordantly aware comic fantasy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10203</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A quirky but surprisingly lighthearted dark comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/02/DDMFT44Q2.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Ruthe Stein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Simultaneously dark and sweet, always a difficult combination to pull off. It views its characters with both archness and affection, and even as it lovingly recalls films of another era it insists that the painful awkwardness of youth is perennial.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2007/10/18/btm/index1.html</url>
         <critic>Andrew O&amp;#039;Hehir</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The film has a spry quality, but the jokes are neither funny nor dark enough, the quirky roadside episodes aren't sufficiently outlandish or imaginative, the romantic sparks don't convince and the plotting becomes increasingly silly and tedious. Dukic conjures an air of play and naughtiness, but that's about as deep as he cuts.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/entertainment/119379210754490.xml&amp;coll=7</url>
         <critic>Shawn Levy</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn't laugh out loud funny, under the circumstances, but it is bittersweet and wistfully amusing; the actors enjoy lachrymosity. We witness the birth of a new genre, the Post-Slasher Movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071101/REVIEWS/711010308</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It is neither as clever nor as funny nor as inventive as the daring title might lead one to expect.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/movies/w/wristcutters.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Quite a bit darker than most mainstream romantic comedies. As you might not expect, it’s also quite a bit more inventive and far wittier than most mainstream romantic comedies.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-wristcutters-a/243081/content</url>
         <critic>Jessica Reaves</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's borderline parody of a kind of fey filmmaking popular at crunchy-granola festivals, but the counterfeit aesthetic is ultimately outshone by the life-affirming message.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-et-wrist26oct26,0,1887995.story?coll=cl-mreview</url>
         <critic>Jan Stuart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Imagine a blend of "The Wizard of Oz," "Beetlejuice" and "Roadside Prophets" and you'll know exactly what Wristcutters is like.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=8370</url>
         <critic>Eric Campos</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though its absurdist inventions occasionally border on twee, this affectionate slow-blooming romance mines an understated vein of comic melancholy that the actors' wistful performances perfectly capture.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;head=sundance&amp;nav=RSundance&amp;articleid=VE1117929364&amp;cs=1&amp;p=0</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A well-wrought indie written and directed by Goran Dukic, has to be the kewpie doll of current zombie flicks: Its walking dead are a bunch of attractive slackers whose wounds are largely internal. They've got attitude.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0742,hoberman,78060,20.html</url>
         <critic>J. Hoberman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite being occasionally hilarious, director Goran Dukic should have toned down the wackiness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135279</url>
         <critic>Staff (Not credited)</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Somewhat original and amusing. But only somewhat.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/imdb/reviews/article_display.jsp?rid=1001884037&amp;vnu_special_account_code=thrsiteimdbpro</url>
         <critic>Kirk Honeycutt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Seems to me, teenage suicide isn't that funny, and nothing in this movie changed my mind.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1123469&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Like some laid-back distant cousin of Tim Burton, writer-director Goran Dukic manages to balance the ghoulishness with whimsy and melancholy, at least for a while. But the strain is obvious in the story's last third, as the filmmaker struggles toward a resolution that fits the logic of the hero's netherworld.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/30570_WRISTCUTTERS_A_LOVE_STORY.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But absurdity alone won’t get the train into the depot, and no amount of quirky characters floating in their chairs or fish changing colors at random can make up for the film’s lack of real humor or meaning. Which is to say, if you’re going to make a comedy about suicide, you’d better make sure the jokes land. There are people out there who could use a laugh.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A555784</url>
         <critic>Josh Rosenblatt</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's described as a black comedy, but you can forget the comedy part. There wasn't so much as a snicker at the screening I attended, though I may have heard a snore or two.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2007/10/19/2007-10-19_short_takes_more_movie_reviews.html</url>
         <critic>Jack Mathews</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$446,165</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$42,808</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>