<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>X-Men: The Last Stand</name>
   <company>Twentieth Century Fox Film Corporation</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Fantasy</genre>
      <genre>Scifi</genre>
      <genre>SuspenseThriller</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Zak Penn</author>
      <author>Simon Kinberg</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Brett Ratner</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Patrick Stewart</actor>
      <actor>Hugh Jackman</actor>
      <actor>Ian McKellen</actor>
      <actor>Halle Berry</actor>
      <actor>Famke Janssen</actor>
      <actor>Anna Paquin</actor>
      <actor>Kelsey Grammer</actor>
      <actor>Rebecca Romijn</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>May 26, 2006</release_date>
   <running_time>103</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>Surprise, surprise. X-Men: The Last Stand, the third big-screen convocation of mutant shape shifters, weather changers, ice makers, energy suckers, healers and telepaths from Marvel Comics, has shifted the shape of the franchise from pretty good, if uninspired, to terrifically entertaining.</snippet>
         <url/>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It delivers pretty much what's expected.</snippet>
         <url>http://movie-reviews.colossus.net/movies/x/x-men3.html</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ratner is unable to maintain the emotional intensity that has made this series so deeply epic. But he sure knows how to put on a show.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/moviereviews/story/420527p-354902c.html</url>
         <critic>Elizabeth Weitzman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Love it or hate it, X-III packs more action and razzle-dazzle visuals into its 104-minute running time than "Mission: Impossible III," "Poseidon" and "The Da Vinci Code" combined.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/271427_xmen25q.html</url>
         <critic>William Arnold</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The happiest news about the third (and final?) X-Men movie is actually quite sad: headstones. Yes, The Last Stand brings the lamentable deaths of several major characters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=6883</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I liked the action, I liked the absurdity, I liked the incongruous use and misuse of mutant powers, and I especially liked the way it introduces all of those political issues and lets them fight it out with the special effects.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060524/REVIEWS/60509005</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If this really is the last stand, it's a stylish farewell indeed.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.dallasobserver.com/Issues/2006-05-25/film/film.html</url>
         <critic>Luke Y. Thompson</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though the picture is not without its wow-inducing, SFX-driven moments, that potent X-factor is considerably diminished in Singer's absence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002539746</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a fast and enjoyable B-movie, though, and Hugh Jackman’s Wolverine brings some good stormy drama to the proceedings.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/17071/index1.html</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result, though it delivers only in fits and starts, is still sharper and more inventive than most comicbook-adapted fare, and eventually gets the job done as far as action buffs are concerned.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=features2006&amp;content=jump&amp;jump=review&amp;dept=cannes&amp;nav=RCannes&amp;articleid=VE1117930584&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Justin Chang</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If little else, the third and supposedly final entry in the  X-Men mega-franchise suggests that some movies -- or at any rate some formulas -- are not just critic-proof, they might even be director-proof.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0621,lim,73310,20.html</url>
         <critic>Dennis Lim</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ratner's version is friskier, shallower-and more fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/12995480/site/newsweek/</url>
         <critic>David Ansen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ratner seems to have found a theme that he can relate to: A terrifying trio of angry, undomesticated women who all but run away with the movie.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/cl-et-xmen26may26,0,3697363.story</url>
         <critic>Carina Chocano</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Whether the entry is good, great or (in this case) indifferent, it's always stimulating to return to the high-flying X-Men series.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/bal-to.xmen26may26,0,3209302.story?coll=bal-artslife-movies</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This is interesting stuff. So why does The Last Stand feel driven to dumb itself down, as if embarrassed by its own ideas?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/review/movie/0,6115,1197626_1_0_,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>I suppose it's asking too much of Ratner to impart some kind of visionary flourish to the proceedings. But without it, these comic-book movies all tend to look the same.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0526/p11s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a couple of emotionally resonant scenes that build on the first two story lines. But it lacks the intriguing moody quality of the previous films. The mutants are more pumped up and angry this time, rather than misunderstood and conflicted.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2006-05-24-x-men_x.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Disappointingly, X-Men: The Last Stand slides back between the first two episodes. It's not stuporous, and it's not super.</snippet>
         <url>http://metromix.chicagotribune.com/movies/mmx-060526-movies-review-x,0,6419139.story?coll=mmx-movies_top_heds</url>
         <critic>Michael Wilmington</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>With more superheroes, more action and more stuff blowing up than ever before, X-Men: The Last Stand has the climactic oomph that suggests a finale, though not the gravitas to suggest a resolution.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20060526.XMEN26/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Movies/</url>
         <critic>Liam Lacey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Comic-book enthusiasts can breathe a sigh of relief: Brett Ratner hasn't completely ruined the X-Men series a.k.a. "The Franchise that Bryan Singer Built."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/article.asp?section_id=2&amp;article_id=2854</url>
         <critic>Ethan Alter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>While I didn't love it, I enjoyed The Last Stand because it made me imagine the mutant powers I want to develop. I'm thinking along the lines of merging Rogue's suction abilities with Storm's controlled-rain skills.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.philly.com/entertainment/ui/philly/movie.html;jsessionid=8DFD08DBEC74BE7901813022092EB53A.prodapp15_ae_01?id=602711&amp;reviewId=20878&amp;startDate=05%2F25%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>But for all the sound, fury and spectacle, the film feels vaguely hollow and unsatisfying.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.tvguide.com/newsearch/detail.aspx?id=46821&amp;sourcetype=m&amp;progseriesparentid=0&amp;tvobjectid=279934&amp;keyword=&amp;more=ucmoviereview</url>
         <critic>Maitland McDonagh</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mostly about extending a Hollywood franchise with ever-diminishing returns.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/movies/69149.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Brett Ratner can't make chicken a la king out of chicken droppings, and that's what writers Simon Kinberg ("XXX: State of the Union") and Zak Penn ("Elektra") supply.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.charlotte.com/entertainment/ui/charlotte/movie.html?id=602711&amp;reviewId=20883&amp;startDate=NEXT7</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Only half a mess -- and even with all its flaws, it's an enjoyable diversion that shows both respect and affection for the formidable legacy of the "X-Men" comics.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2006/05/26/xmen_stand/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Singer's absence is felt but not fatal. By adding too much new blood Ratner loses some of the original DNA, but with its nifty set-pieces and a few nasty surprises, X3's still a worthy enough sequel to ensure it’s no Last Stand.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=9798</url>
         <critic>Dan Jolin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Following two superior entries, Ratner's slick placeholder of a sequel lacks that crucial X-factor called inspiration.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/node/48821</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mostly, as so often with these types of empty entertainments, you are left to wonder why companies that hire so many fine actors to run around under latex and foam and have the best technological wizardry money can buy seem to spend so little attention to the screenplay.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies2.nytimes.com/2006/05/26/movies/26xmen.html</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Almost as mindless as "Fantastic Four," but more annoying in that this one has philosophical pretensions.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/05/25/DDG85J0UQE1.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Despite all the grand gestures of climax and resolution, there's a pronounced sense of autopilot; the only person who seems to be having a good time is Ian McKellen as the scheming Magneto.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/29834_X_MEN_THE_LAST_STAND.html</url>
         <critic>J.R. Jones</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>There's much to enjoy here – Ratner's pacing is fluid and fast and the film rushes along its busy, cluttered way with something approaching melodramatic snarkiness – but it's also terribly busy and cluttered.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A367751</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An uninspired hodgepodge.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2142458/?nav=fo</url>
         <critic>Michael Agger</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Ratner makes a hash of the story and characters his predecessor brought to such complex, sympathetic life, delivering a pumped-up exercise in mayhem, carnage and blunt-force trauma.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1093555&amp;lat=200.0&amp;lon=200.0&amp;displaySearchLocation=&amp;nm=1&amp;categories=Movies</url>
         <critic>Ann Hornaday</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Last stand? My ass. Billed as the climax of a trilogy, the third and weakest chapter in the X-Men series is a blatant attempt to prove there is still life in the franchise.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/_/id/6135195/rid/10383568/</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's a disappointing chapter in what until now has been a highly entertaining, even thought-provoking series.</snippet>
         <url>http://ae.miami.com/entertainment/ui/miami/movie.html;jsessionid=D86E3BD5A4D500571D666679958D7A8D.prodapp14_ae_02?id=602711&amp;reviewId=20866&amp;startDate=05%2F25%2F2006</url>
         <critic>Connie Ogle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Has a few high points, but feels far too disjointed and slapdash to favorably compare to what came before.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=9016</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What a comedown, after the weirdly beautiful things Singer and his technicians did in the first two movies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/critics/cinema/?060605crci_cinema</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Long before the movie's climax, in which Magneto (Ian McKellen) turns smashed-up automobiles into fiery projectiles to be hurled at his enemies, those in the audience will know what it means to behold a flaming hunk of junk.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.laweekly.com/film+tv/film-reviews/film-reviews/13608/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$234,362,462</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$150,000,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$102,750,665</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,690</number_of_screens>
   <oscar_winning_actors_present/>
   <num_oscar_winning_actors>1</num_oscar_winning_actors>
   <oscar_winning_actor>halle berry</oscar_winning_actor>
   <highest_grossing_actors_present/>
   <num_highest_grossing_actors>1</num_highest_grossing_actors>
   <highest_grossing_actor>ian mckellen</highest_grossing_actor>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>true</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>