<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>You Don&amp;#039;t Mess with the Zohan</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures (Sony)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Action</genre>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Adam Sandler</author>
      <author>Robert Smigel</author>
      <author>Judd Apatow</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Dennis Dugan</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Adam Sler</actor>
      <actor>John Turturro</actor>
      <actor>Emmanuelle Chriqui</actor>
      <actor>Nick Swardson</actor>
      <actor>Rob Schneider</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>June 6, 2008</release_date>
   <running_time>minutes,</running_time>
   <rating>PG-13</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>As hig concepts go, You Don't Mess With the Zohan" takes the cake.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0607/p25s02-almo.html</url>
         <critic>Peter Rainer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Director Dennis Dugan knows his way around shin-whacking slapstick, and Sandler is mesmerizing.</snippet>
         <url>http://nymag.com/movies/reviews/47552/</url>
         <critic>David Edelstein</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The result is a laff riot. Well, all right, a laff scuffle -- a picture that isn't quite as funny as it might be, but is as funny as it needs to be.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1812186,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Schickel</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie "Munich" should have been. At the very least, it's got to be the first picture to use smelly-feet jokes as a means of parsing the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. But more than that, it's a mainstream movie that dares to make jokes about the kinds of complex political realities that most of us don't dare bring up at dinner parties.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2008/06/06/zohan/</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>On screen it looks crazed, but the comic energy is huge, if indiscriminate, and Mr. Sandler's performance -- think Topol doing Charles Boyer -- can be as delicate as it is gleefully vulgar or grotesque.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121271272126950681.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sandler works so hard at this, and so shamelessly, that he battered down my resistance. Like a Jerry Lewis out of control, he will do, and does, anything to get a laugh. No thinking adult should get within a mile of this film. I must not have been thinking. For my sins, I laughed.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080605/REVIEWS/806050306</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Essentially, You Don't Mess With the Zohan isn't all that different in tone and sensibility from Sandler's previous films, but he's really trying in this one, and the effort pays off.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/1054/story/558856.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Nothing has brought me more cheap pleasure at a movie this year than the sight of shampoo and conditioner bottles falling off a rocking wall while comedian Alec Mapa, as a fellow stylist, tries to keep a straight face. He does a much better job than I did.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/movies/display?display=movie&amp;id=10847</url>
         <critic>Wesley Morris</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Brazenly self-confident in its refusal to pander to the imagined sensitivity of its audience. In this it differs notably from Albert Brooks's "Looking for Comedy in the Muslim World," which approached some of the same topics with misplaced thoughtfulness and tact.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2008/06/06/movies/06zoha.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>A.O. Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The comedy star's legions of fans will welcome the cheerfully crude proceedings as a return to silliness after several earnest, lower-key character turns. The melange of Middle East diplomacy, action absurdity, sexual healing and, when in doubt, hummus, wavers between muscular and middling. It's a surefire hit.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film/reviews/article_display.jsp?JSESSIONID=r48nLHZW9b101ykfJ2YQRJcymWWGwLyS0FTrqMv6k26Blv1KyHpr!-1330354719&amp;&amp;rid=11224</url>
         <critic>Sheri Linden</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sandler's first collaboration with co-writer and current Hollywood comedy godhead Judd Apatow, is a crazed, delightfully bizarre return to form for Sandler.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A630609</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Less like "The Waterboy" and more like "I Now Pronounce You Chuck and Larry," only funny.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/carrie_rickey/20080606__Zohan_s__silly__separate_peace.html</url>
         <critic>Carrie Rickey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The laughs are hit and miss and the movie is ho-hummus.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2008-06-05-dont-mess-with-the-zohan_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>This picture is to comedy what carpet bombing is to aerial warfare: The onslaught is so relentless that occasional direct hits on the funny bone are a statistical guarantee.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080606.wzohan06/BNStory/Entertainment/home</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>As another run-of-the-mill Sandler movie, it is better than most. At this point it seems a little foolish to want, let alone expect, "more" from the guy. If he can't be bothered to put more effort into his films, why should anybody else?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/la-et-zohan6-2008jun06,0,3774685.story</url>
         <critic>Mark Olsen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An obscene, ridiculous, and occasionally very funny movie, and if it ever gets to the Middle East it will roil the falafel tables on both sides of the Arab-Israeli divide.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/06/23/080623crci_cinema_denby</url>
         <critic>David Denby</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A strange, mostly enjoyable mix of big political questions and crude comedy, Zohan overcomes its skeletal plotting and uneven gag ratio through Sandler?s sheer commitment to nonsense.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=135227</url>
         <critic>Ian Freer</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Intermittently fresh and amusing in a low-down yet schmaltzy way.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/bal-to.zohan06jun06,0,1068527.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Sragow</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Imagine Warren Beatty in "Shampoo" by way of a Jewish Rambo.</snippet>
         <url>http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/movies/365936_zohan06q.html</url>
         <critic>Sean Axmaker</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Forget "Monty Python," You Don't Mess With the Zohan is a circus that never really flies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20204420,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>If nothing else--and there isn't much else--You Don't Mess With the Zohan pronounces the Middle East fair game for absurdist comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/film/0823,you-don-t-mess-with-the-zohan,458822,20.html</url>
         <critic>Ella Taylor</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An Israeli-on-Arab version of "Shampoo," You Don’t Mess With the Zohan is terrible in many ways, and shoddy in every way that has to do with filmmaking. But politically it's sort of interesting.</snippet>
         <url>http://chicago.metromix.com/movies/movie_review/movie-review-you-dont/444476/content</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A little like watching an episode of the TV show of which Adam Sandler is an alum: "Saturday Night Live." Zohan feels like an extended collection of skits tied together by a flimsy umbrella story.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1003</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Spectacularly, unimpeachably, relentlessly preposterous.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/you_dont_mess_with_the_zohan</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie is gross but not unfunny as it covers the Zohan's rise through hair culture, aided by his steamy heterosexuality, his lack of inhibition and his stereotypical career aggressiveness, until the old ladies are lined up all the way to the Bronx for a few minutes of bliss in the Zohan's chair.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?node=cityguide/profile&amp;id=1141801&amp;categories=Movies&amp;nm=1</url>
         <critic>Stephen Hunter</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>By the end of the film, the cliché of everybody getting along is reduced to both sides working together in the ultimate monument to capitalism: a mall. Some message.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/17538118/review/21089025/you_dont_mess_with_the_zohan</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Though a bunch of the jokes are milked too thin, there are some absurdly goofy sight gags--like a hacky sack game enlisting a family pet--and a lineup of fun, silly cameos by guests from Chris Rock to Mariah Carey.</snippet>
         <url>http://onfilm.chicagoreader.com/movies/briefs/33216_YOU_DONT_MESS_WITH_THE_ZOHAN.html</url>
         <critic>Andrea Gronvall</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Directed with sledgehammer subtlety by Dennis Dugan ("I Now Pronounce You Chuck and Larry").</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/seven/06062008/entertainment/movies/flick_falawful_crude_114160.htm</url>
         <critic>Lou Lumenick</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>His humor works best when it's throw-away, but "Zohan" throws everything up to get a yuck. It's a shock to see how many "yuck!" moments Sandler settles for.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2008/06/06/2008-06-06_live__let_dye_zohan_has_a_license_to_cur.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What's more annoying than the crassness, really, is the directorial sloppiness that results in a virtually mirthless first half-hour and a slow build to chuckles thereafter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=91087862</url>
         <critic>Bob Mondello</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The off-the-wall comedy of Robert Smigel and Judd Apatow leaves a mark on the script, but it would require a talent of Peter Sellers' magnitude to conquer this material, and he's not around.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117937339.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Brian Lowry</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Sandler proves even a hardened Israeli secret service agent can be an imbecilic juvenile.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.charlotte.com/entertainment/story/655467.html</url>
         <critic>Lawrence Toppman</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>To find a comparison for You Don't Mess With the Zohan in Adam Sandler's filmography, you have to go back to 2000's "Little Nicky," a film with a fantasy slant that allowed for jokes of unencumbered silliness.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.premiere.com/moviereviews/4607/you-dont-mess-with-the-zohan.html</url>
         <critic>Ryan Stewart</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>In truth, there's not much point to reviewing Adam Sandler comedies. They're almost always widely panned, and yet still manage to earn well over $100 million domestically. Don’' Mess with the Zohan looks to continue both trends, even if exaggerated Yiddish accents and sex with the elderly only take one so far.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=10988</url>
         <critic>Pete Vonder Haar</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Might actually be the stupidest movie with good intentions that I've ever seen.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2008/06/review_the_mess_that_is_you_do.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Serious intent may be lurking somewhere in there, but it's buried under layers of stupidity - not just stupid jokes, which is what you want from Sandler, but also stupid, shallow thinking.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/06/05/DDUL1138B8.DTL&amp;type=movies</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At a time when the images of Arab-Americans are already largely negative, do we really need more violently temperamental, bomb throwing men in turbans and beards?</snippet>
         <url>http://www.tvguide.com/movies/dont-mess-zohan/review/293489</url>
         <critic>Ken Fox</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$100,018,837</US_Gross>
   <weekend_gross>$38,531,374</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,462</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>true</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>