<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
   <name>Zombieland</name>
   <company>Columbia Pictures (Sony)</company>
   <genres>
      <genre>Comedy</genre>
      <genre>Horror</genre>
   </genres>
   <authors>
      <author>Rhett Reese</author>
      <author>Paul Wernick</author>
   </authors>
   <directors>
      <director>Ruben Fleischer</director>
   </directors>
   <origins>
      <origin>USA</origin>
   </origins>
   <actors>
      <actor>Woody Harrelson</actor>
      <actor>Jesse Eisenberg</actor>
      <actor>Emma Stone</actor>
      <actor>Abigail Breslin</actor>
   </actors>
   <release_date>October 2, 2009</release_date>
   <running_time>80</running_time>
   <rating>R</rating>
   <reviews>
      <review>
         <snippet>First-time feature director Ruben Fleischer brings impeccable timing and bloodthirsty wit to the proceedings. Cinematographer Michael Bonvillain captures some interesting images amid the post-apocalyptic carnival of carnage, as when he transforms the destruction of a souvenir shop into a rough ballet.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-zombieland2-2009oct02,0,5535099.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Ordona</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Thankfully there's nothing remotely serious about Zombieland. It's just a heck of carnival attraction (Shoot the ducks/Shoot the zombies) on a roller coaster filled with laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.filmthreat.com/index.php?section=reviews&amp;Id=11916</url>
         <critic>Elias Savada</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zombieland is dead set against being dead serious. Its tonal pallor has more in common with a foreshortened "It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad World" than with "28 Days" or "Weeks Later," and then, again, there's that jaw-dropping cameo. It'll kill ya.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Calendar/Film?Film=oid%3A879956</url>
         <critic>Marc Savlov</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Warts, entrails and all, I had a ball at Zombieland. It’s 81 minutes of my kind of stupid.</snippet>
         <url>http://featuresblogs.chicagotribune.com/talking_pictures/</url>
         <critic>Michael Phillips</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Modestly clever, this is definitely a little thing. Enjoy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/zombieland/article1308645/</url>
         <critic>Rick Groen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Mostly, it's just wicked fun.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/reviews/2009-10-01-zombieland_N.htm</url>
         <critic>Claudia Puig</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The four protagonists aren’t about to let something as minor as the complete breakdown of society get in the way of having a good time, and their fun proves infectious.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.avclub.com/articles/zombieland,33597/</url>
         <critic>Nathan Rabin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>At the bone, Zombieland is a polished, very funny road picture shaped by wisenheimer cable-TV sensibilities and starring four likable actors, each with an influential following.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20309076,00.html</url>
         <critic>Lisa Schwarzbaum</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Falling closer in tone to "Shaun of the Dead" than "28 Days Later" or the George Romero movies, Zombieland has its tongue planted firmly in its rancid cheek while still delivering the visceral goodies.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/zombieland-film-review-1004016254.story</url>
         <critic>Michael Rechtshaffen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An exhilarating ride, start to finish. Edgar Wright and Simon Pegg set a high bar for this subgenre with "Shaun of the Dead," but Reese, Werner and Fleischer may have trumped them. This isn't just a good zombie comedy. It's a damn fine movie, period. And that's high praise, coming from a vampire guy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1927245,00.html</url>
         <critic>Richard Corliss</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The picture is beautifully paced, with an exhilarating, comically violent opening, a halcyon middle section where, in what could be viewed as a sideways homage to "Rebel Without a Cause," our rootless wanderers share a brief respite in an empty, lavish mansion, and a finale filled with light and color and movement (as well as piles of vanquished zombies).</snippet>
         <url>http://www.salon.com/ent/movies/review/2009/10/02/zombieland/index.html</url>
         <critic>Stephanie Zacharek</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>These down moments are fleeting, drowned out by the joyous din of zombie slaying and a scattering of subtler touches, such as Woody Harrelson's shotgun-savant Tallahassee painting a "3" on the side of his various commandeered vehicles, presumably a tribute to NASCAR legend Dale Earnhardt.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.slate.com/id/2231160/</url>
         <critic>Josh Levin</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie's a ride, basically. It's a slick, funny buddy-flick confection about a dork (Jesse Eisenberg), a Twinkie-loving hick (Harrelson), a hottie (Emma Stone) and a sassy kid (Abigail Breslin) who bicker and bond as they drive cross-country after a zombie plague.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.oregonlive.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/10/movie_review_zombieland.html</url>
         <critic>M. E. Russell</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zombieland is still the funniest broad comedy since "The Hangover." Its yowling, marching, munching corpses are as scary as grad students and as hilarious as the plot of "G.I. Joe."</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/movies/dead_of_the_zombieland_class_WnkycCYVoMvfA87zvHGNxN</url>
         <critic>Kyle Smith</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It's great, gruesome fun, a well-written and fantastically cast romp.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nola.com/movies/index.ssf/2009/10/zombieland_comes_to_life_thank.html</url>
         <critic>Mike Scott</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Isn't an especially good horror movie, it succeeds in enough different ways that such a defect hardly matters.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.reelviews.net/php_review_template.php?identifier=1811</url>
         <critic>James Berardinelli</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>It also boasts one of the funniest, loopiest Woody Harrelson turns in years.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.philly.com/inquirer/columnists/steven_rea/20091002_Gore__gags_in_raucous_road_flick.html</url>
         <critic>Steven Rea</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>What Zombieland’ has instead - in spades - is deliciously weary end-of-the-world banter.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/10/02/killer_laughs_bring_zombieland_alive/</url>
         <critic>Ty Burr</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Guilty-pleasure movies should not be underestimated. I had a scary-fun-house blast at Zombieland, in which studly Woody Harrelson, nerdy Jesse Eisenberg, sexy Emma Stone and sunshiny Abigail Breslin roam a near-dead world kicking zombie ass.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/movie/27810103/review/30307970/zombieland</url>
         <critic>Peter Travers</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The secret in this case is the jokes, which are ferocious. Marrying a monster flick with an adolescent romance has produced a merry mutant.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/entertainment/reviews.nsf/movie/story/D22525617107CAA586257641006955FD?OpenDocument</url>
         <critic>Joe Williams</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Who would have guessed such a funny movie as Zombieland could be made around zombies? No thanks to the zombies.</snippet>
         <url>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090930/REVIEWS/909309991</url>
         <critic>Roger Ebert</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Scary? Yes, in spots. Gratuitously gory? You bet. But, first and foremost, Zombieland is a comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.miamiherald.com/entertainment/movies/reviews/story/1260538.html</url>
         <critic>Rene Rodriguez</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Writers Rhett Reese and Paul Wernick wring a surprising amount of juice from the familiar premise, and director Ruben Fleischer heaps on the gore without burying their character-based comedy and surprisingly heartfelt moments. This is worth seeing just for the title sequence.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/MovieTimes?film=978136</url>
         <critic>Cliff Doerksen</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Benefiting from the very different but very appealing comedy styles of Woody Harrelson and Jesse Eisenberg even when the script's wit runs thin, this should be catnip to jaded genre fans.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117941244.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1</url>
         <critic>Dennis Harvey</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>An improbably delicious comedy.</snippet>
         <url>http://online.wsj.com/article/film_review.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Morgenstern</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The movie isn’t particularly scary--not a crime when your goal is laughs. More egregious is the niggling fact that this simply isn’t as witty as "Shaun of the Dead," forever the yuks-meet-yucks standard.</snippet>
         <url>http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/film/79133/zombieland-film-review</url>
         <critic>Joshua Rothkopf</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>The action-comedy Zombieland works because it's played with an emphasis on the living, not the undead.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2009/10/02/2009-10-02_land_of_the_free_home_of_a_whole_lot_of_zombies.html</url>
         <critic>Joe Neumaier</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Yet, even at its worst, Zombieland is better than most movies of its kind - disgusting but not too disgusting, and with a few laughs.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/10/01/MVM519VLT2.DTL</url>
         <critic>Mick LaSalle</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Zombieland is sometimes funny. But those of us who have teeny coronaries every time something goes bump in Zombieland might have a hard time relaxing for long enough to really enjoy ourselves.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.washingtonpost.com/gog/movies/zombieland,1158398/critic-review.html#reviewNum1</url>
         <critic>Ruth McCann</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>A minor diversion dripping in splatter and groaning with self-amusement.</snippet>
         <url>http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/10/02/movies/02zomb.html?ref=movies</url>
         <critic>Manohla Dargis</critic>
      </review>
      <review>
         <snippet>Fitfully amusing romp directed with little ambition and even less distinction by first-timer Ruben Fleischer.</snippet>
         <url>http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-09-29/film/woody-harrelson-as-leathery-roughneck-in-zombieland/</url>
         <critic>Scott Foundas</critic>
      </review>
   </reviews>
   <US_Gross>$75,590,286</US_Gross>
   <production_budget>$23,600,000</production_budget>
   <weekend_gross>$24,733,155</weekend_gross>
   <number_of_screens>3,036</number_of_screens>
   <summer_release>false</summer_release>
   <christmas_release>false</christmas_release>
   <memorial_release>false</memorial_release>
   <independence_release>false</independence_release>
   <labor_release>false</labor_release>
</movie>